<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00286">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Catharine Palmer, 19 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00286</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Catharine Palmer, 19 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-19">May 19, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Catharine Palmer, 19 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-19">May 19, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775&#8211;1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Catharine Palmer</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Samuel Drury</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-03" who="#scl">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-13" who="#jc">proofed for and corrected encoding and transcription
                errors</change>
            <change when="2012-02-15" who="#el">automated checking across files for extra spaces in
                elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription
                errors</change>
            <change when="2012-02-14" who="#el">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary</change>
            <change when="2011-10-12" who="#bj">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-04-27" who="#rr">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-02-18" who="#rv">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00286.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Catharine Palmer</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName> but now residing in <placeName>Washington
                            D.C.</placeName>.</seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she
                    </seg> is a person loyal to the United States, who, at the time of the passage
                    of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> person of African descent <del>of the name of</del> for and during the
                    life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> was discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such
                    service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">fifteen years</seg> and of the
                    personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1"
                        >Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be
                        more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <table rend="handwritten">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Complexion</cell>
                            <cell>Light Mulatto.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Eyes</cell>
                            <cell>Black.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hair</cell>
                            <cell>Black.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Height</cell>
                            <cell>Five Feet &#38; two inches.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>stout &#38; healthy</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00286.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"> Elizabeth Jackson
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here
                        state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">By gift from her husband General <persName>J. N.
                        Palmer</persName>
                    <placeName>U.S.</placeName> Army (who is now with the army under General
                        <persName>McClellan</persName>) in <date when="1855-05">May 1855</date>. his
                    title of her having been acquired by purchase from one <persName>George
                        Stevenson</persName> of <placeName>St. Louis Missouri</placeName>
                    <date when="1852-09-23">September 23d 1852</date> for the sum of one hundred and
                    fifty dollars. The bill of sale is in possession of petitioner &#38; if
                    necessary will be exhibited.</ab>


                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg
                        type="handwritten">one thousand</seg> dollars in money.<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">And that her value was much enhanced by her having been
                        thought if as it were in the family of your petitioner all of whose children
                        she has served. And your petitioner further states that the said
                            <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName> is free from all bodily &#38;
                        mental infirmities.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">Your petitioner further states that the said
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName> is an excellent domestic servant that
                    eighteen months since she refused a check of one thousand dollars for her</ab>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of
                    said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons were</seg> held to service or labor therein under
                    and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >the</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any
                    person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against
                    the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">the</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Elizabeth Jackson</persName>
                    </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Catharine Palmer</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00286.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Catharine Palmer</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Catharine Palmer</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-13">
                            <seg type="handwritten">13</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A.D. 1862</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Saml Drury</persName> JP</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>286 <lb/>Petition of <persName>Catharine Palmer</persName>
                </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-19">May 19, 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>witness <lb/> Mrs. <persName>Feduca R. Jones</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>Roger B. Jones</persName>
                    <lb/> 539 18th st </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
