<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00186">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Samuel Fearson, 13 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
                    <name xml:id="cg">Courtney Geerhart</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00186</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Samuel Fearson, 13 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Samuel Fearson, 13 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Robert White</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-13" who="#jc">revised code for handwritten content on first page of petition; added transcription of evidentiary material</change>
            <change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-10-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-10-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-09-06" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2011-08-31" who="#cg">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-04-18" who="#rv">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-02" who="#rr">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="petition">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00186.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Georgetown D.C.</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <space atLeast="1"/> is a person loyal to the United
                    States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a
                    claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">three</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anna Thomas</persName>, <persName>William Henry Thomas</persName>,
                        and <persName>Anna Maria Thomas</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anna</persName>
                        <persName>William Henry</persName>, and <persName>Anna Maria</persName>
                    </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anna</persName>,<persName>William Henry</persName> and
                            <persName>Anna Maria</persName> were</seg> discharged and freed of and
                    from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of
                    said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anna</persName>,<persName> William Henry</persName> and
                            <persName>Anna Maria</persName> were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1"> Here describe the person, so as to identify him or
                        her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one
                        separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Anna Thomas</persName>, 29 years of age, about Five feet
                            four inches high, of a dark brown color, very healthy</item>
                        <item><persName>William Henry Thomas</persName>, about twelve (12) years of
                            age, about four feet six inches high, of bright-yellow color, and being
                            very healthy</item>
                        <item><persName>Anna Maria Thomas</persName>, about seven years of age,
                            about four feet high, Black, very healthy.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00186.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anna</persName>, <persName>William Henry</persName> &amp;
                            <persName>Anna Maria</persName>
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">
                        Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price
                        or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">The said <persName>Anna</persName> with her said
                        children <persName>William Henry</persName> and <persName>Anna
                            Maria</persName>, were purchased by me from <persName>Joseph A.
                            Pearson</persName> on the <date when="1854-01-20">20th day of January in
                            1854</date> for the sum of Eleven Hundred dollars cash as per bill of
                        sale of that date, will fully appear.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anna</persName>, <persName>William Henry</persName> and
                            <persName>Anna Maria</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">twenty six hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3"> Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"> That your petitioner is unaware of any mental, moral or
                        physical defect in either of said persons, all three of them being healthy
                        during the whole period of his knowledge of them; that he values them as
                        follows: <persName>Anna</persName>, at one thousand dollars ($1000.00);
                            <persName>William Henry</persName>, at Nine Hundred Dollars ($900.00)
                        and <persName>Anna Maria</persName> at Seven Hundred Dollars
                        ($700.00);</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons or either of
                        them</seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons above named</seg> does not originate in or by
                    virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided
                    or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the United
                    States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons as</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>                      
                        
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00185.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>186</ab>
                    <ab><hi rend="underline">Bill of Sale</hi></ab>
                    <ab><persName>Joseph N. Fearson</persName><lb/>
                        to<lb/>
                        <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>,<lb/>
                        of<lb/>
                        <list>
                            <item>Negro woman <persName>Anna</persName>.</item>
                            <item>do boy <persName>Wm Henry</persName>.</item>
                            <item>" girl <persName>Ann Maria</persName>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </ab>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <note type="editorial">The following section of this document is written
                        perpendicular to the previous section.</note>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>Anna</persName></cell>
                            <cell>$1000—</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>Wm Henry</persName></cell>
                            <cell>900</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>Anna Maria</persName></cell>
                            <cell>700</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>$2600 Due By Estates</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00185.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents; That I <persName>Joseph N. Fearson</persName>
                        of <placeName>Georgetown</placeName> in the <placeName>County of
                            Washington</placeName> and <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                        for and in consideration of the sum of Eleven Hundred Dollars, ($1100)
                        current money of the <placeName>United States</placeName> to me in hand paid
                        by <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName> son of <persName>Samuel S.
                            Fearson</persName>, of <placeName>Georgetown</placeName> aforesaid, at
                        and before the ensealing and delivery of these presents, the receipt whereof
                        is hereby acknowledged, have granted, bargained and sold and by these
                        presents do grant bargain and sell unto the said <persName>Samuel
                            Fearson</persName>, his heirs and assigns forever, my negro woman
                        <persName>Anna</persName> aged about twenty six (26) years, and her two
                        children, <persName>William Henry</persName> aged about (9) nine years, and
                        <persName>Ann Maria</persName> aged about four (4) years, the said negro
                        woman <persName>Anna</persName>, negro by <persName>William Henry</persName>
                        and negro girl <persName>Ann Maria</persName>, being slaves for life, and
                        now and for a long time past, hired out to, and living in the family of
                        <persName>Samuel S. Fearson</persName> in
                        <placeName>Georgetown</placeName> aforesaid.</p>
                    <p>To have and to hold, all and singular the said negro woman
                        <persName>Anna</persName> aged 26 years, negro boy <persName>William
                            Henry</persName> aged 9 years and the said negro girl <persName>Ann
                                Maria</persName> aged 4 years, unto the said <persName>Samuel
                                    Fearson</persName>, his heirs, executors, administrators and assigns
                        forever; and I, the said <persName>Joseph N. Fearson</persName>, for myself
                        and my heirs, executors and administrators, the said negro woman
                        <persName>Anna</persName>, negro boy <persName>William Henry</persName>
                        and negro girl <persName>Ann Maria</persName>, have put in the full
                        possession of the said <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>, by personal
                        delivery of them, and by the sealing and delivery hereof, this <date when="1859-01-20">20th day of January in the year of our Lord One
                            thousand Eight hundred and fifty nine</date>. In testimony of all which
                        I have hereto set my hand and seal, the day and last herein before
                        written.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>J. N. Fearson</persName>
                        </signed> Seal<lb/>
                        Signed, sealed and delivered in presence of
                        <signed><persName>Jacob Ramsbury</persName></signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>Joseph A.
                                Hastings</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00186.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-10">
                            <seg type="handwritten">10</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>. </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Robert White</persName>
                                <lb/> Justice of Peace</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>186 <lb/> Petition of <persName>Samuel Fearson</persName>. <lb/> Owner of Three
                    slaves</ab>
                <ab>Act of Congress approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16 1862</date>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>Jones &amp; Ashford <choice>
                        <abbr>Attys</abbr>
                        <expan>Attorneys</expan>
                    </choice> for Claimant.</ab>
                <ab>
                    <persName>Samuel L. Fearson</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>Joseph W. Fearson</persName>
                </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
