<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.01087">
    <teiHeader>   
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Hugh McCormick, 19 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt> 
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.01087</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>   
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Hugh McCormick, 19 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-19">July 19, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Hugh McCormick, 19 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-19">July 19, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>            
        </fileDesc>   
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Hugh McCormick</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-07-02" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-15" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.01087.003.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of
                    April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or
                    labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Baxter</persName>, <persName>Louisa Bell</persName>, <persName>May Bell</persName> and <persName>George Bell</persName>, four</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> <del>of</del> <seg type="handwritten">aforesaid</seg> for and during the li<del>f</del><seg type="handwritten">ves</seg> of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">four persons named were</seg> were discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">four persons were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note> <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Baxter</persName> is about 38 or 40 years old, dark complexion, and of medium size&#8212;<persName>Louisa Bell</persName> is about 34 years old, dark and of the medium size, <persName>May Bell</persName> is about 11 years old, dark and small for her age, and <persName>George Bell</persName> is about 7 years old and very light colored&#8212;</seg></p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.01087.004.jpg"/>
                
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">four persons</seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note> <seg type="handwritten">The said <persName>Ann Baxter</persName> and <persName>Louisa Bell</persName> were acquired by your petitioners wife by inheritance from her  Father the late <persName>George McCanley</persName> of this district, about 20 years ago, and they have been the property of your petitioner ever since; <persName>May</persName> and <persName>George Bell</persName>, the children of said <persName>Louisa Bell</persName> were born in your petitioners family as his slaves and as the issue of a slave mother&#8212;</seg></p>
                
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">four persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">2200</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note> <seg type="handwritten">Said <persName>Ann Baxter</persName> being worth $600, <persName>Louisa Bell</persName> $800 <persName>May Bell</persName> $500 and <persName>George Bell</persName> $300. Said <persName>Ann Baxter</persName> and <persName>Louisa Bell</persName> being excellent cooks, and <persName>Louisa Bell</persName> an accomplished washer and ironer, both being admirably trained in general housework&#8212;said <persName>May</persName> and <persName>George</persName> are intelligent and active children, and all said servants are healthy and valuable&#8212;Your petitioner knows of no mental, moral or physical infirmities in said persons to impair their value&#8212;</seg></p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons or any of them</seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">four persons</seg> w<del>as</del><seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">four persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">four persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>
                
                <closer>
                    (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.01087.005.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> <lb/>
                <placeName>Washington County</placeName> ss.</dateline>
                    
                <p>On this <date when="1862-07-19">19th day of July 1862</date> personally appeared <persName>Richard H. Clarke</persName> of <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, before the undersigned Clerk to the Commissioners under the aforesaid Act of Congress and made oath in due form of law that <persName>Hugh McCormick</persName> a citizen of <placeName>Washington</placeName> and the owner of the four persons of African descent named in the foregoing and annexed petition, had on or about the <date when="1862-06-25">25th day of June 1862</date> prepared his said petition for compensation under said act of Congress, signed and duly made affidavit to the facts set forth in said petition, and that said <persName>Hugh McCormick</persName> either on the <date notBefore="1862-06-25" notAfter="1862-06-26">25th or 26th day of June '62</date> placed said petitioner in the hands of this affiant to be by him filed for said claimant with the Commissioners according to law; that it was the intention of this affiant to file the same accordingly, and said claimant and said affiant, were under the most positive conviction and belief that said petition had been accordingly filed within the time specified by law, and remained under said conviction and belief up to the present time, only four days after the expiration of the time limited for filing such petitions; that it is now discovered to the great astonishment and regret of said affiant that at the time said petition was left with
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.01087.006.jpg"/>
                this affiant at his office, the same became by unaccountable accident mislaid and was not to be found among the papers in affiant's possession relating to similar subjects&#8212;thus the impression fastened itself on the mind of affiant that said petition had been duly filed and affiant remained under this impression and belief to the present time, this affiant having been uniformly careful and particular in punctually and carefully attending to all such matters of business entrusted to his care: and further affiant says that at the time said petition was left in his hands for filing as aforesaid his mind was unusually engrossed and continued so, until the last day for filing such petitions and on said last day when affiant would have carefully examined his cases &#38; papers to ascertain if all petitions in his hands had been duly filed, he was visited by a sudden and <choice><sic>apalling</sic><corr>appalling</corr></choice> visitation of Providence in the sudden and untimely death of his office companion &#38; associate
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.01087.007.jpg"/>    
                the late <persName>John C C. Hamilton</persName>, whose death <gap reason="obscured" extent="one or two words" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/> tragic and painful circumstances attending it rendered affiant disqualified for business, and contributed to the fact of said petitions not having been duly filed. This affidavit is made in the hope that, the equitable circumstances of the case will be duly considered, that said petition may be taken as actually filed according to the law and that said claimant may not be injured in his application for compensation as aforesaid; and further affiant states that said petition having now come to light &#38; found not to have been filed, has been immediately produced &#38; tendered to be filed with said clerk</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Richd H. Clarke</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Subscribed and Sworn to by said <persName>Richard H. Clarke</persName> before me in presence of the Commissioners Saturday <date when="1862-07-19">July 19, 1862</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Wm R Woodward</persName>  <choice><abbr>clk</abbr><expan>clerk</expan></choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.01087.008.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia,</placeName><lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">                    
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-25"><seg type="handwritten">25th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                <closer>
                    (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>F. I. Murphey</persName> J. P.</seg></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>Petition of</ab>
                <ab><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></ab>
                <ab><date when="1862-07-19">July 19, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.01087.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="envelope" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab><choice><abbr>Hon</abbr><expan>Honorable</expan></choice> <persName>Samuel F Vinton</persName></ab>
                <ab>President of the Board of Commissioners of Emancipation</ab>
                <ab><placeName>Washington D. C.</placeName></ab>
                <ab><choice><abbr>Recd</abbr><expan>Received</expan></choice> <date when="1862-07">July <gap reason="cut away" extent="more than one word" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/></date></ab>
            </div1>
            
            <!-- Evidence pertaining to the case begins here -->            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.01087.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                
                <div2 type="section">
                
                    <dateline><date when="1862-08-01">August. 1</date>.</dateline>
                <div3 type="procedural">
                    <ab><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></ab>
                </div3>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Ann Baxter</persName>, 36. Cook principally do housework $6. health indifferent, asthma prevents my working, lays me up 2 weeks together all through life, teeth bad. no children</ab>
                    <ab>$400.</ab>
                </div3>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>George</persName> 6 to 7. complains of right eye sometimes. $400.</ab>
                </div3>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>George McCanley</persName>. I know <choice><abbr>serts</abbr><expan>servants</expan></choice> as <choice><abbr>Petrs</abbr><expan>Petitioner's</expan></choice>. owned woman 30 yrs. child born his. <choice><abbr>Petr</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice> is loyal. opposed to secession &#38; rebellion &#38; in favor of putting them down</ab>
                </div3>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Y. P. Page</persName> Have been neighbor of <choice><abbr>Petr</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice> many years servant is  his <choice><abbr>Petr</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice> is loyal</ab>
                </div3>
                </div2>
                
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><date when="1862-08-05">August 5</date>.</dateline>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Louisa</persName> <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="2"/> Cook wash &#38; iron cant wash &#38; iron much from poor health had to stop. health bad. teeth poor</ab>
                    <ab>$750</ab>
                </div3>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Mary</persName> 8. healthy $500</ab>
                </div3>
                
                <div3 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Geo McCanley</persName> recognize servants as <choice><abbr>Petrs</abbr><expan>Petitioner's</expan></choice> born his</ab>
                </div3>
                </div2>
                
                
                <pb xml:id="leav006v" facs="cww.01087.002.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="cover">
                    <ab><persName>Hugh McCormick</persName></ab>
                    <ab>not filed&#8212;too late</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
