<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00537">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of John W. Mankin, 28 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00537</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of John W. Mankin, 28 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of John W. Mankin, 28 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>John W. Mankin</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-05-20" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-02-04" who="#kk">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-11-07" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00537.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John W Mankin</persName></seg>
                    of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>George Town</placeName> &#38;
                            <placeName>District</placeName> aforesaid</seg> by this <seg
                        type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of
                    Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a
                        certain</seg> person of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Emma Rebecca Netter</persName>.</seg> for and
                    during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Emma
                            Rebecca</persName>.</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten">person was</seg> discharged and freed of and from all
                    claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten">person was</seg> of the age of <seg
                        type="handwritten">of about (5) five years and five (5) months</seg> and of
                    the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">She is dark copper colored, three feet five inches in <choice>
                            <sic>heighth</sic>
                            <corr>height</corr>
                        </choice> with a bright handsome intelligent countenance</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00537.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">person</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">On the <date when="1855-05-25">25th day of May
                            1855</date>, in consideration of the sum of fifty dollars <persName>E.
                            B. Mills</persName> of said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        sold and delivered to your petitioner a negro woman named <persName>Ellen
                            Netter</persName> [the mother of said <persName>Emma Rebecca</persName>]
                        a slave for a term of years; said term of servitude to
                        end three years from and after the <date when="1855-05-07">7th day of May
                            and year last aforesaid</date>: as is Evidenced by a certain Bill of
                        sale dated the <date when="1855-05-25">25th of May 1855</date>: and herewith
                        filed as Exhibit A: and before the expiration of said term of servitude to
                        wit on or about <ref xml:id="r1" target="#a1">&#8270;</ref></seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Emma Rebecca Netter</persName></seg> was, at
                    the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Three hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">Said <persName>Emma Rebecca</persName> enjoys good health; is of excellent
                        disposition&#8212;and is remarkably fine looking&#8212;animated&#8212;and
                        intelligent. There is a slight curve in the bones of the legs below the
                        knees&#8212;which gives the appearance of deformity; but which does not
                        affect her strength or activity or impair her value&#8212;and your
                        petitioner knows of no other imperfection or defect moral, mental, or
                        bodily&#8212;and he does not believe any exists in said
                            <persName>Emma</persName></seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">person</seg> into the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">person</seg> was held to service or labor therein under
                    and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">person</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">person</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>John W Mankin</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
                <note xml:id="a1" target="#r1" type="authorial" rend="handwritten"><seg type="handwritten">&#8270;the <date when="1856-11-25">Twenty fifth Day of November&#8212;1856</date>&#8212;said
                            <persName>Ellen Netter</persName> was delivered of a female child being
                        said <persName>Emma Rebecca Netter</persName>, who thereby according to the
                        laws of said District became the slave for life of
                        your petitioner.</seg></note>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00537.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents that I <persName>E B Mills</persName> of the
                            <placeName>City of Washington</placeName>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> for and in consideration of the
                        sum of fifty&#8212;dollars current money to me in hand paid by
                            <persName>John W Mankin</persName> of the City and District aforesaid at
                        and before the sealing and delivery of these presents, the receipt whereof I
                        the said <persName>E B Mills</persName> do hereby acknowledge, have granted
                        bargained and sold, and by these presents do Grant, bargain and sell <choice>
                            <sic>into</sic>
                            <corr>unto</corr>
                        </choice>
                        the said <persName>John W Mankin</persName> his Executors Administrators and
                        assigns, a Certain Negro woman named <persName>Ellen Netter</persName> a
                        Slave for a term of years, that is to say the <choice>
                            <sic>ballance</sic>
                            <corr>balance</corr>
                        </choice> of the term of Servitude of Said <persName>Ellen Netter</persName>
                        to wit three years from and after the <date when="1855-05-07">Seventh day of
                            May A D one thousand eight hundred and fifty five</date>, when the said
                            <persName>Ellen Netter</persName> will be entitled to her Freedom, with
                        this condition that the said <persName>John W Mankin</persName>, is
                        absolutely restricted from selling the said <persName>Ellen</persName>, out
                        of the <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> or in any manner to be
                        taken out of said County. To Have
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00537.004.jpg"/>
                        
                        And To Hold the said Negro woman
                            <persName>Ellen Netter</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <sic>into</sic>
                            <corr>unto</corr>
                        </choice> the said <persName>John W Mankin</persName> his heirs Executors
                        administrators and assigns, for the time aforesaid and on the condition
                        aforesaid and I the said <persName>E B Mills</persName> for myself my
                        Executors and Administrators, the said Negro woman <persName>Ellen</persName>
                        unto the said <persName>John W Mankin</persName>, his Executors
                        administrators and assigns, for the time and term aforesaid, against all
                        persons claiming or who may claim shall and will warrant and forever defend
                        by these presents the said negro woman <persName>Ellen</persName>. In
                        witness whereof I the said <persName>E B Mills</persName> have hereunto set
                        my hand and seal this <date when="1855-05-25">Twenty Fifth day of May in the
                            year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and fifty five</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>E. B. Mills</persName> seal</signed>
                        <signed>Signed sealed and delivered in presence of <persName>Mary M
                                Dimitry</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>A Exhibit</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00537.005.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John W. Mankin</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J W Mankin</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-28"><seg type="handwritten">28th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName>
                                <choice>
                                    <abbr>clk</abbr>
                                    <expan>clerk</expan>
                                </choice></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>537<lb/>
                    <persName>John W. Mankin</persName><lb/>
                    Petition</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date><lb/>
                    by<lb/>
                    <persName>Hugh <gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word" quantity="10"
                            unit="chars"/></persName></ab>
                <ab><persName>Elizabeth Reeder</persName> <address><addrLine>12th no 449</addrLine></address>
                    <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="8" unit="chars"/></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
