<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00725">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Augustus E. Perry, Trustee, and Ellen R. Middleton, 20 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00725</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Augustus E. Perry, Trustee, and Ellen R. Middleton, 20 June
                        1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-20">June 20, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Augustus E. Perry, Trustee, and Ellen R. Middleton,
                                20 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-20">June 20, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Augustus E. Perry</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Ellen R. Middleton</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">revised values @facs</change>
<change when="2013-05-20" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-02-07" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-02-01" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00725.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Augustus E. Perry</persName>
                        of the</seg>
                    <del>of</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>City of Washington, D.C</placeName>, Trustee,
                        and <persName>Ellen R. Middleton</persName>, of the <placeName>County of
                            Washington, D.C.</placeName> Cestui que trust,</seg> by this <seg
                        type="handwritten">their </seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">they are</seg>
                    <del>is a</del> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">Six</seg> person of African descent of the name<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy
                            Shaw</persName>&#8212;<persName>Gusty
                            Shaw</persName>&#8212;<persName>Dawson
                            Shaw</persName>&#8212;<persName>Sidney
                            Shaw</persName>&#8212;<persName>Sally Price</persName>, and
                            <persName>Gusty Jones</persName>&#8212;</seg> for and during the life of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">Six persons,</seg> and that by said act of Congress
                    said <seg type="handwritten">Six persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and
                    from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of
                    said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy Shaw</persName>
                        was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">Fifty eight (8) years,</seg>
                    and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">a Brown colored woman, 5 ft 5 in high, a Scar over her
                        left eye. and nothing else remarkable about her.</seg>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item>That the said <persName>Gusty Shaw</persName> was of the age of Twenty
                            Seven years, and of the personal description following:<lb/> a Brown
                            colored man, six feet high, stout, straight and well made, having no
                            marks or scars upon his person&#8212;</item>
                        <item>That the said <persName>Dawson Shaw</persName> was of the age of
                            Twenty two years, and of the personal description following:<lb/> a
                            Black man 5 ft 7 &#189; in high, straight and well made, and of ordinary
                            size&#8212;having no marks or scars upon his person&#8212;</item>
                        <item>That the said <persName>Sidney Shaw</persName> was of the age of
                            Eighteen years, and of the personal description following<lb/> a dark
                            mulatto boy five feet nine inches high, tall in his appearance, and no
                            marks or scars upon his person&#8212;</item>
                        <item>That the said <persName>Sally Price</persName> was of the age of Seven
                            years, and of the personal description following:<lb/> a dark Brown girl
                            three feet eleven inches high, of ordinary size, and very
                            sprightly&#8212;a pleasant countenance&#8212;no marks or scars upon her
                            person&#8212;</item>
                        <item>and that the said <persName>Gusty Jones</persName> was of the age of
                            Twenty-Seven years, and of the personal description following:<lb/> a
                            Black man 5 f<hi rend="underline">t</hi> 6 in high, straight and well
                            made, though not large, having lost the nail of his right thumb.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00725.003.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> acquired <seg
                        type="handwritten">their</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of
                    said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy</persName>,
                            <persName>Gusty</persName> and <persName>Dawson</persName></seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By Mr. <persName>E. J. Middleton</persName>, in right of
                        his wife, one of your Petitioners, on the division of the estate of her
                        Father, the late <persName>Richard Ross</persName>, of <placeName>Montgomery
                            County Maryland</placeName>, of which there is no written evidence,
                        unless the late Mr. <persName>Nathan Lugborough</persName>, the Executor, so stated it in his return to and settlement with the Orphans
                        Court of <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>
                            aforesaid&#8212;<persName>Sidney</persName> is the son of the above
                        named <persName>Lucy</persName>, born in the family of Mr.
                            <persName>Middleton</persName> Since his marriage with your Petitioner.
                            <persName>Sally</persName> was also born in the family of Mr.
                            <persName>Middleton</persName>&#8212;her mother died about one year ago;
                        the claim to her service or labor was acquired by Mr.
                            <persName>Middleton</persName> in right of his said wife, one of your
                        Petitioners, on the division of the estate of her mother,
                            <persName>Elizabeth Ross</persName>, who died in this city in the year
                            <date when="1848">1848</date>.<ref xml:id="r1" target="#a1">X</ref></seg></p>

                <!-- begin first pasted on section -->
                <note xml:id="a1" target="#r1" type="authorial" rend="handwritten"><ab
                        type="handwritten">That on the <date when="1862-10-01">1st day of October
                            1852</date>, the said <persName>E. J. Middleton</persName> conveyed the
                        above named servants, except the said <persName>Sally</persName>, to your
                        Petitioner <persName>A. E. Perry</persName>, in trust for the use and
                        benefit of his said wife, as will appear by reference to the Deed of Trust
                        recorded in Liber J. A. S. No 43, folios 444, one of the Land records of the
                            <placeName>County of Washington</placeName>&#8212;</ab>
                    <ab type="handwritten">The said <persName>Gusty Jones</persName> was purchased
                        from Mr. <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName> on the <date
                            when="1857-05-07">7th day of May 1857</date>, for the sum of $1100, as
                        will appear by reference to a Receipt hereto attached&#8212;</ab></note>
                <!-- end first pasted on section -->

                <pb sameAs="leav001v" facs="cww.00725.004.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">Six persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$6,700:</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item>The said <persName>Lucy Shaw</persName> is a good Cook, Washer &#38;
                            Ironer, and a remarkably good Servant in every respect&#8212;and was of
                            the value of $700&#8212;</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Gusty Shaw</persName> is an extraordinary valuable
                            valuable man; being an excellent farmer, gardener and marketer. He now
                            has, and for the last five years has had the entire charge and
                            management of the Farm and garden of Mr. <persName>Middleton</persName>.
                            He as of the value of $1800.&#8212;</item>
                        <!-- begin second pasted on section -->
                        <item>The said <persName>Dawson Shaw</persName> is also a very valuable man,
                            being a first rate house servant and coachman, and was of the value of
                            $1400.&#8212;</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Sidney Shaw</persName> is a most excellent boy,
                            being a good farm hand, very industrious and attentive to his work, and
                            was of the value or $1300.&#8212;</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Sally Price</persName> is a very sprightly and
                            promising girl, and was of the value of $300.&#8212;</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Gusty Jones</persName> is also a valuable man,
                            being a good Farm hand, House Servant, and a first rate Hostler and
                            Coachman. He was bought for $1100, but the price was $1200; the former
                            sum was taken in consideration of his being kept in the neighborhood of
                            his family, and was worth at the time of his discharge from service or
                            labor $1200.&#8212;</item>
                    </list></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">All the above named persons are perfectly moral and
                    reliable&#8212;Indeed it would be difficult to find a better set of servants
                    any where&#8212;with the exception of <persName>Gusty Jones</persName>, they are
                    all family servants&#8212;and Your Petitioners know of no moral, mental or
                    bodily infirmities or defects of the said persons or any of them&#8212;</ab>
                <!-- end second pasted on section -->

                <pb sameAs="leav001v" facs="cww.00725.005.jpg"/>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> hereby declares that <seg
                        type="handwritten">they</seg> bear<del>s</del> true and faithful allegiance
                    to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">they have</seg>
                    <del>has</del> not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName>
                    in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they have</seg>
                    <del>has</del> not brought said <seg type="handwritten">Six persons or either of
                        them</seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the
                    passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof,
                    said <seg type="handwritten">Six persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to
                    the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Six persons</seg> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                    the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> pray<del>s</del> the said
                    Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg
                        type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said
                        <seg type="handwritten">Six persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Augustus E.
                                Perry</persName><lb/> Trustee for <persName>Ellen R.
                                Middleton</persName></seg></signed>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ellen R.
                        Middleton</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00725.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="receipt" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>I hereby acknowledge to have received this day from <persName>Augustus E.
                        Perry</persName>, Trustee of <persName>Ellen R. Middleton</persName>, the
                    Sum of Eleven hundred Dollars for the purchase of my negro Slave
                        <persName>Augustus Jones</persName>&#8212;aged about Twenty two years. Which
                    said negro Slave I now deliver to the said <persName>Augustus E.
                        Perry</persName>, and do hereby warrant him a Slave for life and free from
                    the claims of any and all person or persons whomsoever.</p>
                <p>As witness my hand and seal this <date when="1857-05-07">7th day of May
                        1857</date>.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>N. Boyd Brooks</persName> seal<lb/> Agent for
                            <persName>Nicholas L Queen</persName>.</signed><lb/> Witness
                            <signed><persName>Chs. McNamee</persName></signed></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00725.007.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><del>I,</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">We <persName>Augustus E. Perry</persName>, and
                                <persName>Ellen R. Middleton</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do
                        depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of <del>my</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">our</seg> own knowledge, are true in substance and
                        in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, <del>I</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">we</seg> believe to be true in substance and in
                        fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Augustus E
                                    Perry</persName><lb/> Trustee for <persName>Ellen R.
                                    Middleton</persName></seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ellen R.
                                Middleton</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-17"><seg type="handwritten">17th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>F. I.
                                    Murphey</persName> J. P.</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>725 <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">Exbt</unclear></ab>
                <ab><persName>Augustus E. Perry</persName> Trustee<lb/> and <persName>Ellen R.
                        Middleton</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-20">June 20 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
