<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00435">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of John L. Kidwell, 26 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                    <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00435</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of John L. Kidwell, 26 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-26">May 26, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of John L. Kidwell, 26 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-26">May 26, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>John L. Kidwell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Jenkins Thomas</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-10-12" who="#el">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-09-06" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2011-05-09" who="#rr">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-04-25" who="#rv">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-11-15" who="#bj">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00435.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John L.
                        Kidwell</persName></seg>
                    <del>of</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">of <placeName>George Town</placeName> in the said
                            <placeName>District</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States, who, at
                    the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or
                    labor against <seg type="handwritten">three negroes or</seg> person<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>James
                            Somerville</persName>, <persName>Mary Somerville</persName> and
                            <persName>Sarah Brooks</persName></seg> for and during the
                        <del>life</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">lives</seg> of said <seg type="handwritten">persons or
                        negroes</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"
                        >persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your
                    petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten"
                        >s</seg>
                    <del>of</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word"
                            quantity="2" unit="chars"/></seg> and of the personal description
                        following<del>:</del><seg type="handwritten">;</seg><note type="government"
                        place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or
                        her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one
                        separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">viz: said <hi rend="underline"><persName>James
                                Somerville</persName></hi> was of the age of twenty four
                        years&#8212;a mulatto&#8212;five feet seven and three quarter inches high;
                        the said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Mary Somerville</persName></hi> was
                        three and a half years of age&#8212;also a mulatto, and a child 2 &#189;
                        feet high; and said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Sarah
                            Brooks</persName></hi> was twenty years of age&#8212;a dark mulatto,
                        five feet and five inches high.</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00435.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">negroes or
                        persons</seg> in manner following<del>:</del><seg type="handwritten"
                        >;</seg><note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the
                        claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration;
                        and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or
                        refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">namely&#8212;he purchased said <hi rend="underline"
                                ><persName>James Somerville</persName></hi> between ten and twelve
                        years ago, (who was then a mere boy,) from <persName>Edward N.
                            Roach</persName>, the late Register of Wills of this
                            <placeName>District</placeName>, for five hundred dollars, and the day
                        after was offered one thousand dollars for him by a trader; but petitioner
                        did not buy him for any such purpose; and <persName>Mr. Roach</persName>
                        sold him to petitioner at such a low price because he also was opposed to
                        selling well-behaved negroes from their homes: your petitioner bought him
                        for his domestic use, and has since kept him in his family. <hi
                            rend="underline"><persName>Mary Somerville</persName></hi> petitioner
                        purchased about 3 yrs &amp; 4 <choice>
                            <abbr>mo</abbr>
                            <expan>months</expan>
                        </choice> years since, then a baby the supposed child of
                            <persName>James</persName>, from <persName>William Yerby</persName> of
                        said <placeName>George Town</placeName> for twenty five dollars; and <hi
                            rend="underline"><persName>Sarah Brooks</persName></hi> he also
                        purchased for Eight hundred and fifty dollars about eighteen months ago from
                            <persName>Isaac Barrett</persName> of said <placeName>Town</placeName>,
                        who had previously purchased the said woman from <persName>Wm.
                            Busey</persName> of said place, in whose family she had been raised in
                            <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Maryland</placeName>.</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons or negroes</seg> was, at the time of said
                    discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">two thousand and
                        five hundred &amp; fifty</seg> dollars in money<del>.</del><seg
                        type="handwritten">;</seg><note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3"
                        >Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the
                        same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily
                        infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">namely&#8212;for said <hi rend="underline"
                                ><persName>James Somerville</persName></hi>, fifteen hundred
                        dollars; for whom two years ago he could readily obtained two thousand
                        dollars: he is a healthy, steady, useful man; obliging, diligent and honest;
                        is a good gardener and florist&#8212;also a good cook; but his chief
                        business is the charge of petitioner's garden and green-house, which are
                        extensive: <hi rend="underline"><persName>Mary Brooks</persName></hi> is
                        worth what petitioner gave for her&#8212;viz&#8212;eight hundred and fifty
                        dollars; she is a good house-servant, and has been kept at home, and
                        occupied in the duties of the family: the child, <hi rend="underline"
                                ><persName>Mary Somerville</persName></hi> he considers worth one
                        hundred and fifty dollars. He knows of no moral, mental, or bodily infirmity
                        or defect in said persons, and believes none to exist</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons or
                        negroes</seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Jno L Kidwell</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00435.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>John L. Kidwell</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Jno L Kidwell</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-23">
                            <seg type="handwritten">23</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>. </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Jenkins Thomas</persName> J Peace</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>435</ab>
                <ab>
                    <persName>John L. Kidwell's</persName> Petition. </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-26">May 26, 1862</date>
                </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
