<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.01098">
    <teiHeader>   
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Lloyd Brooke, 19 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt> 
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.01098</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>   
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Lloyd Brooke, 19 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-19">June 19, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Lloyd Brooke, 19 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-19">June 19, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>            
        </fileDesc>   
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Lloyd Brooke</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Matthew Paul Deady</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-07-02" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-27" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.01098.001.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of
                    April 1862</date> entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or
                    labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner <persName>Lloyd Brooke</persName> of <placeName>Fort Vancouver Washington Territory</placeName> by this, his petition in writing represents and states that he is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName> who at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress held a claim to service or labor against a colored person of African descent of the name of <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName> for and during her life, and that by said act of Congress she was discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor, that at the time of said discharge she was of the age about twenty one years, and that not having seen her since the year <date when="1848">1848</date>, your petitioner cannot give a description of her person so as to identify her, but he refers to his brother <persName>Edmund H Brooke</persName> of <placeName>Washington City</placeName> who can give such description of her as may be required. That your petitioner's claim to the service of the said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName>, and to her labor, was by devise
                    
             <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.01098.002.jpg"/>
                and bequest from his mother <persName>H M Brooke</persName> deceased late of <placeName>Montgomery County Maryland</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>That your petitioners claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of eight hundred dollars in money. He has no knowledge of any infirmity or defect which impairs the value here stated, and refers to such description as may be furnished by said <persName>Edmund H Brooke</persName> for all particulars.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner also states in explanation, that he acquired his right to the service and labor of said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName> as a gift from his mother, when said <persName>Kitty</persName> was quite young, that he left her with her mother, and that in the disposition of her property made prior to the death of his mother, she repeated and recognized the ownership and right of your petitioner to said service and labor, which was assented to and recognized by the other members of his mother's family; Your Petitioner was informed that said <persName>Kitty</persName> at the time of the passage of said act was hired 
                    
              <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.01098.003.jpg"/>      
                    to service in said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></p>
                    <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that he bears true and faithful allegiance to the government of the <placeName>United States</placeName> and that he has not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges that he has not brought said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act, and that at the time of the passage thereof said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName>, as he was informed and believes was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges that his said claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine
                    
              <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.01098.004.jpg"/>      
                    
                    the validity of his said claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName> herein above set forth, and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>
                
                <closer>
                   <signed><persName>L Brooke</persName> <lb/>
                    Petitioner</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I <persName>Lloyd Brooke</persName> of <placeName>Fort Vancouver Washington Territory</placeName> being duly sworn do depose and say that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition as of my own knowledge are true in substance and in fact and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>L Brooke</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">                    
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-19">19th day of June AD 1862</date>.</p>
                <closer>
                     <signed><persName>M. P. Deady</persName> Judge U.S. District Court <placeName>Oregon</placeName></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.01098.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <opener>
                    <salute><choice><abbr>Hon</abbr><expan>Honorable</expan></choice> <persName>L F Vinton</persName></salute>
                    <salute><choice><abbr>Dr</abbr><expan>Dear</expan></choice> Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I enclose to you as President of the Board of Commissioners, under the act emancipating the slaves of the <placeName>District</placeName>
                <list>
                    <item><hi rend="underline">1</hi> The Petition of <persName>Lloyd Brooke</persName> for his claim for his girl <persName>Kitty Barbour</persName></item>
                    <item><hi rend="underline">2</hi> A power of Attorney to <persName>E H Brooke</persName>, to act for him before your board.</item>
                </list>
                </p>
                <p>Mr <persName>Brooke</persName> is informed that in consequence of his distance and the uncertainty of communication, his brother has already, or may before this reaches you present his claim &#38; the evidence in support of it. I hope
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.01098.006.jpg"/>
                these papers, if what may be and done by him, be not in compliance with your rules, will arrive within the time limited by law for their presentation and within such period as you may extend for such applications</p>
                <p>Trusting you will give such attention to this claim as may be necessary to secure his rights under the law, and I have assured him it would not be less, in consequence of a request to that effect coming from me, and wishing you all success in the discharge of your important and delicate duty,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I remain Your old friend</salute>
                <signed><persName>E Hamilton</persName></signed>
                <dateline><placeName>Portland Oregon</placeName> <date when="1862-06-19">June 19, 1862</date></dateline></closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
