<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00800">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Lucinda S. Matthews, 30 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00800</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Lucinda S. Matthews, 30 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-30">June 30, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Lucinda S. Matthews, 30 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-30">June 30, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Lucinda S. Matthews</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Robert White</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">performed automated check for regular transcriptions and encoding errors and mistakes at facs</change>
            <change when="2013-02-11" who="#kk">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-01-28" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00800.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucinda S. Matthews</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington County D.C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">four</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Susan Jackson</persName> <persName>Ann Jackson</persName> <persName>Matilda Miller</persName> <persName>Frederick Atkinson</persName></seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Susan</persName>, <persName>Ann</persName>, <persName>Matilda</persName> &#38; <persName>Frederick</persName> respectively</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> <del>was</del> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> <del>of</del><seg type="handwritten">&#8212;</seg>and of the personal description<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Susan Jackson</persName> aged seventy years; tall &#38;
                            stout, of a dark <choice>
                                <orig>colour</orig>
                                <reg>color</reg>
                            </choice>&#8212;</item>
                        <item><persName>Ann Jackson</persName> aged Twenty one years; rather small,
                            stout, in <choice>
                                <orig>colour</orig>
                                <reg>color</reg>
                            </choice> a bright mulatto&#8212;</item>
                        <item><persName>Matilda Miller</persName> aged about fifty years; tall and
                            in <choice>
                                <orig>colour</orig>
                                <reg>color</reg>
                            </choice> a bright mulatto.</item>
                        <item><persName>Frederick Atkinson</persName> aged Twenty eight years; well
                            made, very black&#8212;ordinary height</item>
                    </list></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00800.003.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Susan Jackson</persName> was given to your
                        petitioner and her late Husband <persName>Henry C Matthews</persName> of
                        said County &#38; District deceased, by her Father <persName>John S.
                                H<unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">aw</unclear></persName> late of said District deceased, in the year
                            <date when="1821">1821</date>.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Jackson</persName> is the daughter of said
                        <persName>Susan</persName>'s daughter <persName>Mary Jackson</persName>, and
                    was born of said <persName>Mary Jackson</persName>, while a slave owned by the
                    said <persName>Henry C. Matthews</persName>.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Matilda Miller</persName> was purchased by the said
                        <persName>Henry C. Matthews</persName> from the estate of <persName>Henry H.
                        Chapman</persName> late of said District deceased, on the <date
                        when="1822-09-18">18th of September 1822</date>, for Two hundred &#38;
                    seventy-six, as is evidenced by the bill of sale herewith annexed and
                    filed&#8212;</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Frederick Atkinson</persName> was bequeathed to
                    said Henry C. Matthews as residuary legatee by <persName>Alexander
                        Matthews</persName> late of <placeName>Charles County Maryland</placeName>
                    deceased, by his will dated <date when="1842-04-15">April 15th 1842</date> &#38;
                    now on record in the Orphans Court of said <placeName>Charles
                    County</placeName>. All of the before mentioned persons were bequeathed to your
                    said petitioner by the last will &#38; testament of her said Husband
                        <persName>Henry C. Matthews</persName>, submitted to probate <date
                        when="1862-05-10">May 10, 1862</date> by the Orphans Court of
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName> in said District.</ab>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Three thousand four
                        Hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten"
                            ><persName>Susan Jackson</persName> has been your petitioners cook for
                        the past Forty years, and although some what affected by age still performs
                        the duties of cook, with a diligence commendable in the highest degree, and only
                        equalled by her faithfulness to those whom she has served for almost half a
                        century. <persName>Matilda Miller</persName> has been the nurse of all my
                        children, and is now my house servant &#38; seamstress, and is a servant of
                        well-known efficiency.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Jackson</persName> is a sprightly servant who
                    is an expert washerwoman, and house-servant, and is also a good cook &#38; dining room
                    servant.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Frederick Atkinson</persName> is my gardener,
                    hostler, and general attendant about my premises. He is an excellent hand at
                    washing&#8212;and of a good moral character.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten">These servants (with the exception of <persName>Susan
                        Jackson</persName> whose age has impaired her somewhat) have no moral mental
                    or bodily defects which do at all impair their value, but for efficiency,
                    faithfulness, and honesty are well known in this community.</ab>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucinda S Matthews</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00800.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>The undersigned Heirs at Law and residuary legatees of <persName>Henry C.
                            Matthews</persName> late of the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> deceased do hereby assent to all and singular the
                        matters, &#38; things set forth and contained in a petition under "the act
                        entitled an act for the release of certain persons held to service or <choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>" approved <date
                            when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>, signed by <persName>Lucinda S.
                            Matthews</persName> Executrix of said <persName>Henry C.
                            Matthews</persName>, deceased, and now on file in the office of the
                        Commissioners under the act aforesaid, and do hereby pray said Commissioners
                        that this their assent may be annexed to said petition, and that they may be
                        made parties claimant therein, intending that all the statements and <gap
                            reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="9" unit="chars"/> therein
                        made, shall be as binding upon them as if their several names were thereto
                        subscribed, as witness their hands and seals this <date when="1862-10-30"
                            >thirtieth day of October in the year eighteen hundred and
                            sixty-two</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Thomas H. Matthews</persName> seal</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Alex Matthews</persName> seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, <placeName>County of
                            Talbot</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>Before me <persName>John F. Kemp</persName>, a Justice of the Peace for the
                        County &#38; State aforesaid personally appeared <persName>Alexander
                            Matthews</persName> &#38; <persName>Thomas H. Matthews</persName>, who
                        are Known to me, &#38; made oath on the Holy Evangely of almighty God, that
                        the several matters and things set forth &#38; stated in the petition
                        aforesaid, (and of which they declare themselves to be cognizant) as of their
                        own Knowledge &#38; belief are true as stated; and that the several matters
                        &#38; things therein stated or derived from the Knowledge and information of
                        others are true to the best of their Knowledge &#38; belief.</p>
                    <p>Given under my name and seal this <date when="1862-10-30">thirtieth day of
                            October in the year eighteen Hundred and sixty two</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>John F. Kemp</persName>. seal<lb/> Justice of the
                            Peace.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                    <dateline><hi rend="bold"><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName></hi><lb/>
                        <placeName>TALBOT COUNTY</placeName>, Sct.</dateline>
                    <p>I HEREBY CERTIFY <hi rend="italic">that</hi>
                        <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John F Kemp</persName></seg>
                        <hi rend="italic">Esquire, before whom the annexed</hi>
                        <seg type="handwritten">Affidavit</seg>
                        <hi rend="italic">w</hi><seg type="handwritten">as</seg>
                        <hi rend="italic">made, and who has thereto subscribed his name, was at the
                            time of so doing a Justice of the Peace of the <placeName>State of
                                Maryland</placeName>, in and for <placeName>Talbot
                                County</placeName>, duly commissioned and sworn.</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">In Testimony Whereof, I hereto set my hand and affix the
                            seal of the Circuit Court for <placeName>Talbot County</placeName>,
                            this</hi>
                        <date when="1862-10-31"><seg type="handwritten">31st</seg>
                            <hi rend="italic">day of</hi>
                            <seg type="handwritten">October</seg>
                            <hi rend="italic">A. D. 18</hi>
                            <seg type="handwritten">62</seg></date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Saml J. Hopkins</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00800.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Bill of Sale<lb/> from<lb/>
                        <persName>Mary Chapman</persName><lb/> to<lb/>
                        <persName>H C Matthews</persName></ab>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00800.006.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents that I <persName>Mary Chapman</persName> of
                            <placeName>George Town</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, Administratrix of all and singular the goods and <choice>
                            <sic>chattles</sic>
                            <corr>chattels</corr>
                        </choice> rights and credits which were of <persName>Henry H
                            Chapman</persName> at the time of his death, for &#38; in consideration
                        of the sum of Two hundred &#38; seventy six dollars to me in hand paid by
                            <persName>Henry C Matthews</persName> of the Town of District aforesaid
                        at or before the sealing &#38; delivery of these presents to the receipt
                        whereof I the said <persName>Mary Chapman</persName> do hereby acknowledge,
                        have granted bargained and sold and by these presents do grant bargain and
                        sell unto the said <persName>Henry C Matthews</persName> his executors
                        administrators and assigns a certain mulatto girl slave named
                            <persName>Matilda</persName> which said negro girl was sold by me the
                        said <persName>Mary Chapman</persName> Administratrix as aforesaid to the
                        said <persName>Henry C Matthews</persName> on the <date when="1822-09-18"
                            >Eighteenth day of September 1822</date> then supposed to be about
                        twelve years of age for the aforesaid sum of Two hundred &#38; seventy six
                        dollars, and has even since been in his possession</p>
                    <p>To have and to hold the said mulatto girl slave named
                            <persName>Matilda</persName> above bargained and sold to the said
                            <persName>Henry C Matthews</persName> his executors administrators and
                        assigns forever against myself administratrix as aforesaid and against all
                        and every person of persons of whatsoever, claiming or to claim the
                        same&#8212;In witness whereof I have hereto subscribed my name and affixed
                        my seal this <date when="1828-10-03">third day of October in the year of our
                            Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty eight</date>&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Mary Chapman</persName> seal</signed><lb/> Witness
                                    <signed><persName><unclear>Rob
                            Getty</unclear></persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00800.007.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName> Sct.</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered that on this <date when="1828-10-03">third day of October in
                            the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty eight</date>
                        personally appears <persName>Mary Chapman</persName> party grantor mentioned
                        in this foregoing instrument of writing before me the subscriber a
                        Justice of the Peace for the County aforesaid and acknowledged the said
                        instrument of writing to be her act and deed, and the mulatto girl slave
                        therein mentioned and thereby bargained and sold to be the right and estate
                        of <persName>Henry C Matthews</persName> party grantee, also therein
                        mentioned his heirs and assigns forever&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Rob Getty</persName> J Peace</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>The word "sight" <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">was interlined</unclear>
                        before the signing and delivery of this bill of sale</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Rob Getty</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00800.008.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucinda S Matthews</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucinda S Matthews</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-30"><seg type="handwritten">30th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Robert White</persName> seal<lb/> J. Peace</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>800</ab>
                <ab>Petition<lb/>
                    of<lb/>
                    <persName>Lucinda S. Matthews</persName><lb/>
                    under<lb/>
                    Emancipation Act.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-30">June 30, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
