<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.01094">
    <teiHeader>   
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Mary Stevenson, 31 October 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt> 
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.01094</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>   
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Mary Stevenson, 31 October 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-10-31">October 31, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Mary Stevenson, 31 October 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-10-31">October 31, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>            
        </fileDesc>   
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Mary Stevenson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Reaver</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-07-02" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-19" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.01094.003.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of
                    April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or
                    labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Stevenson</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Georgetown D.C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Thomas Page</persName>, <persName>Polly Taylor</persName> &amp; child two years old &amp; <persName>Lucy Cary</persName></seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">persons were, respectively</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note> <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Thomas Page</persName>, about 30 yrs of age, about medium height light <choice><orig>coloured</orig><reg>colored</reg></choice>, stout &amp; healthy, <persName>Polly Taylor</persName>, about 20 yrs old, dark, under common size, healthy &amp; very capable; <persName>Lucy Cary</persName>, about 50 yrs old, very light, about the usual height and excellent cook &amp; washerwoman; <persName>Polly</persName>'s child, aged about 2 years,</seg></p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.01094.004.jpg"/>
                
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note> <seg type="handwritten">as widow, of the late <persName>Andrew Stevenson</persName>, who died intestate.</seg></p>
                
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">twenty nine hundred</seg> dollars in money<seg type="handwritten">,</seg><note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note> <seg type="handwritten">i.e., <persName>Thomas</persName>$1500, <persName>Pollie</persName>, $800, <persName>Lucy</persName> $500 &amp; <persName>Pollie</persName>'s child, $100—</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">Your Petitioner was absent from the <placeName>District</placeName> when the time for filing her petition expired, being detained by the illness of her sister who subsequently died, and previously by the difficulty of returning to the <placeName>District</placeName> from <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, that such detention was much against her will &amp; inclination &amp; she availed herself of her first opportunity of returning home.</ab>
                
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>
                
                <closer>
                    (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Stevenson</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.01094.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia,</placeName><lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Stevenson</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Stevenson</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">                    
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-10-30"><seg type="handwritten">30th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">October</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Henry Reaver</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>Petition of</ab>
                <ab><persName>Mrs Stevenson</persName></ab>
                <ab><date when="1862-10-31">Oct 31, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.01094.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><date when="1862-11-03">Now 3, 1862</date></dateline>
                <div2 type="procedural">
                    <ab><persName>Mary Stevenson</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Thomas</persName> 30 on <date when="1862-03-10">10 last March</date>. any kind of work driving. <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="5" unit="chars"/> to house. gardener &amp; driving $17 &amp; board. first rate health. splendid teeth strong 5 ft 10 ½ 175 lbs. Common carpentry work or mason work.</ab>
                    <ab>$1400</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Lucy</persName> 52 (<choice><abbr>Pet</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice> says 50) Cook any thing about house never hired out—as good health as any one of my age. suffered some <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">little</unclear> from Rheumatism. manages house for mistress. <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">drew her and her maid</unclear>. as good bread baker as any one. Cook for a family company—bright mulatto</ab>
                    <ab>$450.</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Polly</persName>. 22. housework. wash &amp; iron. can cook but dont do much. $5 with my baby health &amp; teeth good. no <gap reason="illegible" extent="one or two words" quantity="7" unit="chars"/>. sound</ab>
                    <ab>$1200</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Edward</persName> 9 <choice><abbr>mos</abbr><expan>months</expan></choice> <date when="1862-10-16">16 October</date> (3 months on <date when="1862-04-16">16 April</date>. very healthy.</ab>
                    <ab>50</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Judson Mitchell</persName> I know servant belonged to <choice><abbr>Pet</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice> came through husband. <persName>Mrs S</persName> has one child <gap reason="damage" extent="less than one word" quantity="2" unit="chars"/> years old—I should say <choice><abbr>petr</abbr><expan>petitioner</expan></choice> is loyal lady in favor of Union &amp; <choice><abbr>agt</abbr><expan>against</expan></choice> rebellion. have no doubt of it have talked  with her. went from home to <placeName>Virginia</placeName> &amp; could not get back. I know she made repeated applications to get back through lines. only got back recently &amp; that is <gap reason="illegible" extent="less than one word" quantity="1" unit="chars"/></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Edward Chapman</persName> always understood servants Have not conversed with her Believe her loyal</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>P. T. Berry</persName> Have never conversed with <choice><abbr>Pet</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice> shes been about some 15 or 18  years. Since then I know not <gap reason="illegible" extent="four or five words" quantity="18" unit="chars"/> I have no doubt of her loyalty</ab>
                </div2> 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.01094.002.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="cover">
                    <ab>out of time</ab>
                    <ab><persName>Mary Stevenson</persName></ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
