<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00573">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Philip Mackey, 2 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00573</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Philip Mackey, 2 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Philip Mackey, 2 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Philip Mackey</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Naylor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-13" who="#jc">performed semi-automated file cleanup</change>
            <change when="2013-06-04" who="#nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</change>
            <change when="2013-03-28" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00573.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Philip Mackey</persName></seg>
                    of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington D.C</placeName></seg> by this
                        <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">Six</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of
                    African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Nancy Holmes</persName>, <persName>Irene
                            Holmes</persName>, <persName>Thomas Holmes</persName>, <persName>Wesley
                            Holmes</persName>, <persName>Jefferson Holmes</persName>
                        <persName>Stephen Holmes</persName>,</seg> for and during the life of said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Nancy Holmes</persName>,
                        was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">Twenty Five years,</seg> and
                    of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Copper color woman, Five feet high.</seg>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Irene Holmes</persName>, was of the age of Twenty three
                            years, copper color woman, Five feet high.</item>
                        <item><persName>Thomas Holmes</persName>, was of the age of Six years,
                            Copper color boy Three feet high.</item>
                        <item><persName>Wesley Holmes</persName>, was of the age of Twenty One years
                            Dark copper color man, Five feet six inches high. (marked by the small
                            pox)</item>
                        <item><persName>Jefferson Holmes</persName>, was of the age of Two years
                            Bright mulatto boy, Two feet high.</item>
                        <item><persName>Stephen Holmes</persName>, was of the age of Two years,
                            Bright mulatto boy, Two feet high.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00573.003.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">six persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Nancy</persName>,
                            <persName>Irene</persName>, and <persName>Wesley</persName>, are
                        children of <persName>Harriet</persName> and <persName>Henry
                            Holmes</persName>, who were my slaves willed to me about Twenty Five
                        years since by my mother <persName>Mary Mackey</persName>, as by will
                        recorded in <placeName>Easton, Talbot County, Md</placeName> will
                        appear.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Thomas</persName>, <persName>Jefferson</persName>,
                    and <persName>Stephen</persName>, are children of <persName>Nancy</persName> and
                        <persName>Irene</persName></ab>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Forty three hundred</seg>
                    dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state
                        such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to
                        the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Nancy Holmes</persName>, is an excellent nurse &#38; cook
                            valued at $1000.</item>
                        <item><persName>Irene Holmes</persName>, is an excellent Cook&#8212;valued
                            at $1000</item>
                        <item><persName>Thomas Holmes</persName>, is a smart intelligent boy, valued
                            at $500</item>
                        <item><persName>Wesley Holmes</persName>, is a very industrious faithful
                            servant valued at $1200</item>
                        <item><persName>Jefferson Holmes</persName> is a bright healthy child valued
                            at $300</item>
                        <item><persName>Stephen Holmes</persName> is a bright healthy child valued
                            at $300</item>
                    </list>
                    <seg type="handwritten">I know of no moral mental or bodily infirmities or
                        defects in said servants, they are perfectly sound and healthy</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <ab type="handwritten">At the time of the passage of said Act <persName>Wesley
                        Holmes</persName>, was hired temporarily in <placeName>Montgomery County
                        Md</placeName>, but the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> has been
                    his home <choice>
                        <sic>an</sic>
                        <corr>and</corr>
                    </choice> is now, he is now in the <placeName>District</placeName>.</ab>

                <pb sameAs="leaf001v" facs="cww.00573.004.jpg"/>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Philip
                                Mackey</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00573.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>573</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Columbus Alexander</persName></ab>
                <ab>adverse to claim of "<persName>Philip Mackey</persName>"<lb/>&#8212;protesting
                    against payment, &#38;c&#8212;to be filed with papers in (573.)</ab>
                </div2>

           
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00573.006.jpg"/>            
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>To the <hi rend="underline"><choice>
                                <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                                <expan>Honorable</expan>
                            </choice>. the Commissioners</hi> appointed under the Act of Congress
                        entitled "An Act for the release of certain persons &#38;c. &#38;c. in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>:</p>
                    <p>The Petition of <persName>Columbus Alexander</persName> of the
                            <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> humbly represents, that a
                        certain <persName>Philip Mackey</persName> of said City has filed with the
                        Clerk of your Board a Petition, claiming compensation for six persons of
                        Color&#8212;as by reference to the same will appear. But your Petitioner
                        avers, and can prove, that the said claim is unfounded&#8212;that at the
                        time of the passage of said Act of Congress the said
                            <persName>Mackey</persName> had no interest claim or title, to said
                        persons or shadow of title&#8212;but that the same was fully vested in your
                        Petitioner, and this, he is prepared to prove. Your Petitioner therefore
                        prays that the said presented claim of said <persName>Mackey</persName> may
                        not be allowed. And as in duty &#38;c.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Columbus Alexander</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>A. Lloyd</persName>, Attorney,</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00573.007.jpg"/>                
                <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                    <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>
                    
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                    
                    <div2 type="section">
                        <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Philip Mackey</persName>,</seg> being
                            duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                            are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                            are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                            and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                            I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                        <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Philip
                            Mackey</persName></seg></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div2>
                    
                    <div2 type="section">
                        <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-30"><seg
                            type="handwritten">30<hi rend="underline">th</hi></seg> day of <seg
                                type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                        <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H.
                            Naylor</persName> J. Peace</seg></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div2>
                </div1>
                
                <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                    <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                        been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                        only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                        for the Verification.</note>
                    <ab>573</ab>
                    <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                        <persName>Philip Mackey</persName></ab>
                    <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date></ab>
                    <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                        <persName>George Longley</persName><lb/>
                        <persName>James Longley</persName></ab>
                </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
