<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00371">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Robert P. Dunlop, 22 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
<name xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00371</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Robert P. Dunlop, 22 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Robert P. Dunlop, 22 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Robert P. Dunlop</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Reaver</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-09" who="#crl">checked</change>
<change when="2013-05-07" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-15" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00371.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>To the Honorable the Commissioners appointed by the President of
                        the <placeName>United States</placeName> to carry into effect, the
                        provisions of the Act of Congress, "for the release of certain persons held
                        to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> The
                        Petition of <persName>Robert P. Dunlop</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery
                            County</placeName>, in the <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>,
                            sheweth.</p>
                    
                    <p>That at the time of the passage of the Act of Congress aforesaid, your
                        petitioner was the owner of three slaves, named <persName>Martha
                            Wilson</persName> and her son <persName>Frank Wilson</persName>,
                        residents of the said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, &#38;
                            <persName>Lucy Wilson</persName> also residing in said District, who
                        were held to service or labor within the said <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> by reason of African descents, who were born the
                        slaves of your petitioners, who have all their lives been his slaves, and
                        who have never belonged to any other person. That about twenty years ago,
                        your Petitioner resided in <placeName>Georgetown</placeName> in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> and where he had resided for
                        many years previously, and about that time removed to the <placeName>County
                            of Montgomery</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, where he has ever since lived &#38; now lives.
                        That more than twenty years ago, while he resided in the <placeName>District
                            of Columbia</placeName>, &#38; before his removal to the
                            <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, he hired his said servant woman <persName>Martha</persName> to the late <persName><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">Mrs Whitall</unclear></persName> of
                            <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, in said
                    District in whose family she lived for many years&#8212;That after the
                    expiration of her service in the family of Mrs <persName>Whitall</persName>, the said <persName>Martha
                            Wilson</persName> was hired to Mr <persName>George W. Beall</persName>
                        of <placeName>Georgetown</placeName> in said District and
                    has lived with Mr <persName>Beall</persName> as a domestic in his family for seven or
                        eight years last past. That a few days before the passage of the said Act of
                        Congress, for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> &#38; while said bill was pending in Congress, the said <persName>Martha Wilson</persName>, without
                        the knowledge or consent of your petitioner &#38; as he believes without the
                        consent <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00371.003.jpg"/>or knowledge of Mr
                        <persName>Beall</persName>, left the service of Mr
                        <persName>Beall</persName> and came to the home of your petitioner in
                        the <placeName>County of Montgomery</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, bringing with her, <persName>Frank Wilson</persName>
                        her son, aged seven or eight years, alleging that she was unwell and that she was unwell and that the work assigned for her to do, was too much for her to
                        perform. <persName>Frank Wilson</persName> the son of
                            <persName>Martha</persName>, has always lived in the <placeName>District
                            of Columbia</placeName>, &#38; nearly all his life with Mr.
                            <persName>Beall</persName></p>
                    
                    <p><persName>Martha Wilson</persName> is about forty or forty five years of age,
                        is of African descent was born the slave of your petitioner&#8212;and has
                        never belonged in whole or in part to any other person&#8212;she is about
                        five feet, six inches high, is of black color, is esteemed a good
                        house servant&#8212;having been trained to the performance of its duties, is
                        of good character, honest, &#38; has been well thought of by those with whom
                        she has lived&#8212;&#38; her long service with Mrs <persName>Whitall</persName> &#38; Mr. <persName>Beall</persName> in the
                        judgment of your petitioner proves that&#8212;her son <persName>Frank
                            Wilson</persName> is between seven &#38; eight years of age, is about
                        four feet, five inches high of dark complexion, is smart, intelligent
                        &#38; of good conduct, &#38; healthy</p>
                    
                    <p>Your petitioner is informed &#38; believes that <persName>Martha</persName>
                        &#38; her son <persName>Frank</persName> before the rebellion, would have
                        sold for the sum of one thousand dollars or thereabout&#8212;</p>
                    
                    <p><persName>Lucy Wilson</persName> the sister of
                        <persName>Martha</persName>&#8212;was born the slave of your petitioner, and
                        has always been his slave, no other person or persons having any interest in
                        her&#8212;About five years ago, <persName>Lucy</persName> was placed in the
                        family of his <choice>
                            <sic>neice</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice> Mrs <persName>Lowry</persName> wife of Mr. <persName>George
                            Lowry</persName> of <placeName>Washington</placeName> in the
                            District aforesaid, where she has ever since
                        lived, and by whom she has been carefully brought up as a domestic in their
                        family &#38; by whom she is highly esteemed&#8212;<persName>Lucy</persName>
                        is about twenty one years of age, is about five feet six or seven inches
                        high, is of dark complexion of good character, intelligent. well acquainted
                        with the duties of a house servant, and is a first-rate family servant, of
                        great <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00371.002.jpg"/>value, and would as
                        your petitioner believes, before the rebellion, have sold for from eight
                        hundred to one thousand dollars&#8212;is sound &#38; healthy&#8212;</p>
                    
                    <p>Your petitioner declares that the said slaves have not been brought into the
                        said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> after the passage of this
                        Act, nor is the claim for said slaves or either of them, made for or by any
                        person who has borne arms against the government of the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName> in the present rebellion, or in any way given aid or
                        comfort thereto, nor does the said claim now made, originate in or by virtue
                        of any transfer heretofore made, or which shall hereafter be made, by any
                        person who has in any manner aided or sustained the rebellion against the
                        government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212;but that your
                        petitioner is the sole and exclusive owner of said slave, and that no other
                        person is now or has ever been interested in said slaves</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner further declares his allegiance to the government of the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has not borne arms
                        against the <placeName>United States</placeName> during the present
                        rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto</p>

                    <closer>All which is respectfully submitted
                        <signed><persName>Robert P. Dunlop</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div1>
                    
                <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                    <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, <placeName>Washington
                    County</placeName>. Sct</dateline>
                        
                    <p>On this <date when="1862-05-22">twenty Second day of May in the year
                            eighteen hundred &#38; sixty two</date>, before the subscriber one of
                        the Justices of the Peace in &#38; for the county &#38; District aforesaid
                        personally appears <persName>Robert P. Dunlop</persName> named in the
                        foregoing Petition &#38; makes oath that the matters &#38; things set forth in the
                        foregoing Petition from his own knowledge are true &#38; the matters &#38;
                        things, stated from the information of others, he believes to be true.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Robert P. Dunlop</persName></signed></closer>
                    </div2>
                    
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Subscribed and sworn before me this day and year above written</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Henry Reaver</persName> J Peace</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                </div1>
           
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00371.004.jpg"/>            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>371</ab>
                <ab><persName>Robert P. Dunlop</persName>.</ab>
                <ab>Petition for value of three slaves under the Act of Congress</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>George Lowry</persName></ab>
                <ab><persName>George W. Beall</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
