<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00322">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Joseph Bryan, Trustee for Louisa Bryan, 20 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00322</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Joseph Bryan, Trustee for Louisa Bryan, 20 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-20">May 20, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Joseph Bryan, Trustee for Louisa Bryan, 20 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-20">May 20, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Louisa Bryan</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Joseph Bryan</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John S. Hollingshead</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">revised encoding for handwritten signature blocks</change>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-07" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-03-12" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00322.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Joseph Bryan</persName>
                        Trustee for <persName>Louisa Bryan</persName></seg> of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington City DC</placeName></seg> by this
                        <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">a</seg> person of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName> together with her two male
                        children aged respectively <persName>Robert</persName> about four years and
                            <persName>John</persName> (18, Eighteen months old</seg> for and during
                    the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <sic>an</sic>
                            <corr>and</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>John</persName></seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <sic>an</sic>
                            <corr>and</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>John</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and from all
                    claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName> was</seg> of
                    the age of <seg type="handwritten">25, Twenty-five years</seg> and of the
                    personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">The said <persName>Delia</persName> being of dark Colour
                        four feet and eleven inches high, stout and well built and sound and healthy
                        is a good cook washer and Ironer honest and reliable house
                            servant&#8212;<persName>Robert</persName> at the time of his discharge
                        was of the age of (4) four years is a mulatto and slim and healthy; and
                            <persName>John</persName>, was of the age of Eighteen months is about
                        the same colour and sound and healthy</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00322.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName> and <persName>Robert</persName></seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By Bill of Sale from <persName>James S Holland</persName> Executor of <persName>Ann Holland</persName> deceased
                        of the <placeName>City of Anapolis</placeName> <placeName>County of Ann Arundel</placeName>
                        <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName> dated the <date when="1859-05-19">19th day of May 1859</date> when the said
                            <persName>Delia</persName> was of the age of Twenty Two Years, and
                            <persName>John</persName> was born since said claim to
                            <persName>Delia</persName> was acquired</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName> together with her two
                        children</seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of
                        <seg type="handwritten">Twelve hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">Your petitioner avers that the said
                            <persName>Delia</persName> by reason of her honesty intelligence
                        industry and other good qualities was very valuable as a house servant I now
                        give said <persName>Delia</persName>
                        Eight dollars a month as hire for her services and board, her and her two
                        children, and she has no mental or bodily infirmities or defects which would
                        impair her value and was offered Twelve hundred dollars for her before her
                        last child <persName>John</persName> was born</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName>, and <persName>John</persName></seg> into the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName> and <persName>John</persName></seg> was held to
                    service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such
                    service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName> &#38; <persName>John</persName></seg> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                    the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Delia</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName> and <persName>John</persName></seg> herein above
                    set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to
                    the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>(Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> Trustee</seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00322.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents, that, I, <persName>James S.
                            Holland</persName> of the <placeName>City of Washington D.C.</placeName>
                        executor of the estate of <placeName>Ann Holland</placeName> deceased, late
                        of the <placeName>City of Annapolis</placeName>, <placeName>County of Anne Arundell</placeName>; <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, for and in consideration of the sum of nine hundred and fifty dollars current money,
                        to me in hand paid by <persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> Trustee for
                            <persName>Louisa Bryan</persName> of the <placeName>City of Washington
                            D.C.</placeName> at or before the sealing and delivery of these
                        presents, the receipt whereof I, the said <persName>James S.
                            Holland</persName>, executor, do hereby acknowledge, have bargained and
                        sold, transferred and assigned, and by these presents do bargain and sell,
                        transfer and assign unto the said <persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> trustee
                        for <persName>Louisa Bryan</persName>, her heirs, executors, administrators
                        and assigns, a negro slave woman named <persName>Delia</persName>, now aged
                        about twenty-two years, together with her infant male child aged about eight
                        months, for life, together with all my right, title, interest claim and
                        demand of, in, and to the said negro slave woman and male infant child; to
                        have and to hold the said negro slave woman and infant male child above
                        bargained and sold, or intended so to be, to the said <persName>Joseph
                            Bryan</persName> trustee for <persName>Louisa Bryan</persName>, her
                        heirs, executors, and administrators and assigns forever.</p>
                    <p>And, I the said <persName>James S. Holland</persName> executor, for myself,
                        my heirs, executors, administrators and assigns, all and singular, warrant
                        the said negro slave woman and her infant male child unto the said
                            <persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> trustee for <persName>Louisa
                            Bryan</persName>, her heirs, executors, administrators and assigns,
                        against any right, title, claim or demand by me the said <persName>James S.
                            Holland</persName>, executor, my heirs, executors, administrators and
                        assigns, and against the right, title, claim or demand of all and every
                        person or persons whatsoever, shall and will warrant, and defend by these
                        presents.</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal this <date when="1859-05-19">nineteenth day of May,
                            one thousand, eight hundred and fifty-nine</date>. 7th. 13th 23d and
                        29th <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#jc">lines</unclear> "<persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> trustee
                        for" interlined</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>James S. Holland</persName>
                            <choice><abbr>Execor</abbr><expan>Executor</expan></choice> Seal</signed><lb/>
                        Witness
                        <signed><persName>Thomas C Donn</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>On this <date when="1859-05-19">19th day of May, in the year of our Lord one
                            thousand, eight hundred and fifty-nine</date>, personally appeared
                        before me the subscriber, a justice of the peace in and for the
                            <placeName>City of Washington D.C.</placeName>
                        <persName>James S. Holland</persName>, executor, the party grantor, and
                        acknowledged <lb/> (over) <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00322.004.jpg"/>the foregoing
                        bill of sale to be his act and deed for the purposes therein mentioned.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName><lb/>
                        Justice of the Peace for <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc"><placeName><choice><abbr>WCDC</abbr><expan>Washington County District of Columbia</expan></choice></placeName></unclear></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00322.005.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi><lb/><date
                        when="1862-05-19">May 19th, 1862</date></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Joseph Bryan</persName></seg>
                        being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things
                        which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own
                        knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other
                        matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of
                        others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> Trustee</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-12"><seg type="handwritten">12th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>John S
                                    Hollingshead</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>322</ab>
                <ab><persName>Joseph Bryan</persName> Trustee<lb/>
                    for <persName>Louisa Bryan</persName></ab>

                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-20">May 20, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Wm D. Baldwin</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>James S. Holland</persName> <address><addrLine>9th near <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">H</unclear></addrLine></address></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
