<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00102">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Benjamin T. Thorn, 8 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                    <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00102</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Benjamin Thorn, 8 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-08">May 8, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Benjamin Thorn, 8 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-14">May 8, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775&#8211;1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Benjamin Thorn</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName> B. W. Ferguson </persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-07-09" who="#jc">checked transcription for the first page and
                published revised petition</change>
            <change when="2013-06-18" who="#nnk">added transcription for the first page</change>
            <change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-04-05" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-30" who="#scl">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-02-15" who="#el">automated checking across files for extra spaces in
                elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription
                errors</change>
            <change when="2012-02-14" who="#el">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary</change>
            <change when="2012-01-09" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-09-09" who="#bj">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-28" who="#rv">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00102.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Benjamin T.
                        Thorn</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington
                            D.C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">Six</seg> person<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Emily Dison</persName>, <persName>Ann
                            Dyson</persName>, <persName>Delilah Dison</persName>, <persName>Thomas
                            Dison</persName>, <persName>Benjamin Dison</persName>, &#38;
                            <persName>John H. Hawkins</persName>.</seg> for and during the life of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">persons above named</seg> and that by said act of
                    Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons above named are</seg> discharged
                    and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor;
                    that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">persons above
                        named were respectively</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of
                        <seg type="handwritten">37 years, 20 years, 17 years, 14 years, 8 years,
                        &#38; 34 years</seg> and of the personal description following:<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as
                        to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each
                        one separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Emily Dison</persName>, thirty seven years of age. Dark
                            Color, likely person, <choice>
                                <sic>Excelent</sic>
                                <corr>Excellent</corr>
                            </choice> Cook Washer &#38; Ironer. A valuable woman, but occasionally
                            suffers with Rheumatism, eight hundred dollars, $800.00</item>
                        <item><persName>Ann Dison</persName>, twenty years of age, Black Color,
                            Sound &#38; healthy, a good and valuable servant, sometimes a little
                            deaf, worth one thousand dollars.</item>
                        <item><persName>Delilah Dison</persName>, seventeen years of age, Dark
                            Color, Sound &#38; healthy, a likely girl and fine servant, worth one
                            thousand dollars.</item>
                        <item><persName>Thomas Dison</persName>, Fourteen years of age, Dark Color,
                            Sound &#38; healthy, and a first rate boy. worth eight hundred
                            dollars.</item>
                        <item><persName>Benjamin Dison</persName>, eight years of age, sound &#38;
                            healthy, a sprightly lad, &#38; promised to make a good servant. worth
                            Five hundred dollars.</item>
                        <item><persName>John H. Hawkins</persName>, age thirty four years, black
                            color, sound, healthy &#38; well formed, a fine man and very valuable
                            servant. Worth fourteen hundred dollars</item>
                    </list></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00102.001.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"> Persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">he inherited the Said persons at the death of his Father
                            <persName>Alexander A. Thorn</persName> of <placeName>St. Mary's County
                            D.C.</placeName>
                    </seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Persons</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg
                        type="handwritten">Fifty five hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"> Your petitioner would not have sold his servants at the
                        price above named. Said persons have always been well used and are more than
                        ordinarily intelligent. Your petitioner has no knowledge of any other
                        infirmities than those named in the cases of <persName>Emily</persName>
                        &#38; <persName>Ann</persName>.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">said persons</seg>
                    into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said
                    act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was held to service or labor therein under
                    and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"> persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"> persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Benjamin T. Thorn</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00102.002.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="handwritten">
                <ab>102 Copy <lb/> Revaluation &#38; Division<lb/> Of Negroes of<lb/>
                    <persName>Alexander A. Thorn</persName>
                </ab>
                <ab>no. 102 <lb/> Claim <persName>B. T. Thorn</persName> under Act <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16 April 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>The clerk will please file the proper evidence in above case <persName>R. T.
                        Morrell</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Atty</abbr>
                        <expan>Attorney</expan>
                    </choice> for Petitioner</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date>
                </ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00102.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Revaluation &#38; Division of Negroes <persName>Alexander A.
                            Thorn</persName>
                    </ab>
                    <p>The State of <placeName>Maryland</placeName> At an Orphan's Court held for
                            <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName> at the Court house in
                            <placeName>Leonard Town</placeName> on the <date when="1842-11-29">29th
                            day of November in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and
                            forty two.</date>
                    </p>
                    <signed> Present <persName>R. H. Miles</persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <persName>C. Billingsley</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>Esqrs.</abbr>
                            <expan>Esquires</expan>
                        </choice><lb/>
                        <persName>S. H. Gough</persName> Sheriff <persName>G. Combs</persName>
                        Register </signed>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Among other proceedings were the following To wit An Application of
                            <persName>Ann M. Thorn</persName> &#38; <persName>S. W. Dent</persName>
                        Administrators of <persName>Alexander A. Thorn</persName> late of
                            <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName> deceased, It is ordered by
                        the court that <persName>John F. Dent</persName> and <persName>Henry
                            Mattingly</persName> be appointed to revalue and divide the negroes of
                        the said deceased among the legal representatives of the deceased, each of
                        them having first taken the oath hereto annexed a certificate where of they
                        are to return annexed to the said revaluation and Division.</p>
                    <p>Lest <persName>G. Combs</persName> Register of Wills, <placeName>St. Mary's
                            County</placeName> The <persName>John F. Dent</persName> and
                            <persName>Henry Mattingley</persName> do swear that we will, well and
                        truly without partiality or prejudice value and divide the negro slaves of
                            <persName>Alexander A. Thorn</persName> late of <placeName>Saint Mary's
                            County</placeName> deceased, so far as the same shall come to our sight
                        and knowledge and will in all respects execute the above warrant to the best
                        of our skill and judgement. So help us God.</p>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>J. F. Dent</persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <persName>Henry Mattingly</persName>
                        <lb/> Commissioners</signed>
                </div2>

                <div2>
                    <p>I hereby certify that the aforegoing oath was taken and subscribed to by the
                        said <persName>J. F. Dent</persName> and <persName>Henry
                            Mattingly</persName> before the undersigned a Justice of the peace for
                            <placeName>St. Mary's County</placeName> duly commissioned and qualified
                        according to Law this <date when="1842-12-03">third of December 1842</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>H. D. Swann</persName> Justice of the Peace </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>


                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00102.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <salute>To the Honorable Judges of the Orphan's Court of <placeName>St. Mary's
                            County</placeName>
                    </salute>
                    <p>We the undersigned commissioners named in a commission from the Orphan's
                        Court of <placeName>St. Mary's County</placeName> to revalue and divide the
                        negroes of <persName>Alexander A. Thorn</persName> deceased after having
                        first taken the oath annexed to said commission proceeded to revalue and
                        divide said negroes as follows <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Revaluation</cell>
                                <cell>Original <choice>
                                        <abbr>appt.</abbr>
                                        <expan>appointment</expan>
                                    </choice></cell>
                                <cell><choice>
                                        <abbr>Reappmt.</abbr>
                                        <expan>Reappointment</expan>
                                    </choice></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Negro man <persName>Lawson</persName> aged 46 years</cell>
                                <cell>$445.00</cell>
                                <cell>$250.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" " <persName>Elder John</persName> " 44 "</cell>
                                <cell>500.00</cell>
                                <cell>325.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" " <persName>Charles</persName> " 37 "</cell>
                                <cell>600.00</cell>
                                <cell>400.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" " <persName>Younger John</persName> " 15 "</cell>
                                <cell>550.00</cell>
                                <cell>400.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" " <persName>Henry</persName> " 41 "</cell>
                                <cell>400.00</cell>
                                <cell>250.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Elizabeth</persName> " 41" (unhealthy)</cell>
                                <cell>250.00</cell>
                                <cell>175.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Emily</persName> " 19 " </cell>
                                <cell>550.00</cell>
                                <cell>325.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Sally Maria</persName> " 6 " </cell>
                                <cell>75.00</cell>
                                <cell>175.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Richard</persName> " 4 increase</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>175.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>George</persName> " 2</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>150.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Mary</persName> " 1</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>50.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Henry</persName> " 3</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>150.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Ann</persName> " 19 mos.</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>75.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>" <persName>Robert</persName> " 8 years</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>250.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>3375.00</cell>
                                <cell>3150.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Loss</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>225.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>3375.00</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table> We then proceeded to divide said negroes between the widow and two
                        children of the deceased,</p>
                    <p>Lot No. 1 We have given to the widow of the deceased, Consisting of <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Elizabeth</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>$175.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Elder John</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>325.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Sally Maria</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>175.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Robert</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>250.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Henry</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>150.00</cell>
                                <cell>$1075.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>This Lot shall pay to lot No. 2</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>25.00 </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>$1050.00 </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>


                    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00102.005.jpg"/>

                    <p>Lot No 2 we have given to <persName>Matild Thorn</persName> a daughter of the
                        deceased consisting of <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Henry</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>$250.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Charles</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>400.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Mary</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>50.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>George</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>150.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Richard</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>175.00</cell>
                                <cell>$1025.00</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>Lot No 3 we have given to <persName>Benjamin Thorn</persName> A son of the
                        deceased consisting of <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Emily</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>325.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Younger John</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>400.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Ann</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>75.00</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName>Lawson</persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>250.00</cell>
                                <cell>1050.00</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>Given under our hands and seals this <date when="1843-08-08">eighth day of
                            August 1843</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>J. F. Dent</persName> seal<lb/>
                            <persName>Henry Mattingly</persName> seal Commissioners</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>


                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell><persName>J. F. Dent</persName></cell>
                                <cell>1 Day</cell>
                                <cell>$2.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Making report</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>2.00 </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><persName>H. Mattingly</persName></cell>
                                <cell>1 Day</cell>
                                <cell>2.00</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>$6.00</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        <placeName>State of Maryland, Saint Mary's County</placeName> to wit I
                        hereby certify that the aforegoing is a true copy taken from the Original as
                        filed in the Orphan's Court of <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName>
                    </p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed the seal of the
                        Orphan's Court of <placeName>St. Mary's County</placeName> this <date
                            when="1862-07-10">10th day of July 1862</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>Jas. T. M. Rally</persName> Regs of Wills<lb/> for St. Mary's
                            County </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00102.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Benjamin T. Thorn</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Benjamin T. Thorn</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-08">
                            <seg type="handwritten">8th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A.D. 1862</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>B. M. Ferguson</persName> J.P. </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>102<lb/> Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Benjamin T. Thorn</persName>
                </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-08">May 8, 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>
                    <persName>Isaac Bassett</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>R. T. McLain</persName>
                </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
