<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00243">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Frederick Godfray Hesse, 15 May
                    1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
                    <name xml:id="cg">Courtney Geerhart</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00243</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Frederick Godfray Hesse, 15 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Frederick Godfray Hesse, 15 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Frederick Godfray Hesse</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Hillary C. Spalding</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">revised transcription order</change>
            <change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
            <change when="2012-09-19" who="#scl">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-08-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2011-09-02" who="#cg">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-04-20" who="#rr">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-20" who="#rv">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00243.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>F. G. Hesse</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington City, D.C.</placeName>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">the following</seg> person<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Julia Smallwood</persName>, <persName>Ann Smallwood</persName>,
                            <persName>Henrietta Smallwood,</persName>
                        <persName>Lucy Smallwood</persName>, <persName>Mary Smallwood</persName>,
                            <persName>William Smallwood</persName>, <persName>Nelly
                            Smallwood</persName>, <persName>Henry Smallwood</persName>,
                            <persName>Fanny Smallwood</persName>, <persName>Bernard
                            Smallwood</persName>,&amp; <persName>William Thomas</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons above
                        named</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"
                        >persons above named were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim
                    of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten">persons held to service or labor by your petitioner
                        were respectively</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <space
                        atLeast="1"/> and of the personal description following:<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as
                        to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each
                        one separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Julia Smallwood</persName>, about 56 years of age, colour
                            Mulatto, good house servant.</item>
                        <item><persName>Ann Smallwood</persName>, about 22 years of age, very
                            valuable, first class servant in all respects. </item>
                        <item><persName>Henrietta Smallwood</persName>, aged about 20 years, good
                            house servant, &amp; generally useful.</item>
                        <item><persName>Mary Smallwood</persName>, about 16 years Perfectly healthy,
                            and a useful servant.</item>
                        <item><persName>William Smallwood</persName>, about 14 years of age, Stout
                            healthy active boy.</item>
                        <item><persName>Nelly Smallwood</persName>, about 12 years old, sound,
                            healthy &amp; smart girl.</item>
                        <item><persName>Henry Smallwood</persName>, about 10 years old, smart,
                            lively, active boy.</item>
                        <item><persName>Fanny Smallwood</persName>, about 8 yrs old, Bright, lively
                            child.</item>
                        <item><persName>Bernard Smallwood</persName>, about 6 years old, fine
                            healthy child.</item>
                        <item><persName>William Thomas</persName>, aged about 32 years, light brown
                            colour, very valuable, faithful, devoted and reliable servant.</item>
                    </list>
                    <seg type="handwritten">All the above enumerated servants are in <choice>
                            <orig>colour</orig>
                            <reg>color</reg>
                        </choice> varying from light mulattoes to dark copper <choice>
                            <orig>colours</orig>
                            <reg>colors</reg>
                        </choice>, none of them being what is usually termed black.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00243.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">to wit: by his marriage with their mistress,
                            <persName>Mary Camilla Spalding</persName> his present wife.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">servants</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">10250.</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
                    <space atLeast="1"/>
                </p>


                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">slaves</seg> into the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">slaves were</seg> held to service or labor therein under
                    and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">slaves</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">Slaves</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>F. G. Hesse</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>            

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00243.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In the name of God Amen. I <persName>John Spalding</persName> of
                            <placeName>Charles County in the State of Maryland</placeName> being
                        sick and weak in body, but of sound &amp; disposing mind memory and
                        understanding, considering the uncertainty of life, but the certainty of
                        death and the uncertainty of the time thereof, do make and publish this my
                        last will and testament in manner and form following:&#8212;</p>
                    <p><choice>
                            <sic>Inprimis</sic>
                            <corr>Imprimis</corr>
                        </choice>&#8212;I commend my soul to almighty God, and direct that my body
                        be decently buried at the discretion of my executors hereinafter named</p>
                    <p>And as to such worldly estate as it hath pleased God to intrust me with I
                        dispose of the same as follows:</p>
                    <p>First&#8212;I direct that all my death and funeral expenses be paid as soon
                        after my decease as possible, out of the first moneys that shall come into
                        the hands of my executors from any portion of my estate.</p>
                    <p>Item. I give and devise to my dear son <persName>Basil William
                            Spalding</persName> &amp;his heirs forever all that tract or parcel of
                        land upon which I now reside, commonly called "Pleasant Hill" Containing
                        about three hundred and forty acres more or less; also one piece of road
                        land being part of "Green's Inheritance" containing about thirty acres and
                        lying, detached from my residence on the main road leading from
                            <placeName>Port Tobacco</placeName> to <placeName>Piscatawny</placeName>
                        and also one hundred and fifty acres of my woodland lying in
                            <placeName>Panguya</placeName> most convenient to "Pleasant Hill"
                        aforesaid, the said one hundred and fifty acres to be laid out by and under
                        direction of my executors.</p>
                    <p>Item&#8212;I give and devise all the rest and residence of my real estate to
                        by two daughters, <persName>Mary Camilla Spalding</persName> and
                            <persName>Ann Caroline Spalding</persName>, to them and their heirs
                        forever, share and share alike </p>
                    <p>Item&#8212;I give and bequeath unto my daughter <persName>Mary Camilla
                            Spalding</persName> negro man <persName>Williams</persName>, negro woman
                            <persName>Julia</persName> and her four children
                            <persName>Ann</persName>, <persName>Henry</persName>,
                            <persName>Lucy</persName> &amp; <persName>Mary</persName>, and all the
                        natural increase of the said Julia after the date hereof.</p>
                    <p>Item&#8212;I give and bequeath to my daughter <persName>Ann Caroline
                            Spalding</persName>, negroes <persName>Mary</persName>,
                            <persName>Adam</persName>, <persName>Lewis</persName>,
                            <persName>Eliza</persName> and her child <pb xml:id="leaf003v"
                            facs="cww.00243.006.jpg"/>
                        <persName>James</persName>, and all the natural increase of the said
                            <persName>Eliza</persName> from the date hire of</p>
                    <p>Item&#8212;I give and bequeath to my son <persName>Basil William
                            Spalding</persName> negroes <persName>Jacob</persName>,
                            <persName>Jim</persName>, <persName>Ross</persName>,
                            <persName>Sam</persName>, <persName>Peter</persName>
                        <persName>Margaret</persName> and <persName>Nanny</persName>, the daughter
                        of a negro woman, now dead, called <persName>Sarah</persName></p>

                    <p>Item&#8212;I give and bequeath all the rest of my personal property of every
                        description whatsoever to my said three children, <persName>Mary
                            Camilla</persName>, <persName>Ann Caroline</persName>, and
                            <persName>Basil William</persName> share and share alike.</p>

                    <p>And I will and appoint that my much esteemed friend <persName>Francis C.
                            Green</persName> shall have the tuition and guardianship of my dear
                        children aforesaid during their minority; and I earnestly <choice>
                            <sic>intreat</sic>
                            <corr>entreat</corr>
                        </choice> his utmost kindness and affection towards them this greatest care
                        in and about their morals and education.</p>

                    <p>And lastly&#8212;I do constitute my esteemed friends <persName>George
                            Brent</persName> and <persName>Francis C Green</persName> executors of
                        this my last will and testament, hereby revoking all former wills by me
                        heretofore made, ratifying and confirming this and none other as and for my
                        this and sole last will and testament. In testimony whereof I have hereunto
                        set my hand and affixed my seal this <date when="1847-12-13">thirteenth day
                            of December in the year of our Lord eighteen hundred and forty
                            seven</date> signed, sealed published and declared by <persName>John
                            Spalding</persName> the above named testator as and for his last will
                        and testament in the presence of us, who at his request and in his presence
                        and int eh presence of each other, have subscribed our names as witnesses
                        thereto</p>

                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Robt Fergusson</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>James L. Hicks</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Joseph Stevens</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Jno Spalding</persName> seal </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <opener>At the foot of the aforegoing will it is thus written; <pb
                            xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00243.007.jpg"/>
                        <dateline><placeName>Charles County</placeName> Sct: <date when="1848-03-07"
                                >March 7th 1848</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>Then came <persName>James L Hicks</persName> and <persName>Robert
                            Fergusson</persName> two of the subscribing witnesses to the within and
                        aforegoing last will and testament of <persName>John Spalding</persName>
                        late of <placeName>Charles County</placeName> deceased and made oath on the
                        Holy evangely of almighty God that they did see the testator therein named
                        sign and seal this will and that they heard him publish pronounce and
                        declare the same to his last will and testament and at the time of his so
                        doing he was to the best of their apprehensions of sound and disposing mind
                        memory and understanding and that they together with <persName>Joseph
                            Stewart</persName> the other witness respectively subscribed their names
                        as witnesses to this will in the presence and at the request of the testator
                        and in the presence of each other</p>
                    <closer>Test: <signed><persName>D Jenifer <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low"
                                    resp="#jc">Regrofroiles</unclear></persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><placeName>Charles County</placeName> Sct: <date when="1848-04-04">April 4th
                            1848</date> Then came <persName>George Brent</persName> &amp;
                            <persName>Francis C Green</persName> executors of the testament and last
                        will of <persName>John Spalding</persName> late of <placeName>Charles
                            County</placeName> deceased and made oath on the Holy evangely of
                        almighty God that the aforegoing instrument of writing is the true and whole
                        last will and testament of said deceased that hath come their hands or
                        possession and that they do not know of any other</p>
                    <closer>Test: <signed><persName>D Jenifer <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low"
                                    resp="#jc">Regrofroiles</unclear></persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00243.008.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <opener><placeName>State of Maryland<lb/> Charles County</placeName>
                        Sct:</opener>
                    <p>In Testimony that the within and aforegoing is a true copy taken from one of
                        the record books of the Orphans Court for Charles County</p>
                    <p>I have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed the seal of the said court,
                        this <date when="1862-05-13">thirteenth day of May in the year of our Lord
                            Eighteen hundred and Sixty two</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>J. D. Carpinter</persName>, Register of Wills<lb/> for
                                <placeName>Charles County</placeName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00243.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                    Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Frederick Godfrey Hesse</persName>
                    </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>F. G. Hesse</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-12">
                        <seg type="handwritten">12th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>. </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>H. G. Spalding</persName> J. Peace</seg>
                    </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>243<lb/>
                    <persName>Frederick Godfrey Hesse</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
