<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00813">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Charles H. Wiltberger, 30 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00813</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Charles H. Wiltberger, 30 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-30">June 30, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Charles H. Wiltberger, 30 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-30">June 30, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Charles H. Wiltberger</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Naylor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-13" who="#jc">performed semi-automated file cleanup</change>
            <change when="2013-05-31" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-04-15" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00813.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April 1862</date> entitled "an act for the release
                    of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>"..</p>

                <p>Your petitioner <persName>Charles H. Wiltberger</persName> of the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> by this his petition in writing,
                    represents and states, that he is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said Act of
                    Congress held a claim to service or labor against the following described
                    persons of African descent of the names of, <persName>William
                    Hawkins</persName>, <persName>Margaret Guttridge</persName>, <persName>Cornelius
                        Guttridge</persName> and <persName>Sarah
                        Frances Guttridge</persName> for and
                    during the life of said <persName>Margaret</persName>,
                        <persName>Cornelius</persName> and <persName>Sarah</persName>; and for a
                    term of years ending the <date when="1864-02-14">14th day of February
                        1864</date>. of said <persName>William Hawkins</persName>; and that by said
                    Act of Congress said persons were discharged and freed of and from all claim of
                    your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said persons were of the ages and of the personal description as follows:</p>
                <list>
                    <item><persName>William Hawkins</persName> a dark Chestnut Colored man of
                        pleasant Countenance about five feet ten inches in stature and twenty-nine
                        years two months of age..</item>
                    <item><persName>Margaret Guttridge</persName> a bright mulatto girl thick lips
                        straight hair, and fifteen years seven months of age:</item>
                    <item><persName>Cornelius Guttridge</persName> a sprightly boy of dark skin,
                        wool head, and bright eyes; ten years one month of age:</item>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00813.002.jpg"/>
                    <item><persName>Sarah Frances Guttridge</persName> a girl, of yellow skin, Curly
                        head, and large bright eyes; eight years eight months of age:.</item>
                </list>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired his claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said
                    persons in manner following:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Of the said <persName>William Hawkins</persName> by will of
                            <persName>Rebecca Burch</persName> duly recorded in the Register of Will
                        Office an extract of which duly certified is herewith filed:</item>
                    <item>Of the said <persName>Margaret Guttridge</persName>, <persName>Cornelius
                            Guttridge</persName> and <persName>Sarah Frances Guttridge</persName> by
                        purchase of the mother of said persons of Dr. <persName>Hanson
                            Penn</persName> Executor of <persName>Sarah O. Hilleary</persName>
                        deceased and who was sold as a slave for life the bill of sale will be found
                        recorded in the records for the <placeName>County of Washington D.
                            C.</placeName> a Copy of which is herewith filed:.</item>
                </list>

                <p>That your petitioners claim to the service or labor of said persons was at the
                    time of said discharge therefrom of the value of Seventeen hundred and ninety
                    dollars in money: to wit <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>William Hawkins</persName> was hired out at $28. <choice>
                                    <abbr>pr</abbr>
                                    <expan>per</expan>
                                </choice> month <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">neat</unclear> returns $20. <choice>
                                    <abbr>pr</abbr>
                                    <expan>per</expan>
                                </choice> month for 22 months the time to serve.</cell>
                            <cell>value $440.—</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>Margaret Guttridge</persName> a cook who took the place
                                of one hired at $7. <choice>
                                    <abbr>pr</abbr>
                                    <expan>per</expan>
                                </choice> month and for whom $1200. Cash was offered in <date when="1861-03">March 1861</date>.</cell>
                            <cell>value 700.—</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>Cornelius Guttridge</persName> house servant</cell>
                            <cell>do 400.—</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><persName>Sarah Frances Guttridge</persName> ditto</cell>
                            <cell>do 250.—</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total</cell>
                            <cell>$1790—</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00813.003.jpg"/>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that he bears true and faithful allegiance to the
                    Constitution and Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and
                    that he has not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that he has not brought said
                    persons into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage
                    of said act of Congress: and that at the time of the passage thereof, said
                    persons were held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's said claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges that the said claim to the service or
                    labor of said persons does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer
                    heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the
                    present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.—</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges that he knows of no bodily infirmity
                    that would lessen the value of said persons but that he believes each of them to
                    be sound in body and mind; and he prays the said Commissioners to investigate
                    and determine the validity of his said claim to the service or labor of said
                    persons as herein set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName> in
                    Conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>C. H. Wiltberger</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00813.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="receipt" subtype="handwritten">
                <p><date when="1862-06-24">June 24th 1862</date>. Received of <persName>Chas. H.
                    Wiltberger</persName> $.50 for filing and recording Bill of Sale
                    from <persName>Hanson Penn</persName> Executor <persName>S. O.
                        Hilleary</persName> to <persName>Chas. H. Wiltberger</persName>—</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Jno. A. Smith</persName>
                    <gap reason="illegible" extent="less than one word" quantity="3" unit="chars"/><lb/>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>pr</abbr>
                        <expan>per</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <persName>J. M. Hanson</persName></signed></closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00813.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Extract from the last Will and testament of <persName>Rebecca
                        Burch</persName>.</ab>
                    <p>I give and bequeath to my son in law <persName>Charles H.
                        Wiltberger</persName> my slave boy <persName>William</persName> until he
                        is thirty one years of age or during the natural life of my said slave woman
                        <persName>Sally</persName>, if longer than that time, and then he shall
                        be manumitted by the said <persName>Charles H. Wiltberger</persName> his
                        heirs or assigns, and the said <persName>Charles H. Wiltberger</persName> or
                        his heirs shall during the life time of the said slave
                        <persName>Sally</persName> have a charge and see that she is comfortably
                        provided for, either as a free woman or as a slave as the case may be.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>I certify that the aforegoing is a true extract from the last will and
                        testament of <persName>Rebecca Burch</persName>, deceased, filed and
                        recorded in the office of Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> aforesaid.</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of office this <date when="1862-06-24">24th day of June A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Moses Kelly</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00813.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>Charles H. Wiltberger</persName> being duly sworn do
                        depose and say that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge are true in
                        substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things
                        therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe
                        to be true in substance and in fact.—</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>C. H. Wiltberger</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Subscribed and sworn to before me this <date when="1862-06-25">25th day of
                            June A. D. 1862</date>.—</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>H. Naylor</persName>, J. Peace</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>813</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>C. H. Wiltberger</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-30">June 30, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
