<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00953">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Virginia Bell, Esther E. Bell, and Virginia C. Bell, 15 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00953</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Virginia Bell, Esther E. Bell, and Virginia C. Bell, 15 July
                        1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Virginia Bell, Esther E. Bell, and Virginia C. Bell,
                                15 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Virginia Bell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Esther E. Bell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Virginia C. Bell</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Gilbert L. Giberson</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-29" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-21" who="#scl">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">performed automated check for regular transcriptions and encoding errors and mistakes at facs</change>
            <change when="2013-03-01" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-10-03" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00953.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">

                <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>; entitled "An Act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia:"</p>

                <p>Your Petitioners, <persName>Virginia Bell</persName>, <persName>Esther E.
                        Bell</persName> and <persName>Virginia C. Bell</persName>, of the
                        <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>, by this their petition in writing, represent and
                    state, that they are persons loyal to the United States, who, at the time of the
                    passage of the said Act of Congress, held a claim to labor or service against
                    four persons of African descent of the names of <persName>Winney</persName>,
                        <persName>Susan</persName>, <persName>Ottoway</persName> and
                        <persName>Sally</persName> for and during the lives of said persons; and
                    that by said Act of Congress said persons were discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioners to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said persons were of the ages and of the personal descriptions
                    following: <list type="handwritten">
                        <item>The said <persName>Winney</persName>, aged forty-seven years, large
                            and of a bright mulatto color.</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Susan</persName>, aged thirty-seven years, very
                            likely and of a bright mulatto color.</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Ottoway</persName>, aged thirty-five years, of a
                            bright mulatto color.</item>
                        <item>The said <persName>Sally</persName>, aged eighteen years, rather
                            darker than the others and very tall and fine looking.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioners acquired their claim to the aforesaid service or labor of
                    said persons by virtue of a conveyance from the late <persName>Alexander
                        Bell</persName>, the husband of your petitioner <persName>Virginia
                        Bell</persName> and the father of your petitioners <persName>Esther <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00953.002.jpg"/> E. Bell</persName> and
                        <persName>Virginia C. Bell</persName>, to <persName>Robert Hudgin</persName>
                    in trust for your said petitioners; which said conveyance, dated the <date when="1859-05-28">twenty-eighth day of May, 1859</date>, is filed herewith
                    and marked "Exhibit A. No. 1."</p>

                <p>That your petitioners' claim to the service or labor of said persons was, at the
                    time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of four thousand seven hundred
                    dollars in money. Said <persName>Winney</persName> is a good nurse; said
                        <persName>Susan</persName> is a cook and nurse; said
                        <persName>Ottoway</persName> is a coachman; said <persName>Sally</persName>
                    is a sempstress; sand all said persons are free from any moral, mental or bodily
                    infirmity or defect.</p>

                <p>Your petitioners hereby declare that they bear true and faithful allegiance to
                    the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName> and that they have
                    not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                    rebellion nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioners further state and allege that they have not brought said
                    persons into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage
                    of said Act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said
                    persons were held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioners' claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioners further state and allege that their said claim to the service or
                    labor of said persons does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer
                    heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the
                    present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioners pray the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of their said claim to the service or labor of said persons herein
                    above set forth; and if the same be found <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00953.003.jpg"/> to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the
                    value of said claim in money and report the same to the Secretary of the
                    Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity with the
                    provisions of said Act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Virginia Bell</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Esther Ellen Bell</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Virginia Caroline Bell</persName></signed>
                    <lb/> By <persName>Virginia Bell their Guardian</persName>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington County,</hi></placeName> to
                    wit:</dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>Virginia Bell</persName>, being duly sworn do depose and say
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition as of my own knowledge are true in substance and
                        fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated as from the information of others I believe to be true in
                        substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Virginia Bell</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-15">fifteenth day
                            of July, A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Gilbert L. Giberson</persName> JP</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00953.005.jpg"/>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <head type="main"><hi rend="underline">Exhibit A. No. 1</hi></head>
                    <p>This Indenture made this <date when="1859-05-28">28th May 1859</date>, by and
                        between <persName>Alexander Bell</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                            Washington</placeName>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> of the first part
                            <persName>Robert Hudgin</persName> of the <placeName>County of
                            Caroline</placeName> in the <placeName>state of Virginia</placeName> of
                        the second part and <persName>Virginia Bell</persName> wife of the aforesaid
                            <persName>Alexander Bell</persName> and <persName>Esther Ellen
                            Bell</persName> and <persName>Virginia Caroline Bell</persName> children
                        of said <persName>Virginia</persName> by said <persName>Alexander
                            Bell</persName> all of the <placeName>city of Washington</placeName> and
                            <placeName>District</placeName> aforesaid of the third part.</p>
                    <p>Whereas the said <persName>Alexander Bell</persName> is desirous of securing
                        to the said <persName>Virginia</persName> his wife to her sole and separate
                        use during her life with remainder to her children the aforesaid
                            <persName>Esther Ellen</persName> and <persName>Virginia
                            Caroline</persName> at her death the property herein after named and
                        described. Now the Indenture Witnesseth that for and in consideration of the
                        natural love and affection he bears his said wife and daughters and also in
                        consideration of the sum of one dollar to him in hand paid by said
                            <persName>Robert Hudgin</persName> at and before the sealing and
                        delivery of <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00953.006.jpg"/> this Indenture
                        the receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged He the said <persName>Alexander
                            Bell</persName> has given granted bargained sold and assigned and by
                        this Indenture does give grant bargain and sell and assign to said
                            <persName>Robert Hudgin</persName> all the household and kitchen
                        furniture owned by said <persName>Alexander Bell</persName> in and about his
                        residence in the <placeName>city of Washington</placeName> aforesaid
                        <address><addrLine>number four hundred and fifty-five (455) on Twelfth street (12th)</addrLine></address>
                        also the following named negro slaves now in and about the residence of said
                            <persName>Alexander Bell</persName> in <placeName>Washington
                            City</placeName> To wit <persName>Winney</persName>,
                            <persName>Susan</persName>
                        <persName>Jenny</persName> &amp; infant child, <persName>Talley</persName>,
                            <persName>Jesse</persName>, <persName>Beverley</persName> and
                            <persName>Willey</persName> also two other slaves
                            <persName>Ottoway</persName> and <persName>Charles</persName> in the
                        town at <placeName>Chattanooga</placeName> in the <placeName>state of
                            Tennessee</placeName> The said <persName>Hudgin</persName> to hold all
                        said property furniture and slaves to the sole and separate use of the said
                            <persName>Virginia Bell</persName> and at her death to go to the said
                        daughters of the said <persName>Alexander Bell</persName> and said
                            <persName>Virginia Bell</persName> The said <persName>Hudgin</persName>
                        shall have power with the assent of said <persName>Virginia</persName> to
                        sell the furniture and reinvest the proceeds thereof to be held <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00953.007.jpg"/> by him to the same uses and
                        trusts herein before declared the said <persName>Virginia</persName> is to
                        hold the possession and use of the property hereby conveyed during her life
                        without <gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word" quantity="3" unit="chars"/> hindrance or obstruction on the part
                        of said <persName>Hudgin</persName></p>
                    <p>In Testimony whereof the parties have hereto set their hands and affixed
                        their seals the day and year first above written</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>A. Bell</persName> seal</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Robt. Hudgin</persName> seal</signed><lb/>
                        Signed Sealed and delivered in presence of
                                <signed><persName>F. I. Murphey</persName></signed> seal
                        <signed><persName>J. H. Norse</persName> seal<lb/>
                        seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> To wit</dateline>
                    <p>I, F. I. Murphey a Justice of the Peace in and for the <placeName>County of
                            Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> do hereby certify that <persName>Alexander
                            Bell</persName> whose name is subscribed to the foregoing deed of trust
                        bearing date the <date when="1859-05-28">28th May 1859</date> and who is
                        personally known to me to be the <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">identiture</unclear> person who Executed the said deed
                        personally appeared before me in my County and <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00953.008.jpg"/> District aforesaid and acknowledged the same
                        to be his act and deed and desired me to certify his said acknowledgement
                        Given under my hand and seal this <date when="1859-05-28">28th day of May
                            1859</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>F. I. Murphey</persName> J. P. seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Paid $1.25 by <persName>Robt Hudgin</persName></ab>
                    <ab><persName>Alexander Bell</persName><lb/> to<lb/>
                        <persName>Robert Hudgin</persName><lb/>Trustee<lb/> Bill of Sale.</ab>
                    <ab>Received <date when="1859-06-23">23rd June 1859</date> To be Recorded, and
                        the same day was Recorded in Liber J. A. S. No. 177, folios No. 256, 257,
                        &amp; 258. One of the Land Records for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                        and Examined by</ab>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>John A. Smith</signed>, <choice>
                            <abbr>clk</abbr>
                            <expan>clerk</expan>
                        </choice>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00953.009.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>953<lb/> Mrs. <persName>Virginia Bell</persName> &amp; others<lb/> Claim</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Milton S. Latham</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>James M. Carlisle</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
