<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00233">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William D. C. Murdock, 15 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>

               <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
               <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
               <name xml:id="cg">Courtney Geerhart</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00233</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of William D. C. Murdock, 15 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of William D. C. Murdock, 14 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>William D. C. Murdock</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Jenkin Thomas</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
<change when="2012-10-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-10-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-09-06" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2011-09-02" who="#cg">checked</change>
         <change when="2011-04-20" who="#rr">checked</change>
         <change when="2010-09-30" who="#rv">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00233.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William D. C. Murdock</persName>
                   </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington County D.C.</placeName>
                   </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States, who, at the time of the
                    passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against
                        <seg type="handwritten">nine persons (four men &amp; five women)</seg>
                        person of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William Hutchison</persName>, <persName>William H Lee</persName>,
                            <persName>Francis K. Lee</persName>, <persName>Theodore Lee</persName>,
                            <persName>Sophia Hutchison</persName>, <persName>Mary C. Lee</persName>,
                            <persName>Martha A. Lee</persName>, <persName>Margaret A. Lee</persName>
                        &amp; <persName>Ellen Lee</persName>
                   </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">nine persons
                   </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">nine
                        persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your
                    petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said
                        <seg type="handwritten">nine persons</seg>
                    <del>was of the age of</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">were of the ages</seg> and of the personal description
                        following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note></p>
                    <ab type="handwritten">That the said <persName>Wm Hutchison</persName> was of
                        the age of fifty six years, black in complexion, five feet six inches high
                        &amp; of pleasant countenance. <persName>Wm H. Lee</persName> was twenty
                        years of age, a dark chestnut color six feet tall, stout build &amp;
                        bashful countenance&#8212;that <persName>F. H. Lee</persName> was twenty years of
                        age. of copper color, five feet eight inches tall, stout build very
                        intelligent, serious countenance &amp; very likely&#8212;that
                            <persName>Theodore Lee</persName> was sixteen years of age, dark
                        chestnut in color, likely, well made, pleasant, cheerful countenance
                        &amp; five feet five inches tall&#8212;that <persName>Mary C. Lee</persName>
                        was twenty six years of age, copper color in complexion, very likely,
                        intelligent, face &amp; figure good, five feet six inches tall&#8212;that
                            <persName>Martha A. Lee</persName> was twenty four years; copper color
                        in complexion, very likely, five feet, five inches in height, good figure,
                        &amp; pleasant countenance&#8212;<persName>Margaret A. Lee</persName> was of
                        the age of sixteen years, copper colored in complexion, likely, five feet,
                        five inches tall, pleasant countenance, &amp; good figure&#8212;that
                            <persName>Ellen Lee</persName> was fourteen years of age, dark chestnut
                        in color, very likely pleasant countenance, well made &amp; five feet
                        two inches tall&#8212;that <persName>Sophia Hutchison</persName> was of the age
                        of eighty nine years black in color, hair grey, well preserved for her age
                        and about five feet five inches tall.</ab>
          

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00233.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">nine persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">He is the sole child &amp; heir at law of
                            <persName>Addison Murdock</persName>, who died in the year <date when="1808">1808</date>. That at the time of his death the said
                            <persName>Addison Murdock</persName> was the lawful owner of certain
                        slaves and among others of <persName>Sophia</persName> &amp;
                            <persName>Wm Hutchison</persName>, before named &amp;
                            <persName>Susan Hawkins</persName>. That <persName>Susan
                            Hawkins</persName> married &amp; had a daughter named
                            <persName>Eliza Matthews</persName>. That <persName>Eliza
                            Matthews</persName> married <persName>John Lee</persName>, negro,
                        &amp; had by him the following children who are before named that is to
                        say <persName>William H. Lee</persName>, <persName>Francis H.
                        Lee</persName>, <persName>Theodore Lee</persName>, <persName>Mary C.
                            Lee</persName>
                        <persName>Margaret A. Lee</persName>
                        <persName>Martha A. Lee</persName> &amp; <persName>Ellen Lee</persName>. The Said seven Lees together with <persName>Sophia</persName> &amp;
                            <persName>William Hutchison</persName> comprising the nine servants
                        mentioned in this petition</seg>
            </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">nine persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">nine thousand one
                        hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">
                        Two competent &amp; disinterested citizens of
                            <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, lately appraised &amp; fixed the
                        following valuation upon said negroes&#8212;<persName>Sophy
                        Hutchison</persName>, old &amp; infirm, valueless, though your
                   petitioner feels in duty bound to support her&#8212;<persName>Wm
                       Hutchison</persName> $900&#8212;handy honest moral, trusty, good tempered,
                        has been my foreman of out of door work also a well trained house servant,
                        gardener, driver &amp; ostler = <persName>Wm H Lee</persName> $1100.
                        Young, honest moral good tempered, trusty, good driver, ostler &amp;
                        farm hand, strong &amp; capable of hard work at present, but has been
                        slightly ruptured, not however impairing his strength <persName>F. H.
                            Lee</persName> $1200, young a well trained driver ostler &amp;
                   gardener, strong healthy, moral honest, trusty, &amp; good tempered&#8212;<persName>Mary C. Lee</persName> $1400. young, a well trained house
                        servant healthy honest moral, trusty, good tempered &amp; strong&#8212;<persName>Martha A Lee</persName> $1400 young a well trained cook
                        &amp; house servant strong, healthy, honest, moral good tempered
                        &amp; trusty, <persName>Margaret A Lee</persName> $1100 young good
                        tempered trained to house work, honest moral strong &amp; healthy.
                   <persName>Theodore Lee</persName> $1100&#8212;a lad trained to house work
                   driving and gardening, strong, healthy honest moral &amp; good tempered&#8212;<persName>Ellen Lee</persName> $900&#8212;a girl trained to house work and
                        nursing children, strong healthy, honesty moral &amp; good tempered. The Names of the appraiser are endorsed on the back of this petition as
                        witnesses if any are required</seg>
            </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true and faithful allegiance to the
                    Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has
                    not borne arms against the United States in the present rebellion, nor in any
                    way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">negroes nor any of
                        them</seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the
                    passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof,
                    said <seg type="handwritten">servants were</seg>
               <del>was</del> held to service
                    or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service
                    or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">nine servants</seg> herein above set forth; and
                    if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Wm D. C. Murdock</persName>
                       </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00233.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I,
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>William D. C. Murdock</persName>
                       </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>William D. C. Murdock</persName>
                           </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-14">
                     <seg type="handwritten">14</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg>
                            A. D. 1862</date>.
               </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Jenkin Thomas</persName></seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>233 <lb/>Petition of <persName>William D. C. Murdock</persName>
            </ab>
                <ab>The clerk will file this petition <persName>J. C. Marbury</persName> <choice><abbr>atty</abbr><expan>attorney</expan></choice> </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
            </ab>
                <ab>Witnesses as to Valuation <lb/>
                    <persName>Z. A. Lazenby</persName>
               <lb/>
                    <persName>Watkins Addison</persName>
               <lb/> Our title <lb/>
                    Miss <persName>Virginia Burnett</persName>
            </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>