<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00390">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Absalom Brown, 22 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00390</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Absalom Brown, 22 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Absalom Brown, 22 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Absalom Brown</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">revised code for handwritten signature blocks</change>
<change when="2013-05-20" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-13" who="#kp">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-05-10" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-22" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00390.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Absalom Brown</persName></seg>
                    of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName></seg> by this
                        <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">one</seg> person of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName></seg> for and during the
                    life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName></seg> and
                    that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned
                            Howard</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim
                    of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName> was</seg> of the
                    age of <seg type="handwritten">about twenty-seven years</seg> and of the
                    personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1"
                        >Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be
                        more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">about five feet, eight inches in height, dark color,
                        perfectly sound &#38; healthy in mind and body &#38; without any defect
                        whatever His character is such that he commands the highest wages</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00390.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned
                            Howard</persName></seg> in manner following:<note type="government"
                        place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from
                        whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written
                        evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where
                        the same may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">as executor of the late <persName>William
                            Brown</persName>, as exhibited in the accompanying will</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName></seg> was, at the time of
                    said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">fifteen
                        Hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">I
                        aver that I know of no infirmity or defect of said <persName>Ned
                            Howard</persName> &#38; I believe that none exists</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName></seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned
                            Howard</persName></seg> was held to service or labor therein under and
                    by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName></seg> does not originate
                    in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any
                    manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ned Howard</persName></seg> herein
                    above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to
                    the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>(Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Absalom Brown</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00390.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In the name of God, Amen, I <persName>William Brown</persName> of the
                            <placeName>village of Savage</placeName> in the <placeName>County of
                            Howard</placeName> and <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, being
                        of sound mind and memory&#8212;blessed be God for the same&#8212;, do make and
                        publish this my last will and Testament I give and bequeath to my daughters
                            <persName>Ellen</persName>, <persName>Providence</persName> and
                            <persName>Mary</persName>, my four negroes named
                            <persName>Susan</persName>, <persName>Stephen</persName>,
                            <persName>Ned</persName>, and <persName>Amanda</persName> to serve them
                        faithfully during the single life of my said daughters; but provided any of
                        my said daughters should marry then all claim to my said negroes ceases in
                        those who marry, but continues in those who remain single. Should all of my
                        said daughters die before said negroes attain to the ages of forty
                        individually then my remaining heirs are to have equal claim to said
                        negroes; but after said negroes shall have attained to the ages of forty, my
                        said daughters being dead then said negroes have full privilege to live
                        with, or to choose a master as suits their fancy from among my heirs then
                        living&#8212;Should my said negroes not serve faithfully my said daughters,
                        then I grant my executor full authority to sell those misbehaving and he
                        shall retain ten percent of the value of said slave sold, as compensation
                        for his trouble in selling; the residue of said money shall then be put at
                        interest, which interest <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00390.005.jpg"/>above shall be used in the support of my single daughters and be subject
                        to their order; and should any of said money obtained from the sale of said
                        slaves, remain when my single daughters are all dead, then my remaining
                        heirs shall divide the sum equally among them.&#8212;</p>
                    <p>I give and bequeath to my daughter <persName>Ellen</persName> and
                            <persName>Providence</persName> all issue arising from my said negro
                            <persName>Amanda</persName>.</p>
                    <p>I also give and bequeath to my son <persName>Absalom</persName> my bed and
                        bedding.</p>
                    <p>I do appoint my son <persName>Absalom</persName> to be guardian to my
                        daughter <persName>Mary</persName>&#8212;</p>
                    <p>I do nominate and appoint my son <persName>Absalom</persName> to be executor
                        of this my last will and Testament</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal this
                            <date when="1853-01-28">28th day of January in the year of our Lord one
                            thousand eight hundred and fifty three</date></p>

                    <closer><signed>his x mark <persName>William Brown</persName>
                        Seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>signed, sealed, published and declared in the presence of us, by
                            <persName>William Brown</persName> the above named testator as and for
                        his last and Testament, and we have at his request in his presence and in
                        the presence of each other, subscribe our names as witnesses thereto</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Sam K. Dashiell</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Wm V. Haislett</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Joshua B. Davis</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00390.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>Howard County</placeName> sct</dateline>
                    <p>The <date when="1856-02-19">19th day of February 1856</date> came
                            <persName>Samuel K. Dashiell</persName> and <persName>William
                            Haislett</persName> two of the subscribing Witnesses to the foregoing
                        last will and Testament of <persName>William Brown</persName> late of
                            <placeName>Howard County</placeName> deceased and made oath on the Holy
                        evangely of Almighty God that they did see the Testator therein named sign
                        and seal this will and that they heard him publish pronounce and declare the
                        same to be his last will and Testament, that at the time of his so doing he
                        was to the best of their apprehension of sound and disposing mind memory and
                        understanding and they together with <persName>Joshua B. Davis</persName>
                        the other subscribing witness respectively subscribed their names as
                        witnesses to this will in the presence and at the request of the Testator
                        and in the presence of each other</p>
                    <closer>Test <signed><persName>Thomas B. Hobbs</persName> Register of wills for
                                <placeName>Howard County</placeName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In Testimony that the foregoing is a true copy taken from "Wills Liber W. G.
                        no 1 folio 346 &#38; being one of the Records in the Office of the Register
                        of Wills for <placeName>Howard County</placeName> (over)</p>

                    <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00390.007.jpg"/>
                    <p>I hereunto subscribe my name and affix the seal of my office this <date
                            when="1856-02-21">twenty first of February in the year of our Lord
                            eighteen hundred and fifty six</date></p>
                    <closer>Test <signed><persName>Thomas B. Hobbs</persName> Register of wills for
                                <placeName>Howard County</placeName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>A true Copy of the original&#8212;</ab>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>W H Jones</persName><lb/>
                            <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#kk">Act of
                                Congress</unclear></signed>
                        <dateline><date when="1863-02-02">Feb: 2.1863</date></dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00390.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Absalom Brown</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Absalom Brown</persName><lb/> Executor of <persName>Wm Brown</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-12"><seg
                                type="handwritten">12th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Thomas C
                                    Donn</persName><lb/> Justice of the Peace for
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                                <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>390</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Absalom Brown</persName></ab>
                <ab>Presented by <persName>Jno B. Peyton</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Amos Kendall</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Wm Stickney</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Jos. Beasly</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
