<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00641">
    <teiHeader>   
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William G. H. White, 2 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="sd">Shailana Dunn-Wall</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt> 
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00641</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>   
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of William G. W. White, 6 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-06">June 6, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of William G. W. White, 6 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-06">June 6, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>            
        </fileDesc>   
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>William G. W. White</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-28" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-09-12" who="#sd">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00641.001.jpg"/>            
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of
                    April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or
                    labor in the District of Columbia."</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William G. W. White</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the <placeName>District of Coa.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">certain</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>James Anderson</persName> <persName>Eliza Butler</persName> &#38; <persName>Fanny Brown</persName></seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">Persons are</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">Persons were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">about 35, 45, &#38; 20,</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>James Anderson</persName>.  Now at large.  Very likely, about 35 years of age.  height near six feet dark complexion and of genteel address worth to me twelve Hundred Dollars.</item>
                        <item><persName>Eliza Butler</persName> about 45 years of age about 4 feet 11 inches in height dark complexion very valuable as a family servant.  would not have parted with her for one thousand dollars.</item>
                        <item><persName>Fanny Brown</persName> about 20 years of age light complexion, and very likely.  slightly lame in right leg, a very desirable House servant, worth at least one thousand dollars.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00641.002.jpg"/>
                
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note> <seg type="handwritten"><persName>James Anderson</persName> purchased of <persName>R. L. Ogle</persName> of <placeName>Prince George Co. Md.</placeName> for the sum of Seven Hundred &#38; fifty Dollars.  <persName>Eliza Butler</persName> purchased when a child of <persName>John Thompson</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> (then in the <placeName>Dist Co</placeName>) price not recollected.  <persName>Fanny Brown</persName>, raised by me, her mother (owned by me) having died when she was a child.</seg></p>
                
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Thirty Two Hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">And that your petitioner knows of no other, bodily, mental or moral infirmities further than herein stated, and that he believes no others to exist his claim is however subject to a deed of trust to <persName>Jas M Carlisle</persName> favor of <persName>Jas R. Smith</persName> dated <date when="1856-07-12">July 12th 1856</date> &#38; recorded in the clerks office.</seg></p>
                 
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>
                
                <closer>
                    (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm. G. W. White</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00641.003.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William G. W. White</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>W. G. W. White</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">                    
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-06"><seg type="handwritten">6th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                <closer>
                    (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName> <choice><abbr>clk</abbr><expan>clerk</expan></choice></seg></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>641</ab>
                <ab><persName>William G. W. White</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-06">June 6, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>E. J. Middleton</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Samuel Bacon</persName><lb/><!-- Samuel and Peter F. Bacon are listed in the Boyd's 1862 directory.-->
                    <persName>Peter F. Bacon</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
