<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00174">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Lucy R. Miller, Maria Miller, Harriet Miller, and William Miller, 13 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00174</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Lucy R. Miller, Maria Miller, Harriet Miller, and William Miller, 13 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Lucy R. Miller, Maria Miller, Harriet Miller, and William Miller, 13 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Lucy R. Miller</persName>
            </person>
             <person role="petitioner">
                 <persName>Maria Miller</persName>
             </person>
             <person role="petitioner">
                 <persName>Harriet Miller</persName>
             </person>
             <person role="petitioner">
                 <persName>William Miller</persName>
             </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Nicholas Callan</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-19" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-12-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2012-12-04" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
         <change when="2012-11-20" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00174.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <head type="main">
                  <hi rend="underline">Exhibit A</hi>
               </head>

                    <p>In the name of God, Amen. I <persName>Eliza Ariss Miller</persName> of the
                            <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> being sick and weak in body but of sound and
                        disposing mind memory and understanding considering the certainty of death
                        and the uncertainty of the time thereof and being desirous to settle my
                        worldly affairs and thereby be the better prepared to leave this world when
                        it shall please God to call me hence do make and publish this my last will
                        and testament in manner and form, that is to say. First after my debts are
                        paid, I devise and bequeath as follows.&#8212;To my sister <persName>Lucy Roy Miller</persName> 
                        I do hereby give and bequeath my servant <persName>Hannah</persName> and her
                        offspring&#8212;To my Sister <persName>Maria Miller</persName> I do hereby
                        give and bequeath my servant <persName>Isabella</persName> and her
                        offspring.&#8212;To my Sister <persName>Harriet Miller</persName> I do hereby
                        give and bequeath my servants <persName>John Joseph Shorter</persName>,
                            <persName>Charles Edwin Shorter</persName> and
                            <persName>Nancy</persName> to do with said <persName>Nancy</persName> as
                        she may be disposed.&#8212; I do also give and bequeath to my said Sister
                            <persName>Harriet Miller</persName> my Stock twelve hundred Dollars in
                        the <placeName>Peoria</placeName> and <placeName>Oquamka</placeName> Rail
                        Road Company and <placeName>City of St. Louis</placeName>, Riggs &#38;
                        Co.&#8212;Should my two Sisters <persName>Lucy Roy Miller</persName> and
                            <persName>Maria Miller</persName> survive my Sister <persName>Harriet
                            Miller</persName> it is my wish that the aforesaid servants should be
                        <choice><sic>eaqually</sic><corr>equally</corr></choice> divided between my said Sisters <persName>Lucy
                            R.</persName> and <persName>Maria</persName> and also that my aforesaid
                        stock in the <placeName>Peoria</placeName> and
                            <placeName>Oquamka</placeName> Rail Road Co. and <placeName>City of St.
                                Louis</placeName>&#8212;Riggs &#38; Co should be <choice><sic>eaqually</sic><corr>equally</corr></choice>
                        divided between my said Sisters <persName>Lucy R.</persName> and
                            <persName>Maria Miller</persName>. Should my Sister <persName>Harriet Miller</persName> survive my Sisters <persName>Lucy R</persName>. and <persName>Maria Miller</persName> it is my wish that she should heir all
                        of my servants and their offspring as before mentioned.</p>

                    <p>Should my brother <persName>William Miller</persName> survive my three
                        Sisters <persName>Lucy R.</persName> 
                  <persName>Maria</persName> and <persName>Harriet</persName>,
                        it is my wish that he should heir all my servants as before mentioned. viz:
                            <persName>John Joseph Shorter</persName>, <persName>Charles Edwin
                            Shorter</persName>, <persName>Nancy</persName>,
                            <persName>Isabella</persName>, and <persName>Hannah</persName> and their
                        offspring together with the whole of my stock in the
                            <placeName>Peoria</placeName> and <placeName>Oquamka</placeName> Rails
                        Road Company
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00174.003.jpg"/>
                        
                        and <placeName>City of St. Louis</placeName>&#8212;Riggs &#38;
                            Co&#8212;<persName>Nancy</persName> to be taken care of as long as she
                        lives&#8212;</p>
                    <p>Now I make one request of my brother <persName>William Miller</persName> that
                        he must never sell one of my servants unless it is their wish to be sold and
                        moreover they are not to be sold out of the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> and if sold they are to have choice of their
                        masters &#38; place.&#8212;</p>
                    <p>And I do by this my last Will and testament confirm and ratify 
                        every bequest mentioned in said Will and testament and further devise that in case
                        my brother <persName>William</persName> shall survive my Sisters
                            <persName>Lucy R. Miller</persName>, <persName>Maria Miller</persName>
                        &#38; <persName>Harriet Miller</persName> all the Stock and Negroes
                        bequeathed to my said Sisters by me in this my last will shall become his
                        indisputable property and estate&#38;and further that in case my Sisters or
                        either of them shall survive my said brother <persName>William</persName>
                        then and in such case the said bequest to my Sisters shall become the
                        property of the survivor of them as her sole and indisputable property and
                        estate.&#8212;</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal this
                            <date when="1855-12-22">22nd day of December in the year of Our Lord one
                            thousand eight hundred and fifty five</date>.&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Eliza Ariss Miller</persName>.</signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Signed sealed published and declared by <persName>Eliza Ariss
                            Miller</persName> the above testator as and for her last will and
                        testament in the presence of us, who at her request in her presence and in
                        the presence of each other have subscribed our names as witnesses</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>J. W. French</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Rob. A. Lacey</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>William Handy</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00174.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit Orphan's Court <date when="1856-05-03">May 3 1856</date></dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared <persName>Robert A. Lacey</persName> &#38;
                            <persName>William Handy</persName> two of the subscribing witnesses to
                        the aforegoing last will and testament of <persName>Eliza A.
                            Miller</persName> late of <placeName>Washington County</placeName>
                        aforesaid deceased &#38; severally made oath on the Holy Evangels of
                        Almighty God that they did see the testatrix therein named sign this will
                        that she published pronounced &#38; declared the same to be her last will
                        &#38; testament, that at the time of so doing she was to the best of their
                        apprehensions of sound &#38; disposing mind memory &#38; understanding &#38;
                        that they together with <persName>J. W. French</persName> the other
                        subscribing witness respectively subscribed their names as witnesses to this
                        will in the presence &#38; at the request of the testatrix &#38; in the
                        presence of each other</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>Test <persName>Ed. N. Roche</persName> <choice><abbr>Reg.</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> Wills.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>I certify that the aforegoing is a true copy from the original filed and
                        recorded in the office of the Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> aforesaid</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of office this <date when="1862-05-08">eighth day of
                            May Anno Domini 1862</date></p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Moses Kelly</persName><lb/>
                      Register of Wills</signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00174.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                
                    <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An Act for the
                        release of certain persons held to services or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>:"</p>
                    <p>Your petitioners, <persName>Lucy R. Miller</persName>, <persName>Maria
                            Miller</persName>, <persName>Harriet Miller</persName> and
                            <persName>William Miller</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                            Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, by this their petition in writing, represent and
                        state that they are persons loyal to the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said Act of
                        Congress, held a claim to service or labor against five persons of African
                        descent named <persName>Hannah</persName>, <persName>Isabella</persName>,
                            <persName>John Joseph Shorter</persName>, <persName>Charles Edwin
                            Shorter</persName> (otherwise, <persName>Charles Edwin
                        Taylor</persName>) and <persName>Nancy</persName>, for and during the lives
                        of said persons; and that by said Act of Congress said persons were
                        discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioners to such
                        service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said
                            <persName>Hannah</persName> was of the age of twenty-one years, the said
                            <persName>Isabella</persName> of the age of twenty-six years, the said
                            <persName>John Joseph Shorter</persName> of the age of fourteen years,
                        the said <persName>Charles Edwin Shorter</persName> (or
                            <persName>Taylor</persName>) of the age of eleven years and the said
                            <persName>Nancy</persName> of the age of fifty-six years, or thereabout.
                        That said <persName>Hannah</persName> is black, of low stature and well
                        formed; said <persName>Isabella</persName> is black and of low stature; said
                            <persName>John Joseph Shorter</persName> is of a bright mulatto color,
                        well formed and likely; said <persName>Charles Edwin Shorter</persName> (or
                            <persName>Taylor</persName>) is of a bright mulatto color, well formed
                        and very intelligent; and said <persName>Nancy</persName> is of a black
                        color, short and stout. That your petitioners acquired
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00174.006.jpg"/>
                        
                        their claim to the aforesaid service or labor of
                        said persons under the last will and testament of your petitioners' sister,
                        the late <persName>Eliza A. Miller</persName>, deceased; which said last
                        will and testament was duly proved and recorded in the office of the
                        Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> on the <date when="1856-05-03">third day of May in the year one thousand eight
                            hundred and fifty-six</date>; and a certified copy of which, marked
                        "Exhibit A," is herewith filed as part of this petition. That your
                        petitioners' claim to the service or labor of said persons was, at the time
                        of said discharge therefrom, of the value of Four Thousand dollars in money.
                        That said <persName>Hannah</persName> is a good house servant, cook, washer
                        and ironer, of a good constitution and free from any infirmity or defect;
                        said <persName>Isabella</persName> is also a superior cook, washer and
                        ironer, a good house servant, healthy and free from any infirmity or defect;
                        said <persName>John Joseph Shorter</persName> and <persName>Charles Edwin
                            Shorter</persName> (or <persName>Taylor</persName>) are both healthy,
                        capable and efficient as house servants and free from any infirmity or
                        defect; said <persName>Nancy</persName> is a good cook, washer and ironer,
                        but of somewhat delicate health.</p>
                    <p>Your petitioners hereby declare that they bear true and faithful allegiance
                        to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName> and that they
                        have not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the
                        present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                    <p>And your petitioners further state and allege that they have not brought said
                        persons into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the
                        passage of said Act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage
                        thereof, said persons were held to service or labor therein under and by
                        virtue of your petitioners' claim to such service or labor.</p>
                    <p>Your petitioners further state and allege that
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00174.007.jpg"/>
                        
                        their said claim to the service or labor of said
                        persons does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made
                        by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion
                        against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>And your petitioners pray the said Commissioners to investigate and determine
                        the validity of their said claim to the service or labor of said persons
                        herein above set forth; and if the same be found valid, that they appraise
                        and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the
                        Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in
                        conformity with the provisions of said Act of Congress.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Lucy R Miller</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Maria Miller</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Hariot Miller</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Wm. Miller</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
            </div1>
               
                <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                    <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                        <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>We, <persName>Lucy R. Miller</persName>, <persName>Maria Miller</persName>,
                            <persName>Harriet Miller</persName> and <persName>William
                            Miller</persName>, being duly sworn, do depose and say that the several
                        matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition
                        as of our own knowledge are true in substance and in fact; and that all the
                        several other matters and things therein set forth and stated as from the
                        information of others we believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Lucy R Miller</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Maria Miller</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Hariot Miller</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Wm. Miller</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                    </div2>
            
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00174.008.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-12">twelfth day of
                            May A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>N Callan</persName> JP</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00174.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written
                    horizontally.</note>
                <ab>174<lb/>
                    Claim<lb/>
                    of<lb/>
                    <persName>Lucy R. Miller</persName> &#38; Others</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date><lb/>
                    by<lb/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="nnk"><persName>Dandige</persName></unclear> &#38; <persName>Ingle</persName></ab>
                <ab><persName>R A Lacey</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>N Callan</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Tho H Fisher</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>