<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00492">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William A. Linton, 27 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00492</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of William A. Linton, 27 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-27">May 27, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of William A. Linton, 27 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-27">May 27, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>William A. Linton</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Daniel Rowland</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-02-09" who="#jc">automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2013-01-29" who="#kk">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-10-24" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00492.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm. A. Linton</persName></seg>
                    of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington City</placeName></seg> by this
                        <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">Two</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of
                    African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny
                            Stuart</persName> and <persName>Robinson Crusoe Stuart</persName>, her
                        son</seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny Stuart</persName> &amp; <persName>Robinson Crusoe
                            Stuart</persName></seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">Persons are</seg> discharged and freed of and from all
                    claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny Stuart</persName> is
                        supposed to have been</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">Forty
                        years or upwards &amp; her son <persName>Robinson Crusoe Stuart</persName>
                        about the age of twelve years (12)</seg> and of the personal description<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny Stuart</persName> is a hale healthy,
                        robust woman of a dark copper complexion and her son
                            <persName>Robinson</persName> may be called black—that the said
                            <persName>Fanny</persName> is a very valuable servant; of fine quality
                        and of <hi rend="underline">superior qualifications as a Cook</hi> in which
                        Capacity she has served your Petitioner for many years past; to his entire
                        satisfaction: and as he believes to her own satisfaction also as she is
                        still in his service with a knowledge that she is free to depart at any time
                        she pleases—The son <persName>Robinson Crusoe Stuart</persName> has
                        been born since your Petitioner became the owner of the said
                            <persName>Fanny</persName>. He is a likely, smart, active Boy &amp; has
                        been trained to the duties of the house and dining Room, where he can acquit
                        himself as well as Boys of his age usually do.</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00492.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">by purchase from his own son <persName>John A
                            Linton</persName> as to the <hi rend="underline">woman
                                <persName>Fanny</persName></hi>: and as to the son he has been born
                        since the mother became the property of your petitioner &amp; is now near 12
                        years of age The Price paid for <persName>Fanny</persName> he does not
                        recollect it has been so long ago, but he thinks something under $400.<ref xml:id="r1" target="a1">x</ref></seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$1800</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">Eighteen hundred dollars in money but
                        from the excellent moral qualities of the woman, her Integrity, her
                        fidelity, &amp; her Superior qualifications as a Cook he would have been
                        reluctant to part from her at any time; your petitioner avers that he knows
                        of no personal defect or infirmity pertaining to either the mother or the
                        son nor does he believe there is any such. they have always been remarkably
                        healthy</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.<seg type="handwritten">—</seg></p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">servants—</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">servants were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor. <seg type="handwritten">acquired
                        more than twelve 12 years ago.</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">servants.</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm A
                                Linton</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
                <note xml:id="a1" target="r1" type="authorial" rend="handwritten">X negroes were low
                    at the time</note>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00492.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm A Linton</persName></seg> being duly
                        sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are
                        set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are
                        true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and
                        things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I
                        believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm A
                                    Linton</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-27"><seg type="handwritten">27th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>D.
                                    Rowland</persName> J. P.</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb sameAs="leaf002r" facs="cww.00492.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>Know all men by these presents that I, the within named <persName>William A.
                        Linton</persName> in consideration of the sum of one dollar lawful money to
                    me this <date when="1862-08-15">15th day of August A.D. 1862</date>, in hand
                    paid by <persName>George William Phillips</persName> of
                        <placeName>Boston</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                        Massachusetts</placeName>; the receipt of which is hereby acknowledged have
                    sold, assigned, transferred &amp; set over, &amp; by these presents do sell,
                    assign, transfer &amp; set over unto the said <persName>Phillips</persName> his
                    executors, administrators &amp; assigns, all my rights title, interest &amp;
                    claim against the <placeName>United States</placeName>, arising under &amp; by
                    virtue of the Act of Congress, entitled, "An act for the release of certain
                    persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>" approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th
                        1862</date>, Said claim being for compensation allowed under said act in
                    consequence of the emancipation of the two within named persons of African
                    descent, who were slaves for life belonging to me, and who were freed under
                    &amp; by virtue of said act, And I do hereby authorize &amp; empower the said
                        <persName>Phillips</persName> his agent or attorney to receive of &amp; from
                    the <placeName>United States</placeName> such sum or sums of money as may be
                    awarded by the said <placeName>United States</placeName> its agent or
                    Commissioners, as compensation to me for the loss of services of said persons,
                    or howsoever else in the premises</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Wm A Linton</persName> seal</signed><lb/> Witness
                            <signed><persName>R H Laskey</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>C. Alexander</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>492<lb/> The Petition<lb/> of<lb/>
                    <persName>Wm A Linton</persName><lb/> to<lb/> Emancipation <choice>
                        <abbr>Coms</abbr>
                        <expan>Commissioners</expan>
                    </choice></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-27">May 27, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Wm Linton</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
