<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.01084">
    <teiHeader>   
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Moses Kelly, 23 December 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt> 
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.01084</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>   
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Moses Kelly, 23 December 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-12-23">December 23, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Moses Kelly, 23 December 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-12-23">December 23, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>            
        </fileDesc>   
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Moses Kelly</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-07-01" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-02-14" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.01084.003.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                    <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of
                    April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or
                    labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Moses Kelly</persName>, administrator <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">WA</unclear></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William W. Russell</persName>, late of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, deceased</seg>, by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Russell</persName> was</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George Ross</persName> and <persName>Ellen Bumbra</persName></seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> <del>of</del> <seg type="handwritten">above given</seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George Ross</persName> and <persName>Ellen Bumbra</persName></seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George Ross</persName> and <persName>Ellen Bumbra</persName> were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of <del>your petitioner</del> <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Russell</persName></seg> to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName> were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">sixty three and thirty five years, respectively, or thereabout,</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note> <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName>, dark colored, about five feet seven inches in <choice><sic>heighth</sic><corr>height</corr></choice> active and intelligent, and <persName>Ellen</persName>, a mulatto, about five feet and five inches in <choice><sic>heighth</sic><corr>height</corr></choice>, large and strong</seg></p>
                                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.01084.004.jpg"/>
                
                <p>That <del>your petitioner</del> <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Russell</persName></seg> acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName></seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note> <seg type="handwritten">by marriage his wife, having inherited the same from her parents</seg></p>
                
                <p>That <del>your petitioner's</del> <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Russell</persName>'s</seg> claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName></seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">twelve hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> being valued at $300 and <persName>Ellen</persName>, who is a good cook and house servant at $900</seg></p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Russell</persName> bore</seg> <del>bears</del> true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Russell</persName></seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName></seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName> were</seg> <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">the</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName></seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">the</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName></seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>
                
                <closer>
                    (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Moses Kelly</persName>, administrator W. A. of <persName>William W. Russell</persName>.</seg></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <list>
                        <item><persName>George Ross</persName>—$250—</item>
                        <item><persName>Ellen Bumbra</persName>—800—</item>
                    </list>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.01084.005.jpg"/>            
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia,</placeName><lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Moses Kelly</persName>, administrator W. A. of <persName>William W. Russell</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Moses Kelly</persName>, administrator W. A. of <persName>William W. Russell</persName>, <choice><abbr>decd</abbr><expan>deceased</expan></choice></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">                    
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-12-18"><seg type="handwritten">18th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">December</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName> <choice><abbr>Clk</abbr><expan>Clerk</expan></choice>.</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the Verification.</note>
                <ab><persName>Moses Kelly</persName> <choice><abbr>admin</abbr><expan>administrator</expan></choice><lb/>
                <persName>William W. Russell</persName></ab>
                <ab><date when="1862-12-18">18 Dec 186—</date></ab>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.01084.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-12-23">Decr 23, 1862</date>.</ab>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.01084.007.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington City</placeName><lb/>
                    <date when="1862-12-22">December 22, 1862</date>.</dateline>
                    <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                    <p>On the <date when="1862-12-18">18th <choice><abbr>inst</abbr><expan>instant</expan></choice></date> you allowed me to present a claim for compensation for services due by <persName>George Ross</persName>, and <persName>Ellen Bumbra</persName>, persons of African descent, to late Paymaster <persName>William W. Russel</persName>, of the Marine Corps. (said <persName>George</persName> and <persName>Ellen</persName> having been discharged therefrom by Act of Congress approved <date when="1862-04-16">16th April last</date>.) estimating the value of those services at twelve hundred dollars.</p>
                    <p>The Second Section of the act under which this claim arises provided "that all persons loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, holding claims to service or labor against persons discharged therefrom by this act, may, within ninety days from the passage thereof, <hi rend="underline">but not thereafter</hi>, present to the Commissioners hereinafter mentioned their respective statements or petitions in writing" respecting such claims. These "statements or petitions" were also required to be supported by the personal affidavit of the claimant in such case, and as Major <persName>Russell</persName> was actively engaged in the Army near <placeName>Richmond</placeName> at the date of the passage of the Act and continued so to be for more than three months thereafter, it was impossible for him to present his claim within the time prescribed by it.</p>
                    <p>The Act of <date when="1862-04-16">16th April</date> was so amended by Act of <date when="1862-07-12">12th July last</date>, as to allow "resident absentees" to present their claims by Attorneys or Agents, and "persons in the Military <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.01084.008.jpg"/> or Naval Service of the <placeName>United States</placeName>" to verify their statements before "any commander of any military post, or of any Officer having a separate command of any military force in the field, or before any Captain, Commander, or Lieutenant commanding in the Navy." It did not, however, extend the time for presenting claims beyond the ninety days originally allowed, and hence it afforded no relief to <persName>Major Russell</persName>, as he could not by any possibility have heard of its passage until after the expiration of that period</p>
                    <p><persName>Thomas Hutchingson</persName> <choice><abbr>Esq.</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice> who was a clerk to <persName>Major Russell</persName>, has furnished me the following statement in relation to the absence of that Officer from <placeName>Washington</placeName>, and he will no doubt verify the same by his affidavit if requested to do so.</p>
                    <p>"In regard to the absence of <persName>Major Russell</persName>, about which you inquired yesterday, I would state that on the <date when="1862-03-10">10th March 1862</date>, he was attached to the Army as Aid to <persName><choice><abbr>Genl</abbr><expan>General</expan></choice> McClellan</persName>, and left <placeName>Washington</placeName> with the troops on that day. The army being near <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, he occasionally visited <placeName>Washington</placeName> up to the <date when="1862-03-28">28th March</date>, which is the last day he was at this Office within that month. He left the City on the <date notBefore="1862-03-29" notAfter="1862-03-30">29th or 30th of that month</date>, and did not return until the <date notBefore="1862-07-23" notAfter="1862-07-24">23d or 24th of July '62</date>, being constantly present at the Head <choice><abbr>Qrs.</abbr><expan>Quarters</expan></choice> of <persName><choice><abbr>Genl</abbr><expan>General</expan></choice> McClellan</persName>'s Army, during the entire period of his absence. He left this City again on the <date when="1862-08-03">3d of August</date> on business at the north, and returned on or about the <date when="1862-08-20">20th <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.01084.009.jpg"/> August</date>, very sick, and remained in his rooms from that time until the <date when="1862-09-10">10th September, 1862</date>, when he resumed the duties of his Office."</p>
                    
                    <p>When it is remembered that <persName>Major Russell</persName> was a Paymaster in the Marine Corps, whose entire time could have been well employed in the discharge of his own appropriate duties, and, that, notwithstanding this, his zeal in behalf of his country led him to exchange the quiet office for the field of battle, I cannot doubt that you will regard his case a particularly meritorious, and the claim presented on behalf of his estate as justly entitled to your most favorable consideration.</p>
                    <p>Requesting this statement to be filed, and considered part of my petition in the case</p>
                    <closer>I have the honor to remain Very respectfully Your <choice><abbr>Ob't</abbr><expan>Obedient</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Serv't</abbr><expan>Servant</expan></choice>
                    <signed><persName>Moses Kelly</persName><lb/>
                    Administrator W. A. of <persName>William W. Russell</persName></signed>.</closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>To the Board of Commissioners of Emancipation for the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.01084.010.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main"><placeName>United States of America</placeName>,</head>
                <dateline><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                <salute><hi rend="bold">To all to whom these Presents shall Come, Greeting:</hi></salute>
                <p>Know ye, That on the <date when="1862-12-16"><seg type="handwritten">16th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">December</seg> in the year of our Lord 18<seg type="handwritten">62</seg></date>, Letters <seg type="handwritten">of Administration W. A.</seg> of all and singular the goods, chattels, and credits, which were of <seg type="handwritten"><choice><abbr>Maj.</abbr><expan>Major</expan></choice> <persName>William W. Russell</persName></seg> late of <seg type="handwritten">the U. S. Marine Corps</seg> deceased, was, by the Orphans' Court of <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid, granted committed unto <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Moses Kelly</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName></seg> the <seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Moses Kelly</persName></seg> having first entered into bond, with approved securities, for the faithful performance of the duties thereof.</p>
                <closer>
                    Witness <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>William F. Purcell</persName> <choice><abbr>Esq</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice></seg></signed> <lb/>Judge of the Orphans' Court of <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, this <date when="1862-12-23"><seg type="handwritten">23rd</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">December</seg> Anno Domini <seg type="handwritten">1862</seg></date><lb/>
                Test:
                <signed><seg type="handwritten">Z. C. Robbins</seg><lb/>
                Register of Wills.</signed></closer>
            </div1>                
           
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.01084.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><date when="1862-12-17">Dec 17</date>.</dateline>
                <div2 type="procedural">
                    <ab><persName>Moses Kelly</persName> <choice><abbr>adr</abbr><expan>administrator</expan></choice> of <persName>Russell</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Ellen</persName> dont know age—hired her 3 years bad teeth. Cook worth $7—health good—strong no children (<unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">can say</unclear> 35 years)</ab>
                    <ab>$800</ab>
                </div2>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.01084.002.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="procedural">
                    <ab><date when="1862-12">Dec</date></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>Andrew Mcheffy</persName> I recognize servant as <persName>Major Russel</persName>s servant title through wife. <persName>Major Russel</persName> was I believe loyal—<unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">children all valued</unclear></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab><persName>George Rose</persName>, 62 or 63 Saw wood &amp;c paid master $8 a month &amp; clothed &amp; supported myself rheumatism.</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="testimony">
                    <ab>Major <persName>Geo Bender</persName>. Recognize property of <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc"><persName>May Bowie</persName></unclear> then Mrs <persName><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">Flitch</unclear></persName> then Major <persName>Russel</persName> by his wife— Major <persName>Russel</persName> was loyal $259</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
