<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00639">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Jane E. Beall, Matilda B. Louisa Beall, and
               Margaret J. Beall, 6 June 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
               <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
               <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
               <name xml:id="sd">Shailana Dunn-Wall</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00639</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
                     Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/).
                     Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available
                     non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission
                     for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project
                     team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Jane E. Beall, Matilda B. Louisa Beall, and Margaret J. Beall, 6
                  June 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-06-06">June 6, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Jane E. Beall, Matilda B. Louisa Beall, and Margaret J.
                        Beall, 6 June 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-06-06">June 6, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury,
                        1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                        Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                        (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm
                  copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Jane Elizabeth Beall</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Matilda B. Louisa Beall</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Margaret J. Beall</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>David H. Bowie</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2013-02-11" who="#jc">blessed</change>
         <change when="2013-02-10" who="#kp">blessed</change>
         <change when="2012-12-28" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
            necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
            encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2012-09-19" who="#sd">checked</change>
         <change when="2012-09-13" who="#jc">transcribed and encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00639.001.jpg"/>

         <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
            <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
            <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                  when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of
               certain persons held to service or labor in the District of Columbia."</p>

            <p>Your Petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>, <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Jane E. Beall</persName>, <persName>Matilda B. L. Beall</persName> and
                     <persName>Margaret J. Beall</persName>
               </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <placeName>Rockville Maryland</placeName>
               </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> petition in writing, represents
               and states, that <seg type="handwritten">they are</seg>
               <del>is a</del> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> loyal to the United States,
               who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service
               or labor against <seg type="handwritten">seventeen</seg> person<seg
                  type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten"
                  >s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Cicily Talbott</persName>, <persName>Charlotte Plowden</persName>,
                     <persName>Charles Plowden</persName>, <persName>Lotty Plowden</persName>,
                     <persName>Teresa Tyler</persName>, <persName>Henry Tyler</persName>,
                     <persName>Ann Maria Tyler</persName>, <persName>Sophia Clements</persName>,
                     <persName>Harriet Smith</persName>, <persName>Jennie Smith</persName>,
                     <persName>Bell Smith</persName>, <persName>Margery Smith</persName>,
                     <persName>Louisa Smith</persName>, <persName>Billy Smith</persName>,
                     <persName>Mary Jane Smith</persName>, <persName>Chas. Smith</persName> and
                     <persName>Maurice</persName>
               </seg> for and during the life<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of said <seg
                  type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                  type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim
               of your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> to such service or labor; that at
               the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Cicily Talbott</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg
                  type="handwritten">about seventy years</seg> and of the personal description
                  following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                  person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                  describe each one separately.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">black woman five feet two or three inches in height active
                  and healthy</seg>
               <list type="handwritten">
                  <item>2 <persName>Charlotte Plowden</persName> black woman about five feet five or
                     six inches in height and stout</item>
                  <item>3 <persName>Charles Plowden</persName> black boy nine years of age</item>
                  <item>4 <persName>Lotty Plowden</persName> black girl seven years of age</item>
                  <item>5 <persName>Teresa Tyler</persName> black woman very tall forty years
                     old</item>
                  <item>6 <persName>Henry Tyler</persName> black man about forty four years old
                     about five feet eight inches in height</item>
                  <item>7 <persName>Sophia Clements</persName> black woman five feet three or four
                     inches in height forty one years old</item>
                  <item>8 <persName>Harriet Smith</persName> mulatto woman five feet three inches in
                     height thirty years old</item>
                  <item>9 <persName>Jennie Smith</persName> bright mulatto girl nine years
                     old</item>
                  <item>10 <persName>Bell Smith</persName> bright mulatto girl four years old</item>
                  <item>11 <persName>Margery Smith</persName> bright mulatto girl one year
                     old</item>
                  <item>12 <persName>Louisa Smith</persName> black woman twenty eight years
                     old</item>
                  <item>13 <persName>Billy Smith</persName> copper colored boy eleven years
                     old</item>
                  <item>14 <persName>Mary Jane Smith</persName> mulatto girl nine years old</item>
                  <item>15 <persName>Chas. Smith</persName> black boy six years old</item>
                  <item>16 <persName>Maurice</persName> mulatto man twenty nine years old lame from
                     having had his leg broken</item>
                  <item>17 <persName>Ann Maria Tyler</persName> mulatto girl nine years old very
                     smart</item>
               </list>
            </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00639.002.jpg"/>

            <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> acquired <seg type="handwritten"
                  >their</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg
                  type="handwritten">persons</seg> in manner following:<note type="government"
                  place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom,
                  and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of
                  title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                  found.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Cicily Talbott</persName>, <persName>Henry Tyler</persName>,
                     <persName>Charlotte Plowden</persName>, <persName>Teresa Tyler</persName>,
                     <persName>Sophia Clements</persName>, <persName>Harriet Smith</persName>,
                     <persName>Louisa Smith</persName>, <persName>Lucy Moore</persName> and
                     <persName>Maurice</persName> were inherited by petitioners from their mother
                  Mrs. <persName>Jane N. Beall</persName></seg> of <placeName>Montgomery Co.
                  Maryland</placeName> and the other servants are the children of the above named
               ones born while they were owned by petitioners</p>

            <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> claim to the service or labor of
               said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
               therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$9400</seg> dollars in money.<note
                  type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be,
                  touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the
                  person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral,
                  mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of
                  the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with
                  an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said
                  person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and
                  that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity
                  or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with
                  an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
               <list type="handwritten">
                  <item>
                     <persName>Cicily Talbott</persName> for her age is very active &#38; healthy is
                     a good cook valued at $50&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Charlotte Plowden</persName> is a first-rate cook, ironer and washer
                     stout strong &#38; healthy valued at $800&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Charles Plowden</persName> is a smart and likely boy strong and
                     healthy valued at $500&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Lotty Plowden</persName> stout and healthy girl valued at
                     $350&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Henry Tyler</persName> is a strong and healthy man is an house
                     servant valued at $1000</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Teresa Tyler</persName> is a strong and healthy woman an excellent <choice>
                        <sic>nourse</sic>
                        <corr>nurse</corr>
                     </choice>, first rate cook, ironer &#38; washer valued at $800&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Ann Maria Tyler</persName> is a very smart and active child strong
                     and healthy valued at $500&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Sophia Clements</persName> is an house servant, a good cook, ironer
                     and washer valued at $800&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Harriet Smith</persName> is a very capable house servant in every
                     department, an excellent cook, ironer and washer valued at $900&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Jennie Smith</persName> a smart and intelligent child valued at
                     $500&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Bell Smith</persName> is a bright child valued at $300 </item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Margery Smith</persName> is a very healthy child valued at
                     $100</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Louisa Smith</persName> is a strong and healthy woman good cook,
                     ironer and washer valued at $600</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Billy Smith</persName> raised as house servant valued at
                     $600&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Mary Jane Smith</persName> strong, healthy girl very smart valued at
                     $500&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Charles Smith</persName> strong healthy child&#8212;valued at
                     $300&#8212;</item>
                  <item>
                     <persName>Maurice</persName> has been an excellent servant very reliable, a
                     first-class field hand and house servant, but at present is unable to do any
                     thing on account of his leg being broken valued at $500&#8212;These persons are
                     free from any infirmities with above exception either bodily mental or moral,
                     &#38; are honest, industrious and faithful.</item>
               </list>
            </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v2" facs="cww.00639.003.jpg"/>
            <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> hereby declares that <seg
                  type="handwritten">they</seg> bear<del>s</del> true and faithful allegiance to the
               Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">they have</seg>
               <del>has</del> not borne arms against the United States in the present rebellion, nor
               in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

            <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                  allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they have</seg>
               <del>has</del> not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the
               District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time
               of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
               <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                  petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> claim to such service or labor.</p>

            <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                  allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the
               service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in
               or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner
               aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the United
               States.</p>

            <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> pray<del>s</del> the said
               Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten"
                  >their</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"
                  >persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that
               they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
               the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the provisions
               of said act of Congress.</p>

            <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                  <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Jane Elizabeth Beall</persName>.</seg>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Matilda B. L. Beall</persName>.</seg>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Margaret J. Beall</persName>.</seg>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div1>

         <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00639.004.jpg"/>

         <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
            <p>The Miss <persName>Beall's</persName> residing in <placeName>Montgomery County
                  Maryland</placeName>, 8 or 10 miles from the <placeName>District of
                  Columbia</placeName> have for the last 12 or 15 years been in the habit of hiring
               their Slaves here&#8212;when the emancipation act passed (<date when="1862-04-16"
                  >16th April</date>) a portion only, of those, who had been in the habit of being
               here, were here, the other, not having places, were in <placeName>Montgomery
                  County</placeName>, waiting to be hired here&#8212;Those that were here, on the
                  <date when="1862-04-16">16th April</date>, &#38; entitle to the <choice>
                  <sic>benifit</sic>
                  <corr>benenfit</corr>
               </choice> of that law, are included in their petition, &#38; the application now is,
               to amend their petition, so as include those that were accidentally absent on the
               passage of the law&#8212;</p>
            <closer>
               <placeName>Washn. City</placeName>
               <date when="1862-07-11">July 11th. 1862</date>
            </closer>
         </div1>

         <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00639.005.jpg"/>

         <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
            <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                  Petition.</hi>]</head>

            <dateline>
               <del>
                  <placeName>District of Columbia,</placeName>
               </del>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic"><del><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</del></hi>
               <lb/>
               <seg type="handwritten">
                  <placeName>State of Maryland Montgomery County,</placeName> to with; </seg>
            </dateline>

            <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
               <p>
                  <seg type="handwritten">We</seg>
                  <del>I</del>, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Jane E Beall</persName>, <persName>Matilda B L Beall</persName> &#38;
                        <persName>Margaret J. Beall</persName>
                  </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                  things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of <seg
                     type="handwritten">our</seg>
                  <del>my</del> own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the
                  several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                  information of others, <seg type="handwritten">we</seg>
                  <del>I</del> believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
               <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Jane Elizabeth Beall</persName>.</seg>
                  </signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Matilda B. L. Beall</persName>.</seg>
                  </signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Margaret J Beall</persName>.</seg>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div2>

            <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
               <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-31">
                     <seg type="handwritten">thirty-first</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                        >May,</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
               <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>D. H. Bowie</persName> J. P.</seg>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div2>
            <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
               <dateline>
                  <placeName>State of Maryland Montgomery County</placeName> Sct</dateline>
               <p>I hereby certify that <persName>Daivd H. Bowie</persName> Gentleman before whom
                  the aforegoing affidavit was made and whose genuine signature is thereto
                  subscribed was at the time thereof one of the <placeName>State of
                     Maryland's</placeName> Justices of the peace in and for <placeName>Montgomery
                     County</placeName> duly commissioned and sworn</p>
               <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed the seal of
                  the Circuit Court for said County this <date when="1862-06-03">3d day of June AD
                     1862</date>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>James G. Henning</persName>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>ClR</abbr>
                        <expan>clerk</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <lb/> Circuit Court for <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div2>
         </div1>

         <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
            <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been
               imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one
               place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the
               Verification.</note>
            <ab>639<lb/>
               <persName>Jane E.</persName>
               <persName>Matilda B. Louisa</persName>
               <persName>Margaret J. Beall</persName>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <persName>Jno. A. Smith</persName>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice>
            </ab>
            <ab>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Rev</abbr>
                  <expan>Reverend</expan>
               </choice>. <persName>Lorenza Russell</persName>
               <lb/> P. Office Dept.</ab>
            <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-06">June 6, 1862</date>
            </ab>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
