<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00363">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Emily W. Farquhar, 22 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00363</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Emily W. Farquhar, 22 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Emily W. Farquhar, 22 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>A. Hyde</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-08" who="#crl">checked</change>
<change when="2013-05-08" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-02" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00363.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">

                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Georgetown D.C.</placeName></seg>
                    by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny Brooks</persName>, and her two children
                            <persName>Frank</persName> &#38; <persName>Melinda</persName></seg>
                        person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny Brooks</persName>, and her two children
                            <persName>Frank</persName> &#38; <persName>Melinda</persName></seg> for
                    and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName>
                        &#38; the said Children</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName> and the said Children
                        are</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to
                    such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName>, and her children,
                            <persName>Frank</persName> and <persName>Melinda</persName>,
                        were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg
                        type="handwritten">twenty four, or thereabout, Five, and Three,
                        respectively:</seg> and of the personal description following:<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as
                        to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each
                        one separately.</note> <seg type="handwritten">The said <persName>Fanny</persName> is about five feet
                        four inches in height; dark colored healthy and strong, and a very capable
                        cook, washer and ironer, honest and faithful, and in every respect a
                        valuable house servant.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The said <persName>Frank</persName> is a very bright,
                        intelligent and handsome mulatto, and of the ordinary size of children of
                        his age:</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten">The said <persName>Melinda</persName>, of the same
                        description and appearance, and both perfectly healthy</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00363.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName></seg> in manner following:<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was
                        acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held
                        under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the
                        public record where the same may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">by devise of <persName>Anthony Smith</persName> late of
                            <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, deceased, by Will; a copy of
                        which is hereto annexed, which said decedent owned said
                            <persName>Fanny</persName> since she was about eight
                        years of age</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName> and her children</seg> was, at
                    the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">twelve hundred</seg> dollars in money<seg type="handwritten">,</seg><note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">said <persName>Fanny</persName> being perfectly healthy, never having had a
                        day's sickness, other than healthy child bearing, is strong to labor, and
                        very capable as a Kitchen and house servant, and both the children are
                        healthy &#38; free from physical defects, the latter being of a color and
                        appearance that would always command a high price. <persName>Fanny</persName> is also a good seamstress</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">slaves</seg>
                    into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said
                    act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName> &#38; children</seg>
                        w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor
                    therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                    labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName> &#38; children</seg> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                    the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fanny</persName>,
                            <persName>Frank</persName> &#38; <persName>Melinda</persName></seg>
                    herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise
                    and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the
                    Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in
                    conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>(Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName>.</seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00363.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>Copy</ab>
                <ab>The will<lb/>
                    of<lb/>
                    <persName>Anthony Smith</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00363.003.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In the name of God, Amen. I <persName>Anthony Smith</persName>, of
                            <placeName>Georgetown</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> being of sound and disposing mind, memory and
                        understanding, but weak in body; and considering the uncertainty of life and
                        the certainty of death, and being desirous to settle and dispose of my
                        worldly estate, so make and declare this my last will and testament as
                        follows; that is to say.</p>
                    <p>Item. I will and direct that all my debts and funeral expenses be first paid
                        by my Executor, hereinafter named.</p>
                    <p>Item. I give and bequeath my servant <persName>Fanny</persName> and her issue
                        to <persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName>, now living with me.</p>
                    <p>Item. I will and direct that all the residue of my estate real, personal, and
                        mixed, be turned into money, as far as practicable, by my Executor, and the
                        aggregate thereof, after paying legal expenses, to be disposed of as
                        hereinafter named.</p>
                    <p>Item. One third of said aggregate to the said <persName>Emily W.
                            Farquhar</persName>; one third to <persName>Anna M.</persName> the wife
                        of <persName>Anthony Hyde</persName> of <placeName>Georgetown,
                            D.C.</placeName> and the remaining one third to my said Executor, herein
                        after named, <hi rend="underline">in trust</hi>, for the use and benefit of
                            <persName>Elizabeth M.</persName>, the wife of <persName>Samuel M.
                            Bootes</persName> of <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, and her
                        children, and if she and they refuse to <choice><sic>recieve</sic><corr>receive</corr></choice> it, then to divide said third equally between said <persName>Emily
                            W. Farquhar</persName> and the said <persName>Anna M.
                        Hyde</persName>.</p>
                    <p>And I do hereby nominate and appoint <persName>Anthony Hyde</persName> of
                            <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, my Executor, of this my last will and
                        testament.</p>
                    <p>Singed, sealed, published and declared as and for <pb xml:id="leaf003r"
                            facs="cww.00363.005.jpg"/>my last will and testament this <date
                            when="1859-02-21">twenty first day of February A.D. eighteen hundred and
                            fifty-nine</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Anthony Smith</persName> his X mark Seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Signed, sealed, published and declared, as and for his last will and
                        testament, by the said <persName>Anthony Smith</persName> in the presence of
                        us, who, at his request, and in his presence, and in the presence of each
                        other, have signed our names hereto as witnesses thereof, said
                            <persName>Smith</persName> signing by "his mark" being too weak to write
                        his name.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>P. H. Sweet</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>F. S. Barbarin</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Jacob Young</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit;<lb/>                       
                        Orphans Court<lb/>
                        <date when="1859-03-08">March 8th 1859</date></dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared <persName>Parker H. Sweet</persName> and <persName>Francis
                            S. Barbarin</persName> two of the subscribing witnesses to the
                        aforegoing last will and testament of <persName>Anthony Smith</persName>
                        late of <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid, deceased and
                        severally made oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that they did see
                        the testator, therein named, sign and seal this will (by making his mark
                        thereto,) that he published, pronounced and declared this same to be his
                        last will and testament, that at the time of so doing, he was, to the best
                        of their apprehensions, of sound and disposing mind memory and
                        understanding. And that they, together with <persName>Jacob Young</persName>
                        the other subscribing witness, respectively subscribed their names as
                        witnesses to this will, in the presence and at the request of the Testator,
                        and in the presence of each other&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>Test;
                        <signed><persName>Ed. N. Roach</persName> <choice><abbr>Regr</abbr><expan>Register of</expan></choice> wills.</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00363.006.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>I certify, that the aforegoing is a true copy from the original file and
                        recorded in the Office of the Register of Wills, for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName>, aforesaid.</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of office, this <date when="1859-03-15">15 day of
                            March in the year 1859</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Ed; N. Roach</persName> <choice><abbr>Regr.</abbr><expan>Register of</expan></choice> Wills</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00363.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say,
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in
                        fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in
                        substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-13"><seg
                                type="handwritten">13th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>A. Hyde</persName><lb/>Notary Public</seg></signed></closer>                    
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>The within named <persName>Fanny</persName> is in my service, and has been
                        for several months, and other children within named are with her, and I
                        fully confirm the statements of the petition except as to her value, which I
                        consider too low.</p>                    
                    <closer><dateline><date when="1862-05-21">May 21st 1862</date></dateline>
                        <signed><persName>John B. Davidson</persName></signed><lb/>
                        <address><addrLine>No 126 Washington St.<lb/>
                            <placeName>Georgetown</placeName></addrLine></address></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I have personal knowledge of <persName>Fanny</persName>'s worth, and think
                        the value fixed at a low figure. She was in the Testator's (my
                        Father-in-law's) family, since she was about 12 years old, and under my
                        constant observation, and, <choice><abbr>altho</abbr><expan>although</expan></choice>' not <choice>
                            <sic>prepossing</sic>
                            <corr>prepossessing</corr>
                        </choice> in appearance, she is a very valuable and capable
                        kitchen and house servant.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>A. Hyde</persName></signed><lb/>
                        <address><addrLine>122 Wash. St. <placeName>Geo. Town</placeName></addrLine></address>
                        <dateline><date when="1862-05-22">May 22/62</date></dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>


            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>363</ab>
                <ab><persName>Emily W. Farquhar</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
