<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00370">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Nicholas Acker, 22 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                    <name xml:id="kn">Kaci Nash</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00370</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Nicholas Acker, 22 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Nicholas Acker, 22 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-01-16" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-12" who="#scl">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-12-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2012-10-22" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-01-30" who="#kn">transcribed, encoded</change>
            <change when="2012-02-16" who="#kn">made corrections to original encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00370.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the City of <placeName> Washington D.
                            C.</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a</seg> person of
                    African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName> a slave</seg> for and during
                        <del>the</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> life <del>of said</del> and that by said act
                    of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Maria
                        Adams</persName></seg> was discharged and freed of and from all claim of
                    your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>
                    </seg> was of the age of <seg type="handwritten">about seventeen years</seg> and
                    of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Five feet and three inches <choice>
                            <sic>heigh</sic>
                            <corr>height</corr>
                        </choice>, dark chestnut color &#38; nose slightly depressed</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00370.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here
                        state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">to wit. By purchase from <persName>John E.
                            Thompson</persName> administrator of <persName>William
                            Burford</persName> deceased. Said purchase was made in
                            <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> in the State of
                            <placeName>Maryland</placeName> on the <date when="1858-10-15">15th
                            October A.D. 1858</date>, for the sum of six hundred and fifty dollars
                        as will appear by reference to the receipt herewith filed, marked "Petition
                        exhibit A."</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Anne Maria Adams</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg
                        type="handwritten">at least one thousand</seg> dollars in money.<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">That she is an excellent house servant and of good and
                        easy disposition perfectly healthy and free from all mental and bodily
                        defects or infirmities. That your petitioner has been offered and has
                        refused eleven hundred dollars for the said <persName>Ann Maria
                            Adams</persName>
                    </seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>
                    </seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress;
                    and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>
                    </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>
                    </seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any
                    person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against
                    the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">Ann Maria Adams</seg> herein above set forth;
                    and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value
                    of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of
                    the United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00370.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>Collar</sic>
                        <corr>Colored</corr>
                    </choice> girl, <lb/>Bill of Sale <date when="1858">1858</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>In the matter of the petition of <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>&#8212;for
                    Compensation for a slave woman named <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>
                </ab>
                <ab>Petitioners Exhibit A.</ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00370.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>
                    <placeName>Montgomery County, Md.</placeName>
                    <date when="1858-10-15">October, 15, 1858</date>.</p>
                <p>By virtue of an order from the Orphan's Court of this county, to sell sufficient
                    of the personal estate of <persName>William Burford</persName> to pay the debts
                    of the same I, as one of the Administrators upon said property hereby agree to
                    sell the negro girl <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>, (aged about 13 years,
                    and appraised at Six Hundred Dollars) to Mr. <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>
                    upon the following terms, viz&#8212;Two Hundred and Fifty Dollars cash, and Two
                    Hundred Dollars payable in eight months, and Two Hundred Dollars payable in ten
                    months from date with interest, making in all the sum of Six Hundred and Fifty
                    Dollars, that sum being fifty dollars more than said negro girl's appraised
                    value.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>J. E. Thompson</persName><lb/> Administrator of <persName>Wm.
                            Buford</persName> deceased.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>
                    <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>
                    <placeName>Md.</placeName>
                    <date when="1858-10-15">October, 15, 1858</date>.</p>
                <p>Received in <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>
                    <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, from <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName> Two
                    Hundred Dollars cash and his two notes for Four Hundred Dollars viz., one note
                    for Two Hundred Dollars payable in eight months and one note for Two Hundred
                    Dollars payable in ten months, both with interest from date. Said cash and notes
                    being in full of the purchase money of negro girl Ann Maria Adams belonging to
                    the personal estate of <persName>Wm. Burford</persName> deceased and sold by
                    order of the Orphan's <choice>
                        <sic>County</sic>
                        <corr>Court</corr>
                    </choice> of said County, to pay the debts of said Estate.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>J. E. Thompson</persName>, Administrator <persName>William
                            Burford</persName> deceased</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00370.005.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-22">
                            <seg type="handwritten">22</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>F. I. Murphey</persName><lb/> Justice of the Peace in and
                                for the <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> in the
                                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>370</ab>
                <ab><persName>Nicholas Acker</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Petition of <persName>Nicholas Acker</persName>&#8212;</ab>
                <ab>1. slave, named <persName>Ann Maria Adams</persName>.</ab>
                <ab>Witnesses <lb/>
                    <persName>Wm. H. Thompson</persName>, <address><addrLine>7th Street Island&#8212;</addrLine></address><lb/>
                    <persName>John E. Thompson</persName>
                    <address><addrLine>corner of 2d street west &#38; E. street
                    North&#8212;</addrLine></address></ab>

            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
