<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00188">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Margaret Ann Hutchinson, 13 May
                    1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
            <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00188</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Margaret Ann Hutchinson, 13 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Margaret Ann Hutchinson, 13 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Margaret Ann Hutchinson</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values @ facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2013-01-17" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
         <change when="2012-12-17" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00188.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                    <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                    <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Margaret A.
                                Hutchinson</persName>
                 </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                     <placeName>Washington City DC</placeName>
                 </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                        that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of
                        the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a man servant, a</seg> person of African descent of
                        the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James Shaw</persName>
                 </seg>
                        for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James
                                Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James Shaw</persName> has been</seg>
                        discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such
                        service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James Shaw</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">Twenty two years</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">of dark complexion, black
                            eyes, and black hair, about five feet seven inches high, and of medium
                            build; no scars or marks visible.</seg>
               </p>



                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00188.002.jpg"/>

                    <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                        aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servant
                                <persName>James Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was
                            acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if
                            held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer
                            to the public record where the same may be found.</note>
                        <seg type="handwritten">By will from her brother in law <persName>Thomas W.
                                Jones</persName>, which will was admitted to record in the Orphans
                            Court of this City &#38; County on the <date when="1859-06-25">25th day
                                of June 1859</date>: the said servant <persName>James
                                Shaw</persName>, having been born of a slave woman, owned by
                                <persName>George Bean</persName> father of your petitioner, &#38;
                            upon his decease, was <choice>
                                <sic>alloted</sic>
                                <corr>allotted</corr>
                            </choice> to <persName>F. W. Jones</persName> on division of his, (the
                            said <persName>Geo. Bean</persName>'s) estate, by mutual consent of all
                            the heirs;</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servant <persName>James Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> was, at
                        the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Twelve hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                            there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                            labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if
                            any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of
                            said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                            service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                            petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                            impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and
                            that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such
                            infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim
                            should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such
                            infirmity or defect.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">That said <persName>James Shaw</persName> is a smart active intelligent man,
                            an excellent house servant, &#38; accustomed to the care and management
                            of horses is of a good Constitution and of sound bodily health, never having been
                            sick since his early infancy: is sound in mind and body, and is
                            perfectly honest and trustworthy: that your petitioner is not aware of
                            any mental, moral or bodily defects or infirmities that would impair his
                            value, and she does not believe any exist</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears
                        true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not
                        borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                        rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James
                                Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> into the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and
                        that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> was held to service or labor
                        therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor.</p>

                    <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> does not
                        originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who
                        has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the
                        Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine
                        the validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service
                        or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James
                            Shaw</persName>
                 </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found
                        to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in
                        money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                        said act of Congress.</p>

                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>M A
                                    Hutchinson</persName>
                    </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00188.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Copy</ab>
                    <ab>The will of <persName>Thomas W. Jones</persName></ab>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00188.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I <persName>Thomas W. Jones</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                            Washington</placeName> being of sound &#38; disposing mind and memory
                        make this my will.</p>
                    <p>I give, devise, and bequeath to my sister-in-law Mrs. <persName>Margarett Ann
                            Hutchinson</persName> her heirs and assigns all and whatsoever property
                        and estate, I may die seized and possessed of, or in which I may be in any
                        manner interested of whatsoever kind and nature the same may be real
                        personal or mixed, and wheresoever it may be situated.</p>
                    <p>And I hereby appoint the said <persName>Margarett A. Hutchinson</persName>
                        Executrix of this my last will&#8212;</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal this <date when="1857-03-31">thirty first day of
                            March in the year Eighteen Hundred and Fifty seven</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Thos W. Jones</persName> Seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Signed, sealed, published, and declared by <persName>Thomas W.
                            Jones</persName>, to be his last will &#38; testament, in our presence,
                        who, at his request, in his presence, and in the presence of each other,
                        have hereto set our names, as witnesses&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Richard M. Hanson</persName>.</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Joseph M. Adams</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Thos. Hutchingson</persName>&#8212;</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>District</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00188.005.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline>
                  <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>; Orphans'
                            Court<lb/>
                  <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit, <date when="1859-06-07">June 7, 1859</date>.</dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared, <persName>Thomas Hutchingson</persName> one of the
                        subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing last will &#38; testament of
                            <persName>Thomas W. Jones</persName> late of <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> aforesaid, deceased, &#38; made oath on the Holy
                        Evangels of Almighty, that he did see the Testator therein named sign &#38;
                        seal this will, that he published, pronounced &#38; declared the same to be
                        his last will &#38; testament, that at the time of so doing, he was to the
                        best of his apprehension of sound and disposing mind, memory &#38;
                        understanding, &#38; that he together with <persName>Richard M.
                            Hanson</persName> &#38; <persName>Joseph M. Adams</persName> the other
                        subscribing Witnesses, respectively subscribed their names, as witnesses to
                        this will; in the presence &#38; at the request of the Testator, &#38; in
                        the presence of each other&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>Test; <signed><persName>Ea. N. Roach</persName> <choice><abbr>Reg.</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> Wills</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline>
                  <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                  <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit;</dateline>
                    <p>I certify that the aforegoing is a true copy from the original filed &#38;
                        recorded in the office of the Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName>, aforesaid&#8212;</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand &#38; seal of Office this <date when="1859-06-27">27th day of June in the year
                            1859</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Ea. N. Roach</persName>&#8212; <choice><abbr>Reg.</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> Wills</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00188.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">

                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Margaret Ann Hutchinson</persName>&#8212;</seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>M A Hutchinson</persName>
                    </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-13">
                     <seg type="handwritten">13th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by)
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName> <choice><abbr>clk.</abbr><expan>clerk</expan></choice></seg></signed>
                       </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>188</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Margaret Ann Hutchinson</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>George B. Smith</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>John Jolly</persName><lb/>
               <placeName>Blagdens Wharf</placeName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>