<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00824">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Rebecca R. Darby, Ruth E. Darby, and James A. Darby, 1 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00824</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Rebecca R. Darby, Ruth E. Darby, and James A. Darby, 1 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Rebecca R. Darby, Ruth E. Darby, and James A. Darby, 1 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Ruth E. Darby</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>James A. Darby</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Naylor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-13" who="#jc">performed semi-automated file cleanup</change>
            <change when="2013-05-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-04-17" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00824.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName>
                        &amp; <persName>Ruth E. Darby</persName>, and <persName>James A.
                            Darby</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Montgomery
                            County, Md</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">their</seg>
                    petition in writing, represent<del>s</del> and state<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they are</seg> <del>is a</del> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the
                    passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against
                        <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName> a</seg> person
                    of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel
                            Chambers</persName></seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName></seg> and that by
                    said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel
                            Chambers</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim
                    of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName> was</seg> of
                    the age <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as
                        to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each
                        one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">She is about twenty six or seven years old: black: above
                        the medium height: her general health has always been good; she is a good
                        cook, can wash and iron well: is a good nurse in sickness watchful and
                        prudent: a first rate chambermaid and house servant, with intelligence and
                        practical experience which fit her for, and she is a good housekeeper: a
                        dairy woman, and can take charge of &amp; superintend the planting and
                        management of a kitchen garden and knows how to raise and the management of
                        poultry</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00824.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> acquired <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of
                    said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName></seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By gift from their father <persName>Aden
                            Darby</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery County Maryland</placeName>
                        about the year <date notBefore="1851" notAfter="1852">1851 or 1852</date>.
                        (your petitioner <persName>Rebecca R</persName>, being the older of the two
                        sisters &amp; brother filed the claim in this case under the Statute in her
                        own name, but intended it to be for the benefit of both herself &amp; sister
                        &amp; brother) and they filed herewith the original bill of sale and stated
                        further that her said brother is now &amp; has been for a long time a
                        cripple confined to his bed &amp; incapable of transacting any
                        business</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName></seg> was, at the
                    time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">one
                        thousand</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3" target="#r1">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching
                        the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person,
                        as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral,
                        mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the
                        value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such
                        statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities
                        or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to
                        such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">Your Petitioners further say that this girl <persName>Rachel</persName> ought to come up to the highest market value not
                        only for the qualities they have already mentioned, but for her superior
                        moral qualities her truthfulness, integrity, and devotedness to their
                        interests, which led them to trust her without constraint, not only with the
                        keys, but with access to all their moveables</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> hereby declare<del>s</del> that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> bear<del>s</del> true and faithful allegiance
                    to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> has not borne arms against the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion, nor in any
                    way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further states and alleges,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<del>s</del> not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName></seg> into the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel</persName></seg> was held to service or
                    labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                    labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to
                    the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel
                            Chambers</persName></seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or
                    labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Chambers</persName></seg>
                    herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise
                    and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the
                    Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in
                    conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rebecca. R.
                                Darby</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00824.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab><persName>Aden Darby</persName><lb/> To<lb/>
                        <persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName><lb/> And<lb/>
                        <persName>Ruth E. Darby</persName></ab>
                    <ab>Bill of Sale</ab>
                    <ab><choice>
                            <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                            <expan>Received</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <date when="1852-05-24">24th May 1852</date> To be Recorded and the same day
                        was Recorded in Liber J. G H No 1 Folios 282 and 283 one of the Land Records
                        of the Circuit Court for <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> and
                        examined per</ab>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>James G. Hening</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                                <expan>Clerk</expan>
                            </choice></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00824.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents that I <persName>Aden Darby</persName> of the
                            <placeName>County of Montgomery</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, for and in Consideration of the Natural love and
                        affection which I have and bear to my daughters <persName>Rebecca R.
                            Darby</persName> and <persName>Ruth R. Darby</persName>, and to my son
                            <persName>James A. Darby</persName>, and for the further Consideration
                        of the sum of fifty dollars current money to me in hand paid by the said
                            <persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName> and <persName>Ruth E.
                            Darby</persName> before the execution and delivery hereof, have given
                        bargained and sold, and I do hereby give bargain and sell to the said
                            <persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName>, &amp; <persName>Ruth E.
                            Darby</persName>, the following named negroes—slaves for
                        life—to wit. <persName>Harriet</persName> aged about forty years,
                            <persName>Thomas</persName> aged about twenty one
                            years—<persName>Frank</persName> aged about nineteen years,
                            <persName>Rachel</persName> aged about eighteen years,
                            <persName>Robert</persName>
                        <persName>Laura</persName>
                        <persName>Janet</persName> and <persName>Maryella</persName>—To have
                        and to hold the said negroes and their increase to the said
                            <persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName> and <persName>Ruth E.
                            Darby</persName> and the survivor of them, and the executors
                        administrators and assigns of such survivor, for and during the life of my
                        son <persName>James E. Darby</persName> in trust, that the use hire and
                        profit of the said negroes and their increase shall be applied to the
                        support and maintenance of my said daughters and son equally and alike and
                        from and after the death of my said son, should both my said daughters be
                        then living, said negroes and their increase to be equally divided between
                        them, but should either of them be then dead the survivor to have the
                        whole.</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof I have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed my seal
                            <date when="1852-05-06">sixth day of May AD. 1852</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Aden Darby</persName> Seal</signed>
                        <signed><persName>G S Etchison</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> To wit.</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered and it is hereby certified that on this <date when="1852-05-06">sixth day of May in the year of our Lord one thousand
                            eight hundred and fifty two</date> before me the subscriber a justice of the
                            Peace of the <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName> in and for
                                <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> aforesaid, personally
                            appears <persName>Aden Darby</persName> he being known to me<pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00824.005.jpg"/> to be the person who is
                        named and described as and professing to be a party to the foregoing bill of
                        sale or indenture, and doth acknowledge the said bill of sale or instrument
                        of writing to be his act and deed. In testimony whereof, I have hereunto
                        subscribed my name on the day and year aforesaid—</p>
                    <closer>Acknowledged before <signed><persName>G S
                        Etchison</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> To wit</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered that on this <date when="1852-05-06">sixth day of May
                            eighteen hundred and fifty two</date> before me the subscriber a Justice
                        of the Peace of the <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName> in and for said
                        County personally appears <persName>Rebecca R. Darby</persName>, and
                            <persName>Ruth E Darby</persName> and makes oath on the holy Evangely of
                        Almighty God that the consideration mentioned in the above bill of sale is
                        true and bona fide as therein set forth.</p>
                    <closer>Sworn to before <signed><persName>G S
                        Etchison</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p><date when="1852-05-24">1852 May 24th</date>. <choice>
                            <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                            <expan>Received</expan>
                        </choice> one dollar the stamp duty on the above Bill of sale</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Jas D Hening</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                                <expan>Clerk</expan>
                            </choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00824.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rebecca R Darby</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rebecca R
                                    Darby</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-30"><seg type="handwritten">30th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H.
                                    Naylor</persName> J. Peace</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>824</ab>
                <ab><persName>Rebecca R</persName>. &amp; <persName>Ruth E. Darby</persName><lb/>
                    Petition for a slave.</ab>
                <ab>Ex Bill of sale (original)</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>B &amp; B</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
