<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00343">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Mary Fenwick, 21 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
<name xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>

            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00343</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Mary Fenwick, 21 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Mary Fenwick, 21 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Hamilton Loughborough</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-08" who="#crl">checked</change>
<change when="2013-05-07" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-01" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00343.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">

                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Fenwick</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Georgetown, District of
                            Columbia</placeName>,</seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >she</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann
                            Shorter</persName>, <persName>Robert Shorter</persName> and
                            <persName>Lucy Shorter</persName>&#8212;</seg> person<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Shorter</persName>, <persName>Robert
                            Shorter</persName> and <persName>Lucy Shorter</persName>&#8212;The said
                            <persName>Ann Shorter</persName> being held to service&#8212;</seg> for
                        <del>and during the life of said</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">eleven years, four months and fourteen days said
                            <persName>Robert</persName> being held to service for twenty one years,
                        4 months and 14 days, &#38; said <persName>Lucy</persName> being held to
                        service for life</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Shorter</persName>, <persName>Robert
                            Shorter</persName> and <persName>Lucy Shorter</persName> were</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann Shorter</persName>, <persName>Robert Shorter</persName>
                        and <persName>Lucy Shorter</persName> were of the age, twenty five
                        years</seg> <del>of the age of</del> <seg type="handwritten">six years and one year 8 &#189; months
                        respectively</seg> and of the personal description following:<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as
                        to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each
                        one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">that is to say, <persName>Ann Shorter</persName> is of
                        black <choice><choice><orig>colour</orig><reg>color</reg></choice></choice>, five feet 2 inches high, strong and very healthy, of handsome
                        countenance, intelligent and experienced as a Cook; a female 25 years
                            old:&#8212;<persName>Robert Shorter</persName> is a male six years old,
                        of black <choice><orig>colour</orig><reg>color</reg></choice>, three feet 2 inches high, handsome, healthy, bright &#38;
                            intelligent:&#8212;<persName>Lucy Shorter</persName>, (two years old on
                        the <date when="1862-07-31">31st July 1862</date>) a female of light black
                        <choice><orig>colour</orig><reg>color</reg></choice>, a healthy &#38; well formed child.&#8212;The above persons
                            <persName>Ann Shorter</persName> and <persName>Robert Shorter</persName>
                        were purchased for terms of years&#8212;the first for 15 years commencing on
                            <date when="1858-09-01">1. September 1858</date> and the 2d
                            (<persName>Robert</persName>) for 25 years
                        from <date when="1858-09-01">1. September 1858</date>&#8212;The child
                            <persName>Lucy</persName> was born since said purchase&#8212;The
                        purchase was from Mrs. <persName>Margaret Barber</persName> of this
                            <placeName>District</placeName> &#38; was recorded in the Clerks Office of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> about
                        the date thereof&#8212;viz. about <date when="1858-09-01">1st September
                            1858</date>&#8212;</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00343.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann
                            Shorter</persName> &#38; <persName>Robert Shorter</persName></seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By purchase from Mrs. <persName>Margaret
                            Barber</persName> <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="5" unit="chars"/> of the said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> as
                            above specified and that <persName>Lucy Shorter</persName>, a child of
                            said <persName>Ann</persName> was born since the date of said
                            purchase&#8212;</seg></p>


                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons, <persName>Ann</persName>,
                            <persName>Robert</persName> &#38; <persName>Lucy</persName>,</seg> was,
                    at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">eighteen hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government"
                        place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching
                        the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person,
                        as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral,
                        mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the
                        value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such
                        statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities
                        or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to
                        such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">The said persons thus held to service possessed the qualities above
                        specified and were without any defects, moral, mental or bodily as far known
                        to Your Petitioner such as would impair the value of them&#8212;</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons,
                            <persName>Ann</persName>, <persName>Robert</persName> &#38;
                            <persName>Lucy</persName>,</seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann</persName>, <persName>Robert</persName> &#38;
                            <persName>Lucy</persName> were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann</persName>
                        <persName>Robert</persName> &#38; <persName>Lucy</persName></seg> herein
                    above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to
                    the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>(Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Fenwick</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>

            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00343.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>Paid $1.25</ab>
                <ab><persName>M. C. Barber</persName><lb/>
                    to<lb/>
                    <persName>M. Fenwick</persName><lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Assignmt</abbr><expan>Assignment</expan></choice> &#38; Manumission.</ab>
                <ab>Received <date when="1858-09-13">13th September 1858</date> to be recorded and
                    the same day was recorded in Liber J. A. S. 154 folios 394 &#38; 395 one of the
                    Land Records for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> in the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> and examined by</ab>
                <closer><signed><persName>Jno. A. Smith</persName> <choice><abbr>Clk</abbr><expan>Clerk</expan></choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00343.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>To all whom it may concern. Be it known that I <persName>Margaret C. Barber</persName> of the
                            <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District
                            of Columbia</placeName>, for divers good causes and considerations me thereunto moving, as also in further consideration of the sum of five hundred dollars current money to me in hand paid by
                            <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> of <placeName>George Town</placeName> in the said County before the execution hereof
                        (the receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged) have bargained sold and
                        assigned and by this instrument do bargain sell and assign unto the said
                            <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> her Executors administrators and
                        assigns my Negro woman, <persName>Ann Shorter</persName>, aged twenty three
                        years, and her two children, one named <persName>Robert</persName>, born in
                            <date when="1855-09">September Eighteen hundred and fifty five</date>,
                        and the other named <persName>Harriet</persName> born on <date
                            when="1858-07-18">July the eighteenth, last past</date> To have take and
                        hold my said Woman and her said children unto and by the said <persName>Mary
                            Fenwick</persName> her Executors administrators and assigns for the
                        following periods or terms of years&#8212;namely&#8212;the said
                            <persName>Ann Shorter</persName> to serve her and them for the term of
                        fifteen years, commencing from the <date
                            when="1858-09-01">first of
                            September next</date>, and the said two children until they shall
                        respectively attain the age of twenty five years; the mother to be free at
                        the expiration of the said fifteen years, and her said two children to be
                        returned to me or my representatives at their said respective ages of twenty
                        five years, and to serve me and mine, each of them, for the term of five
                        years thereafter, and then to be free; and during the time of their
                        servitude to said <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> or her representatives,
                        neither the mother nor her said children shall be sold or removed from or
                        out of the said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> And further I
                        the said <persName>Margaret C. Barber</persName> for the
                        considerations aforesaid, and I the said <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> in consideration
                        of one dollar to me paid, have, and we do hereby, jointly and severally,
                        release from slavery, manumit, liberate and set free the said negro woman,
                            <persName>Ann Shorter</persName>, from and immediately after the
                        expiration of the said period or term of fifteen years, for which she is to
                        serve me the said <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> or my representatives as
                        aforesaid, and her said two children at their re<pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00343.005.jpg"/>spective ages of thirty years: and we do
                        hereby declare that the said <persName>Ann Shorter</persName> and her said
                        two children shall from the period or term, and ages, aforesaid, be
                        thenceforth respectively free, manumitted and discharged from all manner of
                        servitude or service to us and each of us, our and each of our Executors
                        administrators and assigns forever And I the said <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> do hereby
                        covenant for myself my Executors administrators and assigns with the said
                            <persName>Margaret C. Barber</persName> her Executors and Administrators
                        that the said negro woman and her said two children shall not during their
                        respective periods of servitude to me as aforesaid, be removed from or sold
                        out of the said <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> In testimony
                        whereof we the said <persName>Margaret C. Barber</persName> and
                            <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> have hereunto set our hands and seals
                        this <date when="1858-08-30">thirtieth day of August in the year one
                        thousand eight hundred and fifty eight</date></p>
                    
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>M. C. Barber</persName>. Ss</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Mary Fenwick</persName> Ss</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Signed sealed and delivered in the presence of</ab>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Robert White</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>John Adlum Barber</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>. <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> to wit</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered that on this <date when="1858-08-30">thirtieth day of August
                            Eighteen hundred and fifty eight</date> personally appear
                            <persName>Margaret C. Barger</persName> and <persName>Mary
                            Fenwick</persName> parties to the aforegoing instrument of writing,
                        before me the subscriber, a justice of the peace in and for the said County,
                        and acknowledge the same to be their respective act and deed for the
                        purposes therein mentioned, and according to the tenor and effect thereof,
                        and the act of assembly in such case made and provided.</p>
                    <closer>Acknowledged before me.
                        <signed><persName>Robert White</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>

            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00343.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Fenwick</persName></seg>
                        being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things
                        which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own
                        knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other
                        matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of
                        others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Mary Fenwick</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-20"><seg
                                type="handwritten">20th</seg> day of <seg
                                type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Hamilton
                    Loughborough</persName><lb/>
                        a Justice of the Peace in &#38; for said District &#38; County</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>343</ab>
                <ab><persName>Mary Fenwick</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Hamilton Loughborough</persName></ab>
                <ab><persName>Matthew McLeod</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
