<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00858">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William V. H. Brown, 8 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00858</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of William V. H. Brown, 8 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-08">June 8, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl><title>Petition of William V. H. Brown, 8 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-08">June 8, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>William V. H. Brown</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>J. F. Brown</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-02-28" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-02-13" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-15" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-10-09" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00858.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William V. H.
                        Brown</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the City of
                            <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg
                        type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">two</seg> person<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha
                            Vandrey</persName> and <persName>William Vandrey</persName> (Son of
                            <persName>Martha</persName>)</seg> for and during the life of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Martha Vandrey</persName> and <persName>William
                            Vandrey</persName></seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Martha Vandrey</persName> and <persName>William
                            Vandrey</persName> were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim
                    of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha</persName> and
                            <persName>William</persName> were</seg> of the age<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">about thirty seven and
                        nineteen years respectively</seg> and of the personal description
                        following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"> The said <persName>Martha Vandrey</persName> is of
                        brown complexion, five feet four or five inches in height&#8212;well formed
                        and genteel personal appearance. She can read, and is quite an intelligent
                        woman.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The said <persName>William Vandrey</persName> is a light
                        mulatto&#8212;is five feet four and a half inches in height&#8212;Compact
                        and well built&#8212;has a <choice><sic>handsom</sic><corr>hansom</corr></choice> full suit of black hair, but slightly
                        curling; is a sprightly, intelligent boy&#8212;can read and write very well,
                        and is quite prepossessing in his personal appearance.</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00858.001.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha</persName> and <persName>William</persName></seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Your petitioner, at the earnest solicitation and
                        importunity of said <persName>Martha</persName>, purchased her and her son
                        William, in the month of <date when="1847-07"><hi rend="underline">July
                                1847</hi></date>, to prevent them being sold to go further south. He
                        purchased them from a widow lady by the name of <persName>Preuss</persName>, then a
                        resident of this City, and who has children still living in this city. He
                        purchased said servants in the name of his father, the late <choice><abbr>Rev</abbr><expan>Reverend</expan></choice>.
                            <persName>O. B. Brown</persName>, who was at the time temporarily absent
                        from his home in this city&#8212;and the Bill of sale, or title paper, was
                        made out in the name of said <persName>O. B. Brown</persName>, and your
                        petitioner at the death of his father, said <persName>O. B. Brown</persName>
                        in <date when="1852-05">May 1852</date> fell heir to said servants&#8212;
                        The title paper your petitioner cannot find, &#38; he does not recollect the
                        price paid for said servants.</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <space atLeast="1"/> was, at the time of said
                    discharge therefrom, of the value of <space atLeast="1"/> dollars in money.<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">Your petitioner is unable to state
                        what might have been the value of his claim to the services of said servants
                        at the time of the discharge therefrom. Your petitioner can only state that,
                            before the outbreak of our present political
                        difficulties he was offered $800.00 for said servant woman
                            <persName>Martha</persName>, and was repeatedly offered the sum of <hi
                            rend="underling">$1500.00</hi> for said <persName>William</persName>,
                        her son&#8212;; that said offers was made by persons not engaged in the
                        trade, from which fact your petitioner infers that the said prices offered
                        were at the time not above the real value of said servants; but as your
                        petitioner had no desire to buy or to sell at any price, he sought no
                        definite information on the subject. The said <persName>Martha</persName> is
                        an excellent Cook, and house servant&#8212;honest and trustworthy, and can
                        always command the highest wages&#8212;she can read and is quite
                        intelligent&#8212;</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The said servant boy <persName>William</persName>
                        has been raised with much care in the family of your petitioner&#8212;He can
                        read and write very well&#8212;is honest, trustworthy and of good moral
                        character, &#38; a very intelligent boy&#8212;Your petitioner has no
                        knowledge of any infirmity or defects of any kind that would impair the
                        value of said servants as aforesaid. He believes them both to be first class
                        servants.</ab>
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> into
                    the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">Servants</seg>
                    w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of
                    your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">Servants</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">Servants</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm V. H.
                                Brown</persName>
                        </seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00857.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William V. H. Brown</persName></seg>
                        being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things
                        which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own
                        knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other
                        matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of
                        others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm. V. H. Brown</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-05"><seg type="handwritten">5th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J. F. Brown</persName><lb/>
                        Alderman, &#38; ex officio J. P.</seg> seal.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>858</ab>
                <ab><persName>Wm V. H. Brown</persName></ab>
                <ab>2 Servants</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-08">June 8, 1862</date></ab>
                

            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
