<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00627">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Mary Queen and Elizabeth Queen, 5 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00627</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Mary Queen and Elizabeth Queen, 5 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-05">June 5, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Mary Queen and Elizabeth Queen, 5 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-05">June 5, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Mary Queen</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-14" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-05-10" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00627.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s <persName>Mary Queen</persName>, &#38; <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwriiten"><placeName>Washington Co. D. C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> petition in writing, represent<del>s</del>
                    and state<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they are</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">Twenty Four</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Fendall Taylor</persName>, <persName>Charlotte
                            Taylor</persName>, <persName>Frances Taylor</persName>, <persName>Louis
                            Taylor</persName>, <persName>Rachel Taylor</persName>, <persName>Gabriel
                            Taylor</persName>, <persName>Catharine Taylor</persName>
                        <persName>Lloyd Taylor</persName>, <persName>Olivia Taylor</persName>,
                            <persName>Mary Abbey Taylor</persName>, <persName>Andrew
                            Price</persName>, <persName>Eveline Gutridge</persName>, <persName>Henry
                            Gutridge</persName>
                        <persName>Sally Gutridge</persName>, <persName>Virginia Gutridge</persName>
                        <persName>Henrietta Gutridge</persName>, <persName>Charles
                            Gutridge</persName>, <persName>Albert Gutridge</persName>,
                            <persName>Francis Gutridge</persName>, <persName>Basil
                            Gutridge</persName>,</seg> for and during the life of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons <persName>Albert Bodely</persName>,
                            <persName>Edward Bodely</persName>, <persName>George Bodely</persName>,
                            <persName>Louisa Brooks</persName>, who were slaves until they arrive at
                        the age of Thirty Five years,</seg> and that by said act of Congress said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said 
                    <list>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fendall Taylor</persName>, was</seg> of the age of <seg
                                type="handwritten">Forty seven years</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note><seg type="handwritten">Black man, Five feet Six inches high, hump shoulders, (valued at $800.)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Charlotte Taylor</persName>, his wife was of the age of Forty years, Five feet Two inches high, black woman, corpulent (valued at $500.)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Frances Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Twenty one years, Five feet Three inches high black woman, good personal appearance (valued at $800)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Louis Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Nineteen years, black man Six feet&#8212;high. (valued at $1200)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Seventeen years, black girl, Five feet Four inches high, stout, (valued at $80<unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#nnk">0</unclear>)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Gabriel Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Sixteen years black boy, Five feet Eight inches high, stout, (valued at $1000)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Catharine Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Thirteen years black girl Four feet 11 inches high, (valued at $700)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lloyd Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Ten years, black boy, Four feet Five (inches high) (valued at $600.)</seg></item><pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00627.002.jpg"/>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Olivia Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Seven years, black girl, Four feet&#8212;high, (valued at $300)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Abby Taylor</persName>, was of the age of Five years Brown girl, three feet Seven inches high (valued at $300)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Andrew Price</persName>, was of the age of Thirty Three years, black man, Five feet Ten &#188; inches high, fine personal appearance (valued at $1200.)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Eveline Gutridge</persName>, was of the age of Forty Five years, <choice><sic>chesnut</sic><corr>chestnut</corr></choice> color, Four feet Eleven inches high, (valued at $800)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Henry Gutridge</persName>, was of the age of Twenty three years, copper color man, Five feet Six inches high genteel looking (valued at $1200)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Sally Gutridge</persName>, was of the age of Twenty One years, copper color woman, Five feet One <choice><sic>inche</sic><corr>inch</corr></choice> high, stout, (valued at $800)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten">Virginia Gutridge was of the age of nineteen years, copper color woman, Five feet high fine appearance (valued at $800</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Henrietta Gutridge</persName> was of the age of Seventeen years, copper color woman Four feet Ten inches high, large eyes (valued at $800)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Charles Gutridge</persName>, was of the age of Fifteen years, copper color man, Five feet five inches high, (valued at $1000)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Albert Gutridge</persName> was of the age of Thirteen years, copper color boy, Four feet Ten inches high (valued at $1000)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Francis Gutridge</persName> was of the age of Eleven years, copper color boy, Four feet Seven inches high (valued at $800)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Basil Gutridge</persName> was of the age of Five years, copper color child, Three feet four inches high, (valued at $400)</seg></item><pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00627.003.jpg"/>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten">The man <persName>Albert Bodely</persName>, was of the age of Twenty Seven years Five feet seven inches high, Brown man, (term of service valued at $900.)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Edward Bodely</persName>, was of the age of Twenty One years, Five feet Two inches high, copper color, (term of service valued at $900.)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>George Bodely</persName> was of the age of nineteen years, Five feet six inches high, copper color (term of service valued at $900)</seg></item>
                        <item><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Louisa Brooks</persName>, was of the age of, Twenty one years Five feet One and one half inch high, (term of service valued at $500.)</seg></item>
                    </list></p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00627.005.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Fendall Taylor</persName>, <persName>Charlotte
                            Taylor</persName>, and their Eight children
                        <persName>Frances</persName>, <persName>Lewis</persName>,
                            <persName>Rachel</persName>, <persName>Gabriel</persName>,
                            <persName>Catharine</persName>, <persName>Lloyd</persName>
                        <persName>Olivia</persName> and <persName>Mary Abbey</persName>, also
                            <persName>Andrew Price</persName>, <persName>Eveline
                            Gurtridge</persName>, and her nine children, <persName>Henry</persName>
                        <persName>Sally</persName>, <persName>Virginia</persName>
                        <persName>Henrietta</persName>, <persName>Charles</persName>,
                            <persName>Albert</persName>, <persName>Francis</persName>,
                            (<persName>Mary</persName>, now dead) and <persName>Basil</persName>,
                        also <persName>Albert Bodely</persName>, (<persName>Lavinia
                            Brooks</persName> set free) <persName>Edward Bodely</persName>
                        <persName>George Bodely</persName> &amp; <persName>Louisa Brooks</persName>,
                        were conveyed to us by our Father, <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName>,
                        about Five years ago, as by Bill of sale herewith filed will more fully
                        appear, (the last four to be slaves until they reach the age of Thirty Five
                        years as by will of <persName>John M. Wight</persName>, will
                    appear. (The last four to be slaves until they reach the age of Thirty Five years as by will of <persName>John M. Wight</persName> will appear.</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$19,000</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Charlotte Taylor</persName>, has had the scrofula, when young, she
                        now in very good health, an excellent cook washer &amp; ironer.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The other servants I believe to be sound and healthy, They are all strictly
                        moral and honest, some of them practical members of the church, generally
                        intelligent and capable to work and though the value of some may seem to be
                        over estimated, it has been offered and refused, not wishing to part with
                        them.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten">I know of no moral mental or bodily infirmities or defects in any
                        of them, except <persName>Charlotte</persName>, who has been sick, but now
                        seems to have good health,</ab>
                
                <pb sameAs="leaf004r" facs="cww.00627.006.jpg"/>
                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> hereby declare<del>s</del> that
                        <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> bear<del>s</del> true and faithful
                    allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and
                    that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg>
                        ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg>
                        w<seg type="handwritten">were</seg> held to service or labor therein under and by
                    virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to
                    the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                    the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> pray<del>s</del> the said
                    Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg
                        type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Queen</persName></seg></signed>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00627.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>The last Will and Testament of <persName>John M. Wight</persName> recorded in the office of the Register of Wills <date when="1819-09-02">Sept. 2nd 1819</date>.</p>
            </div1>           

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00627.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab><persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName><lb/>
                    to<lb/>
                    <persName>Mary Queen</persName> &amp;<lb/>                    
                    <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName><lb/>
                    Bill of Sale</ab>
                <ab>Received <date when="1857-10-03">3rd October 1857</date>.</ab>
                <ab>To be Recorded and the same day was Recorded in Liber JAS no 137, folios 455, &amp; 456, and of the Land Records as for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> and Examined by</ab>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Jno A Smith</persName> <choice><abbr>clk</abbr><expan>clerk</expan></choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="cww.00627.008.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Know all men by these Present, That I, <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName> of
                    the <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, for and in consideration
                    of the natural love and affection which I have for my daughters <persName>Mary
                        Queen</persName> and <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>, of the County and
                    District aforesaid, and the further consideration of the Sum of Five dollars,
                    lawful money of the <placeName>United States</placeName> to me in hand paid by
                    the said <persName>Mary</persName> and <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>, at
                    and before the Sealing and delivery of these presents, the receipt of which I do
                    hereby acknowledge, Have granted, bargain and Sold, and by these presents, do
                    grant, bargain and Sell and deliver unto them the said <persName>Mary</persName>
                    and <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>, their Executors, administrators and
                    assigns, the following negro Slaves, to wit: <persName>Fendall Taylor</persName>
                    aged about Forty years, and his wife <persName>Charlotte</persName> aged about
                    Thirty five years, and their Eight children, <persName>Frances</persName> aged
                    about Sixteen years, <persName>Lewis</persName> aged about Fourteen
                        years&#8212;<persName>Rachel</persName> aged about Ten
                        years&#8212;<persName>Gabriel</persName> aged about Eight
                        years&#8212;<persName>Catharine</persName> aged about Seven
                        years&#8212;<persName>Lloyd</persName> aged about Five
                        years&#8212;<persName>Olivia</persName> aged about three years&#8212;and
                        <persName>Mary Abbey</persName> aged about six months&#8212;also
                        <persName>Albert Bodely</persName> aged about Twenty two
                        years&#8212;<persName>Edward Bodely</persName> aged about Seventeen
                    years&#8212;and <persName>George Bodely</persName> aged about twelve
                        years&#8212;<persName>Louisa Brooks</persName> aged about Sixteen years&#8212;<pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="cww.00627.009.jpg"/> and <persName>Lavenia
                        Brooks</persName> aged about Fourteen years&#8212;<persName>Sally
                        Price</persName> aged about Sixty years&#8212;and <persName>Andrew
                        Price</persName> aged about Twenty five years&#8212;<persName>Eveline
                        Gutridge</persName> aged about Forty Years&#8212;and her nine
                        children&#8212;<persName>Henry</persName> aged about Eighteen
                        years&#8212;<persName>Sally</persName> aged about Sixteen
                        years&#8212;<persName>Virginia</persName> aged about Fourteen
                        years&#8212;<persName>Henrietta</persName> aged about Twelve
                        years&#8212;<persName>Charles</persName> aged about Ten years
                        <persName>Albert</persName> aged about Eight
                        years&#8212;<persName>Francis</persName> aged about Six
                        years&#8212;<persName>Mary</persName> aged about Four years&#8212;and
                        <persName>Basil</persName> aged about Three months&#8212;and
                        <persName>William Jones</persName> aged about nineteen years&#8212;To Have
                    and To Hold all and singular the said negro Slaves above bargained and Sold or
                    mentioned and intended so to be, unto the said <persName>Mary Queen</persName>
                    and <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>, their Executors, administrators and
                    assigns forever. And I, the said <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName> for
                    myself, my heirs, executors and administrators, all and Singular the said negro
                    Slaves, unto them the said <persName>Mary Queen</persName> and
                        <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName> their executors, administrators and
                    assigns against me the said <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName>, my heirs
                    executors &amp; administrators, and against all persons whomsoever, shall and
                    will warrant and forever defend by these present. And all which said negro
                    slaves, I, the said <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName> have this day put
                    into the possession of the said <persName>Mary Queen</persName> and
                        <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>&#8212;</p><pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="cww.00627.010.jpg"/>

                <p>In Testimony whereof, I, the said <persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName> have
                    hereunto Subscribed my name, and affixed my Seal this <date when="1857-10-01">first day of October, in the year of our Lord, Eighteen hundred and fifty
                        Seven&#8212;</date></p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Nicholas L. Queen</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">            
                <p>Signed, Sealed &amp; delivered In the presence of</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>E. J. Middleton</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Geo McHenry</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <placeName>County of Washington</placeName>, To wit:</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered, that on this <date when="1857-10-01">First day of October
                            in the year of our Lord, one thousand eight hundred and fifty
                            Seven</date>, before the Subscriber a Justice of the Peace in and for
                        the county and district aforesaid, personally appeared <persName>Nicholas L.
                            Queen</persName>, who being personally well known to me as the person
                        who executed the foregoing Bill of Sale, and acknowledged the Same to be his
                        act and deed&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>Acknowledged before and certified by&#8212;
                        <signed><persName>E. J. Middleton</persName> J. P. seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="cww.00627.011.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><seg type="handwritten">We <persName>Mary Queen</persName>, &amp; <persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName>,</seg> being duly sworn, do
                        depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of <seg type="handwritten">our</seg> own knowledge, are true in substance and in
                        fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, <seg type="handwritten">We</seg> believe to be true in substance and in
                        fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Queen</persName></seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Elizabeth Queen</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-05"><seg type="handwritten">5th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>F. I. Murphey</persName> J. P.</seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>627</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Mary Queen</persName> &amp; <lb/>
                    Elizabeth Queen</ab>
                <ab>Refer to<lb/>
                    <persName>E. J. Middleton</persName><lb/>
                    and<lb/>
                    <persName>George McHenry</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-05">June 5, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
