<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00176">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Susanna Boarman, 13 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00176</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Susanna Boarman, 13 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Susanna Boarman, 13 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>William L. McDaniel</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-03-19" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-12-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2012-12-04" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-09-10" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00176.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Charles County Md</placeName>.</seg> by this <seg
                        type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the United States,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a female Slave</seg> person of
                    African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy Harper</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> was discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such
                    service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> was of the age of <seg type="handwritten">Thirty one years.</seg> and of
                    the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy Harper</persName> is a bright yellow woman about thirty one
                        years of age, as near as can be recollected. She is about five feet one, or
                        two, inches in height. Black hair, and black, or dark eyes, not fleshy, but
                        of muscular form, no marks visible, or otherwise.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00176.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here
                        state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By will of <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName> of
                            <placeName>Charles County, Maryland</placeName>, date <date
                            when="1837-03-14">March 14th, 1837</date>. A copy whereof is herewith
                        annexed, Marked Exhibit (A).</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg
                        type="handwritten">1,000&#8212;</seg> dollars in money,<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy Harper</persName> is a fine cook, washer, and ironer, and in
                        every respect, a valuable house servant,. She is likely and her health was
                        good, while in my employment, and believed to be so now, of sound ming and
                        character unimpeachable, and believed to be without infirmities, and has
                        resided with my brother in <placeName>Washington City D.C.</placeName> for
                        the last eight or ten years.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress;
                    and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any
                    person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against
                    the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Trecy</persName>
                    </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00176.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In the name of God Amen. I <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName> of
                            <placeName>Charles County</placeName> and <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName> being of sound disposing mind memory and
                        understanding do make this my last will and Testament in manner and form
                        following, that is to say First and principally I commit my soul to Almighty
                        God who gave it me, and my body to the earth to be decently buried by my
                        Executors herein after named, and as to what worldly Goods it has pleased
                        God to bless me with I give and <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium"
                            resp="#jc">
                            <choice>
                                <sic>divese</sic>
                                <corr>divest</corr>
                            </choice>
                        </unclear> as follows.</p>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item>Item 1st I give and bequeath to <persName>Henry L. Mudd</persName> a
                            tract of Land by whatever name it may be called, being the same on which
                            I have a quarter called <placeName>Moses' quarter</placeName> and
                            joining the Lands of a certain <persName>James Moore</persName> and the
                            said <persName>Henry L Mudd</persName> to him and his Heirs
                            forever</item>
                        <item>Item 2d I give and bequeath to <persName>Edward Dyer</persName> of the
                                <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District
                                of Columbia</placeName>, and to his Heirs forever <choice>
                                <sic>intrust</sic>
                                <corr>entrust</corr>
                            </choice> and to and for the use intent and purposes herein after named,
                            all and every other part of my real Estate and lying near where <choice>
                                <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                                <expan>Doctor</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>George Boarman</persName> now resides, in trust nevertheless
                            that he the said <persName>Edward Dyer</persName> shall keep and
                            preserve the whole of the said property for the use, benefit and
                            enjoyment of my nephew <choice>
                                <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                                <expan>Doctor</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>George Boarman</persName> during his natural life, and at his
                            death to convey and pay over and deliver the same and every part thereof
                            to the <choice>
                                <sic>lawfull</sic>
                                <corr>lawful</corr>
                            </choice> heirs of him the said <choice>
                                <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                                <expan>Doctor</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>George Boarman</persName> who are to have and possess the same
                            in fee&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 3d I give and bequeath to my great niece <persName>Mary
                                Boarman</persName> daughter of <choice>
                                <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                                <expan>Doctor</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>Geo. Boarman</persName>, my negro Boy
                                <persName>Baptist</persName> son of <persName>Gracy</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>Item 4th I give and bequeath to <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                            daughter of <choice>
                                <abbr>Doctr.</abbr>
                                <expan>Doctor</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>Geo. Boarman</persName>, my negro Girl <persName>
                                <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">Serece</unclear>
                            </persName> daughter of <persName>Cecy</persName>&#8212;</item>

                        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00176.005.jpg"/>
                        <item>Item 5th I give and bequeath to <persName>Frances D.
                                Gardiner</persName> son of my niece <persName>Dorothy
                                Gardiner</persName>, my negro Boy <persName>Elly</persName> son of
                            woman <persName>Gracy</persName> and negro Boy <persName>Davy</persName>
                            son of woman <persName>Anna</persName>&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 6th I give and bequeath to <persName>Sophia Paign</persName>
                            daughter of my <choice>
                                <abbr>decd</abbr>
                                <expan>deceased</expan>
                            </choice> nephew <persName>Thomas C. Boarman</persName>, negro Boy <persName>
                                <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">Gusty</unclear>
                            </persName> son of negro woman <persName>Anna</persName>&#8212;</item>

                        <item>Item 7th I give and bequeath to <persName>Elizabeth Boarman</persName>
                            daughter of my nephew <persName>Charles Boarman</persName> my Boy
                                <persName>Francis</persName> son of woman
                                <persName>Harriet</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>Item 8th I give and bequeath to <persName>Elizth Gardiner</persName>
                            widow of a certain <persName>Aloysius Gardiner</persName> late of
                                <placeName>Prince Georges County</placeName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>decd</abbr>
                                <expan>deceased</expan>
                            </choice> my Boy <persName>Alfred</persName> son of woman
                                <persName>Harriet</persName>&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 9th I give and bequeath to <persName>Thomas S.
                                Gardiner</persName> son of my niece <persName>Dorothy
                                Gardiner</persName>, my Boy <persName>Pius</persName>, son of woman
                                <persName>Harriet</persName>&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 10th I give and bequeath to my friend <persName>Sarah
                                Jenkins</persName> now living with me, my negro Boy
                                <persName>Robert</persName> son of woman <persName>Cecy</persName>,
                            one Bed and furniture, and one hundred and fifty dollars, also my
                            wearing apparel&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 11th I give and bequeath to <persName>Rose Ann
                                Gardiner</persName> daughter of my niece <persName>Dorothy
                                Gardiner</persName>, my negro Girl <persName>Ally</persName>,
                            daughter of woman <persName>Cecy</persName>.&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 12th I give and bequeath to <persName>Maria D. Hughes</persName>
                            daughter of Major <persName>Jno. Hughes</persName>, my negro Boy
                                <persName>Ambrose</persName> son of woman <persName>Delia
                                Ann</persName>&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 13th. I give and bequeath to whatever Reverend Gentleman that may
                            be attending this congregation at my death the sum of fifty
                            Dollars&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 14th I give and bequeath to the poor of the upper Zekiah
                            Congregation the sum of one hundred dollars to be paid to such as my
                            Executors herein after mentioned shall think most
                            deserving&#8212;</item>
                        <item>Item 15th I give and bequeath all the residue of my <pb
                                xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00176.006.jpg"/> Estate to be divided in
                            equal proportions between <persName>James Edelen</persName> son of my
                            nephew <choice>
                                <abbr>Dr.</abbr>
                                <expan>Doctor</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>Richard Edelen</persName>, <persName>Sophia
                                Gardiner</persName> wife of <persName>George H. Gardiner</persName>,
                                <persName>Elizabeth Ann Hughes</persName> daughter of <choice>
                                <abbr>Majr.</abbr>
                                <expan>Major</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>Jno. Hughes</persName> and <persName>Elizabeth
                                Boarman</persName> daughter of my nephew <persName>A J P
                                Boarman</persName> to them and their Heirs forever&#8212;</item>
                    </list>

                    <p>And Lastly I constitute and appoint <persName>John Hughes</persName> and
                            <persName>George Gardiner</persName> to be Executors of this my last
                        will and Testament revoking and annulling all others heretofore by me
                        made&#8212;In testimony I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal this
                            <date when="1837-03-14">14th day of March in the year of our Lord
                            Eighteen Hundred and thirty seven</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName> seal</signed>
                        <lb/> signed sealed published and declared as and for the last Will and
                        Testament of <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName> in presence of each other
                        and at the request of the above named testatrice we have subscribed our
                        names as witnesses thereto<lb/>
                        <persName>Wm. A Mudd</persName>, <persName>Edward Smith</persName>,
                            <persName>Stanislaus Farrall</persName>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>On the Back of the aforegoing will it is there written <placeName>Charles
                            County</placeName> Sct <date when="1840-05-06">May 6th 1840</date> then
                        came <persName>John Hughes</persName> and <persName>George
                            Gardiner</persName> Executors of <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName>
                        late of <placeName>Charles County</placeName> deceased and severally made
                        oath on the Holy Evangely of Almighty God that the within and aforegoing
                        instrument of writing is the true and whole last will and Testament of said
                        deceased that hath come to their hands and possession and that they doth not
                        know of any other.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>Test <persName>Aquilla Bateman</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Regr</abbr>
                                <expan>Register</expan>
                            </choice> of wills</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>
                        <placeName>Charles County</placeName> Sct <date when="1840-05-06">May the
                            6th 1840</date> then came <persName>Stanilaus Farral</persName> one of
                        the subscribing witnesses to the within and aforegoing last will and
                        Testament <choice>
                            <sic>of of</sic>
                            <corr>of</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName> late of <placeName>Charles
                            County</placeName> deceased and made oath on the Holy Evangely of
                        Almighty God that he did see the Testatrice therein named sign and seal <pb
                            xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00176.007.jpg"/> this will that he heard her
                        publish pronounce and declare the same to be her last will and Testament and
                        that at the time of her so doing she was in the best of his <choice>
                            <abbr>apprehen</abbr>
                            <expan>apprehension</expan>
                        </choice> of sound and disposing mind memory and understanding and that he
                        together with <persName>William A Mudd</persName> and <persName>Edward
                            Smith</persName> respectively subscribed their names as witnesses to
                        this will in the presence and at the request of the Testatrice and in the
                        presence of each other&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>Test <signed>
                            <persName>Aquilla Bateman</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Regr</abbr>
                                <expan>Register</expan>
                            </choice> of wills</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>State of Maryland Charles County</placeName> to wit</dateline>
                    <p>I hereby certify that the aforegoing instrument of writing is a true copy
                        taken from one of our Record Books of the Orphans Court of
                            <placeName>Charles County</placeName>
                    </p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed the seal
                        of the said Court this <date when="1841-01-28">28th day of January in the
                            year of our Lord one thousand Eight hundred and Forty one</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer>Test <persName>Aquilla Bateman</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>Regr</abbr>
                            <expan>Register</expan>
                        </choice> of wills for <placeName>Chas County</placeName>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>A</ab>
                    <ab>Copy <persName>Elizabeth Reeves</persName>
                        <lb/> will<lb/>
                    </ab>
                    <ab>Cost $1.47</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00176.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <del>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia,</placeName>
                    </del>
                    <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic"><del><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</del></hi>                    
                    <placeName><seg type="handwritten">Charles County Md</seg></placeName>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-08">
                            <seg type="handwritten">8th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May,</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Wm. L. McDaniel</persName>
                                <lb/> Justice of the peace</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>;<lb/>
                            <placeName>Charles County</placeName> Sct:</seg>
                    </dateline>
                    <p>
                        <seg type="handwritten">I <persName>Gerard W. Crain</persName> Clerk of the
                            Circuit Court for <placeName>Charles County</placeName>; do hereby
                            certify that <persName>William L. McDaniel</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                                <expan>Esquire</expan>
                            </choice>. before whom the aforegoing Affidavit appears to have been
                            made was at the date thereof a Justice of the Peace of the
                                <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, in &#38; for
                                <placeName>Charles County</placeName>; duly Commissioned and Sworn,
                            and that his Signature thereby is genuine;</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <seg type="handwritten">In Testimony whereof I hereunto Set my hand and
                            affixed the Seal of the Circuit Court for <placeName>Charles
                                County</placeName>; this <date when="1862-05-09">9th day of May Anno
                                Domini 1862</date>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <seg type="handwritten">Test:</seg>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>G. W. Crain</persName>
                                <choice>
                                    <abbr>clk</abbr>
                                    <expan>clerk</expan>
                                </choice> of the <choice>
                                    <abbr>C</abbr>
                                    <expan>Circuit</expan>
                                </choice>. <choice>
                                    <abbr>C</abbr>
                                    <expan>Court</expan>
                                </choice>. for <placeName>Chas. Co. Md.</placeName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00176.009.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>176<lb/> Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Susanna Boarman</persName>
                </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>
                    <persName>Sylvester B. Boarman</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>Thomas C. Magruder</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                        <expan>Doctor</expan>
                    </choice>. <persName>Jas. E. Morgan</persName>
                </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
