<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00167">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Elizabeth C. Peerce, 13 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00167</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Elizabeth C. Peerce, 13 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Elizabeth C. Peerce, 13 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-13"/>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Elizabeth C. Peerce</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Robert White</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-19" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-12-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2012-11-27" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
         <change when="2012-11-05" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00167.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16. 1862</date> entitled "An act for the release of
                    certain persons held to service or labour in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>".</p>
                <p>Your Petitioner, <persName>Elizabeth C. Peerce</persName> of
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>, administratrix of <persName>Joseph M.
                        Peerce</persName> care of said County deceased, by this petition in writing
                    represents &#38; states, that she is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of
                    Congress, held a claim to the service or labour, of a person of African descent
                    of the name of <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName>, for and during the life of
                    said <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName>, and that by said act of Congress said
                        <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName> was discharged and freed of &#38; from
                    all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of such
                    discharge said <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName> was of the age of Twenty-eight
                    years, and of the personal description following; of a dark chestnut color,
                    delicately made, rather Tall, and has a scar upon his left cheek caused by a
                    burn. That your petitioner acquired her claim to the aforesaid service or labour
                    of said <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName>, by virtue of letters of
                    administration granted to her upon the personal estate of her husband the said
                        <persName>Joseph M. Peerce</persName> deceased, by the Orphans Court of said
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, said letters being dated &#38;
                    granted <date when="1855-05-08">May 8th, 1855</date>;
                    and that her said Husband bought the said <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName>
                    from <persName>John T. Power</persName> of said County and
                        <placeName>District</placeName> for the sum of Two Hundred &#38; five
                    Dollars on the <date when="1847-07-08">8th day of July
                        in the year eighteen Hundred &#38; forty seven</date>, as is evidenced by
                    the bill of sale herewith annexed &#38; filed&#8212;</p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labour of said <persName>Henry
                        Wheeler</persName> was at the time of said discharge
                    
                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00167.002.jpg"/>
                    
                    therefrom of the value of nine Hundred Dollars;
                    that she received from him wages at the rate of Twelve dollars per month, for
                    his services as a first class waiter and dining room servant&#8212;</p>

                <p>and your petitioner hath no knowledge of any moral mental, or bodily defect in
                    said <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName>, as impair the value of her claim to
                    such service or <choice><orig>labour</orig><reg>labor</reg></choice>&#8212;</p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that she bears true &#38; faithful allegiance to
                    the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that she hath
                    not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in the present
                    rebellion nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto. And your petitioner
                    further states and alleges that she hath not brought said <persName>Henry
                        Wheeler</persName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since
                    the passage of said act of Congress; and that at the time of the passage thereof
                    said <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName> was held to service or labour therein
                    under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labour.</p>
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges that her said claim to the service or
                    labour aforesaid does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore
                    made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present
                    rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                    States</placeName>.</p>
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of the said claim to the service of said <persName>Henry
                        Wheeler</persName> herein set forth, and if the same be found to be valid,
                    that they appraise the value of same in money and apportion said value, and
                    report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> in conformity to the provisions of said Act of
                    Congress&#8212;</p>
                <closer>
               <signed><persName>Elizabeth C. Peerce</persName></signed><lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>admx</abbr><expan>administratrix</expan></choice> of <persName>Joseph M. Peerce</persName>
            </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00167.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> to wit.</dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>Elizabeth M. Peerce</persName> administratrix of
                            <persName>Joseph M. Peerce</persName> deceased being duly sworn do
                        depose and say that all the several matters &#38; things set forth and
                        stated in the foregoing petition as of my own knowledge are true in
                        substance and in fact, and that all the several other matters and things
                        therein stated &#38; set forth as from the information of others, I believe
                        to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Elizabeth C Peerce</persName><lb/>
                      <choice><abbr>admx</abbr><expan>administratrix</expan></choice> of
                                <persName>Joseph M Peerce</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to &#38; subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-10">Tenth day of
                            May A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Robert White</persName> J. Peace</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

            </div1>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00167.005.jpg"/>
                    <p>Know all men by these presents, That I <persName>John T Power</persName> of
                        the County and City of
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, for and in consideration
                        of the Sum of Two hundred and five dollars, current money, to me in hand
                        paid, by <persName>Joseph M Peerce</persName> of said
                            <placeName>County</placeName> and <placeName>City</placeName> in the
                            <placeName>District</placeName> aforesaid, at and before the sealing and
                        delivering of these presents, the receipt whereof I, the said,
                            <persName>John T. Power</persName>, do hereby acknowledge, Have granted,
                        bargained, and sold, and by these presents do grant, bargain, and sell, unto
                        the said <persName>Joseph M Peerce</persName>, his Executors,
                        administrators, and assigns&#8212;A certain Negro boy Slave named
                            <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName> about Thirteen years of age&#8212;To
                        have and to hold the said Negro boy Slave named <persName>Henry
                            Wheeler</persName> about Thirteen years of age as above bargained and
                        sold to the said <persName>Joseph M Peerce</persName>, his executors,
                        administrators, and assigns, forever; and I, the said <persName>John T.
                            Power</persName>, for myself, my heirs, executors &#38; administrators,
                        The said Negro boy Slave named <persName>Henry Wheeler</persName> unto the
                        said <persName>Joseph M Peerce</persName>, his executors, administrators,
                        and assigns, against me the said <persName>John T Power</persName>, my
                        executors, and administrators, and against all and every other person or
                        persons whatsoever, shall and will warrant and forever defend by these
                        presents;</p>
                    <p>In writings whereof I the said <persName>John T Power</persName> have
                        hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal This <date when="1847-07-28">Twenty
                            Eighth day of July in the year Eighteen hundred and forty
                        seven</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>John T. Power</persName> seal
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="postscript">
                    <p>Signed Sealed and acknowledged before us&#8212;the worth <choice><sic>eigth</sic><corr>eighth</corr></choice>&#8212;being
                        first interlined&#8212;<lb/>
                  <persName>Lund Washington <choice><abbr>Senr.</abbr></choice></persName><lb/>
                  <persName>John Thornberry</persName>.</p>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00167.006.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>County &#38; City <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                        <date when="1847-07-28">July 28<hi rend="underline">th</hi> 1847</date>.
                        Received of <persName>Joseph Mill Peerce</persName> Two hundred and five
                        dollars current money the consideration mentioned in the within bill of
                        sale</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>John T. Power</persName></signed><lb/>
                        Witness
                        <signed><persName>Lund Washington</persName> <choice><abbr>Senr.</abbr></choice></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab><persName>Power</persName><lb/>
                        to<lb/>
                        <persName>Peerce</persName><lb/>
                        bill of sale&#8212;</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00167.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>167</ab>
                <ab><persName>Elizabeth C. Peerce</persName> <choice><abbr>admx</abbr><expan>administratrix</expan></choice>. of<lb/>
               <persName>Joseph M. Peerce</persName></ab>
                <ab>Petition under the Emancipation Act.</ab>
                <ab>Summon<lb/>
               <persName>William H. Craig</persName> of <placeName>Geo. Town, D. C.</placeName></ab>

                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date><lb/>
                    by<lb/>
               <persName>Chas M. Matthews</persName> <choice><abbr>Esq</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>