<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00349">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William B. Magruder, 21 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00349</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of William B. Magruder, 21 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of William B. Magruder, 21 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>William B. Magruder</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John S. Hollingshead</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-22" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-16" who="scl">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-12" who="#jc">performed automated file cleanup</change>
            <change when="2013-05-13" who="#crl">proofed, checked</change>
            <change when="2013-03-05" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00349.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William B.
                        Magruder</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"
                            ><placeName>Brookville</placeName>
                        <placeName>Montgomery Co Md</placeName>.</seg> by this <seg
                        type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of
                    Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a
                        female</seg> person of African descent of the name of <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen Campbell</persName></seg> for and
                    during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen
                            Campbell</persName></seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen Campbell</persName> was</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"
                            ><persName>Mary Ellen Campbell</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg
                        type="handwritten">Eighteen years</seg> and of the personal description
                        following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">of Dark Brown Color, five feet Three inches high (5 ft.
                        3 in) well built&#8212;full face pleasant countenance, rather thick
                        lips</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00349.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen
                            Campbell</persName></seg> in manner following:<note type="government"
                        place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from
                        whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written
                        evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where
                        the same may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">I purchased her mother of <persName>Nathan
                            Cook</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery Co Md</placeName>. Said
                            <persName>Cook</persName> became possessed of her by his wife who was
                        the deponents Sister. and the Said <persName>Mary Ellen</persName> was born
                        my Slave</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen Campbell</persName></seg> was, at
                    the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten"
                        >One thousand</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten"
                        >Your petitioner avers that the said <persName>Mary Ellen</persName> by
                        reason of her intelligence, honesty industry, and physical ability, was very
                        valuable either as a house servant or cook, and he has no knowledge whatever
                        of any moral, mental or bodily infirmity or defect which would impair the
                        value of your petitioners claim to her service or labor.</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary
                            Ellen</persName></seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary
                            Ellen</persName></seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by
                    virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen</persName></seg> does not originate
                    in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any
                    manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Ellen</persName></seg> herein
                    above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to
                    the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>William B.
                                Magruder</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00349.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>William B Magruder</persName></seg>
                        being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things
                        which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own
                        knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other
                        matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of
                        others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>William B.
                                    Magruder</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-21"><seg
                                type="handwritten">21st</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>John S
                                    Hollingshead</persName><lb/> Notary Public</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>349</ab>
                <ab><persName>William B. Magruder</persName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Brookville Md</placeName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>E. G. Hall</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Augustus E. Perry</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
