<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00192">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Susannah Harriet Tobias, 13 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                <name xml:id="sd">Shailana Dunn-Wall</name>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
            <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00192</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Susannah Harriet Tobias, 13 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Susannah Harriet Tobias, 13 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Susannah Harriet Tobias</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>John H. Johnson</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values @ facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
          <change when="2013-01-17" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
          <change when="2013-01-10" who="#sd">checked</change>
         <change when="2013-01-08" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00192.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                    <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                    <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Susannah Harriet
                                Tobias</persName>,</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                     <placeName>Washington D. C.</placeName>
                 </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                        that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of
                        the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">one Female Slave&#8212;a&#8212;</seg> person of
                        African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>,</seg> for and during the life of said
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>,</seg> and that by
                        said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Treacy</persName>
                 </seg> was discharged and freed
                        of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at
                        the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Treacy</persName></seg> was of the age of
                            <seg type="handwritten">about 38 years,</seg> and of the personal
                        description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                            describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more
                            than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">She is black in complexion, hair and Eyes; in height,
                            about five feet Eight inches; very large and muscular; quite fat,
                            weighing near three hundred pounds&#8212;is healthy, industrious and
                            intelligent,</seg>
               </p>

                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00192.002.jpg"/>
                    <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                        aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Treacy</persName></seg> in manner
                            following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state
                            how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                            consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                            exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                            found.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">By devise of the Aunt of your
                            Petitioner, <persName>Susannah Beck</persName> deceased, late of the
                                <placeName>County of St. Mary's</placeName> in the state of
                                <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, as shown by exhibit herewith of a
                            certified copy of the Last Will and Testament of said <persName>Susannah
                                Beck</persName>, and other exhibits.</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>
                 </seg> was, at the time of
                        said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$1,300 00/100</seg> dollars in
                            money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                            facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to
                            the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also
                            such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities
                            or defects of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim
                            to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment
                            that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said
                            person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or
                            labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner
                            specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the
                            value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                            knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">Your petitioner further represents that the value of said service or
                            labor was, as she believes, much enhanced by the following personal
                            qualities of the said <persName>Treacy</persName>: She was not viable to
                            maternity: she was of uncommon bodily strength: she was healthy: she was
                            industrious: she was docile and obedient. Your petitioner further avers
                            that she knows of no mental or bodily infirmity to impair the value of
                            said service and labor.</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears
                        true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not
                        borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                        rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>
                 </seg> into the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and
                        that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>
                 </seg> was held to service or labor
                        therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor.</p>

                    <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>
                 </seg> does not originate
                        in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any
                        manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                        the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine
                        the validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service
                        or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Treacy</persName>
                 </seg>
                        herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                        appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same
                        to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said act of
                        Congress.</p>

                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Susannah Harriet Tobias</persName><lb/>
                         Formally <persName>Susannah Harriet <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nnk">Keech</unclear></persName></seg></signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten"><address><addrLine>424 Sixth Street</addrLine></address></seg>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>          
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00192.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>The last Will &#38; Testament of <persName>Susanna Beck</persName></ab>
               
                    <p>In the Name of God amen. I <persName>Susanna Beck</persName> of
                            <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, being in perfect health of body and of sound and disposing me <gap reason="torn edge" extent="less than one word" quantity="4" unit="chars"/> memory and understanding, considering the certainty
                        of death and t<unclear reason="torn" cert="medium" resp="#nnk">he</unclear> uncertainty of the time thereof, and being desirous to
                        settle my worldly affairs and thereby be the better prepared to leave this
                        world when it shall please God to call me hence do therefore make and
                        publish this my Last Will and Testament in the manner and form following
                        that is to say,&#8212;first and principally I commit my soul into the hands
                        of Almighty God, and my body to the earth to be buried at the discretion of
                        my Executors herein after named and after my debts and funeral charges are paid I devise and bequeath as follows&#8212;</p>
                    <p>Item I
                        give and bequeath unto my nephew <persName>William Sothoron
                        Keech</persName> all the Lands I purchased of my brother <persName>James Keech</persName> it being apart of two tracts or parcels of Land containing about two hundred and thirty four acres
                        during the lifetime of my brother <persName>James Keech</persName> and
                            <persName>Clarissa</persName> his wife, and after each of their deaths
                        my will is for said Lands to be equally divided between my six <choice>
                            <sic>neaces</sic>
                            <corr>nieces</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Susanna Harriot</persName>, <persName>Mary Elizabeth</persName>,
                            <persName>Clarissa
                        Evelina</persName>,
                            <persName>Martha Matilda</persName>, and <persName>Alice
                            Keech</persName>, daughters of my
                        Brother <persName>James</persName>, it being my intention and wish to
                        provide a <choice>
                            <sic>supporte</sic>
                            <corr>support</corr>
                        </choice> for my brother <persName>James Keech</persName> and their youngest
                        children, Item I give and bequeath unto my brother <persName>Samuel
                            Keech</persName> my undivided Interest of the Land where my brother now
                        lives to him and his heirs forever&#8212;Item I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Evelina Keech</persName> my undivided Interest in and to the
                        plantation where my late mother Lived to her and her heirs forever but if
                        she should die without heir then my will is for my part of said Land to be
                        the property of my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Martha Matilda Keech</persName> and her heirs forever, Item I give
                        and bequeath unto my <hi rend="underline">
                     <choice>
                                <sic>Nefphew</sic>
                                <corr>nephew</corr>
                            </choice>
                  </hi>
                        <persName>William Sothoron Keech</persName>, my part of the carriage which
                        is one half of the horses with a desire for him to keep it in order for the
                        use of his mother during her life. Item I give and bequeath unto my Brother
                            <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> his natural Life seven negroes
                            <persName>Charles</persName>, <persName>Mary</persName>, <persName>Bazel</persName>, <persName>Sabra Ann</persName>,
                            <persName>Treacy</persName>, <persName>George Thomas</persName> and
                            <persName>Benjamin Benedict</persName>, and after the death of my
                        Brother <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> my will and desire is that my
                        negro woman
                    
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00192.005.jpg"/>
                    
                  <persName>Mary</persName> shall be sold, for her to have choice of her
                        master, and the money arising from the sale to be equally divided between my
                        late Brothers <persName>Philimore Keech</persName>'s Children
                            <persName>James Edward</persName>, <persName>Philimore
                        Estess</persName> and <persName>Jane Eliza
                            Keech</persName>&#8212;Item I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Susanna Harriot
                        Keech</persName> after the death of
                        my Brother <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> my negro girl
                            <persName>Treacy</persName>. Item I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>neaces</sic>
                            <corr>nieces</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Mary Elizabeth Keech</persName> after the death of my Brother
                            <persName>Samual Keech</persName> my negro girl <persName>Sabra
                            Ann</persName>&#8212;Item I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Evelina Keech</persName> after the death of my Brother
                            <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> my negro boy
                            <persName>Bazel</persName>, and for twenty dollars of the income of said
                        negro boy to be paid annually to my brother <persName>John E.
                            Keech</persName>, during his life&#8212;Item, I give and bequeath unto
                        my nephew <persName>James Alexander Keech</persName> after the death of my
                        Brother <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> my negro man
                            <persName>Charles</persName>&#8212;Item, I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Alice Keech</persName> youngest daughter of my Brother
                            <persName>James Keech</persName> after the death of my Brother
                            <persName>Samuel Keech</persName>, my two negroes boy <persName>George
                            Thomas</persName>, and <persName>Benjamin Benedict</persName>, the hire
                        of <persName>Benedict</persName> to be paid annually by, for four years to
                        my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Mary Anne Keech</persName>&#8212;Item, I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>Nefphew</sic>
                            <corr>nephew</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>James Alexander Keech</persName> and my <choice>
                            <sic>neace</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Mary Anne Keech</persName>, after the death of my Brother
                            <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> the residue of my Estate to be equally
                        divided between them my further will and desire as if any of nephews or <choice>
                            <sic>neaces</sic>
                            <corr>nieces</corr>
                        </choice> should die before they arrive at age or without Heirs then and in
                        that case for the survivor or survivors of them that may be dead to them in
                        equal proportions the property they being dead would have been entitled to, and Lastly I do
                        hereby constitute and appoint my Brother <persName>James Keech</persName>
                        and my Nephew <persName>William Sothoron Keech</persName>, to be my whole
                        executors of this my Last Will and Testament, revoking and annulling all
                        former wills by me heretofore made, <choice>
                            <sic>satifying</sic>
                            <corr>satisfying</corr>
                        </choice> and confirming this and none other to be my Last Will and
                        Testament. In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my
                        seal this <date when="1828-12-31">thirty first day of December in the year
                            of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty
                        eight</date>&#8212;</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Susanna Beck</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Signed, Sealed, published and declared by <persName>Susanna Beck</persName>
                        the above named testatrix as and
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00192.006.jpg"/>
                        
                        for her Last Will &#38; Testament in the presence of us who at her request
                        in her presence and in the presence of each other have subscribed our names
                        as witnesses thereto&#8212;(the word December in the eighteenth line of this
                        page, being first interlined&#8212;</p>
                    <p><persName>John Ralph</persName>, <persName>James Reeder</persName>,
                            <persName>William H. Reeder</persName>
                        <placeName>St. Mary's County</placeName> Court. The <date when="1831-03-08">8th March 1831</date> Then came
                            <persName>William Keech</persName> of <persName>James</persName> before
                        me the subscriber one of the Justices of the Peace in and for the County
                        aforesaid and <choice>
                            <sic>mad</sic>
                            <corr>made</corr>
                        </choice> oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that on the <date when="1831-03-07">7th day of March</date>
                        Instant he gave notice in the name and at the request of <persName>William
                            S.
                        Keech</persName> one of the Executors of <persName>Susanna Beck</persName> late of
                            <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName> deceased, give notice to
                            <persName>Samuel Keech</persName> and <persName>John E. Keech</persName>
                        brothers of the deceased, that the will of the deceased would be offered for
                        <choice><sic>probat</sic><corr>probate</corr></choice> before the Orphan's Court on this <date when="1831-03-08">8th day of March 1831</date> and that they
                        might attend if they thought proper&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>Sworn before <signed><persName>James Keech</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    
                  <dateline><placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName> to wit, The <date when="1831-03-08">8th day of March 1831</date></dateline>
                        <p>Then came <persName>John Ralph</persName> and <persName>William H.
                            Reeder</persName> two of the three subscribing witnesses to the within
                        last Will &#38; Testament of <persName>Susanna Beck</persName> late of
                            <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName> deceased, and severally made
                        oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that they did see the testatrix
                        therein named sign and seal this Will, and that they heard her publish,
                        pronounce and declare the same to be her last Will &#38; Testament, that at
                        the time of her so doing she was to the best of their apprehensions of sound
                        and disposing mind, memory and understanding, and that they respectively
                        subscribed their names as witnesses to this will, in the presence, and at
                        the request of the testatrix and in the presence of Each other, and also
                        that they did see <persName>James Reeder</persName> the other witness to this
                        will subscribe the same, in the presence and at the request of the said
                        testatrix</p>
                    <closer>Certified by
                        <signed><persName>E. J. Millard</persName> <choice><abbr>Regr</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> of Wills for <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00192.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>True Copy</ab>
                    <ab>Test</ab>
                    <closer>
                    <signed><persName>James T. M. Raley</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Regst.</abbr>
                        <expan>Register</expan>
                    </choice> of wills for <placeName>Saint Mary's County</placeName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>Copy<lb/>Last Will and Testament<lb/>of<lb/>
                    <persName>Susanna Beck</persName></ab>
                <ab>Cost of Copy $1.75</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00192.008.jpg"/>            

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">

                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
               <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                  <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
            </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Susannah Harriet Tobias</persName>,</seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition,
                        as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the
                        several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Susannah Harriet Tobias</persName>
                    </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-10">
                     <seg type="handwritten">10</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg>
                            A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Jno. H Johnson</persName> J. P. seal</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab><persName>JM. Binckley</persName>, Attorney</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>192</ab>
                <ab>Petition of <persName>Susanna Harriet Tobias</persName></ab>                
                <ab>Witnesses:<lb/>
                    <persName>Alexander Keech</persName>, <placeName>Bladensburg Md.</placeName><lb/>
                    Mr. <persName>Frances Keech</persName>, his wife, <hi rend="underline">dv.</hi><lb/>
                    <persName>John M Binckley</persName><lb/>
                    Attorney <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#kk">ai</unclear></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13. 1862</date>.</ab>


            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>