<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00351">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of M. Alice Shulze, 21 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00351</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of M. Alice Shulze, 21 May 1862 </title>
                    <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of M. Alice Shulze, 21 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775&#8211;1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName> M. Alice Shulze </persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Edmund F. Brown</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-03" who="#scl">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-03-19" who="#jc">proofed for and corrected transcription and encoding
                errors</change>
            <change when="2012-02-15" who="#el">automated checking across files for extra spaces in
                elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription
                errors</change>
            <change when="2012-02-14" who="#el">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary</change>
            <change when="2011-06-16" who="#bj">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-04-06" who="#rr">checked</change>
            <change when="2010-10-21" who="#am">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00351.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"> Mrs. <persName>M. Alice
                            Shulze</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington City </placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">one male</seg>
                    person of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and
                    from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of
                    said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg
                        type="handwritten">twenty nine years, or thereabouts,</seg> and of the
                    personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">
                        Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more
                        than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">about five feet six inches high, of black color, flat
                        nose, large mouth, good teeth, has had his leg and shoulder hurt; but his
                        employers, <choice>
                            <abbr>Messrs.</abbr>
                            <expan>Messieurs</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Kelleher</persName> &#38; <persName>Pywell</persName>, at whose
                        Livery Stable he has been hired several years, state that he is now in sound
                        condition and a good faithful man at business; that he is valuable to them
                        and they have been paying and are now paying him the highest class wages for
                        such a man.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00351.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpehus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">
                        Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price
                        or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By inheritance from the Estate of her late Father; and
                        the said <persName>Orpheus</persName> is held in Trust for her use, by a
                        Trustee who is now beyond the jurisdiction of the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>; that said Trust was created by a marriage contract
                        entered into before her marriage with her husband <persName>Francis S.
                            Shulze</persName>; and which marriage contract is recorded in the Land
                        Records of <placeName>Rivee George's County, Maryland</placeName> in Liber
                        E.W.B. N:1 Files 11 &#38; 78 on <date when="1855-02-22">22. Feby.
                            1855</date>
                    </seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg
                        type="handwritten">twelve hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note
                        type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3"> Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">He is worth at least the above amount because he has
                        yielded her an income of over one hundred and fifty dollars per annum clear
                        of all expenses for several years past, and is declared by his employers to
                        be now a faithful hand and in good sound condition. She knows of no moral,
                        mental, or bodily infirmities or defects to impair his value, except the
                        hurt in his shoulder and leg, referred to on the preceding page, and she
                        believes none other to exist.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress;
                    and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten"><persName>Orpheus Countee</persName></seg> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                    the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Orpheus Countee</persName>
                    </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>M. Alice Shulze</persName>
                            <lb/> Attest<lb/>
                            <persName>Edm. F. Brown</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00351.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">Mrs. <persName>M. Alice Shulze</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>M. Alice Shulze</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-19">
                            <seg type="handwritten">19th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A.D. 1862</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Edm F. Brown</persName>
                                <lb/>Notary Public </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>351 <lb/>
                    <persName>M. Alice Shulze</persName>
                </ab>
                <ab> Filed <date when="1862-05-21">May 21, 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>
                    <persName>Kellher</persName> &#38; <persName>Pywell</persName>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName> Wm
                    Bell</persName><address><addrLine> F st near 12</addrLine></address></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
