<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00823">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Martha Isherwood, 1 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00823</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Martha Isherwood, 1 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Martha Isherwood, 1 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Martha Isherwood</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Naylor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-13" who="#jc">performed semi-automated file cleanup</change>
            <change when="2013-05-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2013-04-17" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00823.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha
                        Isherwood</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the <placeName>City of
                            Washington</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Richard
                            Ross</persName>, <persName>Caddy Foreman</persName>, and <persName>Saml
                            Brooks</persName></seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African
                    descent <del>of the name of</del> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Richard</persName>, <persName>Caddy</persName>,
                        and <persName>Samuel</persName> respectively</seg> and that by said act of
                    Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Richard</persName>,
                            <persName>Caddy</persName>, and <persName>Samuel</persName> were</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Richard</persName>, <persName>Caddy</persName>, &amp;
                            <persName>Samuel</persName> were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or
                        her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one
                        separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Richard Ross</persName> is about twenty six or twenty seven
                            years of age; black; stout; healthy, and able bodied man; farm hand;
                            take care of horses and drive a carriage, cart: or wagon: &amp; good
                            house servant.</item>
                        <item><persName>Caddy Foreman</persName>, twenty four or five years old; has
                            been much afflicted with <choice>
                                <sic>inflamatory</sic>
                                <corr>inflammatory</corr>
                            </choice> rheumatism by which her hands, and legs are distorted: when
                            she is well she can cook very well, but can neither wash nor
                            iron—black:</item>
                        <item><persName>Samuel Brooks</persName> about 11, or 12, (probably 11 <date when="1861-12">last December</date>) black; good sized; bright
                            active boy—can wait in the house very well, and do almost any
                            thing a boy of his age can do</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00823.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">to <persName>Richard
                            Brooks</persName>/<persName>Ross</persName> and <persName>Caddy
                            Foreman</persName> by the will of <persName><unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#nnk">Robert</unclear> Isherwood</persName> late
                        of said county deceased who was, her husband, and of which she files
                        herewith a true copy: to <persName>Samuel Brooks</persName> by gift from her
                        Father, Mr <persName>Aden Darby</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery
                            County</placeName> Md when the said boy was an infant &amp; she files the
                        original bill of sale</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Two thousand</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">She knows nothing to add to or detract
                        from the fair market value of the said servants beyond what she has already
                        stated</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> w<del>as</del><seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha
                                Isherwood</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00823.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Paid $—31</ab>
                    <ab><persName>Aden Darby</persName><lb/> B of Sale<lb/>
                        <persName>Martha Isherwood</persName></ab>
                    <ab><choice>
                            <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                            <expan>Received</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <date when="1853-03-22">22d March 1853</date></ab>
                    <ab>to be Recorded &amp; Same day was recorded in Liber J. A. S. No. 53 folios
                        435 &amp; 436 one of the Land Records of <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> And Examined by</ab>
                    <closer><signed><persName>John A. Smith</persName><lb/> Clerk</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00823.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Know all men by these Presents that I <persName>Aden Darby</persName> of
                            <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> and <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName> for the Consideration of one Dollar Current Money
                        to me in hand paid by <persName>Martha Isherwood</persName> of
                            <placeName>Washington County</placeName>
                        <placeName>D. of Columbia</placeName> the Receipt Whereof I do hereby
                        Acknowledge have Granted Bargained and sold and Delivered unto the said
                            <persName>Martha Isherwood</persName> my two negro slaves namely
                            <persName>Johnson Brooks</persName> 4 years old and <persName>Samuel
                            Brooks</persName> about 8 months old Which said Slaves I will Warrant
                        and Defend to the said <persName>Martha Isherwood</persName> her Executors
                        Administrators and Assigns Against me my Executors Administrators or Assigns
                        and Agents and every other person or persons Whomsoever I Witness Whereof I
                        have hereunto set my hand and seal this, <date when="1851-08-27">27th day of
                            August 1851</date>—</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Aden Darby</persName>
                            seal</signed><lb/>
                        Witness <signed><persName>Annie E. Dawes</persName>;</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00823.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>In the name of God, Amen. I, <persName>Robert Isherwood</persName>, of the
                            <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, being sick in body but of sound and disposing
                        mind, memory and understanding considering the certainty of death, and the
                        uncertainty of the time thereof, and being desirous to settle my worldly
                        affairs, and thereby be the better prepared to leave the world when it shall
                        please God to call me hence, do therefore make and publish this my last will
                        and Testament, in manner and form following, that is to say:</p>
                    <p>First and principally, I commit my soul into the hands of Almighty God, and
                        my body to the earth, to be decently buried at the discretion of my
                        Executrix hereinafter named, and after my debts and funeral charges are
                        paid, I devise and bequeath to my dearly beloved wife, <persName>Martha
                            Isherwood</persName> all my property and estate of every description,
                        Real personal and mixed, and all my goods, <choice>
                            <sic>Chattles</sic>
                            <corr>Chattels</corr>
                        </choice>, moneys rights and credits that I may die seized or possessed of
                        or in any way or manner entitled to, to be held and enjoyed by her during
                        her life and widowhood in common with my dear children <persName>Frances Ann
                            Isherwood</persName> and <persName>Robert James Isherwood</persName> and
                            <persName>Margaret E. Isherwood</persName>, and if my said wife shall
                        marry again, then from the period of such marriage, said devise and bequest
                        so far as concerns her, shall cease to operate and in lieu thereof, she
                        shall take absolutely one third of all my personal estate, of every
                        description, and her dower in my Real estate.—</p>
                    <p>Item—I give, devise and bequeath at the death or marriage of my said
                        wife all the residue of my property<pb xml:id="leaf003v " facs="cww.00823.006.jpg"/> and Estate, then remaining to my said dearly
                        beloved children, <persName>Francis Ann Isherwood</persName>
                        <persName>Robert James Isherwood</persName> and <persName>Margaret E.
                            Isherwood</persName> Equally to be divided between them, their
                        respective heirs Executors, administrators and assigns, share and share
                        alike.—</p>
                    <p>Item—I authorize and empower by dear wife to fulfil and complete all
                        existing contracts at the time of my death, by which I am bound in any event
                        to sell and convey, any of my property, by executing all necessary
                        conveyance to the parties entitled.</p>
                    <p>Item—I also empower my said wife, at any time during her widowhood and
                        when it shall appear to her and my highly esteemed friend <persName>Thomas
                            Blagden</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>Esqr.</abbr>
                            <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice> to be for the common interest and benefit of herself and my said
                        children to make sale and conveyance of all or any part of my property and
                        estate &amp; the purchaser or purchasers whereof, shall by virtue of such
                        conveyance or conveyances, be exonerated from all responsibility for the
                        application of the purchase money and the proceeds reinvested in other
                        property to be held in the like manner, or expend the same, in the necessary
                        current maintenance and support of herself and my said children.—</p>
                    <p>And lastly, I do hereby constitute and appoint my dear wife <persName>Marsha
                            Isherwood</persName> to be sole executrix of this my last will and
                        Testament, revoking and annulling all former wills by me heretofore<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00823.007.jpg"/> made, ratifying and
                        confirming this, and none other, to be my last will and Testament, and as I
                        owe little or no debts, request that no security be required of her and
                        exonerate her from all responsibility for losses happening otherwise than
                        from wilful and corrupt misconduct.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal, this
                            <date when="1847-12-15">fifteenth day of, December 1847</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Robert Isherwood</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Signed, sealed, published and declared by <persName>Robert
                            Isherwood</persName> the above names Testator, as and for his last will
                        and Testament, in the presence of us who at his request, in his presence,
                        and in the presence of each other, have subscribed our names as witnesses
                        thereto.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Thos. Blagden</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>J. P. Fugitt</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>H. Naylor</persName></signed><lb/>
                        <dateline><date when="1847-12-15">15th Decr. 1847</date></dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit<lb/> Orphans Court<lb/>
                        <date when="1849-06-19">June 19, 1849</date>.</dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared, <persName>Thomas Blagden</persName> and <persName>Henry
                            Naylor</persName> two of the subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing
                        last will &amp; testament of <persName>Robert Isherwood</persName>, late of
                            <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid, deceased, &amp;
                        seasonally made oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that they did
                        see the Testator therein named sign and seal this will, that he published
                        pronounced and declared the same to be his last will &amp; testament, that
                        at the time of so<pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00823.008.jpg"/> doing, he
                        was to the best of their apprehensions of sound &amp; disposing mind, memory
                        and understanding, and that they together with <persName>J. P.
                            Fugitt</persName>, the other subscribing witness, respectively
                        subscribed their names as witnesses to this will, in the presence &amp; at
                        the request of the Testator, and in the presence of Each other.</p>
                    <closer><signed>Test. <persName>Ed. N. Roach</persName><lb/>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Regr.</abbr>
                                <expan>Register</expan>
                            </choice> Wills</signed>.</closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>I hereby certify that the aforegoing is a true copy from the last will and
                        testament of <persName>Robert Isherwood</persName>, deceased, filed and
                        recorded in the Office of Registers of Wills for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> aforesaid.</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of Office this <date when="1862-06-13">13th day of
                            June A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Moses Kelly</persName><lb/> Register of
                            Wills</signed>.</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00823.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha Isherwood</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Martha
                                    Isherwood</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-30"><seg type="handwritten">30th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H.
                                    Naylor</persName> J Peace</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>823</ab>
                <ab><persName>Martha Isherwood</persName></ab>
                <ab>Petition for 3 Slaves</ab>
                <ab>Exhibits<lb/> Copy of Will &amp; original Bill of sale</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">B &amp; B</unclear><lb/>
                    <persName><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">Ann Dawes</unclear></persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Rebecca R Darby</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
