<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00408">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William Hickey, 23 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
<name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
               <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
               <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00408</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of William Hickey, 23 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-23">May 23, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of William Hickey, 23 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-23">May 23, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775&#8211;1978, National Archives and
                                        Records Administration</orgName>
<note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                                microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>
                    William Hickey
               </persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>S. J. Bowen
               </persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
<change when="2012-03" who="#scl">blessed</change>
          <change when="2012-03-19" who="#jc">proofed for and corrected transcription and encoding errors</change>
<change when="2012-02-15" who="#el">automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
<change when="2012-02-14" who="#el">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary</change>
          <change when="2011-11-11" who="#bj">checked</change>
          <change when="2011-04-19" who="#rv">checked</change>
          <change when="2010-09-20" who="#el">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00408.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>The Statement and petition of <persName>William Hickey</persName> a loyal citizen
                    of the <placeName>United States</placeName> residing within the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>.</p>

                <p>Presented this <date when="1862-05-23">twenty third day of May, eighteen hundred
                        and sixty two</date>, to The Honorable <persName>Samuel F.
                    Vinton</persName>, <persName>Daniel R. Goodloe</persName>, and <persName>Horatio
                        King</persName>, Commissioners appointed in pursuance of the "Act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>," approved the <date when="1862-04-16">sixteenth of
                        April, eighteen hundred and sixty two</date>.</p>

                <p>Respectfully represents:<lb/> That he has been the bone fide owner up to the
                    moment of their discharge by the aforesaid act, and held to service and labor
                    within the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, the following named
                    colored persons, all of African descent and slaves for life, to wit:
                        <persName>John Massy</persName>, <persName>Rachael Fletcher</persName> and
                    her offspring, named <persName>Henry Gantt</persName>, <persName>Augustus
                        Fletcher</persName>, <persName>Andrew Fletcher</persName>, <persName>John
                        Fletcher</persName> and <persName>Charlotte Fletcher</persName>;
                        <persName>Sarah Dover</persName> and her offspring, named <persName>Dick
                        Massy</persName>, alias <persName>Lee</persName> and <persName>Bettie
                        Dover</persName>; and <persName>Mary Butler</persName> and her offspring
                    named <persName>Jim Butler</persName>, <persName>Bob Butler</persName>,
                        <persName>Nelly Butler</persName>, <persName>Mary Butler, Jr.</persName> and
                        <persName>Maria Butler</persName>.</p>

                <p>That to <persName>John Massy</persName>, <persName>Rachael Flecher</persName> and
                        <persName>Sarah Dover</persName>, he acquired a right by his marriage to his
                    wife, to whom those colored persons then belonged, they having been acquired by
                    her, as part of her patrimony from her father's estate, and the offspring of the
                    said <persName>Rachel</persName> and <persName>Sara</persName>, have been born
                    to them since they have been under the ownership and in the possession and
                    service of your petitioner.</p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00408.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That <persName>Mary Butler</persName> was purchased by your petitioner to prevent
                    her from being sold away from her husband <persName>Jim Butler</persName>, who
                    then belonged to your petitioner, but who died some years since. Her offspring
                    by the said <persName>Jim Butler</persName>, have all been born since the said
                    purchase.</p>

                <p>This explains, as required by the second section of the before mentioned act, the
                    manner in which your petitioner acquired the right and claim to the said colored
                    persons of African descent and to their service and labor.</p>

                <p>The following statement will show the names, sexes, ages and personal description
                    of the said colored persons of African descent, and the facts touching and
                    showing the value of those persons and of their services and labor,
                    respectively, of which the petitioner has been deprived by the operation of the
                    aforesaid act of Congress; to wit: <list>

                        <item>1. <persName>John Massy</persName>, male, aged thirty seven year,
                            black color, 5 feet 8 inches high. Healthy, Stout &#38; Strong. An
                            excellent farm and garden hand, hostler and driver, trusty and faithful,
                            being the Head working man on the farm. The just compensation claimed
                            for him is the sum of $1,500.</item>

                        <item>2. <persName>Rachael Fletcher</persName>, female, aged 45 years, black
                            color 5 feet 4 7/16 inches high. She is stout and strong&#8212;is a
                            good cook, washer, Ironer and an excellent Dairy maid&#8212;is very
                            willing, well disposed and faithful and her just value is . . . . . . .
                            . $700.</item>

                        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00408.003.jpg"/>

                        <item>3. <persName>Henry Gantt</persName>, male, aged 23 years, black color,
                            &#38; marked by the small pox&#8212;5 feet 11 1/8 inches, high.
                            He is healthy, Stout and a good strong farm and garden
                            hand&#8212;can handle to advantage the plough, axe, pick, spade and
                            Shovel, scythe, and grain cradle. He is willing and well disposed and
                            his just value is $1,500.</item>

                        <item>4. <persName>Augustus Fletcher</persName>, male, aged 18 years, black
                            color. 5 feet, 9 1/2 inches high. He is healthy, Stout, Strong and
                            active, a good farm and garden hand–understands the care of
                            horses and cattle, and is a driver. He is willing and Steady and his
                            just value is . . . . . . . . . . . $1,500</item>

                        <item>5. <persName>Andrew Fletcher</persName>, male aged 8 years black
                            color&#8212;4 feet 3 inches high. He is a fine healthy, robust boy,
                            very anxious, &#38; willing . . . . to do boys work and his value in
                            justice is . . . . . . . $500.</item>

                        <item>6. <persName>John Fletcher</persName>, male, aged 6 years, black
                            color&#8212;4 feet high. He is also a healthy robust and active boy
                            and is useful for his age. His just value is . . . . . . .
                            $300.</item>

                        <item>7. <persName>Charlotte Fletcher</persName>, female aged 9 months. She
                            is of black color and a healthy and lively infant, and only valued at .
                            . . . . . . . . . $50.</item>

                        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00408.004.jpg"/>

                        <item>8. <persName>Sarah Dover</persName>, female, aged 39 years, second
                            shade of black color, 5 feet 2 8/10 inches high. She is a healthy,
                            stout, strong and a complete house servant and Dairy maid and well
                            qualified as a cook, washer and ironer, Dining room and parlor servant,
                            chambermaid,&#8212;a good seamstress and house servant generally.
                            She has also gathered the produce of the Dairy and market garden and has
                            sold it in market and made correct and satisfactory returns.&#8212;Her loss would be difficult to replace and her just value claimed is . .
                            . . . . . . . $1,200.</item>

                        <item>9. <persName>Dick Massy</persName>, alias <persName>Lee</persName>,
                            male, aged 21 years, third shade in black color, 5 feet 9 inches high.
                            He stutters in speaking. Is stout, strong and healthy&#8212;a good
                            farm and garden hand. He is an excellent coachman and driver generally,
                            and is a complete manager of horses and cattle &#38; his just value
                            claimed is $1,500.</item>

                        <item>10. <persName>Bettie Dover</persName>, female, aged, 11 years, second
                            shade of black color, 4 feet 6 1/2 inches high and robust in health. She
                            is a very willing, active and useful girl about the house&#8212;can
                            sew, wait upon table and in the house generally, and her just value
                            claimed is . . . . . . . . . . . . . . $500.</item>

                        <item>11. <persName>Mary Butler</persName>, female, aged 49 years, second
                            shade of black color, 5 feet /4 inch high. She is in good health and is
                                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00408.005.jpg"/>
                            
                            a very fine, well
                            instructed and complete house servant maid, in every
                            respect&#8212;for parlor, dining room, chamber and kitchen, being
                            also an excellent cook, washer and ironer and her just value claimed is
                            . . . . . . $800. </item>

                        <item>12. <persName>James Butler</persName>, male, aged 24 years, black
                            color, 5 feet 5 inches high. He is strong healthy and steady and an
                            excellent farm and garden hand. He is a good driver and understands the
                            care and management of horses and cattle, and his just value claimed is
                            . . . . . . . . . . . . . $1,500</item>

                        <item>13. <persName>Bob Butler</persName>, male, aged 15 years, second shade
                            of black color, 5 feet 1/10 inch high. He is a smart boy, very useful
                            about the house, farm and garden. He understands the case of horses and
                            cattle and drives carts, wagons and other vehicles. He is healthy and
                            active &#38; and his just value claimed is . . .  $700.</item>

                        <item>14. <persName>Nelly Butler</persName> female, aged 22 years, black
                            color, 5 feet 1/2 inch high. She is in good health &#38; Strong and
                            is a faithful housemaid, and nurse for children, being kind and amiable
                            in disposition&#8212;can wash, iron &#38;c, and her just value
                            claimed is . . . . . . . $800.</item>

                        <item>15. <persName>Mary Butler, <choice><abbr>Junr</abbr><expan>Junior</expan></choice></persName>. female, aged 20 years,
                            black color, 5 feet, 1 3/8 inches high. She is a servant of particular
                            merit and usefulness and very healthy and robust and is
                            
                            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00408.006.jpg"/>
                            
                            capable of doing any
                            kind of house work. She is a kind nurse to children and an obliging,
                            faithful and excellent servant and her just value claimed is . . . . . .
                            .$1,200.</item>

                        <item>16. . . . <persName>Maria Butler</persName>, female, aged 17 years, black
                            color, 5 feet 1/4 inch high. This girl is an excellent seamstress,
                            chambermaid, parlor and dining room servant and house maid generally.
                            She is healthy, active and intelligent&#8212;her just value claimed
                            is $800.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>

                <p>This statement and schedule embracing the names, sexes, ages and personal
                    description of the said colored persons, will be found also to embrace the
                    personal condition and qualifications of each of those persons, these items
                    being necessary to complete their personal description, and having a direct
                    relation to their value, or that of their service and labor, as required to be
                    stated by the second section of the aforementioned act.</p>

                <p>It is also but just, in this connection, to state the fact, that much time and
                    trouble have been taken in instructing these servants, from their infancy, in
                    their respective duties as stated, which has rendered them very valuable in the
                    several avocations above mentioned; and that, the sudden operation of this law,
                    depriving the claimant of the services of the servants, has made a radical
                    change in the mode of working and managing his farm and in the domestic
                    arrangements
                    
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00408.007.jpg"/>
                    
                    and has subjected
                    your petitioner to new and expensive modes of having the work done, that has
                    heretofore been performed by these servants; and their value to the petitioner
                    can be best appreciated and calculated, when there is taken into view, the amount
                    of wages and other expenses that he will have to pay, to replace all the labor,
                    service and advantages derived from these servants, of which he has been so
                    suddenly deprived by the instantaneous operation of the aforesaid act.</p>

                <p>It may also be proper for the claimant to state, that the aggregate of the whole
                    of the foregoing valuation, is less by five thousand dollars, than was offered
                    by a gentleman from <placeName>Texas</placeName> for those servants, on account
                    of their character, condition, and qualifications, a short time before the
                    breaking out of the present rebellion, which was declined because it would
                    separate married people, and remove the others forever from their relations and
                    friends, and also, because they supplied and subserved all the requirements, and
                    could not be replaced in the homestead, on the farm and in the garden so
                    satisfactorily by other persons.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner therefore respectfully prays the allowance of the valuation
                    placed by him on those colored persons, respectively, in the foregoing schedule,
                    knowing the same to be less than he could have obtained for them, before the
                    rebellion broke out, and probably much less than he would have been able to
                    obtain for them, when the rebellion shall have been overcome, had not this act
                    been passed by Congress, and he therefore
                    
                    <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00408.008.jpg"/>
                    
                    believes that the adoption of this valuation
                    would be within the term "just compensation" which the constitution provides for
                    the private citizen, in such cases, and which he is happy to believe may be
                    accorded to him, under the liberal appropriation by Congress, on the basis of a
                    slave population in this <placeName>District</placeName>, of upwards of three
                    thousand persons, the average being evidently extended to that number, which
                    would appear to fully authorize the allowance of a "just compensation" according
                    to the Constitution, for a much less number of colored persons, provided the
                    whole sum allowed for all slaves in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> shall not exceed the sum of money appropriated.</p>

                <p>As regards the loyalty of your petitioner, he has the honor to state, that when
                    invested with the command of a Brigade of the Militia of the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>, he took the oath to support the Constitution, and
                    to perform the duties of a Brigadier General; that on the <date when="1861-08-26">26th day of August, 1861</date>, he took the oath of
                    allegiances as chief clerk in the Senate of the United States, as required by
                    the act of the <date when="1861-08-06">6th day of August, 1861</date>, a copy of
                    which oath is hereto annexed, and which he now reiterates, and that he not only "has not borne arms against the United States
                    during the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid and comfort thereto," but
                    that he assisted in raising volunteers to defend the government in
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, when it was daily threatened by attack,
                    and, being the Senior Brigadier, he verbally and in writing, offered his
                    services to the Commanding General, and through him to the War Department, as
                    being willing and ready to perform his duty
                    
                    <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00408.009.jpg"/>
                    
                    to his country in defence of its government and
                    national authorities.</p>

                <p>All of which is now verified by the oath of your petitioner and is most
                    respectfully submitted</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>W. Hickey</persName>
                    </signed>
                    
                  <placeName>Washington county, District of Columbia,</placeName>
                        <date when="1862-05-21">May 21st 1862</date>.
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                    <placeName>Washington county</placeName> . . . Sct</dateline>

                <p>On this <date when="1862-05-21">twenty first day of May, eighteen hundred and
                        sixty two</date>, personally appeared before me the subscriber a Justice of
                    the peace in and for the county aforesaid, <persName>William Hickey</persName>,
                    well known to me, who has, in my presence subscribed his name to the foregoing
                    statement and schedule, and made oath in due form of law, that the same and all
                    the items contained therein are correct and true to the best of his knowledge
                    and belief; that he duly presented to and filed with the Clerk of the Circuit
                    Court of the <placeName>United States</placeName> for the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                    the Statement and schedule required by the ninth section of the act of Congress
                    of the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date> referred to in the
                    preceding statement; that it was filed with the said Clerk on the<date when="1862-04-26">26th day of April, 1862</date>, and contained the names,
                    ages, sexes and particular descriptions of each of the colored persons whose
                    names &#38;c are contained in the preceding statement and schedule, and the
                    said <persName>William Hickey</persName> now reiterates the oath of allegiance
                    under the act of Congress of the <date when="1861-08-06">sixth of
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="cww.00408.010.jpg"/>
                        
                        August, eighteen hundred
                        and sixty one</date>, which he took on the <date when="1861-08-26">26th day
                        of August, 1861</date>, before <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>, a
                    justice of the Peace for <placeName>Washington county</placeName>,
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S. J. Bowen</signed> J.P. seal</closer>

            </div1>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        <placeName>Washington county</placeName> 
                  <lb/> Sct.
                    </dateline>

                    <p>"I, <persName>William Hickey</persName>, do solemnly swear that I will
                        support, protect and defend the Constitution and government of the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName> against all enemies, whether
                        domestic or foreign, and that I will bear true faith, allegiance, and
                        loyalty to the same, any ordinance, resolution, or law of any state
                        convention or legislature to the contrary notwithstanding; and further, that
                        I do this with a full determination, pledge, and purpose, without any mental
                        reservation, or evasion whatever; and further, that I will well and
                        faithfully perform all the duties which may be required of me by law. So
                        help me God."</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>W. Hickey</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>

                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>On this <date when="1862-05-21">twenty first day of May, eighteen hundred and
                            sixty-two</date>, personally appeared before me the subscriber, a
                        Justice of the peace in and for the county of
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName> and <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, <persName>William Hickey</persName>, the claimant
                        and petitioner who has made and subscribed the foregoing statement and
                        schedule and took and subscribed the above oath of allegiance before me
                        according to law.&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>S. J. Bowen</persName>
                        </signed> J. P. seal</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00408.011.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>408<lb/>
               <persName>William Hickey</persName></ab>
                <ab>Sett <lb/>158299</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-23">May 23, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Mr <persName>Benson M. Polier</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Clarke Mills</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Allen Dodge</persName><lb/>
                    Mrs. <persName>Fenwich</persName></ab>
            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
