<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00607">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of George W. Wren and Catherine A. Wren, 2 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00607</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of George W. Wren and Catherine A. Wren, 2 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of George W. Wren and Catherine A. Wren, 2 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>George W. Wren</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Catherine A. Wren</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-06-13" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-05-24" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00607.002.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    <seg type="handwritten">residents</seg> of <seg type="handwriiten">
                        <placeName>Washington City D. C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg
                        type="handwritten">their</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">they are</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">the following persons</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Alice Lewis</persName>, <persName>Oscar Lewis</persName>,
                            <persName>Helen Lewis</persName>, <persName>Mashack Lewis</persName>,
                            <persName>Cora Lewis</persName>, <persName>Sarah Curtis</persName>,
                            <persName>Watlis Curtis</persName>, <persName>Henry Curtis</persName>,
                        and <persName>George Cane</persName></seg> for and during the life of said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Alice Lewis</persName></seg> was of the age of <seg
                                type="handwritten">42 years</seg> and of the personal description
                                following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                                describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be
                                more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                            <list type="handwritten">
                                <item>5 feet 1 inches high dark color, joint of little finger of the right hand off</item>
                                <item><persName>Oscar Lewis</persName> was of the age of 29 years 5 feet 8 inches high, dark color, scar under the chin</item>
                                <item><persName>Helen Lewis</persName>, 24 years 5 feet 1 inches high copper color, scar on her right wrist</item>
                                <item><persName>Mashack Lewis</persName>, 4 years, bright mulatto</item>
                                <item><persName>Cora Lewis</persName>, 2 years bright mulatto</item>
                                <item><persName>Sarah Curtis</persName> 32 years 5 feet 3 inches high copper color, scar in her forehead</item>
                                <item><persName>Watlis Curtis</persName> 11 years, <space atLeast="1"/> feet <space atLeast="1"/> inches high copper color, a very likely Boy</item>
                                <item><persName>Henry Curtis</persName> 6 months, copper color</item>
                                <item><persName>George Cane</persName>, 42 year 5 feet 8 inches high black</item>
                            </list></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00607.003.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">by wills from <persName>Sarah S. Wren</persName> made in
                        the year <date when="1842">1842</date> conveying <persName>George
                            Cane</persName> to <persName>Catherine Ann Wren</persName> to have and
                        to hold for her separate use and benefit said <persName>Catherine Ann
                            Wren</persName> being the wife of <persName>George W. Wren</persName>.
                        By will from <persName>Sinah E. Lee</persName> made in the year <date
                            when="1851">1851</date> devising <persName>Alice Lewis</persName> <persName>Oscar Lewis</persName>
                        <persName>Helen Lewis</persName>, <persName>Sarah Curtis</persName> with
                        their increase, the remainder of the children in petition mentioned being the
                        increase from said persons, to <persName>Catherine Ann Wren</persName> wife
                        of <persName>George W. Wren</persName> to have and to hold to her separate
                        use and benefit which said wills are of Record at Fairfax Court House <placeName>Fairfax County
                            Virginia</placeName></seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">five thousand</seg> dollars
                    in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts,
                        if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service
                        or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if
                        any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">That all of said persons are sound and
                        healthy and free from any moral, mental, or bodily infirmity or
                        defect That the adults are first rate servants and the children
                        promising and likely</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg>
                        bear<del>s</del> true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not borne arms
                    against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion, nor
                    in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not brought said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg>
                        w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor
                    therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                    labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Geo. W. Wren</persName></seg></signed>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten">Catharine A Wren</seg></signed></closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00607.005.jpg"/>           
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Extract from the Will of <persName>Sinah Lee</persName>, on record among the
                    records of <persName>Fairfax</persName> County Court&#8212;</p>
                    <p>Seventh, my son in law <persName>George W. Wrenn</persName> to
                        secure the payment of a debt due to me from him, having heretofore conveyed
                        by deed dated the <date when="1842-11-19">19th day of November 1842</date>
                        and duly recorded, to <persName>Richard K. Lee</persName> in trust, negro
                        woman <persName>Alice</persName> and her two children
                            <persName>Oscar</persName> and <persName>Helen</persName>, and I now
                        desiring to give to my daughter <persName>Catherine Ann
                            Wrenn</persName>, wife of the said <persName>George W.
                            Wrenn</persName>, a sole and <choice><sic>seperate</sic><corr>separate</corr></choice> estate in the said debt and
                        security, for her <choice>
                            <sic>seperate</sic>
                            <corr>separate</corr>
                        </choice> and exclusive use during her life, remainder to her children
                        surviving at the time of her death and the children of such as may be dead,
                        do hereby give and bequeath to my said daughter <persName>Catharine Ann
                            Wren</persName>, the said debt and security for her sole and <choice>
                            <sic>seperate</sic>
                            <corr>separate</corr>
                        </choice> use during her life, remainder to her children surviving at the
                        time of her death, and the children of such as may be then dead, to take per <choice>
                            <sic>stipes</sic>
                            <corr>stirpes</corr>
                        </choice>&#8212;I also give to my said daughter <persName>Catharine Ann
                            Wrenn</persName> for her <choice>
                            <sic>seperate</sic>
                            <corr>separate</corr>
                        </choice> and exclusive use free from the control of her husband, for and
                        during her life, the following negroes and the increase of the females from
                        the date hereof, to wit <persName>Sarah</persName> and her two children,
                            <persName>James</persName> and an infant not named or name unknown, and
                        at the death of my said daughter, I direct that the said negroes and the
                        increase as aforesaid be equally divided amongst the children of my said
                        daughter her surviving and the children of such as may be dead, to take per <choice>
                            <sic>stipes</sic>
                            <corr>stirpes</corr>
                        </choice>;&#8212;But if my said daughter shall have no children or child,
                        nor the descendants <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00607.006.jpg"/>of such
                        children or child her surviving, then she may by last will or letter of
                        appointment in the nature thereof give the property and interest herein
                        bequeathed to her use as aforesaid, to any of her blood kin that she may
                        choose And the legal title to the property and interest herein given and
                        bequeathed for the <choice>
                            <sic>seperate</sic>
                            <corr>separate</corr>
                        </choice> use of my said daughter for life remainder over as aforesaid, I
                        give to and vest in <persName>William S. Edwards</persName>, to be held by
                        him in trust for the purposes of bequest and none other</p>
                    
                <closer>Teste
                    <signed><persName>Alfred Moss</persName></signed><lb/>
                    By <persName>Tho: Moore</persName> <placeName>D. C.</placeName></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab><persName>Sinah Lee</persName>'s Will</ab>
                    <ab>Extract&#8212;</ab>
                    <ab>Fee for Copy <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">20 <choice><abbr>c</abbr><expan>cents</expan></choice></unclear></ab>
                </div2>                
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00607.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab><persName>Wren Sarah S</persName></ab>
                <ab>Will</ab>
                <ab>Copy</ab>
                <ab>For <persName>Wm. S. Edwards</persName></ab>
                </div2>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00607.008.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>In the name of God amen, I <persName>Sarah S. Wren</persName> of the
                        <placeName>County of Fairfax</placeName> &amp; <placeName>State of
                        Virginia</placeName>, being weak in body, but of sound and perfect mind and
                    memory, do make and publish my last will and testament&#8212;in manner and form following&#8212;First&#8212;I give and bequeath to my beloved daughters
                                <persName>Susan Wren</persName> and <persName>Elizabeth
                                Wren</persName>, my woman <persName>Lucy</persName> (a slave for
                            life) also to each of them one Bed with the quilts, Blankets &amp;c. and all
                            the furniture belonging to said Bed. I also give and bequeath to my daughter <persName>Susan
                                Wren</persName> my large Brass andirons, my large table &amp; one
                            half of my large silver spoons. I also give and bequeath to my Daughter
                                <persName>Elizabeth Wren</persName> my Clock and one half of my
                            large Silver spoons it is also my will and desire that my earthenware be equally
                            divided between my daughters <persName>Susan Wren</persName>, <persName>Elizabeth Wren</persName>
                            &amp; my son <persName>Charles B Wren</persName>. I also give and
                            bequeath to my beloved daughter <persName>Jane Davis</persName> my large
                            bell <choice><sic>mettal</sic><corr>metal</corr></choice> Kettle</p>
                        <p>I also give and bequeath to my beloved son <persName>Charles B. Wren</persName>, all my cows, sheep and hogs, also
                            three beds &amp; furniture (being the residue of my beds after the two above disposed of are selected) one Safe, half
                            dozen chairs (first choice) also my small Kettle, my silver Ladle and german Silver spoons, and all my farming utensils including Cart &amp; <gap
                                reason="illegible" extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="5"/>; It
                            is also my (will &amp;) desire that my son <persName>Charles B.
                                Wren</persName> be permitted to occupy my farm without charge until
                            claimed by the heirs, and that he have, and I hereby give and bequeath to him all
                            the Crops, either made, or making which may be on the place at my
                            death&#8212;It is also my will and desire that the negro boy
                                <persName>Alfred</persName> serve the balance of his time with my
                            son <persName>Charles B. Wren</persName>.</p>
                        <p>And whereas <persName>George W. Wren</persName> is indebted to me (by note) in the
                            sum of five hundred Dollars, which debt is secured by deed of Trust on negro man slave
                            named <persName>George</persName>, and bearing date <date when="1842-10-21">21st day of October 1842</date>, now it is my will
                            and desire and I do hereby will and bequeath the said note of five
                            hundred dollars; together with all my right title and interest in and to said
                            Slave <persName>George</persName> to my daughter in Law
                                <persName>Catharine A. Wren</persName> (wife of <persName>G W.
                                Wren)</persName>) and her Child or Children for her or their only
                            use &amp; benefit. It is also my<pb xml:id="leaf008r"
                                facs="cww.00607.009.jpg"/> will and desire, and I hereby direct that
                            all the rest residue &amp; remainder of my property, not disposed of by
                            this will, be sold as soon as possible after my death, and that the
                            proceeds of said sale after the payment of my just debts &amp; funeral
                            expenses, be equally divided between (my daughters <persName>Susan Wren</persName> &amp; <persName>Elizabeth
                                Wren</persName> and my son <persName>Charles B. Wren</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Lastly I hereby appoint my son <persName>Albert Wren</persName>
                            Executor of this my Last will and Testament; hereby revoking all former
                            wills by me made.</p>
                <p>In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand and seal the <date
                        when="1842-04-15">fifteenth day of April in the Year of or Lord eighteen
                        hundred &amp; forty two</date>.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Sarah S. Wren</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Signed Sealed &amp; published in presence of</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>James Thrift</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>John Crump</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline>At a Court held for the <placeName>County of Fairfax</placeName> the <date when="1843-05-15">15th day of May 1843</date></dateline>
                    <p>This last will and Testament of <persName>Sarah S. Wren</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>decd.</abbr>
                            <expan>deceased</expan>
                        </choice> was this day presented to the Court&#8212;and the same being
                        proved by the oaths of <persName>James Thrift</persName> and <persName>John
                            Crump</persName> subscribing Witnesses thereto,&#8212;is submitted to
                        probate</p>
                    <closer>Teste
                        <signed><persName>S M Ball</persName> C. C.</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>C &amp; Copy</ab>
                    <closer>Teste
                        <signed><persName>S. M. Ball</persName> C. C.</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="cww.00607.010.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>George W. Wren</persName> &amp;
                                <persName>Catherine A. Wren</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do
                        depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> <del>my</del>
                         own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, <del>I</del> <seg
                            type="handwritten">they</seg> believe to be true in substance and in
                        fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Geo. W. Wren</persName></seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Catharine A Wren</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-27"><seg type="handwritten">27th</seg> day of <seg
                                type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Thomas C Donn</persName><lb/>
                        Justice of the Peace for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">                
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>607</ab>
                    <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                        <persName>George W. Wren</persName> &amp;<lb/>
                        <persName>Catherine A. Wren</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>Misc <gap reason="illegible" exclude="one word" unit="chars" quantity="2"/><lb/>
                    158<unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">2</unclear>99<lb/>
                    FE <gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word" unit="chars" quantity="6"/><lb/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">Treas US</unclear></ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
