<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00540">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of William L. Hoyle, 28 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00540</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of William L. Hoyle, 28 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of William L. Hoyle, 28 May 1862 </title>
                            <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>John C. McKelden</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John H. Johnson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">revised order of transcription</change>
            <change when="2013-01-18" who="#jc">fixed typo in spelling of McKelden's name; updated
                tei header with additional people in particDesc</change>
            <change when="2012-11-09" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-10-05" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2011-11-17" who="#bj">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-11" who="#rr">transcribed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00540.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Wm L. Hoyle</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">three</seg>
                        person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>, <persName>Margaret Dyson</persName>,
                            <persName>Matilda Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and
                    that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">persons
                        were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <space atLeast="1"/>
                    and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1"> Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName><choice>
                                <orig>Margaret</orig>
                                <reg>Mary</reg>
                            </choice> Dyson</persName> is about forty-seven years of age, Mulatto,
                        about the medium height and robust person; she is sound and healthy in mind
                        and body of excellent character for honesty and industry, and a first rate
                        cook</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Margaret Dyson</persName> is about seventeen years
                    of age, dark color, about the medium height, stout person, sound in body and
                    mind, of excellent character, and is a good house servant &amp; child
                    nurse.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Matilda Dyson</persName> is about ten years old,
                    dark color, well grown, sound &amp; healthy in mind and body and is a really
                    good girl.</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00540.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2"> Here state
                        how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"> by marriage <persName>Susan A. J. Rollins</persName> of
                            <placeName>Prince George County MD</placeName>. in <date when="1848">1848</date>. </seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">person</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">three thousand</seg> dollars
                    in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3"> Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>, one thousand <choice>
                            <abbr>dolls</abbr>
                            <expan>dollars</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Margaret Dyson</persName> twelve hundred <choice>
                            <abbr>dolls</abbr>
                            <expan>dollars</expan>
                        </choice>. <persName>Matilda Dyson</persName> eight hundred <choice>
                            <abbr>dolls</abbr>
                            <expan>dollars</expan>
                        </choice>. And your petitioner avers that knows of no infirmity or defect
                        that impairs the value of his claim and he believes that none exists. </seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into
                    the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim
                    to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>W. L. Hoyle</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>            

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00540.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName> trustee and <persName>John C.
                            McKelden</persName> cestui que trust</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> petition in writing,
                        represent<del>s</del> and state<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they are</seg>
                    <del>is a</del> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> loyal to the United
                    States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a
                    claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a</seg> person of
                    African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and from
                    all claims of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">about forty seven years</seg> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n4"> Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">viz a mulatto above medium size and height and of a
                        large person</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00540.007.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> acquired <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n5">
                        Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price
                        or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">one <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName> being indebted
                        to said <persName>McKelden</persName> in the sum of $132.94 for which said
                            <persName>McKelden</persName> held the promissory note of said Hoyle
                        dated <date when="1858-01-09">January 9th 1858</date> and at thirty days
                        after date to his order for $132.94. by his deed bearing date on <date when="1858-01-27">January 27th 1858</date> conveyed said <persName>Mary
                            Dyson</persName> to said <persName>Woodward</persName> in trust to
                        secure said debt. which is now due and unpaid—Your petitioners
                        herewith annex the original deed of trust marked <hi rend="underline">WBW</hi>, which has been recorded in the proper office in the
                            <placeName>county of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District
                            of Columbia</placeName> Liber JAS 149 <choice>
                            <abbr>fol</abbr>
                            <expan>folio</expan>
                        </choice>. 360 <gap reason="illegible" extent="one or two words" quantity="5" unit="chars"/></seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$166 17/100</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n6"> Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"> The said <persName>Mary Dyson</persName> was at the
                        date of the passage of said law of the value of $.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">Your petitioners claims that the sum of $132.94 with interest
                    there from <date when="1858-02-11">February 11th 1858</date> Shall be allowed
                    and paid to them from whatever amount shall be allowed for said <persName>Mary
                        Dyson</persName> made the act of Congress aforesaid—</ab>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> hereby declare<del>s</del> that
                        <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> bear<del>s</del> true and faithful
                    allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not borne
                    arms against the United States in the present rebellion, nor in any way given
                    aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress;
                    and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor. <seg type="handwritten">and the
                        claim of said <persName>Wm L Hoyle</persName> as owner.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                        allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to
                    the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of
                    the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> pray<del>s</del> the said
                    Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary Dyson</persName>
                    </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>(Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Wm. R. Woodward</persName><lb/> Trustee</seg></signed>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J. C.
                        McKelden</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00540.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>We, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>William L. Woodward</persName>and <persName>John C.
                                McKelden</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of
                            <del>my</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">our</seg> own knowledge, are true in substance and
                        in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, <del>I</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">we</seg> believe to be true in substance and in
                        fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Wm Woodward</persName> Trustee</seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J. C.
                            McKelden</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-08">
                            <seg type="handwritten">8th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>. </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>John H. Johnson</persName> JP. Seal</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

            </div1>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>540<lb/>
                    <persName>Wm. R. Woodward</persName> trustee<lb/> and<lb/>
                    <persName>John C. McKelden</persName></ab>
                <ab>Counter petition to <persName>Wm L. Hoyles</persName> Claim</ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00540.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Paid $1.00</ab>
                    <ab><persName>William L. Hoyle</persName><lb/> To<lb/>
                        <persName>Wm. R. Woodward</persName></ab>
                    <ab>Bill Sale in Trust</ab>
                    <ab>WRW</ab>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Received <date when="1858-02-12">12th February 1858</date> To be recorded
                        &amp; same day was Recorded in Liber L. Sp. S. No. 149 Folio 360, 361, 362,
                        &amp; 363, One of the Land Records of <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        &amp; examined by</ab>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>John S. Smith</persName>. <choice>
                                <abbr>clk</abbr>
                                <expan>clerk</expan>
                            </choice></signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <ab>To be recorded in 20 days</ab>
                    </postscript>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00540.010.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>This indenture made the <date when="1858-01-27">twenty seventh day of January
                            Eighteen hundred and fifty eight</date> between <persName>William L.
                            Hoyle</persName> of the first place and <persName>John C.
                            McKelden</persName> of the second part and <persName>William R.
                            Woodward</persName> of the third part. All of the City of<placeName>
                            Washington in the District of Columbia</placeName>. There as the said
                            <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName> is indebted unto said
                            <persName>John C. McKelden</persName> in the full amount of his
                        promissory note dated the <date when="1858-01-09">ninth day of
                            January</date> instant for the sum of one hundred and thirty two dollars
                        and ninety four cents payable at thirty days of the date thereof with
                        interest there on from date and decision by there presents to secure the
                        payment of said note by a regular <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">curtail</unclear> thereof of fifteen dollars paid at the end
                        of each and every thirty days until the whole of said debt note and interest
                        is paid. This indenture there on witnesseth that the said <persName>William
                            L. Hoyle</persName> in consideration of the premises and also of the sum
                        of one dollars current money to him paid by the said <persName>William
                            Woodward</persName> at or before the execution hereof (the receipt is
                        hereby acknowledged) Hath bargained sold assigned and transferred and by
                        these presents doth bargain sell assign and transfer unto the said
                            <persName>William R. Woodward</persName> his executors administrators
                        and assigns one slave called <persName>Mary Dyson</persName> to have and to
                        hold the said Slave <persName>Mary Dyson</persName> unto and to the use of
                        the said <persName>William R. Woodward</persName> his executors,
                        administrators and assigns upon the trusts following nevertheless and to and
                        for no other use intent or purpose whatsoever, that is to say upon trust to
                        permit the said <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName> to have hold use and
                        employ, and receive the rents of said <persName>Mary Dyson</persName> as
                        though this deed had not been made until default made in the payment of the
                        said note in manner as aforesaid or of any note or notes given in
                        substitution or renewal thereof or herein after provided and upon any
                        default in the regular payment every thirty days of <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">curtail</unclear> of said note
                        till all is paid or of any note given in restitution or renewal of the same
                        or any part thereof by said <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName> or as
                        herein the provided through no default shall have been made it shall be the
                        duty of said <persName>William R. Woodward</persName> his executors,
                        administrators or assigns on the request of said <persName>John C.
                            McKelden</persName> or the legal holder of the note as in default to
                        make into his and their exclusive possession the said <persName>Mary
                            Dyson</persName> and to sell the same at public auction of the such
                        notice and upon such times as the trustee shall determine and most for <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00540.011.jpg"/> for the interest of all
                        concerned, and out of the proceeds of sale he shall pay the costs and
                        expenses there of including a commission of fine of five percent on the
                        gross amount there of to himself and next he shall pay to the person
                        entitled and debt and note the whole of said debt, note and interest then
                        owing and unpaid (no further contact or the act being did of in such
                        default) and the residue shall be paid over to the said <persName>William L.
                            Hoyle</persName> his executors, administrators or assigns. Provided
                        always and upon this further trust that whenever it shall appear to the
                        trustee that any disposition of said slave otherwise than is consistent with
                        these presents and the final execution thereof by said <persName>William L.
                            Hoyle</persName> in the event of the death of said
                            <persName>Hoyle</persName> or of any executor or other process being
                        levied or attempted to the levied on said slave at shall and may be lawful
                        for the said trustee and it is made his duty; he deeming it seems any for
                        the security of said debt to the said slave and sell as of and apply the
                        proceeds as aforesaid and to that end to institute all and every necessary
                        process at law and in equity and the said <persName>William L.
                            Hoyle</persName> doth hereby covenant with said <persName>William R.
                            Woodward</persName> that he the said <persName>William L.
                            Hoyle</persName> shall and will during the continuance of this trust nor
                        cause or permit to be done, any act to impair or hinder the security hereby
                        granted and that on any default as aforesaid he shall and will quietly and
                        peacefully deliver the exclusive possession of said slave to said
                            <persName>William R. Woodward</persName> his executors, administrators
                        or assigns to be disposed of in the manner herein before set forth. In
                        witness whereof the said <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName> hath hereto
                        set his hand and seal an the day and year first hereunto written</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>W.L. Hoyle</persName> seal</signed><lb/> Signed, Sealed
                        and delivered <signed><persName>F. I. Murphey</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>D. H. Goodard</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>


                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00540.012.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        <lb/>
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> to wit </dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered that on this <date when="1858-01-27">27th day of January in
                            the year Eighteen hundred and fifty eight</date> before me the
                        subscribed a justice of the peace on and for the county aforesaid personally
                        appeared <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName> to me as the person who
                        executed deed dated the <date when="1858-01-27">27th day of January
                            instant</date> to <persName>William R. Woodward</persName> and unto
                        answered and acknowledged the same to be his act and deed 27th given under
                        my hand and seal.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>F. I. Murphey</persName> J.P. seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00540.004.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                    Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William L. Hoyle</persName>
                    </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>W. L. Hoyle</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-28">
                        <seg type="handwritten">28th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>. </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName> Justice of the Peace for
                            <placeName>Washington County</placeName>
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>540<lb/> Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>W. L. Hoyle</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Presented by<lb/>
                    <persName>Tho. B. Peyton</persName></ab>
                <ab><persName>R. W. Carter</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Lewis L. Rollins</persName></ab>
            </div1>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
