<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00680">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Peter G. Washington, 16 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
<name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00680</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Peter G. Washington, 16 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-16">June 16, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Peter G. Washington, 16 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-16">June 16, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Peter G. Washington</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Nicholas Callan</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-17" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-11" who="#scl">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-10" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-30" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00680.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>P. G. Washington</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington, D. C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg
                        type="handwritten">five</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of
                    African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of 
                    <list type="handwritten">
                            <item>1 <persName>Lucinda Black</persName></item>
                            <item>2 <persName>Louisa Gantt</persName>.</item>
                            <item>3 <persName>Georgiana</persName> "</item>
                            <item>4 <persName>Lucinda</persName> "</item>
                            <item>5 <persName>Sophia</persName>&#8212;"</item>
                    </list> 
                    for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons have been</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons were of the</seg> <del>of the age of</del> <seg type="handwritten">ages and</seg>
                    <del>and of the</del> personal description following:<note type="government"
                        place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or
                        her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one
                        separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">to wit</seg>
                        <list type="handwritten">
                            <item>1. <persName>Lucinda Black</persName> of the age of about sixty
                                two years, mulatto, of medium complexion and delicate figure</item>
                            <item>2 <persName>Louisa Gantt</persName>, of the age of about thirty years, mulatto, of light complexion and delicate figure</item>
                            <item>3 <persName>Georgiana Gantt</persName>, in the eighth year of her
                                age, mulatto of dark complexion,</item>
                            <item>4 <persName>Lucinda Gantt</persName> in the sixth year of her age,
                                mulatto of dark complexion</item>
                            <item>5 <persName>Sophia Gantt</persName> about seven months old,
                                mulatto, of dark complexion.</item>
                        </list>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00680.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Upon the purchase of <persName>Lucinda</persName> in
                            <date when="1829">1829</date> from one <persName>Graham</persName>, the property was conveyed to
                            <persName>John M Berrien</persName> in trust for the benefit of
                            <persName>Margaret M Washington</persName> wife of your petitioner and subsequently under authority reserved in the deed. Said <persName>Margaret</persName> directed, and said
                            <persName>Berrien</persName> transferred the said property to
                        petitioner, as will appear by the deed herewith filed. <persName>Louisa
                            Gantt</persName>, is the child of said <persName>Lucinda</persName> and
                            <space atLeast="1"/> are the children
                        of said <persName>Louisa</persName>.</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">1,500</seg>
                    dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state
                        such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to
                        the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten"> as follows, <persName>Lucinda
                            Black</persName> <choice><abbr>altho</abbr><expan>although</expan></choice> always delicate but rarely sick is uncommonly smart and being a
                        good cook &#38; washer. I estimate as worth $100. <persName>Louisa
                            Gantt</persName> is uncommonly bright intelligent reliable. Her value
                        would be very great if her health was perfect. As the passage of the act she
                        was much reduced in flesh by nursing her infant and probably by over work, and her
                        condition now is not free from danger. Under these circumstances I estimate
                        her value at 600$. Her three children are uncommonly bright healthy and
                        promising. I estimate the oldest at $400, the next at 300$ and the youngest
                        at 100$ At the passage of the act herein referred to I know of no defect in any of said mulattoes
                        other than herein stated and believe none existed. Within the last ten days
                            <persName>Louisa</persName> has been under treatment of Dr.
                            <persName>Hall</persName>, who express some doubt whether she has not incipient bronchitis.</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">mulattoes</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">mulattoes were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">mulattoes</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">mulattoes</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>P. G Washington</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00680.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="indenture" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>This Indenture made this <date when="1829-09-12">Twelfth day of September in the
                        year of our Lord One thousand eight hundred and twenty nine</date>, between
                        <persName>Philip Halbrook Nicklin</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                        Philadelphia</placeName> in the <placeName>State of Pennsylvania</placeName>
                    of the first part, <persName>Margaret Washington</persName> wife of
                        <persName>Peter G. Washington</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                        Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> of
                    the second part, and the Honorable <persName>John Macpherson Berrien</persName>
                    also now of the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> of the third part:
                    Whereas by deeds of Indenture bearing date on the <date when="1826-07-17">Seventeenth day of July eighteen hundred and twenty Six</date> between
                        <persName>Peter G. Washington</persName> and <persName>Margaret</persName>
                    his wife, <persName>Philip H Nicklin</persName> and <persName>Clement C
                        Biddle</persName>, the lands and tenements which were of the said
                        <persName>Margaret</persName> prior to her intermarriage with
                        <persName>Peter G Washington</persName>, in the <placeName>District of
                        Northern Liberties</placeName> in the <placeName>County of
                        Philadelphia</placeName> and <placeName>State of Pennsylvania</placeName>,
                    were conveyed to <persName>Philip H Nicklin</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                        Philadelphia</placeName> aforesaid, in trust that he would permit the said
                        <persName>Margaret Washington</persName>, notwithstanding her coverture to
                    receive the rents and profits of the said premises to her own use, and that the
                    receipts of the said <persName>Margaret</persName> should be good and
                    sufficient discharges to such person or persons as might be liable to pay the
                    same, and that the said <persName>Philip H Nicklin</persName> would convey the
                    said premises to such persons, and for such uses, and in such manner and form,
                    as the said <persName>Margaret</persName> might direct; as by reference to the
                    said deeds <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00680.004.jpg"/>of record in the
                    said <placeName>County of Philadelphia</placeName> will more fully and at large
                    appear; And whereas, the sum of Three hundred and Sixty two dollars and fifty
                    cents, being part of the proceeds of the said trust estate thus payable to the
                    separate use of the said <persName>Margaret</persName> as aforesaid, has been
                    laid out in the negro slaves hereinafter described; that is to say, one woman
                    named <persName>Lucinda</persName>, about thirty <gap reason="damage"
                        extent="one word" unit="chars"/> years of age and her male child about
                    fourteen months old, one girl named <persName>Ann</persName> about eight years
                    of age, and one girl named <persName>Kitty</persName> about Seven years of age:
                    And whereas the said <persName>Margaret</persName> has expressed a desire that
                    the said property shall be conveyed to the Honorable <persName>John Macpherson
                        Berrien</persName> under the <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#scl">like</unclear>
                         <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#jc">trust</unclear>. Now therefore this Indenture witnesseth that
                    the said <persName>Philip H Nicklin</persName> for and in consideration of the
                    premises and also of the sum of one dollar current money to him in hand paid at
                    or before the ensealing and delivery of these presents, the receipt of which he doth
                    hereby acknowledge and by direction of the said <persName>Margaret
                        Washington</persName>, testified by her becoming a party hereto, hath
                    granted bargained and sold, and by these presents doth grant bargain and sell
                    unto the said <persName>John Macpherson Berrien</persName> his heirs and assigns
                    all and singular the several negroes herein before named and described. To Have
                    and to Hold the said negroes, to wit <persName>Lucinda</persName> and her child,
                        <persName>Ann</persName> and <persName>Kitty</persName> being slaves for
                    life, to him the said <persName>John Macpherson Berrien</persName> his heirs and
                    assigns <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00680.005.jpg"/>to his and their own
                    proper use and behoof forever; In trust, nevertheless, to and for the uses
                    intents and purposes following, to wit: In trust that he the said <persName>John
                        Macpherson Berrien</persName> and his Heirs shall and will from time to time
                    and at all times hereafter, quietly and peaceably permit and suffer the said
                        <persName>Margaret Washington</persName> to have possess and enjoy the
                    several negroes before described, to and for her own free use and service and to
                    and for such other uses and purposes as she the said
                        <persName>Margaret</persName> shall please and think fit at her own free
                    will and pleasure, and upon this further trust and confidence that he the said
                        <persName>John Macpherson Berrien</persName> and his heirs shall and will,
                    convey, order and dispose of the hereby conveyed negroes, to such person or
                    persons, and for such uses and purposes, and in such manner and form as she the
                    said <persName>Margaret Washington</persName>, notwithstanding her coverture and
                    as if she were a feme sole, shall by any act or acts, deed or deeds in writing,
                    or by her last will and testament in writing, or by any writing purporting so to be, order, direct or appoint, and for default
                    of such order, direction or appointment, then to the right heirs of the said
                    Margaret, and upon no other trust, use, intent, or purpose whatever, provided
                    nevertheless and it is expressly agreed by and between the parties aforesaid
                    that the said <persName>John Macpherson Berrien</persName> may at any time
                    hereafter transfer and make over the trust hereby conveyed by a declaration in writing made
                    upon these presents, with the assent of the <pb xml:id="leaf005r"
                        facs="cww.00680.006.jpg"/>said <persName>Margaret Washington</persName>.</p>
                <p>In testimony whereof the parties aforesaid have hereunto set their hands and
                seals the day and year first herein before written</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Philip H Nicklin</persName> seal</signed>
                    <signed><persName>Margt. Washington</persName> seal</signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
                
             <div2 type="section">
                <p>Sealed and delivered in the presence of</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">John W. Berrian</unclear></persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Clement C. Biddle</persName></signed><lb/>
                    witnesses to the signature of <persName>P. H. Nicklin</persName>
                </closer>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Will. <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#nnk">Webb</unclear></persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>P. G. Washington</persName></signed><lb/>
                    witnesses to the signature of <persName>Margaret Washington</persName></closer></div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>Be it known that on this <date when="1829-09-12">Twelfth day of September Anno
                        domini 1829</date>, before me <persName>Clement C. Biddle</persName>,
                    Esquire, Notary Public for the <placeName>Commonwealth of
                        Pennsylvania</placeName>, residing in the <placeName>City of
                        Philadelphia</placeName>, personally appeared <persName>Philip H
                        Nicklin</persName>, of the said <placeName>City of Philadelphia</placeName>,
                    party of the first part, named in the above and foregoing deed of Indenture, and
                    in due form of law, acknowledged the same Indenture to be his voluntary act and
                    deed for the uses and purposes their contained.</p>
                <p>In testimony whereof, I the said Notary Public have hereunto set my hand and seal
                    of office the day and year last above written.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Clement C. Biddle</persName></signed><lb/>
                Notary Public.</closer>
                
            </div1>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>On this <date when="1829-09-17">Seventeenth day of September, Anno domini
                        1829</date> before us two justices of the peace in and for the
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>, personally appeared <persName>Margaret
                        Washington</persName>, wife of <persName>Peter G Washington</persName>,
                    party of the second part named in the above and foregoing deed of Indenture, and
                    acknowledged the said deed or instrument of writing to be her voluntary act and
                    deed for the uses and purposes therein contained according to the true intent
                    and meaning thereof.</p>
                <closer>Taken and acknowledged before us&#8212;<lb/>
                    <signed><persName>P. S. Briscoe</persName> J. P.</signed>
                    <signed><persName>Will. Webb</persName> J. P.</signed></closer>
            </div1>


            <pb sameAs="leaf002r" facs="cww.00680.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>In virtue of the condition reserved in the last clause of this instrument of
                    writing, I hereby authorize and request the <choice><abbr>Hon</abbr><expan>Honorable</expan></choice> <persName>John Mcapherson
                        Berrien</persName> my trustee therein named to transfer and convey the
                    property mentioned and described to <persName>Peter G Washington</persName>, his
                    heirs or assigned and hereby declare my full and free assent to such transfer
                    and conveyance</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Margaret M Washington</persName></signed>
                    <dateline><date when="1839-06-14">June 14&#8212;1839</date></dateline></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb sameAs="leaf003r" facs="cww.00680.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>Georgia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>City of Savannah</placeName></dateline>
                <p>By virtue of the power vested in me by this deed, and conforming to the request
                    of Mrs <persName>Margaret Washington</persName> on the first page thereof inscribed, I
                    do hereby assign and transfer to the within mentioned <persName>Peter G Washington</persName> his heirs and assigns all my right, titles, interest
                    and estate of in and to the within mentioned negro slaves and in testimony
                    thereof have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed my seal this <date when="1839-07-06">sixth day of July one thousand Eight hundred and thirty
                        nine</date></p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Jno. Macpherson Berrien</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Acknowledged before me,</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>James M. Naylor</persName></signed><lb/>
                    <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="7"/> justice<lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Sup</abbr><expan>Supreme</expan></choice> Court <placeName>U. States</placeName></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00680.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>P. G. Washington</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>P. G. Washington</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-16"><seg type="handwritten">16th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by)
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>N Callan</persName> JP seal</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>680</ab>
                <ab><persName>Peter G. Washington</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-16">June 16, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
