<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00569">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of the Sisters of the Visitation of Georgetown
                    D. C., 2 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="crl">Courtney Rebecca Lawton</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00569</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of the Sisters of the Visitation of Georgetown D. C., 2 June
                        1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of the Sisters of the Visitation of Georgetown D. C., 2
                                June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <org role="petitioner">
                    <orgName>The Sisters of the Visitation of Georgetown D.C.</orgName>
                </org>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Mary Angela Harrison</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Reaves</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-22" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-16" who="scl">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-12" who="#jc">performed automated file cleanup</change>
            <change when="2013-05-16" who="#crl">proofed, checked</change>
            <change when="2013-03-25" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00569.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16 of April 1862</date> Entitled "An Act for the release
                    of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName></p>
                <p><orgName>The Sisters of the Visitation of <placeName>Georgetown
                        D.C</placeName></orgName> incorporated by Act of Congress approved <date when="1828-05-24">May 24th A.D. 1828</date>, by this their petition in
                    writing through their Mother Superior respectfully represent that they are
                    persons loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName> who at the time of the
                    passage of the said act of Congress held a claim to service or labor against
                        <persName>Ignatius Tighlman</persName> and <persName>Mary Elizabeth
                        Tighlman</persName> and their seven (7) children namely
                        <persName>Mary</persName>—<persName>Charles</persName>—<persName>Ignatius</persName>—<persName>Jane</persName>—<persName>Cecelia</persName>—<persName>Josephine</persName>
                    &amp; <persName>Rosalie Tighlman</persName> also against <persName>Benjamin
                        Mahoney</persName>—<persName>Thomas Weldon</persName> and
                        <persName>Joseph Dixon</persName> for and during the lives of the said named
                    persons Respectively and that by said Act of Congress the said persons of
                    African descent were discharged and freed of and from all claim of your
                    petitioner to such service or labor: that at the time of said discharge the said
                    persons were respectively of the ages and personal description following</p>

                <list>
                    <item>1st <persName>Ignatius Tighlman</persName>—A dark mulatto man Forty
                        (40) years of age, 5 feet 2 inches high, a smart healthy negro and valued at
                        Twelve hundred (1200) dollars</item>
                    <item>2nd <persName>Mary Elizabeth Tighlman</persName>—the wife of
                            <persName>Ignatius</persName> Forty one years of age, Color Black,
                        height 5 feet <pb xml:id="lef001v" facs="cww.00569.002.jpg"/> a very
                        intelligent stout active woman perfectly healthy and valued at nine hundred
                        (900) dollars</item>
                    <item>3rd <persName>Mary Tighlman</persName> daughter of
                            <persName>Ignatius</persName> and <persName>Mary Elizabeth</persName> a
                        strong healthy mulatto girl 4 feet 8 inches high Seventeen (17) years of age
                        and valued at seven hundred (700) dollars</item>
                    <item>4th <persName>Charles Tighlman</persName> a smart active mulatto boy
                        perfectly healthy 4 feet 6 inches high Fifteen (15) years of age and valued
                        at six hundred dollars</item>
                    <item>5th <persName>Ignatius Tighlman Jr</persName> a healthy active mulatto Boy
                        4 feet 5 inches high Thirteen years of age valued at four hundred and fifty
                        (450) dollars. He is now with the Federal Army at
                            <placeName>Yorktown</placeName></item>
                    <item>6th <persName>Jane Tighlman</persName> a healthy mulatto girl Ten years of
                        age about Four feet high valued at Three hundred dollars</item>
                    <item>7th <persName>Cecelia Tighlman</persName> a healthy mulatto girl three
                        feet high Four years of age valued at about Two hundred dollars</item>
                    <item>8th <persName>Josephine Tighlman</persName> a healthy mulatto girl Two
                        years of age and valued at about one hundred dollars</item>
                    <item>9th <persName>Rosalie Tighlman</persName> mulatto child 6 <choice>
                            <abbr>mo</abbr>
                            <expan>months</expan>
                        </choice> old value 50 <choice>
                            <abbr>dolls</abbr>
                            <expan>dollars</expan>
                        </choice></item>
                    <item>10th <persName>Benjamin Mahoney</persName> a very valuable bright mu<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00569.003.jpg"/>latto man about Five feet
                        six inches high Twenty five years of age strong and healthy has a knowledge
                        of carpenters work and is of superior moral character. He is of the highest
                        value; Eighteen hundred dollars would be a low Estimate of his value to our
                        Institution</item>
                    <item>11th <persName>Thomas Weldon</persName> a hard working negro man about
                        Five feet Four inches high and about Twenty eight years of age strong
                        healthy and understands gardening valued at about Twelve hundred (1200)
                        dollars</item>
                    <item>12th <persName>Joseph Dixon</persName> a <hi rend="underline">black</hi>
                        negro man about Four feet three inches high, Twenty one years of age active
                        and perfectly healthy, is rather sulky and has a bad countenance. He ran
                        away after the battle of <placeName>Manassas</placeName> and is now with the Federal Army He is
                        valued at about 1000 dollars—</item>
                </list>

                <p>That your petitioners acquired their claim to the services or labor of
                        <persName>Ignatius</persName> and <persName>Mary Elizabeth
                        Tighlman</persName>
                    <persName>Benjamin Mahoney</persName> and <persName>Thomas Weldon</persName> by
                    gift from <persName>Notley Young</persName> to his daughter
                        <persName>Martha</persName> as her portion of his Estate in the year <date when="1841">1841</date>. <persName>Martha Young</persName> (Sister
                        <persName>Mary Ellen</persName>) was a member of this institution and gave
                    them to the <orgName>Sisters of the Visitation of <placeName>Georgetown
                            D.C.</placeName></orgName></p>
                <p>The Children of <persName>Ignatius</persName> and <persName>Mary Elizabeth
                        Tighlman</persName> have been born since we acquired title to their
                    parents</p>
                <p><persName>Joseph Dixon</persName> was acquired by gift from <persName>John
                        Neal</persName> to his daughter <persName>Margaret</persName> (Sister
                        <persName>Regina</persName>) about <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00569.004.jpg"/> the year <date when="1842">1842</date> who being
                    a member of this Institution gave them to the <orgName>Sisters of the Visitation
                        of <placeName>Georgetown D.C.</placeName></orgName></p>

                <p>That Your petitioners claim to the service or labor of said persons was at the
                    time of said discharge therefrom of the value hereinbefore stated opposite their
                    respective names—amounting in the aggregate to 8500 dollars—</p>

                <p>That Your petitioners know of no infirmity or defect of said persons except as
                    stated which impair the value of petitioners claim to such service or labor and
                    believe none other exists</p>

                <p>Your petitioners, through their superior, hereby declare that they bear true and
                    faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> and deem it unnecessary to State that they have not born
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion;
                    nor have they given aid or comfort thereto—</p>

                <p>And your Petitioners further state and allege that they have not brought said
                    persons above named into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since
                    the passage of said Act of Congress and that at the time of the passage thereof
                    said persons were held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioners claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioners further state that their said claim to the service or labor of
                    said persons does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made
                    by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion
                    against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00569.005.jpg"/>

                <p>And your petitioners pray the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of their said claim to the service or labor of said persons hereinabove
                    set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName> in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed>Sister <persName>Mary Angela Harrison</persName><lb/> Superior of the
                            <orgName>Sisters of the Visitation of <placeName>Georgetown
                                DC</placeName></orgName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I Sister <persName>Mary Angela Harrison</persName> Mother Superior of the
                            <orgName>Sisters of the Visitation of <placeName>Georgetown
                                D.C.</placeName></orgName> being duly sworn do depose and say that
                        all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the
                        foregoing petition are true in substance and in fact and that all the
                        several other matters and things therein set forth and stated as from the
                        information of others I believe to be true in substance and in fact</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><choice>
                                <abbr>Sr</abbr>
                                <expan>Sister</expan>
                            </choice>
                            <persName>Mary Angela Harrison</persName> Superior of the
                                <orgName>Sisters of the Visitation <placeName>George Town
                                    DC</placeName></orgName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-23">23d day of May
                            AD 1862</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Henry Reaves</persName> J Peace</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00569.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>569</ab>
                <ab><orgName>Sisters of the Visitation<lb/> Georgetown DC</orgName></ab>
                <ab><persName>Thos. B. King</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Atty</abbr>
                        <expan>Attorney</expan>
                    </choice></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00569.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the Commissioners under the act of Congress for the emancipation of colored
                    persons in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></p>
                <p>The petition of <persName>Ignatius Tilghman</persName>.</p>
                <p>He states that on the <date when="1856-07-07">7th July 1856</date>, he and his
                    wife and five children were slaves belonging to the <orgName>Sisters of the
                        Visitation of <placeName>George Town</placeName></orgName>; that the said
                    Sisters then agreed with your petitioner that upon his paying the sum of five
                    hundred dollars he and his wife and children should be free; which is shown by
                    the agreement and several receipts, signed by said Sisters, and contained in the
                    book he now files herewith. He shows further that he has paid to said sisters on
                    account of said contract divers sums amounting in the whole to $298:76, which
                    also appears from said book and their entries therein. That one of his children,
                        namely,<persName>John</persName>, died after the agreement. He admits that
                    $201:25 of the 500$ remain due to said sisters, which he thinks it right they
                    should receive, with interest, but no more; and he submits that what he has
                    paid—not for the purchase of himself—but for his wife and children,
                    should be paid to him.</p>
                <p>After the said contract he maintained himself and family without expense to said
                    sisters, and made them the payments above out of his earnings.</p>
                <p>That three of his children, now claimed for by said Sisters, have been born since
                    the date of said agreement—namely—<persName>Cecelia</persName>,
                        <persName>Rosalie</persName> and <persName>Josephine</persName>. He thinks
                    no allowance should be made for them to said sisters. If to any one, he thinks
                    it should be to himself: but he does not wish to be considered as claiming for
                    them.</p>
                <p>The aggregate value of himself, his wife, and four children living at the date of
                    the agreement, is $4600:—viz—for himself $1000—for his wife
                    $800—for <persName>Mary</persName> $1000—<persName>Jane</persName>,
                        $500—<persName>Ignatius</persName> $700. &amp;
                        <persName>Charles</persName> 600$. The latter two are not yet appraised. His
                    payments on account for the whole of these, have been $298.75, which would be
                    about 6 ½ per cent. The proportion for himself would be $65. which being
                    deducted from the amount of his payments would leave $233.75 <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00569.008.jpg"/> paid by him on account of his
                    wife and children.</p>
                <p>He perceives no other way of coming at what is just, and he submits that this
                    mode is so—that the said Sisters should receive the $201:25, and your
                    petitioner the 233:75 for his wife and children.</p>
                <p>He prays that such order may be taken in the premises.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>W. Redin</persName><lb/> for <choice>
                            <abbr>Petr</abbr>
                            <expan>Petitioner</expan>
                        </choice></signed>
                    <dateline><date when="1862-08-14">14. Aug. 1862</date>.</dateline></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00569.013.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>569.</ab>
                <ab>Petition of <persName>Ignatius Tiglman</persName> to be filed as Counter in
                    above case.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-08-15">15 August 1862.</date></ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00569.010.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p><orgName>The Sisters of the Visitation</orgName> respectfully submit in answer to
                    the Petition of <persName>Ignatius Tighlman</persName> that said
                        <persName>Ignatius</persName> his wife and five children were at the time of
                    the passage of the Emancipation Act held to service or labor in its full and
                    most complete sense; and in law, liable to all the incidents of Sale and
                    transfer at the option of their Owners.</p>
                <p>From this service with all its incidents they were discharged, not by any act of
                    their Owners, but by law approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>
                    providing compensation for their value. There is nothing in its terms altering
                    the incidents of servitude as existing prior thereto. Your Respondents submit
                    that as the law has intervened between them and their servants and prescribed
                    its own terms for their Emancipation it should not appropriate to itself their
                    act of Charity and benevolence or at least their intention, by making a humane
                    permission granted to their servants to purchase themselves, which has not been
                    fulfilled, an excuse for depreciating their value. It would be an act of
                    injustice to give full compensation to those owners who were disposed to
                    exercise their full right towards their servants and to deny it to those
                    inclined to be more humane and to lighten the burden of servitude. It would be
                    giving a premium to the strict and severe master at the expense of the more
                    lenient Such would be in conflict with the spirit of the Act and with the
                    principles of its framers.</p>
                <p>It would be an Act of justice to the Sisters as they were Emancipated by the law
                    that their value should be estimated by the law as it existed at the time of the
                    passage of this Act. That law did not regard their value as lessened by any
                    promise of future Emancipation. In fact there could be no Emancipation but by
                    deed according to the provisions of the <placeName>Maryland</placeName> Act
                        <date when="1796">1796</date> ch 67 and by last will and Testament; and no
                    executory Contract between Master and Slave is of force either at Law or in
                        Equity—<persName>Jos Brown</persName> vs <persName>Wingard</persName>
                    2nd <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">Cranch</unclear> p500. 412.634</p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="cww.00569.011.jpg"/>
                <p>There is a difference between a contract and a benevolence In this instance the
                    privilege given <persName>Ignatius</persName> to purchase himself and his
                    children was a mere benevolence for there could be no consideration as all the
                    money he and his family earned belonged to the <orgName>Sisters of the
                        Visitation</orgName>. It was more by a permission of the Sisters which might
                    be withdrawn according to circumstances; for instance if it was injurious to
                    creditors or if the servants showed an incapacity to provide for themselves or
                    upon the commission of any offence or in case of sickness—And the sum
                    exacted was only required to insure the Sisters from loss provided they should
                    fall back in sickness or distress on them for support as it was too small for a
                    consideration or price for <persName>Ignatius</persName> his wife and
                    children.</p>
                <p>But <persName>Ignatius</persName> cannot claim any benefit from what he terms the
                    agreement for the purchase of himself and Family—He could not do so prior
                    to the Act and there is nothing in the Act enabling him to do so. Neither has he
                    done more than make a very lame effort to fulfil his portion of the "agreement".
                    In six years he has only paid $298.75/100 a large portion of which was in work
                    for the Sisters themselves. This would not amount to more than $4 per month for
                    himself wife and children for whom if hired by the Sisters prices might be
                    obtained ranging from 12 to 3 dollars per month for at least 4 of these servants
                    and therefore by every just and candid mind it must be conceded that
                        <persName>Ignatius</persName> only paid them their own money and but very
                    little of that</p>
                <p>Under such circumstances Your Respondents submit that their claim is under the
                    Act full an complete and that its value should not rightfully be depreciated by
                    a benevolence or permission granted their Servants not recognized either at law
                    or in Equity and which many circumstances would justify them in withdrawing.
                    They urge that <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00569.012.jpg"/> as
                        <persName>Ignatius</persName> could pay them no money which was not already
                    in law their own that they may be allowed their full and just compensation
                    without any regard to the "agreement" and leave to their own benevolence which
                    had already manumitted many of their servants to make such provision for
                        <persName>Ignatius</persName> and his family out of the proceeds as their
                    liberality may dictate</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Thos B King</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>Answer of the <orgName>Sisters of the Visitation</orgName> to the Petition of
                        <persName>Ignatius Tighlman</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-12-12">Dec 12, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
