<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00169">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of James W. West and Eliza Martha West, 13 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
            <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00169</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of James W. West and Eliza Martha West, 13 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of James W. West and Eliza Martha West, 13 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>James W. West</persName>
            </person>
             <person role="petitioner">
                 <persName>Eliza Martha West</persName>
             </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Charles Walter</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
          <change when="2013-08-13" who="#jc">revised coding for handwritten signature blocks</change>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-12-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2012-12-03" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
         <change when="2012-11-08" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="petition">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00169.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                    <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                    <p>Your Petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James W.</persName> &amp; <persName>Eliza M.
                                West</persName>
                  </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the City of
                                <placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName>
                  </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> petition in writing,
                            represent<del>s</del> and state<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg>
                  <del>is a</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">are</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                        loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the
                        passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor
                        against <seg type="handwritten">Ten female and one male</seg>
                            person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Julia
                                Burgess</persName>, <persName>Jane Walker</persName>, alias
                                <persName>Burgess</persName> (daughter of
                                <persName>Julia</persName>) <persName>Susan Burgess</persName> (daughter of <persName>Julia</persName>) <persName>Sarah
                                Burgess</persName> (daughter of <persName>Julia</persName>)
                                <persName>Margaret Burgess</persName> (daughter of
                                <persName>Julia</persName>)
                            <persName>George Burgess</persName> (son of <persName>Julia</persName>)
                                <persName>Josephina Walker</persName> (daughter of <persName>Jane
                                Walker</persName> alias <persName>Burgess</persName>)
                            <persName>Tempe Burgess</persName> (daughter of <persName>Susan
                                Burgess</persName>.) <persName>Mille Burgess</persName> (daughter of
                                <persName>Susan Burgess</persName>.) <persName>Alec
                                Burgess</persName> (daughter of <persName>Sarah
                                Burgess</persName>) and <persName>Cynthia Burgess</persName> (daughter of <persName>Sarah Burgess</persName>.)</seg> for and during
                        the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act
                        of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> discharged and freed of and
                        from all claim of your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> to such
                        service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">Julia Burgess</seg> w<seg type="handwritten">as</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">48 years or
                            thereabouts</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so
                            as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe
                            each one separately.</note>
               
                  <seg type="handwritten">A Bright Mulatto Woman, well proportioned of
                            medium size, erect in her carriage, tolerable stout and strong. She has
                            a peculiar expression of countenance arising from the fact that one of
                            her legs is thicker than the other and one of her eyes is apparently
                            larger than the other: Said <persName>Jane Walker</persName> alias
                                <persName>Burgess</persName> was of the age of twenty four
                            (24.) years, or thereabout, has a dark brown Complexion—tall and
                            stout—quite erect in her Carriage—likely and intelligent:
                            Said <persName>Susan Burgess</persName>, was of the age of 22 years, or
                            thereabouts, a dark mulatto woman—medium size—Stoops a
                            little in walking tolerably tall but not very stout likely
                            and intelligent <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="nnk"><choice><abbr>sd</abbr><expan>said</expan></choice></unclear> <persName>Sarah Burgess</persName>, was of the age of 19 or thereabouts,
                            a Mulatto woman–Small in Stature, erect in her Carriage, she has a
                            peculiar expression of Countenance from the fact that one of her eyes is
                            apparently larger than the other, likely, and intelligent: Said
                                <persName>Margaret Burgess</persName> was of the age of 17 years or
                            thereabouts—has a black complexion tall and Stout, erect in
                            her Carriage; likely and intelligent: Said <persName>George
                                Burgess</persName> was of the age of 15 years, or
                            thereabouts.—a Mulatto boy–of medium
                            height—note very stout—erect in his
                            carriage—likely and intelligent: <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="nnk"><choice><abbr>sd</abbr><expan>said</expan></choice></unclear>
                            <persName>Josephine Walker</persName> was of the age of Two (2) years or
                            thereabouts—of a light brown Complexion—note very
                            stout—likely Said <persName>Tempe Burgess</persName>, was of the
                            age of Four (4) years, or thereabouts: of a Black
                            Complexion—rather small in stature: eyes weak—likely and
                            intelligent. Said <persName>Mille Burgess</persName> was of the age of 2
                            years—or thereabouts, a bright Mulatto child—well
                            proportioned, rather stout for her age, likely and intelligent for her
                            age. Said <persName>Alice Burgess</persName>, was of the age of 4 years,
                            or thereabouts, a bright mulatto—likely and intelligent for her
                            age. —well proportioned. Said <persName>Cynthia
                            Burgess</persName>, was of the age of 2 years or thereabouts, a bright
                            Mulatto child—likely and smart for her age, well
                            proportioned.</seg></p>
                    <p><seg type="handwritten">Your Petitioners further represent that they have
                            filed their statement or schedule, of Said persons in the Clerks Office
                            of the Circuit Court of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                            as required by said Act of Congress</seg></p>

                    <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00169.003.jpg"/>

                    <p>That your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> acquired <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons (described)</seg> in manner
                            following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state
                            how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                            consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                            exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                            found.</note>
                        <seg type="handwritten">that is to say, under and by virtue of the Last will
                            and Testament of <persName>Wm Mills</persName>
                            who died in <placeName>Fairfax County, Virginia</placeName>, in the year
                                <date when="1827">1827</date>, or about, leaving <persName>Mills</persName> (his widow) and <persName>Eliza M.
                                West</persName> (your Petitioner, who has since intermarried with
                                <persName>James W West</persName>, your Petitioner.) and
                                <persName>John Mills</persName> and <persName>Nancy
                            Mills</persName>—his children and Devisees and Legatees: that the
                            interest of the said <space/>
                            <persName>Mills</persName>, (the Mother of your Petitioner
                                (<persName>Eliza M West</persName>) now advanced in years &amp;
                            being a life interest) was regularly and properly transferred and conveyed
                            to your Petitioner. <persName>Eliza</persName>, in consideration of love
                            and affection—and that the interest of the said
                                <persName>John</persName> and <persName>Nancy Mills</persName> was
                            given to your Petitioner <persName>Eliza</persName>—that your
                            Petitioners have endeavoured to procure a Copy of Said Will—as an
                            Exhibit to this their Petition from the <placeName>Fairfax
                                County</placeName> Court—but have failed in their effort to
                            this end.—and they are apprehensive that the original Will (owing
                            to the Rebellion) has been destroyed, the transfer from:—
                                <persName>Mills</persName> in favor of said <persName>Eliza M.
                                West</persName>, your Petitioner, is hereto appended.</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>That your petitioner<del>'</del>s claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons above described</seg> was, at the time of
                        said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$5900</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value
                            of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may
                            enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral,
                            mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the
                            value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude
                            such statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other
                            infirmities or defects of said person which impair the value of
                            petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes none
                            other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                            then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with
                            an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                            defect.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">To wit <persName>Julia
                                Burgess</persName> $300. <persName>Jane Walker</persName> alias
                                <persName>Burgess</persName>. $1000 <persName>Susan
                                Burgess</persName> $1000. <persName>Sarah Burgess</persName> $1100
                                <persName>Margaret Burgess.</persName> $1000 <persName>George
                                Burgess</persName> $1000. <persName>Josephine Walker</persName>
                            $100.&amp; <persName>Tempe Burgess</persName> $150. <persName>Mille
                                Burgess</persName> $100. <persName>Alice Burgess</persName> $150.
                                <persName>Cynthia Burgess</persName> $100: that they are all sound
                            and healthy according to the best of your Petitioners knowledge and
                            belief; that the said <persName>Julia</persName>,
                                <persName>Jane</persName>, <persName>Susan</persName>,
                                <persName>Sarah</persName> &amp; <persName>Margaret</persName> are
                            very useful and capable of doing any thing in the way of house work;
                            that the said <persName>George</persName> is very active and smart and
                            useful as a farm hand and in other branches of business,—that they
                            are all honest and well disposed, and your Petitioners aver that they
                            have no knowledge of any moral, mental, or bodily infirmity in any of
                            said persons, in the least calculated to affect or impair your Petitioner's
                            Claim.</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> hereby declare<del>s</del>
                        that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> bear<del>s</del> true and faithful
                        allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                        and that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not borne arms against the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName> in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or
                        comfort thereto.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del>
                        and allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> ha<seg type="handwritten">ve</seg> not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and
                        that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> w<del>as</del>
                  <seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to
                        service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to
                        such service or labor.</p>

                    <p>Your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> further state<del>s</del> and
                            allege<del>s</del>, that <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim
                        to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg>
                            do<del>es</del> not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore
                        made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present
                        rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> pray<del>s</del> the said
                        Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> said claim to the service or labor of
                        said <seg type="handwritten">persons,</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                        the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                        said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of
                        the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                        said act of Congress. </p>

                    <closer> (Signed by)
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>James W West</persName></seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Eliza Martha West</persName></seg></signed>                        
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab><persName>A Lloyd</persName> Counsel for Petitioner.</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00169.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In the name of God amen. I <persName>William Mills</persName> of the
                            <placeName>County of Fairfax</placeName> and State of <placeName>
                            Virginia</placeName> do make and ordain this my last will and testament
                        in the form following. To wit, I give and bequeath unto my beloved wife
                            <persName>Martha Ann</persName>, my negro woman
                            <persName>Julia</persName> together with all the residue of my
                        estate: The debt due me from <persName>John Mills</persName> my brother and
                        all other debts now due me, or which may be due me at the time of my death,
                        to have and to enjoy the use thereof during her life, and after her death I
                        will that the whole thereof be equally divided amongst the two children my
                        wife now has <persName>John</persName> and <persName>Mary</persName> and the
                        one she may have as she probably is now pregnant, but should the child which
                        she may have die before it arrives at age then I devise the part hereby
                        devised to it, be equally divided between the two before named children. And
                        I do constitute and appoint my wife <persName>Martha Ann</persName> the sole
                        executrix of this my last will and testament. In witness whereof I have
                        hereunto set my hand this <date when="1827-08-23">23d day of August in the
                            year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty seven</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>his X mark <persName>William Mills</persName></signed>
                        <lb/>Signed and acknowledged in the presence of<lb/>
                        <signed><persName>Jno Dulin</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>H. O. Lindsay</persName></signed>
                        <signed>his X mark <persName>Thos. Simons</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>John Vallandingham</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00169.006.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>At a Court held for <placeName>Fairfax County</placeName> the <date when="1828-07-21">21st day of July 1828</date></p>
                    <p>This last will and Testament of <persName>William Mills</persName> deceased
                        was presented in Court by <persName>Martha Ann Mills</persName> the
                        Executrix therein named and the same being proved by the oaths of
                            <persName>Jno Dulin</persName> and <persName>John
                            Vallandingham</persName> two of the subscribing witnesses thereto is
                        admitted to record</p>
                    <closer>Test
                        <signed><persName>Wm Moss</persName>C C</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I certify this to be a true copy of the will of <persName>Wm Mills</persName>
                        as appears upon the records of <placeName>Fairfax County</placeName> Court,
                        Liber P Folio 149 of wills</p>
                  <closer>
                      <dateline><date when="1862-07-31">July 31st 1862</date></dateline>
                      <signed><persName>H Hawxhurst</persName> <placeName>D. C.</placeName></signed>
                  </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab><persName>Wm Mills</persName> 169<lb/>
                        Will<lb/>
                        a<lb/>
                        copy</ab>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>County Seal is not found<lb/>
                  <persName>J.H.</persName>
               </ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00169.007.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                  <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
            </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><seg type="handwritten">We</seg>, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James W West</persName> and <persName>Eliza M.
                                West</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say,
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition, as of <seg type="handwritten">our</seg>
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, <seg type="handwritten">We</seg> believe
                        to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by)
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>James W West</persName></seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Eliza Martha West</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-12">
                     <seg type="handwritten">12th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by)
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Chas. Walter</persName> JP</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>169<lb/>
                    Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>James W West</persName><lb/>
                    &amp; <persName>Eliza M West</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date><lb/>
                    by<lb/>
                    <persName>Asbury Lloyd</persName> <choice><abbr>Esq</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
