<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00657">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of James E. Morgan, 11 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00657</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of James E. Morgan, 11 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-11">June 11, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of James E. Morgan, 11 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-11">June 11, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>James E. Morgan</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Daniel Rowland</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-28" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-05-06" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00657.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>James E Morgan</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">the following three</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Columbus Warren</persName>, <persName>John Warren</persName>,
                            <persName>Louisa Warren</persName>,</seg> for and during the life of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> and that by said act of
                    Congress said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of
                    your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> of the age <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Columbus Warren</persName> Mulatto aged 13 or
                        14 years He is likely, sprightly, and intelligent. <persName>Louisa
                            Warren</persName>, Mulatto, aged 42 or 43 years She is tall and
                        rather athletic <persName>John Warren</persName> Mulatto aged 6 or 7
                        years He is thick Set and rather dark.</seg></p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00657.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg>
                    in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state
                        how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">I bought all three of them from <persName>N.
                        Callan</persName> and <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName>Somerville Nicholson</persName> U. S. N. Administrators on the property of <persName>A A Nicholson</persName> deceased.</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">nineteen hundred</seg>
                    dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state
                        such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to
                        the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">as follows—</seg>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Louisa Warren</persName> is an excellent Cook Washer and ironer she is perfectly sound in body but is subject at time to depression of spirits, this as a Physician I considered as not of the least importance and <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">inherent</unclear> to nearly all females. Her honest value was $600.</item>
                        <item><persName>Columbus Warren</persName> is perfectly healthy and robust He drove my carriage, was my house Waiter and at times attended to my <choice><sic>carraiges</sic><corr>carriages</corr></choice> and horses. I brought him up to my liking and he therefore to me was invaluable. He was worth to any one eight hundred dollars to me much more—</item>
                        <item><persName>John Warren</persName> is a likely intelligent boy would in a year or two been very useful. Had he been for sale five hundred dollars would not have bought him—</item>
                    </list></p>

                <pb sameAs="#leaf001v" facs="cww.00657.003.jpg"/>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg>
                    into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said
                    act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> was held to service or labor therein
                    under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of
                    any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or
                    sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">three persons</seg> herein above set forth; and
                    if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>James E. Morgan</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00657.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>James E Morgan</persName> of
                                <placeName>Washington City</placeName></seg> being duly sworn, do
                        depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in
                        substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things
                        therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe
                        to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Jame E Morgan</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-06"><seg type="handwritten">6</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg>
                            A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>D. Rowland</persName> J. P.</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>657</ab>
                <ab>Dr. <persName>James E. Morgan</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-11">June 11, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>James Adams</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Jno. Carroll Brent</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Jas. E. Morgan</persName> for <persName>T. E. Lloyd</persName> <choice><abbr>Atty.</abbr><expan>Attorney</expan></choice></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
