<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00606">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Edward Craycroft, 2 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00606</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Edward Craycroft, 2 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Edward Craycroft, 2 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Edward Craycroft</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-23" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-19" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-06-13" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-05-28" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00606.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">resident</seg> of <seg type="handwriiten">
                        <placeName>Montgomery Co. Md</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of
                    Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> person of African descent of the
                    name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> for and
                    during the <del>life of said</del> <seg type="handwritten">period until the said
                            <persName>John Clark</persName> shall arrive at the age of 25
                        years</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and
                    from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of
                    said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">ten years</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">a bright mulatto Boy</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00606.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from
                        whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written
                        evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where
                        the same may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">by marriage with <persName>Ann A. Hollin</persName> who
                        received the same by will from <persName>Mrs. Ray</persName> of
                            <placeName>Montgomery County Maryland</placeName> which said will is of
                        Record in <placeName>Rockville</placeName>
                        <placeName>Montgomery County Maryland</placeName></seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> was, at the time of
                    said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">four hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">That said <persName>John
                            Clark</persName> is sound in every respect and free from any moral,
                        mental or bodily infirmity or defect, and a likely and promising Boy</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John
                            Clark</persName></seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by
                    virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> does not originate
                    in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any
                    manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>John Clark</persName></seg> herein
                    above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to
                    the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Edward Craycroft</persName></seg></signed></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00606.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>606</ab>
                <ab><persName>Ed Craycroft</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00606.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>In the name of God Amen. I <persName>Amelia Holland</persName> of
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                        Maryland</placeName>, being weak of body but of sound and disposing mind
                    memory and understanding, do make and publish this my last will and Testament in
                    manner and form following. That is to say first and principally I commit my soul
                    to Almighty God and my body to the earth to be decently buried at the discretion
                    of my Executor's herein after named, and after my funeral charges and just debts
                    are paid I give devise and bequeath as follows<lb/>
                    To wit<list>
                        <item>Item I give and bequeath to my son <persName>Isaac Holland</persName>
                            one cent, and no more of estate either real personal or mixed. to him the
                            said <persName>Isaac</persName> his Heirs and assigns forever.</item>
                        <item>Item I give and bequeath to my Grandson <persName>Steven
                                Holland</persName> son of <persName>Isaac Holland</persName> the sum
                            of fifty Dollars to be paid the said <persName>Steven</persName> out of
                            the money now due and owing to me by the said <persName>Isaac
                                Holland</persName>, to him the said <persName>Steven</persName> his
                            Heirs or assigns forever.</item>
                        <item>Item I give devise and bequeath to my son <persName>John
                                Holland</persName> fifty acres of land lying and being in
                                <placeName>Hampshire County</placeName> in commonwealth of
                                <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, (to be laid out on one side of the
                            Tract so as to exclude the buildings and leave the other part of said
                            Tract in a good form as practicable) to him the said <persName>John
                                Holland</persName> his Heirs or assigns forever.</item>
                        <item>Item I give and bequeath to my daughter, <persName>Rachel
                                Holland</persName> one Feather bed, bedstead and furniture, to her
                            the said <persName>Rachel</persName> her Heirs or assigns
                            forever.</item>
                        <item>Item I give and bequeath to my daughter <persName>Ann Amelia
                                Holland</persName> one Feather bed, bedstead and furniture, to her
                            the said <persName>Ann Amelia</persName> her Heirs or assigns
                            forever.</item>
                        <item>Item I give devise and bequeath to my Daughters <persName>Martha
                                Holland</persName> <persName>Rachel Holland</persName>, <persName>Deborah
                                Holland</persName>, and <persName>Ann Amelia Holland</persName> all
                            the rest and residue of my Estate either real personal or mixed to them the said
                                <persName>Martha</persName>, <persName>Rachel</persName>,
                                <persName>Deborah</persName> and <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00606.005.jpg"/>
                            <persName>Ann Amelia</persName> or the survivor of them, their Heirs or
                            assigns forever. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                    <p>And lastly I do hereby constitute and Appoint my two Daughters <persName>Rachel Holland</persName> and <persName>Ann Amelia Holland</persName> Executrix, of this my last Will and Testament, revoking and annulling all former wills by me Heretofore made.</p>
                    
                <p>In Witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal this <date when="1829-12-26">Twenty Six day of December in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty nine</date>.</p>
                    
                <closer><signed><persName>Amelia Holland</persName> Seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">            
                <p>Signed, sealed, published and declared by <persName>Amelia Holland</persName> the
                    above named Testatrix as and for her last Will and Testament in the presence of
                    us, who at her request in her presence and in the presence of each other have
                    subsisted our names as Witnesses thereto.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>George Cashell</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>George W. Cashell</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>E D W <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">Bliss</unclear></persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00606.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>602</ab>
                <ab>Certified Copy Will</ab>
                <ab><persName>Deborah Ray</persName></ab>
                <ab>Cost $1.11</ab>
                </div2>
                    
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00606.007.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">            
                <p>In the name of God Amen: I <persName>Deborah Ray</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> in the <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>
                    being sick and weak of body but of sound disposing mind memory and understanding
                    do make and publish this instrument of writing as and for my last will and
                    testament in manner and form following that is to Say, I <choice><sic>reqest</sic><corr>request</corr></choice> that my body be decently buried at the discretion of my executor herein after named, and after my funeral charges and just debts are paid then I
                    give devised and bequeath as follows:</p>
                    
                    <p>To my brother <persName>Frederick Gaither</persName>, his heirs and
                            assigns in fee simple, I give devise and bequeath all my right title
                            claim and interest of in and to a tract of land called, "Care not" in
                            <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> and <placeName>State of
                                Maryland</placeName> also all my land in <placeName>Hamshire County Virginia</placeName> by whatsoever name the same
                            may be known or called, and my negro man <persName>Ned</persName>, for
                            and during the term of Six years from &amp; after my decease, and at the
                            expiration of that time I give to my said negro man
                                <persName>Ned</persName> freedom.</p>
                        <p>To my sister <persName>Amelia Holland</persName> and her heirs I give
                            and bequeath my two negro women <persName>Jinny</persName> and
                                <persName>Eliza</persName> to serve my said sister six years from
                            and after my decease and at the expiration of said term I give to my
                            said two negro women <persName>Jinny</persName> and
                                <persName>Eliza</persName> freedom. I also give to my said Sister
                                <persName>Amelia Holland</persName> and her heirs my negro girl
                                <persName>Sally</persName> to serve until she accomplishes her
                            twenty fifth year of age. I then give to my said negro
                                <persName>Sally</persName> freedom: And whereas it may happen that
                            the aforesaid negro woman <persName>Jenny</persName> &amp;
                                <persName>Eliza</persName> &amp; my negro <persName>Sally</persName>
                            may have during this servitude issue or children—It is therefore
                            my will and I therefore give and bequeath my said Sister
                                <persName>Amelia Holland</persName> and her heirs all issue or
                            children which my said negroes <persName>Jenny</persName>,
                                <persName>Eliza</persName>, or <persName>Sally</persName> may have
                            during this time of Servitude, to serve until such issue or children
                            arrive at the age of twenty five years when I give to the said issue or
                            children freedom.</p>
                        <p>To my negroes <persName>Fanny</persName>, <persName>Joshua</persName>
                            and <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">Famer</unclear>,
                            I five freedom at my death.</p>
                        <p>To my negro woman <persName>Fanny</persName> I give and bequeath my
                            negro girl <persName>Anna</persName> to serve until she accomplishes her
                            sixteenth year of age when I give to my negro girl
                                <persName>Anna</persName> freedom.</p>
                        <p>These I will and direct that the rest and residue of my estate of
                            every description <hi rend="underline">by</hi> divided equally share and share alike among my twelve nieces,
                            to wit: <persName>Maria Gaither</persName>, wife of <persName>Samuel R
                                Gaither</persName>, <persName>Rebecca Gaither</persName>,
                                <persName>Martha Griffith</persName> wife <persName>John
                                Griffith</persName>, <persName>Elizabeth Gaither</persName>,
                                <persName>Juliet Gaither</persName>, <persName>Deborah Jane
                                Gaither</persName>, and <persName>Sarah Gaither</persName> daughter
                            of my brother <persName>Frederick Gaither</persName>, <persName>Martha Holland</persName>, <persName>Rachel Holland</persName>,
                                <persName>Ann Holland</persName> and <persName>Deborah
                                Holland</persName>, daughters of my Sister <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00606.008.jpg"/> <persName>Amelia Holland</persName> and <persName>Deborah <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">Warfield</unclear></persName> daughter of sister <persName>Mary
                                Dorsey</persName> to them and each of their heirs and assigns
                            respectfully forever—And lastly I hereby nominate and appoint my
                            brother <persName>Frederick Gaither</persName> executor of this my last
                            will and testament revoking and annulling all former will by me made
                            ratifying and confirming this and none other to be my last will and
                            testament. In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed
                            my seal this <date when="1828-05-21">21st day of May 1828</date>
                        </p>                    
                <closer><signed><persName>Deborah Ray</persName> Seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">            
                <p>Signed Sealed published and declared by the above named testatrix as and for her
                    last will and testament in presence of us who at her request in her presence,
                    and presence of each other have subscribed our names as <hi rend="underline">witness</hi> thereto</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Ephraim Gaither</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Thomas J. Hobbs</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Wm Price</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>H. C. Gaither</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">            
                <dateline rend="bold"><placeName>STATE OF MARYLAND</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                
                    <p>On the <date when="1828-06-10"><seg type="handwritten">10th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> 18<seg type="handwritten">28</seg></date> came <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ephraim Gaither</persName> and <persName>Henry C. Gaither</persName>
                            two</seg> of the subscribing witnesses to the last Will and Testament of
                            <seg type="handwritten">Deborah Ray</seg> late of <placeName>Montgomery
                            county</placeName>, deceased, and <seg type="handwritten">severally</seg> made oath on the Holy Evangely of Almighty God that
                            <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> did see the Testat<seg type="handwritten">rix</seg> herein named, sign and seal this Will, and
                        that <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> hear h<seg type="handwritten">er</seg> publish, pronounce and declare the same to be h<seg type="handwritten">er</seg> last Will and Testament, and at the time of h<seg type="handwritten">er</seg> so doing <seg type="handwritten">s</seg>he was to the best of <seg type="handwritten">their</seg>
                        apprehension of sound and disposing mind, memory and understanding, and that
                            <seg type="handwritten">they</seg> respectively subscribed <seg type="handwritten">their</seg> names to this Will as<seg type="handwritten">—</seg>witnesses, in the
                        present, and at the request of the Testat<seg type="handwritten">rix</seg>,
                        and in the presence of each other; also in the presence of <seg type="handwritten">the other two subscribing witnesses thereto and in
                            the presence of each other</seg>
                        <del>the other subscribing witness <space extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="4"/> hereto, who also subscribed the same in the
                                Testat<space extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="5"/>
                            presence.</del></p>
                    
                    <closer>CERTIFIED BY <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Solomon Holland</persName></seg> <hi rend="italic">Register</hi>.</signed><lb/>
                        <seg type="handwritten">(9 3/10 S)</seg></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>St Md.</placeName> <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>I hereby certify that the aforegoing is a true copy as it stands recorded</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal of office this <date when="1862-08-11">11th day of August 1862</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>John W. Spates</persName> Register Will for <placeName>Montgomery Co Md</placeName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="cww.00606.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Edward Craycroft</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Edward Craycroft</persName></seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-27"><seg type="handwritten">27</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg>
                            A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Thomas C Donn</persName><lb/>
                        Justice of the Peace for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>606</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Edward Craycroft</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-02">June 2, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
