<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00194">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of James Dobbyn, 13 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
               <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
               <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
               <name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
               <name xml:id="sd">Shailana Dunn-Wall</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00194</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0
                     Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/).
                     Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available
                     non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission
                     for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project
                     team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of James Dobbyn, 13 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of James Dobbyn, 13 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-13">May 13, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury,
                        1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                        Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                        (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm
                  copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>James Dobbyn</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Charles Walter</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2013-01-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
         <change when="2013-01-09" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
         <change when="2012-09-24" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
            necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
            encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2012-06-08" who="#el">checked</change>
         <change when="2012-06-07" who="#sd">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00194.001.jpg"/>

         <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
            <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
            <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                  when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of
               certain persons held to service or labor in the District of Columbia."</p>

            <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>James Dobbyn</persName>
               </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <placeName>Washington City</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                     Columbia</placeName>
               </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
               states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States,
               who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service
               or labor against <seg type="handwritten">one</seg> person of African descent of the
               name of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> was discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such
               service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> was of the age of <seg type="handwritten">about fifty seven years </seg> and
               of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot"
                  xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there
                  be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">She is a stout, able bodied woman about five feet four inches
                  in height, black complexion and believed to be a full blooded African</seg>
            </p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00194.002.jpg"/>

            <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
               aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Bailey</persName>
               </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here
                  state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                  consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit
                  thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">Said <persName>Elizabeth</persName> was purchased in <date
                     when="1854-04">April 1854</date> from <persName>Benjamin Taylor</persName>, by
                  me for the sum of two hundred dollars. At the time I purchased said
                     <persName>Elizabeth</persName> she was in ill health, but has since entirely
                  recovered and is now strong and hearty</seg>
            </p>

            <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg
                  type="handwritten">Two hundred and fifty</seg> dollars in money.<note
                  type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be,
                  touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the
                  person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral,
                  mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of
                  the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with
                  an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said
                  person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and
                  that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity
                  or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with
                  an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">The said <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName> was employed by
                  your Petitioner as a cook and general household servant. She is a good cook and
                  washer and ironer. It would cost your Petitioner to employ a person in his house
                  to do the work heretofore done by <persName>Elizabeth</persName>, about seven
                  dollars per month. Your petitioner has no knowledge of any mental, bodily or moral
                  infirmity or defect in said <persName>Elizabeth</persName> as would impair your
                  Petitioner's claim to her service or labor and he believes that none such
                  exist</seg>
            </p>

            <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true and
               faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                  type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in the
               present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

            <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg>
               has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Bayly</persName>
               </seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and
               that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's
               claim to such service or labor.</p>

            <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg>
               said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any
               person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the
               Government of the United States.</p>

            <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
               value of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said
                  <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Elizabeth Baily</persName>
               </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
               appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the
               Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the provisions of
               said act of Congress.</p>

            <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                  <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James Dobbyn</persName>
                  </seg>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div1>

         <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00194.003.jpg"/>

         <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
            <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                  Petition.</hi>]</head>

            <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
            </dateline>

            <div2 type="section">
               <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>James Dobbyn</persName></seg> being duly
                  sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set
                  forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in
                  substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein
                  set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in
                  substance and in fact.</p>
               <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>James Dobbyn</persName>
                     </seg>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div2>

            <div2 type="section">
               <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-12">
                     <seg type="handwritten">12th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A.
                     D. 1862</date>. </p>
               <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Chas Walter</persName> JP seal</seg>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div2>
         </div1>

         <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
            <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been
               imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one
               place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the
               Verification.</note>
            <ab>194</ab>
            <ab>Petition of <persName>James Dobbyn</persName></ab>
            <ab>Filed May 13, 1862<lb/> by<lb/>
               <persName>Wm. <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#el">Y.</unclear>
                  Fendall</persName>
            </ab>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
