<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00893">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Columbus Alexander, 11 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00893</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Columbus Alexander, 11 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Columbus Alexander, 11 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Columbus Alexander</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Charles Walter</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-05-08" who="#jc">added transcription of additional documents that have been filed with petition cww.00892; reorganized transcription</change>
            <change when="2013-03-28" who="#nnk">transcribed evidentiary materials as part of petition cww.00892</change>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">performed automated check for regular transcriptions and encoding errors and mistakes at facs</change>
            <change when="2013-02-12" who="#kk">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-09-18" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00893.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <div2 type="section">
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of
                    April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or
                    labor in the District of Columbia."</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Columbus Alexander</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington, DC</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">fifteen</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Beverly Davis</persName>,—<persName>Nancy Holms</persName> <persName>Thomas Holms</persName>—<persName>Arena Holms</persName>—<persName>Jefferson D. Holms</persName>—<persName>Maria Bowman</persName>—<persName>Josephine Bowman</persName>—<persName>Frank Diggs</persName>—<persName>George Singleton</persName>—<persName>John Wesley</persName> (sometimes called <persName>John Wesley Holms</persName>")—<persName>Wesley Holms</persName>—<persName>Betty Hopp</persName>—<persName>Eliza Jones</persName> <persName>Lucy Jones</persName>—<persName>John Jones</persName> and <persName>Stephen Holms</persName></seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Beverly Davis</persName>—a male person was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">Twenty-five years, or thereabout.</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note> <seg type="handwritten">Black Complexion. Medium Size or about five feet, Eight inches high, likely and intelligent. <persName>Nancy Holms</persName>—a female—was of the age of Twenty five years, or thereabouts—Copper Color,—about five feet high—likely and intelligent. <persName>Thomas Holms</persName>, a male, was of the age of Six years or thereabouts—Copper color about three feet high—likely and intelligent; <persName>Arena Holms</persName>, Female—was of the age of Twenty three years or thereabouts. Copper color—about five feet high—likely and intelligent; <persName>Jefferson D. Holms</persName>—Male—was of the age of one year or thereabout. Copper Color or Mulatto,—about two feet high. likely and intelligent; <persName>Maria Bowman</persName> Female—was of the age of Eighteen years, or thereabout. Black Complexion—about four feet, nine inches high, likely and intelligent; <persName>Josephine Bowman</persName>—Female—was of the age of Two years, or thereabout, Bright Mulatto—about two feet, Seven inches high—likely and intelligent; <persName>Frank Diggs</persName>. Male—was of the age of Twenty one years, or thereabouts. Black Complexion—Medium size; or about five feet, nine (9) inches high—likely and intelligent: <persName>George<pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00893.002.jpg"/> Singleton</persName>. Male—was of the age of Twenty five years, or thereabout. Black Complexion—thick lips—Medium Size—or about five feet, eight inches high likely and intelligent; <persName>John Wesley</persName> (Male) was of the age of Twenty one <choice><abbr>yrs</abbr><expan>years</expan></choice>, or thereabout,—dark Copper Color or inclined to black—marked with the small Pox.—about five feet six inches high—likely and intelligent: <persName>Betty Hopp</persName> (Female.) Black Complexion—was of the age of Seventy years, or thereabouts—of low Stature—Complains of defective eye-sight. <persName>Eliza Jones</persName>: (Female.) was of the age of Thirty five years, or thereabout, of a Black complexion—low Stature—about four feet, nine inches high—likely and intelligent: <persName>Lucy Jones</persName>. was of the age of Six years, or thereabouts, of a black complexion—likely and intelligent: <persName>John Jones</persName>. was of the age of one year, or thereabouts, of a dark Copper Color—well formed for its size, and age, intelligent: <persName>Stephen Holms</persName>. (child of <persName>Nancy Holms</persName>) was of the age of one year or thereabout; a bright mulatto, well formed for his age.</seg></p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00893.003.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">fifteen Persons</seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Beverly</persName>—sometimes called "<persName>Beverly Davis</persName>"—herein before mentioned—was purchased on the <date when="1858-07-29">29th day of July 1858</date> from <persName>Lewis Warrington</persName>—the consideration paid for him was $800 as by reference the Receipt for the purchase money herewith filed "Marked A" will appear. <persName>Nancy Holms</persName> and <persName>Thomas Holms</persName>—her child—were purchased of <persName>Philip Mackey</persName>, the consideration paid for them including child <persName>Maria-Louise</persName> deceased,—was $1200. as by reference to the Land &amp; Chattel records of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>—in Liber J. A. S. No. 17 &amp; <choice><abbr>fols</abbr><expan>folios</expan></choice> 174 — 175. for bill of Sale—the Same</seg><pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00893.004.jpg"/>
                        
                        <note type="authorial"><seg type="handwritten">(A.A.)</seg></note> <seg type="handwritten">bearing date <date when="1859-06-06">June 6th 1859</date>. will fully appear. <persName>Arena Holms</persName> was purchased of <persName>John Waters</persName> on the <date when="1857-09-12">12th day of September A.D. 1857</date> the Consideration paid for her was $189 41/100—and to perfect the Title, a Bill of Sale was also executed and delivered to this Petitioner by <persName>Philip Mackey</persName>—the said last mentioned Bill of Sale bearing date the <date when="1857-09-14">14th day of Septr 1857</date>. the consideration expressed in the last Bill of Sale is $926. and your Petitioner refers to the said Bills of Sale—duly recorded in Liber J. A. S. No. 141 folios 420 &amp; 455 one of the Land &amp; Chattel Records of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> &amp; it will more fully and at large appear. <persName>Jefferson D Holms</persName>—child of <persName>Arena Holms</persName>—passes under the Bills of Sale above mentioned. <persName>Maria Bowman</persName> was purchased of Dr. <persName>Johnson Elliot</persName> the <date when="1855-02-14">14th day of February 1855</date>.—the consideration paid for her was $300.—and your Petitioner files herewith the Bill of Sale for said <persName>Maria</persName> marked the same being duly recorded in Liber J.A.S. No. 94 folio 4. one of the Land and Chattel records of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>. <persName>Josephine Bowman</persName>—child of said <persName>Maria Bowman</persName> transferred and vested in your Petitioner by widow of the above mentioned Bill of Sale transferring the mother. <persName>Frank Diggs</persName> was purchased by your Petitioner, on the <date when="1852-04-09">9th day of April 1852</date> from <persName>Wm J Duvall</persName>—the consideration paid for him was $500. And your Petitioner files herewith the Bill of Sale and Receipt for said <persName>Diggs</persName>—and said Consideration and prays that the same may be read and considered as a part of this Petition marked No. 7 <persName>George Singleton</persName>, was purchased by your Petitioner on the <date when="1836-02-23">23rd day of Feby. 1836</date>, from the late Major <persName>Wm B Scott</persName>. &amp; <persName>Ann</persName> his wife—the consideration paid for him was $600. And Your Petitioner herewith files Bill of sale <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00893.005.jpg"/> for said <persName>George</persName> duly executed &amp;c. Marked No. 8 and prays that the same may be <choice><abbr>recd</abbr><expan>recorded</expan></choice>. and considered as a part of this Petition. <persName>John Wesley</persName> (sometimes called <persName>John Welesy Holms</persName>—and <persName>Wesley Holms</persName>.) was purchased by your Petitioner on the <date when="1858-04-08">8th day of April 1858</date>. the consideration paid for him was $825—And your—Petitioner begs leave to refer to the Land &amp; Chattel record of the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> Liber J A.S. No 152 folios 364–365–366—Being a Bill of sale from <persName>Jacob F King</persName> Constable and <persName>Philip Mackey</persName>, bearing date <date when="1858-04-10">April 10th 1858</date>. <persName>Betty Hopp</persName>, was purchased by Petitioner from <persName>Wm H. Grinnell</persName> <date when="1844-03-01">March 1st 1844</date>.—the consideration paid for her was $80.—and your Petitioner files herewith Bill of sale and receipt marked Exhibit No. 10 and prays &amp;c. <persName>Eliza Jones</persName>, was purchased from the Estate of a deceased Relation by Petitioner—and has been in his possession some 12 or 15 years.—the consideration paid for her was $600—<persName>Lucy Jones</persName> &amp; <persName>John Jones</persName>—children of <persName>Eliza Jones</persName> (above mentioned.) born while in the possession of your Petitioner and raised by him—an passing under the purchase of the mother as aforesaid. <persName>Stephen Holms</persName> the son of <persName>Nancy Holms</persName> passes to your Petitioner under and by virtue of the instrument above referred to transferring the said mother—and by virtue of the Law applicable.—</seg></p>
                        
                <pb sameAs="leaf001v" facs="cww.00893.003.jpg"/>
                
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$13,850</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">as follows: <persName>Beverly Davis</persName>, is a most excellent and handy servant. Your Petitioner has never seen his equal at any thing he has employed him to do—He is an elegant dining room servant—a good Carriage driver—Hostler—ploughman &amp; mower—he can cook scour &amp; scrub—is a faithful and trustworthy man—and is highly prized by your Petitioner. as being one of the best Servants he has ever met with—Your Petitioner under the circumstances finds it difficult to name a price on one so useful and valuable. not less that $2000. a nominal price. (See B. B <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc"><choice><abbr>annexd</abbr><expan>annexed</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>contin</abbr><expan>continuation</expan></choice></unclear></seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> w<seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress. <seg type="handwritten">But your Petitioner declares that nothing herein contained may operate to exclude or defer him from</seg> <del>(Signed by)</del> <seg type="handwritten">applying to Congress, at any future day for such further compensation or claim as under all the circumstances, he may conceive himself entitled to.</seg></p>
                
                <closer>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>C. Alexander</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00893.008.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <note type="authorial">
                        <ab>B.B.</ab>
                    </note>
                    <list>
                        <item><persName>Nancy Holms</persName>, is a good cook and washes and irons
                            well, and can command good wages at any time. Valued at $1200.</item>
                        <item><persName>Thomas Holms</persName>—Son of said
                            <persName>Nancy</persName>, is a smart active boy. Valued at
                            $600.</item>
                        <item><persName>Stephen Holms</persName>, Son of said
                            <persName>Nancy</persName>, is a bright healthy child—valued
                            at $300.</item>
                        <item><persName>Arena Holms</persName>, is a very useful woman, can cook
                            wash and iron well. valued at $1200.</item>
                        <item><persName>Jefferson D Holms</persName>—Son of said
                            <persName>Arena Holms</persName>—is a bright; healthy child,
                            valued at $300.</item>
                        <item><persName>John Wesley</persName>, sometimes called "<persName>John
                            Wesley Holms</persName>" &amp; "<persName>Wesley
                                Holms</persName>", is a hardworking, industrious, man, he has been
                            accustomed to driving a cart. Valued at $1200.</item>
                        <item><persName>Maria Bowman</persName>—is an excellent house
                            keeper—She is a good Cook and washer &amp; irons well.—She is
                            active and useful generally valued at $1200.</item>
                        <item><persName>Josephine Bowman</persName>—daughter of
                            <persName>Maria Bowman</persName>—is a sprightly healthy
                            child—valued at $350.</item><pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00893.009.jpg"/>
                        <item><persName>Frank Diggs</persName>—is a good Engineer, having been
                            accustomed to run a Steam Engine in the Printing establishment of your
                            Petitioner for Several years—He is also a good field
                            hand—can plough mow—Cradle &amp;c.—is a good wagoner
                            &amp; Hostler—cook well—valued at $1800.</item>
                        <item><persName>George Singleton—is an excellent field hand—Can
                            plough mow, Cradle—is a good Hostler and Wagoner—Can
                            also Cook—valued at $1500.</persName></item>
                        <item><persName>Betty Hopp</persName>—is not very
                            valuable—rather old, and complains of want of sight—or
                            defective vision—though she could be made useful, in taking care
                            of young children. Valued at $100.</item>
                        <item><persName>Eliza Jones</persName>, is a valuable House help—is an
                            excellent Cook, washer &amp; irons well, and in the Judgment of your
                            Petitioner is a Superior hand at any thing connected with house-keeping.
                            Valued at $1200.</item>
                        <item><persName>Lucy Jones</persName>—daughter of <persName>Eliza
                            Jones</persName> is a sprightly, healthy, active child<pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00893.010.jpg"/> valued at $600.</item>
                        <item><persName>John Jones</persName>—Son of <persName>Eliza
                            Jones</persName>—is a sprightly, healthy child, valued at
                            $300.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>All of the said persons (excepting the old woman <persName>Betty Hopp</persName>
                        who is suffering with the infirmities of age.) are of good general health and
                        morals—according to the best of your Petitioners knowledge and belief.</p>
                    <p>And your Petitioner knows of no moral, mental, or bodily infirmities, or defects
                        of any kind in any of said persons, except as herein before stated concerning
                        the old woman <persName>Betty Hopp</persName>—and he believes none other to exist.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00893.013.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>No A</ab>
                    <ab><persName>Lewis Warrington</persName>s Bill of Sale of <persName>Beverly</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="cww.00893.014.jpg"/>    
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName> <date when="1858-07-29">July 29th, 1858</date>.</dateline>
                    
                    <p>Received of <persName>Columbus Alexander</persName> eight hundred dollars
                        being payment in full for the purchase of a negro man named "<persName>Beverly</persName>" The Right and title of the Said man
                        "<persName>Beverly</persName>" I Warrant and defend against the claim or
                        claims of all persons whatsoever and likewise warrant him Sound and healthy
                        in body and mind, and a Slave for life—Given under my hand and seal
                        the date above written</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Lewis Warrington</persName> seal</signed><lb/>
                        Witness
                        <signed><persName>Walter. O. Alexander</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>                
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00893.011.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>No 7</ab>
                    <ab>Bill of Sale for <persName>Frank Diggs</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="cww.00893.012.jpg"/>    
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName>
                        <date when="1852-04-09">April 9th 1852</date></dateline>
                    <p><persName>Columbus Alexander</persName> Bought of <persName>William T.
                        Duvall</persName> one Negro boy called <persName>Frank Diggs</persName> for
                        the Sum of five hundred dollars, the Receipt hereof I hereby acknowledge, &amp;
                        which Said boy I warrant to be free of all <choice><orig>incumbrance</orig><reg>encumbrance</reg></choice> &amp; a Slave for life.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>William T. Duvall</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="cww.00893.017.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab><persName>Wm B Scott</persName> X (No 8)</ab>
                    <ab>Wife—Bill of Sale to <persName>C Alexander</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="cww.00893.018.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents, that we, <persName>William B.
                        Scott</persName> and <persName>Ann Scott</persName> his wife, of the
                        <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> and <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, for and in consideration of the sum of six hundred
                        dollars, to us in hand paid by <persName>Columbus Alexander, Jr.</persName>,
                        of the same place, do hereby sell, transfer and make over to the said
                        <persName>Columbus Alexander, Jr.</persName>, a
                        negro Boy called <persName>George Singleton</persName> aged nineteen years
                        or thereabouts, the said boy <persName>George Singleton</persName> being
                        black, and medium size, a slave for life, which boy <persName>George
                            Singleton</persName> we represent to the said <persName>Columbus
                                Alexander, Jr.</persName>, to be our Just and lawful property, and free
                        from encumbrance of every kind whatsoever; and we do hereby warrant and
                        defend to the said <persName>Columbus Alexander, Jr.</persName>, against the
                        claim of us, the said <persName>William B. Scott</persName> and
                        <persName>Ann</persName> his wife, and against the claim of all and
                        every other person claiming the same, and will forever warrant and defend
                        the same.</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof, we have hereunto set our hands and affixed our seals this
                        <date when="1856-02-23">Twenty third day of February one thousand eight
                            hundred and fifty-six</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Wm. B. Scott</persName> (Seal.)</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Ann Scott</persName> (Seal.)</signed></closer>                    
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sealed and delivered and possession delivered in presence of</p>
                    <closer>Witness—
                        <signed><persName>Jas. T. Scott</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="cww.00893.015.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>No 10</ab>
                    <ab><persName>W H Gunnell</persName>s Bill of Sale of <persName>Betty Hopp</persName></ab>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="cww.00893.016.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><choice><abbr>Rec.</abbr><expan>Received</expan></choice> of <persName>Columbus Alexander</persName> Eighty dollars which I warrant a slave for life named <persName>Betty Hop</persName> which woman I warrant to defend from all claims that may be made hereafter <date when="1844-03-01">March 1, 1844</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>W. H. Grinnell</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><choice><abbr>Rec.</abbr><expan>Received</expan></choice> of <persName>C. Alexander</persName> all sums paid <persName>Betty</persName> for wages up to this date <date when="1844-03-01">Mch 1, 1844</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>W. H. Gunnell</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="cww.00893.006.jpg"/>  
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the Petition.</hi>]</head>
                
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">Columbus Alexander</seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>C. Alexander</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">                    
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-10"><seg type="handwritten">10th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Chas. Walter</persName> J. P. seal</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>893.</ab>
                <ab>Emancipation Act.</ab>
                <ab><persName>Columbus Alexander</persName><lb/>
                    Claimant<lb/>
                    [15 Slaves]</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>4 Exhibits &amp; Continuation Marked "B.B."</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
