<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00618">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Egbert Thompson, 11 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00618</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Egbert Thompson, 11 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Egbert Thompson, 11 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John S. Hollingshead</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John Q. Harman</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-06-17" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-05-20" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00618.001.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><placeName>U. S.</placeName> Gun Boat, <placeName>Pittsburgh</placeName>,<lb/>
                    near <placeName>Fort Pillow</placeName> <placeName>Tennessee</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName> <date when="1862-05-22">May 22d 1862</date>.</dateline>
                <salute><persName>J. H. C. Mudd</persName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington City D. C.</placeName></salute>
                <p>The Petition and Schedule you forwarded for me to swear and sign before some
                    magistrate, Notary Public, Clerk of a Court reached me this morning.</p>
                <p>It is impossible for me to obtain permission to leave the important duty assigned
                    my command to proceed several hundred miles to where I will find the loyal
                    officials you name to execute the papers</p>
                <p>I am hourly expecting to be called into more active service&#8212;I have
                    therefore had a copy taken and executed them before the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> Naval officer in command of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> Naval Forces on the Western Waters&#8212;I trust this letter may be all that is necessary for my
                    attorney, or wife <persName>Emily. B. Thompson</persName> to execute the
                    necessary papers in regard to the Emancipation Act for the release of certain
                    persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>.</p>
                <closer>I am, Very Respectfully, Your <choice><abbr>obd't</abbr><expan>obedient</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Serv't</abbr><expan>Servant</expan></choice>,
                    <signed><persName>Egbert Thompson</persName><lb/>
                        <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk"><choice><abbr>Commdr</abbr><expan>Commander</expan></choice></unclear></signed></closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00618.002.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab><hi rend="underline">Petition<lb/>
                    of</hi><lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Lieut.</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice>
                    <persName><hi rend="underline">Egbert Thompson</hi></persName>, under the Act of
                    Congress of <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>&#8212;generally known
                    as the <hi rend="underline">Emancipation Act</hi> with Exhibits marked <hi rend="underline">A, B</hi> and <hi rend="underline">C.</hi></ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00618.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main"><hi rend="underline">Petition</hi></head>
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress, Approved, <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, entitled "<hi rend="underline">An Act for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></hi>."</p>

                <p>The Petitioner, <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, a citizen of <placeName>Washington</placeName>, (now in command of the <placeName>United States</placeName> Gunboat "<hi rend="underline">Pittsburgh</hi>" on the <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName>,) hereby represents, that he is loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that at the time of the passage of the Act of Congress, "for the release of certain persons held to service of labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," Approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, he held a claim to the service or labor <hi rend="underline">for life</hi> of <persName><hi rend="underline">Betsy Greenfield</hi></persName>, and her children, <persName><hi rend="underline">Louisa</hi></persName> <persName><hi rend="underline">Alice</hi></persName> and <persName><hi rend="underline">George Greenfield</hi></persName>, and jointly with another, (whose interest under said Act of Congress has since passed to him,) the service or labor for life of <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName>; all of whom are of African descent, and were freed and discharged from service or labor by the Act of Congress aforesaid.</p>


                <p>The petitioner further represents, that said <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00618.004.jpg"/><persName><hi rend="underline">Betsy Greenfield</hi></persName> is about thirty-five, or thirty-six years of age; of a yellow, or copper color, about five feet, five or six inches in height, and of full habits. <persName><hi rend="underline">Louisa Greenfield</hi></persName> is about fourteen years of age; of a dark brown color, and of ordinary height. Has a blink right eye, the sight of which is bad, and usually a slow, shuffling gait. <persName><hi rend="underline">Alice Greenfield</hi></persName> is about ten years of age; of a yellow or copper color; is well-grown; and very quick and active. She is left-handed. <persName><hi rend="underline">George Greenfield</hi></persName> is about eight years of age; of a very dark complexion, nearly black; is of good size, well built; and has a pleasant expression. <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName> is about six years of age; of a bright copper color; is well-grown for her age; and quick and intelligent. Is very bow-legged</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that he had and held the service or labor for life of the four persons first aforementioned and described, and the service or labor for life of <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName> (as one half owner) in right of his wife <persName>Emily B. Thompson</persName>, formerly <persName>Mudd</persName>, who took and acquired the four persons first-named as legatee under the last will and testament of her Mother, which was admitted to probate in the Orphans' Court for the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, in the month of <date when="1861-08">August, 1861</date>. (<hi rend="underline">A Copy of said will is herewith presented, and marked, "Exhibit A")</hi></p>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00618.005.jpg"/>
                <p>He farther represents, that his said wife in whose right he claims, took and acquired the service or labor of said <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName> as property as heir at-law of her Mother, late of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> aforesaid, deceased, jointly with her brother <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, the only other heir at-law.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that the said <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, entitled as aforesaid to the one-half of the service or labor for life of said <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName>, by an assignment, under date of <date when="1862-05-10">May 10, 1862</date>, (<hi rend="underline">which is herewith presented and marked Exhibit B</hi>) for a valuable consideration, assigned, transferred, and set over to him all his right, title, interest, and demand in such sum as may be allowed under the claim for compensation, in virtue of the Act of Congress aforesaid, because of the freedom and discharge of the said <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName>, from service or labor as aforesaid.</p>

                <p>The petitioner submits and requests, therefore, that in fixing and valuing the claim, arising by reason of the freedom from service or labor of said <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName>, by the Act of Congress aforesaid, the whole amount will be his, and should be so apportioned.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that the claim to the service or labor of said <persName><hi rend="underline">Betsy Greenfield</hi></persName>, at the time of her discharge therefrom, was of the value of eight hundred dollars. ($800.) She is a first rate cook, <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00618.006.jpg"/>a good washer and ironer, and generally useful as a servant. So great is her trustiness, that she had entire control of all family stores for years; and as the petitioner is informed and believes, twelve hundred dollars ($1200.) was several times offered for her, for private use, during the life of her former owner, within four or five years past.</p>

                <p>The said <persName><hi rend="underline">Betsy Greenfield</hi></persName> is stout, and generally healthy. She is subject, however, and has been, as your petitioner understands and believes, from an early age to severe attacks of sick, or nervous headache, which sometimes cause temporary "flightiness."</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that the said <persName><hi rend="underline">Louisa Greenfield</hi></persName>, at the time of her discharge therefrom, was, for service or labor, of the value of four hundred ($400.) She is a fair nurse for children, and familiar with ordinary house-work.</p>
                
                <p>The petitioner further represents, that at the time of their discharge therefrom, the said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Alice</persName></hi>, <persName><hi rend="underline">George</hi></persName>, and <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName>,&#8212;the two first named of whom are very handy and useful,&#8212;were of the value, as to service or labor, separately, as follows;&#8212;the first-named, of the value of four hundred dollars; ($400.) the second-named, of the same value as the first: ($400,) and the third, of the value of two hundred and fifty dollars. ($250.)</p>
                
                <p>The petitioner further represents, that all of the afore-mentioned and described persons are free, so far as he knows, and as he believes, from mental, moral,<pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00618.007.jpg"/> and bodily defects, and infirmities, other than such as the description herein before given of each of them, under either head, may, or does embrace. He knows of no defect, or infirmity in either; nor is he informed of any, which should, or did impair the usefulness, or value of either.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, in this connexion, that the persons aforesaid were assessed, for the purposes of taxation, by the <placeName>Corporation of Washington</placeName> for the year <date when="1861">1861</date>. (by some oversight they were not assessed for the year <date when="1862">1862</date>.) as the personal property of Mrs. <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, since deceased, at twenty-two hundred dollars, ($2,200.)&#8212;which was deemed below their value,&#8212;and taxes were paid in accordance with that assessment. (<hi rend="underline">"See Exhibit marked C.</hi>")</p>
                
                <p>The petitioner further represents, that he is a Lieutenant in the Navy of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and holds an important command, as before stated; and that, inasmuch as he is actively engaged in the work of putting-down the present rebellion, he deems it unnecessary to say, that he has given neither aid nor comfort to it; nor borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName>, his faith and allegiance to which are attested by his fidelity to his Commission, and to the National Flag.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that none of the persons named in this Petition were, or have been brought into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="cww.00618.008.jpg"/>passage of the Act of Congress aforesaid, Approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, whereby they were freed and discharged; and that each and everyone of them were then, and long before, held to, and owed service or labor in said District, as hereinbefore stated.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that his claim of compensation under the "Act of Congress, entitled <hi rend="underline">An Act for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></hi>," as the same is herein fully and specifically stated, did not, and does not originate in, or by virtue of any transfer, assignment, or sale of any person, who has in any manner aided, or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>; nor did, or does any part, or portion of said claim so originate.</p>

                <p><hi rend="underline">Wherefore</hi> the petitioner prays the Commissioners aforesaid, that the value and validity of his claim, as herein presented, may be investigated an determined, and, if found valid, that the appraisement and apportionment of its value may be reported to the Secretary of the Treasury, in accordance with the provision of the Act of Congress aforesaid, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>.</p>
                
                <closer><signed><persName>Egbert Thompson</persName></signed><lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Cmmdr</abbr><expan>Commander</expan></choice> <placeName>U. S.</placeName> G. B. Pittsburgh</closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-22">Twenty second day of May, A. D. 1862</date>, near <placeName>Fort Pillow</placeName> in the state &amp; county aforesaid</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>C. H. Davis</persName></signed>,<lb/>
                    Flag Officer <choice><abbr>Com'g</abbr><expan>Commanding</expan></choice> Western Flotilla, <placeName>Miss. River</placeName>.</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="cww.00618.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><hi rend="underline">Verification</hi></dateline>
                <dateline><placeName>Mississippi River</placeName> Near <placeName>Fort Pillow</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>State of Tennessee</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>County of Tipton</placeName> ss.</dateline>

            </div1>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>I <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, Lieutenant in the Navy of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, now in command of the Gunboat <hi rend="underline">Pittsburgh</hi>, on the <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName>, being duly sworn, on my oath do depose and say that of the several matters and things, which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, on my own knowledge, are true in substance and fact, and that all which are stated and set forth on the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and fact.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Egbert Thompson</persName></signed><lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Cmmdr</abbr><expan>Commander</expan></choice>
                    G. B. Pittsburgh</closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-22">twenty second day of May A. D. 1862</date>, near <placeName>Fort Pillow</placeName> in the State and county aforesaid</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>C. H. Davis</persName></signed>,<lb/>
                    Flag Officer, <choice><abbr>Com'g</abbr><expan>Commanding</expan></choice> Western Flotilla, <placeName>Miss. River</placeName>.</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="cww.00618.010.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>Last Will and Testament of Mrs. <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, deceased.</ab>
                <ab>Filed with the petition of <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName> as <hi rend="underline">Exhibit A</hi>.</ab>
                <ab>Cost $1.25</ab>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="cww.00618.011.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">            
                <p>I, <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, of the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName>, widow of <persName>Ignatius Mudd</persName> deceased, being of sound mind and memory, and knowing the uncertainty of life, do hereby make and publish this, my last and only Will and Testament:</p>
                    
                <p>I give, devise, and bequeath to my daughter <persName>Emily B. Thompson</persName>, wife of <choice><abbr>Lieut.</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> Navy, all my estate and property of every kind and description,&#8212;including my house and lot on <address><addrLine>Maryland Avenue</addrLine></address> in said <placeName>City of Washington</placeName>; my servant woman <persName>Betsy</persName> and her three children, <persName>Louisa</persName>, <persName>Alice</persName>, and <persName>George</persName>, all slaves for life; my silverware and furniture and household effects, and all money due or owing to me,&#8212;to her and her heirs forever.</p>
                    
                <p>It is my wish, as my son <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName> is a non-resident, and my son-in-law aforesaid is likely to be, as he now is, on official duty, that <persName>Stanislaus Murray</persName> <choice><abbr>Esq.</abbr><expan>Esquire</expan></choice> of the city aforesaid, should act as executor, and I do hereby nominate and appoint him as such, of this my last Will and Testament. And, to give him as little trouble as possible it is my wish and request, that no security may be demanded of him, and that all inventories and <choice><sic>appraisments</sic><corr>appraisements</corr></choice> and other forms not indispensable in the settlement of my estate may be dispensed with.</p>
                    
                <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto affixed my signature, this <date when="1856-04-03">third day of April, in the year one thousand, eight hundred and fifty-six</date>, at the city aforesaid</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Mary Mudd</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Signed and acknowledged in the presence of</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>C. H. Keller</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Henrietta C. Keller</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Mary J. Jamison</persName></signed></closer>
                    <note type="autorial" rend="handwritten">* Probate to the Will</note>
                </div2>                          

            <pb xml:id="leaf011v" facs="cww.00618.012.jpg"/>                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>I execute and publish this codicil to my last will and testament that <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, my son-in-law shall be my sole executor, without security.</p>
                <p>Witness my hand and seal this <date when="1861-03-13">thirteenth day of March one thousand eight hundred and sixty one</date></p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Mary Mudd</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">    
                <p>Witnessed by</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Henrietta C. Keller</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>J. H. Everett</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Alexis Mudd</persName></signed></closer>
                    <note type="authorial" rend="handwritten">* Probate to Will</note>
                </div2>                    
            
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName> to wit<lb/>
                        Orphans Court <date when="1861-08-26">August 26 1861</date></dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName> and <persName>Henrietta C. Keller</persName> two of the subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing last will &amp; testament of <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, late of <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid deceased, &amp; severally made oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that they did see the Testatrix therein named, sign this will, that she published pronounced &amp; declared the same to be her last will &amp; testament that at the time of so doing she was, to the best of their apprehensions of sound &amp; disposing mind, memory &amp; understanding; &amp; that they together with <persName>C. H. Keller</persName> &amp; <persName>Mary J. Jamison</persName> the other subscribing witnesses respectively subscribed their names as witnesses, to this will; in the presence &amp; at the request of the Testatrix &amp; in the presence of each other.</p>
                    <closer>Test: <signed><persName>Ed. N. Roach</persName> <choice><abbr>Regr</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> Wills</signed></closer>                        
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName> to wit
                    Orphans Court <date when="1861-08-31">August 31, 1861</date></dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared <persName>C. H. Keller</persName> one of the subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing last will &amp; testament of <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, late of <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid deceased <pb xml:id="leaf012r" facs="cww.00618.013.jpg"/>&amp; made oath in the Holy Evangels of Almighty God that he did see the Testatrix therein named sign this will, that she published pronounced &amp; declared the same to be her last will &amp; testament, that at the time of so doing she was to the best of his apprehension of sound &amp; disposing mind, memory &amp; understanding; &amp; that he together with <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, <persName>Henrietta C. Keller</persName> &amp; <persName>Mary J. Jamison</persName>, the other subscribing witnesses respectively subscribed their names as witnesses to this will in the presence &amp; at the request of the Testatrix, &amp; in the presence of each other</p>
                    <closer>Test: <signed><persName>Ed. N. Roche</persName> <choice><abbr>Regr</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> Wills</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName> to wit;</dateline>
                <p>I certify that the aforegoing is a true copy from the original filed and recorded in the office of the Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid</p>                    
                <p>Witness my hand and seal of office this <date when="1862-04-22">22nd day of April in the year 1862</date></p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Moses Kelly</persName></signed><lb/>
                    Register of Wills</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf013r" facs="cww.00618.014.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab><persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName><lb/>
                    to<lb/>
                    <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName></ab>
                <ab>Assignment</ab>
                <ab>Filed with the petition of <choice><abbr>Lieut.</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, as <hi rend="underline">Exhibit, B</hi>.</ab>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf014r" facs="cww.00618.015.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">            
                <p><hi rend="underline">Know all men by these presents</hi>, that I, <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, of the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> and <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, for and in consideration of one hundred and fifty dollars to me in hand paid by <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, Lieutenant in the <placeName>United States</placeName> Navy, of the city aforesaid, hereby assign, transfer, and set over to him, for his own proper use and benefit, whatever sum may be allowed by the Commissioners of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, under a claim for compensation arising under and by virtue of the Act of Congress of <date when="1862-04-16">April Sixteen, Eighteen Hundred and Sixty-two</date>, entitled "<hi rend="underline">An Act for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></hi>," whereby a certain person held by said <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName> and myself in joint ownership was freed and discharged from the service or labor which she owed to us as aforesaid, <hi rend="underline">for life</hi>; and all my right, title, interest, and demand in, and to the claim aforesaid, and I hereby give and grant to said <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName> full power and authority irrevocable, in his own name, or as assignee hereunder, to petition for and receive the same, and upon receipt thereof to discharge my one-half interest in said claim as fully as his own, and acquit the <placeName>United States of America</placeName> thereof, in "full and complete compensation."</p>
                    
                <p>The girl aforesaid is named <persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName>; of African descent; of a <pb xml:id="leaf015r" facs="cww.00618.016.jpg"/>bright copper color; well-grown for age, which is six years; quick and intelligent; and free from mental and moral defects, and from bodily, also, except that she is bow-legged. She has not been brought into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of the Act of Congress aforesaid, but was at the time held to service or labor therein for life as aforesaid, by said <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName> and myself. The said <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName> held his claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName> in right of his wife <persName>Emily B. Thompson</persName>, formerly <persName>Mudd</persName>, and I held my claim as aforesaid as an heir at law of my Mother, <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, late of the city aforesaid, to whom said <persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName> was held as aforesaid from her birth, (her mother being of African descent and a slave,); and my said Sister inherited said <persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName> jointly with me.</p>
                <p>And, I, hereby covenant with said <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, that my one-half interest in the claim for compensation aforesaid has not been voided by reason of my having borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> during the present rebellion, or by giving aid and comfort in any way thereto; and I hereby declare that I am now, and have been always, true and faithful in allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf016r" facs="cww.00618.017.jpg"/>
                <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand seal, this <date when="1862-05-10">tenth day of May, Eighteen Hundred and Sixty-two</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, S.S.</signed></closer>
                    <closer>Witnessed by 
                        <signed><persName>Henry A. Clark</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Thos. T. Everett</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Count of Washington</placeName> ss.</dateline>                
                    <p>Personally appeared, on this <date when="1862-05-12"><choice><sic>twelvth</sic><corr>twelfth</corr></choice> day of May, Eighteen Hundred and Sixty two</date>, before me, a Notary Public in and for the District and County aforesaid, <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, who is personally known to me as the person who executed the foregoing instrument, and being duly sworn, on his oath says, that he executed the same freely and voluntarily for the purposes therein mentioned.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and seal, the day and year before written.</p> 
                    <closer><signed><persName>John S Hollingshead</persName></signed><lb/>
                        Notary Public</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf017r" facs="cww.00618.018.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="receipt" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>Receipt for city taxes for <date when="1861">1861</date>, showing the assessment of certain slaves lately owned by <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed with the petition of <choice><abbr>Lieut.</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, as <hi rend="underline">Exhibit C</hi></ab>
                </div2>
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf018r" facs="cww.00618.019.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                <dateline>Page <seg type="handwritten">157</seg><lb/>
                <hi rend="bold">To <placeName>Washington Corporation</placeName>, Dr.</hi></dateline>
                    <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Mudd</persName></ab>
                    <ab><hi rend="italic">To Tax of Property for the year</hi> <date when="1861">186<seg type="handwritten">1</seg></date></ab>                        
                <table>
                    <row><cell>$ <seg type="handwritten">26.06</seg></cell></row>
                    <row><cell><hi rend="underline">5 21</hi></cell></row>
                    <row><cell>$ <seg type="handwritten">20.85</seg></cell></row>
                </table>
                    
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Square.</cell>
                        <cell>Lot.</cell>
                        <cell>Value of Lot.</cell>
                        <cell>Improvements.</cell>
                        <cell>Personal.</cell>
                        <cell>Deduct per cent</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row rend="handwritten">
                        <cell>299</cell>
                        <cell>of 13</cell>
                        <cell>711</cell>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row rend="handwritten">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>2200</cell>
                        <cell>(s<ref xml:id="r1" target="#a1">*</ref>)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row rend="handwritten">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><note xml:id="a1" target="#r1" type="authorial"><seg type="handwritten">* <hi rend="underline">Slaves.</hi></seg></note></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                    
                <closer>
                    <dateline><date when="1861-08-22"><seg type="handwritten">Aug't 22, 1861</seg></date></dateline> <hi rend="italic">Received payment,</hi>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Wm Dixon</persName></seg> <hi rend="hadnwritten">Collector.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf019r" facs="cww.00618.020.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>618</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="underline">Petition</hi><lb/>
                    of<lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, under the Act of Congress of <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, generally known as the <hi rend="underline">Emancipation Act</hi>; with Exhibits <hi rend="underline">A, B,</hi> and <hi rend="underline">C.;</hi> and a letter of the Petitioner stating why it was necessary to verify his <hi rend="underline">Petition</hi> before <choice><abbr>Commore</abbr><expan>Commodore</expan></choice> <persName>Davis</persName>.</ab>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf0020r" facs="cww.00618.021.jpg"/>
            <fw>SOLD BY<lb/>
                <persName>Jas. B. Smith &amp; Co.<lb/>
                    <address><addrLine>No. 610 Chesnut Street,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</addrLine></address></persName></fw>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main"><hi rend="underline">Petition</hi>.</head>

                <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress, Approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, entitled "<hi rend="underline">An Act for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></hi>."</p>

                <p>The Petitioner, <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, a citizen of <placeName>Washington</placeName>, (now in command of the <placeName>United States</placeName> Gunboat <hi rend="underline">Pittsburg</hi>, on the <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName>,) hereby represents, that he is loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that at the time of the passage of the Act of Congress, "for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," Approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, he held a claim to the service or labor <hi rend="underline">for life</hi> of <persName><hi rend="underline">Betsy Greenfield</hi></persName>, and her children, <hi rend="underline"><persName>Louisa</persName></hi>, <hi rend="underline"><persName>Alice</persName></hi>, and <hi rend="underline"><persName>George Greenfield</persName></hi>; and jointly with another (, whose interest under said Act of Congress has since passed to him,) the service or labor for life of <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi>, all of whom are of African descent and were freed and discharged from service or labor by the Act of Congress aforesaid.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, <pb xml:id="leaf0021r" facs="cww.00618.022.jpg"/>that said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Betsy Greenfield</persName></hi> is about thirty-five or thirty-six years of age; of a yellow, or copper color; about five feet, five or six inches in height, and of full habit. <hi rend="underline"><persName>Louisa Greenfield</persName></hi> is about fourteen years of age; of a dark brown color, and of ordinary height. Has a blink right eye, the sight of which is bad, and, usually, a slow, shuffling gait. <hi rend="underline"><persName>Alice Greenfield</persName></hi> is about ten years of age; of a yellow, or copper color; is well-grown, and very quick and active. She is left handed. <hi rend="underline"><persName>George Greenfield</persName></hi> is about eight years of age; of a very dark complexion, nearly black; is of good size, well-built, and has a pleasant expression. <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi> is about six years of age; of a bright copper color; is well-grown for her age, and quick and intelligent. Is very bow-legged.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that he had and held the service or labor for life of the four persons first aforementioned and described; and the service or labor for life of <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi>, (as one half-owner) in right of his wife, <persName>Emily B. Thompson</persName>, formerly <persName>Mudd</persName>, who took and acquired the four persons first named as legatee under the last will and testament of her Mother, which was admitted to probate in the Orphans' Court for the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, in the <date when="1861-08">month of August, 1861</date>. (<hi rend="underline">A Copy of said will is herewith presented, and marked, "Exhibit A.")</hi></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf0022r" facs="cww.00618.023.jpg"/>
                <fw>SOLD BY<lb/>
                    <persName>Jas. B. Smith &amp; Co.<lb/>
                        <address><addrLine>No. 610 Chesnut Street,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</addrLine></address></persName></fw>

                <p>He further represents, that his said wife in whose right he claims, took and acquired the service or labor of said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi> as property, as heir-at-law of her said Mother, late of the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> aforesaid, deceased, jointly with her brother <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, the only other heir-at-law.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that the said <persName>J. H. Clay Mudd</persName>, entitled as aforesaid to the one-half of the service or labor for life of said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi>, by our assignment, under date of <date when="1862-05-10">May 10, 1862</date>, (<hi rend="underline">which is herewith presented and marked, "Exhibit B.</hi>") for a valuable consideration, assigned, transferred, and set over to him all his right, title, interest, and demand in such sum as may be allowed under the claim for compensation, in virtue of the Act of Congress aforesaid, because of the freedom and discharge of the said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi> from service or labor as aforesaid.</p>

                <p>The petitioner submits and requests, therefore, that in fixing and valuing the claim, arising by reason of the freedom from service or labor of said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Rachel Greenfield</persName></hi>, by the Act of Congress aforesaid, the whole amount will be his, and should be so apportioned.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that the claim to the service or labor of said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Betsy Greenfield</persName></hi>, at the time of <pb xml:id="leaf0023r" facs="cww.00618.024.jpg"/>her discharge therefrom, was of the value of eight hundred dollars. ($800.) She is a first rate cook; a good washer and ironer, and generally useful as a servant. So great is her trustiness, that she had entire control of all family stores for years; and, as the petitioner is informed and believes, twelve hundred dollars ($1,200.) was several times offered for her, for private use, during the life of her former owner, within four or five years past.</p>

                <p>The said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Betsy Greenfield</persName></hi> is stout, and generally healthy. She is subject, however, and has been, as your petitioner has understood, and believes, from an early age, to severe attacks of sick, or nervous headache which sometimes cause temporary "flightiness."</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represent, that the said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Louisa Greenfield</persName></hi>, at the time of her discharge therefrom, was, for service or labor, of the value of four hundred ($400.) She is a fair nurse for children, and familiar with ordinary housework.</p>
                
                <p>The petitioner further represents, that at the time of their discharge therefrom, the said <hi rend="underline"><persName>Alice</persName></hi>, <hi rend="underline"><persName>George</persName></hi>, and <persName><hi rend="underline">Rachel Greenfield</hi></persName>,&#8212;the two first named of whom are very handy and useful,&#8212;were of the value, as to service or labor, separately, as follows; the first named, of the value <pb xml:id="leaf0024r" facs="cww.00618.025.jpg"/><fw>SOLD BY<lb/>
                    <persName>Jas. B. Smith &amp; Co.<lb/>
                        <address><addrLine>No. 610 Chesnut Street,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</addrLine></address></persName></fw> of four hundred dollars; ($400.) the second-named, of the same value as the first; ($400.) and the third, of the value of two hundred and fifty dollars. ($250.)</p>
                
                <p>The petitioner further represents, that all of the aforementioned and described persons are free, so far as he knows, and as he believes, from mental, moral, and bodily defects and infirmities, other than such as the description hereinbefore given of each of them, under either head, may, or does embrace. He knows of no defect, or infirmity in either, nor is he informed of any, which should, or did impair the usefulness, or value of either.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, in this connexion, that the persons aforesaid were assessed, for the purposes of taxation, by the <placeName>Corporation of Washington</placeName> for the year <date when="1861">1861</date>, (, by some oversight they were not assessed for the year <date when="1862">1862</date>,) as the personal property of Mrs. <persName>Mary Mudd</persName>, since deceased, at twenty-two hundred dollars, ($2,200.)&#8212;which was deemed below their value,&#8212;and taxes were paid in accordance with that assessment. (<hi rend="underline">See</hi>, "<hi rend="underline">Exhibit, marked C.</hi>"</p>
                
                <p>The petitioner further represents, that he is a Lieutenant in the Navy of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and holds an important command, as before stated; and that, inasmuch as he is actively engaged in the work of putting down the present <pb xml:id="leaf0025r" facs="cww.00618.026.jpg"/>rebellion, he deems it unnecessary to say that he has given neither aid, nor comfort to it; nor borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName>, his faith and allegiance to which are attested by his fidelity to his Commission, and to the National Flag.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that none of the persons named in this Petition were, or have been brought into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of the Act of Congress aforesaid, Approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, whereby they were freed and discharged; and that each and every one of them was then, and long before, held to, and owed service, or labor in said District, as hereinbefore stated.</p>

                <p>The petitioner further represents, that his claim of compensation under the Act of Congress, entitled "<hi rend="underline">An Act for the release of certain persons held to service, or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></hi>," as the same is herein fully and specifically stated, did not, and does not, originate in, or by virtue of any transfer, assignment, or sale of any person, who has in any manner aided, or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>; nor did, or does any part, or portion of said claim so originate.</p>

                <p><hi rend="underline">Wherefore</hi> the petitioner prays the Commissioners aforesaid, that the value and validity of his claim, as <pb xml:id="leaf0026r" facs="cww.00618.027.jpg"/><fw>SOLD BY<lb/>
                    <persName>Jas. B. Smith &amp; Co.<lb/>
                        <address><addrLine>No. 610 Chesnut Street,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>.</addrLine></address></persName></fw> herein presented, may be investigated and determined, and, if found valid, that the appraisement and apportionment of its value may be reported to the Secretary of the Treasury, in accordance with the provision of the Act of Congress aforesaid, approved <date when="1862-04-16" >April 16, 1862</date>.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>
                    <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Cmmdr</abbr><expan>Commander</expan></choice>
                    <placeName>US</placeName> Gunboat Pittsburgh</signed></closer>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><hi rend="underline">Verification</hi>.</dateline>
                <dateline><placeName>State of Illinois</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>County of Alexander</placeName> ss.</dateline>
                
                    <p>I <persName>Egbert Thompson</persName>, Lieutenant in the Navy of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, now in command of the Gunboat <hi rend="underline">Pittsburg</hi>, on the <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName>, being duly sworn, on my oath do depose and say, that all of the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, on my own knowledge, are true in substance and fact; and that all which are stated and set forth on the information <pb xml:id="leaf0027r" facs="cww.00618.028.jpg"/>of others, I believe to be true in substance and fact.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Egbert Thompson</persName></signed><lb/>
                        <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <choice><abbr>Cmmdr</abbr><expan>Commander</expan></choice> <placeName>US</placeName> Gunboat Pittsburgh</closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn to an subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-05">5th day of July A. D. 1862</date>, at the City <placeName>Cairo</placeName> in the state and county aforesaid. I further certify that I am authorized to administer oaths take acknowledgment of <gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" unit="chars" quantity="5"/> and other instruments of writing</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of office this <date when="1862-07-05">5th day of July AD 1862</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>John Q Harman</persName></signed><lb/>
                        Clerk County Court in and for the <placeName>County of Alexander</placeName> and <placeName>State of Illinois</placeName></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>618</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="handwritten">Petition<lb/>
                    of</hi><lb/>
                    <choice><abbr>Lieut</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> <persName><hi rend="underline">Egbert Thompson</hi></persName>, under the Act of Congress of <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, generally known as the <hi rend="underline">Emancipation Act</hi>, with Exhibits marked, <hi rend="underline">A, B,</hi> and <hi rend="underline">C.</hi></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-11">11 July 1862</date> by permission of the Commissioner in lieu of and substitution of that filed <date when="1862-06-03">June 3 1862</date> by attorney for <choice><abbr>Petr</abbr><expan>Petitioner</expan></choice></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
