<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00387">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Edward H. Edelin, 22 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="scl">Susan C. Lawrence</name>
                    <name xml:id="sd">Shailana Dunn-Wall</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00387</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Edward H. Edelin, 22 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Edward H. Edelin, 22 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-26">May 22, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Edward H. Edelin</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Charles Walter</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">removed underlining on signature block</change>
            <change when="2013-01-16" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-12" who="#scl">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-12-28" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2012-10-23" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2012-06-14" who="#sd">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00387.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Edward H. Edelin</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington D. C.</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">fourteen</seg>
                        person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Frank Syles</persName>, <persName>Joseph Pinkney</persName>,
                            <persName>George</persName>, <persName>Barney</persName>,
                            <persName>Henry Ross</persName>, <persName>Annanias</persName>,
                            <persName>Deloyier</persName>, <persName>Agnes</persName>,
                            <persName>Rachel</persName>, <persName>Sophy</persName>,
                            <persName>Emily</persName>, <persName>Sidny</persName>,
                            <persName>Jane</persName> &#38; a male infant <choice>
                            <sic>un-named</sic>
                            <corr>unnamed</corr>
                        </choice>.</seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"
                        >persons of African descent</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all
                    claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> of the age<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <space atLeast="1"/> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Frank Syles</persName>&#8212;is about
                        twenty-eight years of age, very dark color, large size and <unclear
                            reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#jc">stout</unclear></seg></p>

                <ab type="handwritten">He is sound in body and mind, except a slight hernia, which
                    does not impair his usefulness. His moral character is good. I hire him for $15 <choice>
                        <abbr>p</abbr>
                        <expan>per</expan>
                    </choice>. month.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Joseph Pinkney</persName> is about fourteen years
                    of age, bright mulatto and well grown for his age he is sound &#38; healthy in
                    body and mind and of good character.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>George</persName>&#8212;is about twelve years old,
                    light copper color, rather tall &#38; spare, sound &#38; healthy in body and
                    mind, intelligent &#38; of good character.</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00387.003.jpg"/>

                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Barney</persName> is about fourteen years of age,
                    light copper color, stout made, is sound and healthy in body and mind, active
                    &#38; intelligent and of good character.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Henry Ross</persName>&#8212;is about eleven years
                    of age, bright mulatto, not very well grown, sound in mind but rather delicate
                    in person &#38; of good character.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Annanias</persName>&#8212;about nine years of age,
                    a bright mulatto, a little under size, sound &#38; healthy in body and mind and
                    of excellent character.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Deloyier</persName>&#8212;about three years of age,
                    a bright mulatto, sound in body and mind.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Agnes</persName> about fifty-eight years of age
                    under medium height, dark color, is sound in body &#38; mind &#38; of good
                    character she is a good plain cook.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Rachel</persName>&#8212;is about forty-four years
                    of age copper color, robust person, sound in body and mind, of good character,
                    and an excellent cook, washer and ironer, she is hired to Ms.
                        <persName>Spaulding</persName> @ $9. pr. month.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Sophy</persName>&#8212;is about thirty-four year of
                    age, dark color, under medium height, she is a good cook, washer and ironer, her
                    general health is not good, rather loose morals she is hired to Ms.
                        <persName>Lurpin</persName> at $6&#8212;per month.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Emily</persName> is about twenty-two years of age,
                    light copper color, a littler under the medium height, very good looking, sound
                    in body and mind tho' not of robust person good character, hired to Ms.
                        <persName>Coombs</persName> @ $7. pr. month.</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00387.004.jpg"/>

                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Sidny</persName>&#8212;is about fifteen years of
                    age, a bright mulatto, above the usual height, sound &#38; healthy in body and
                    mind, very good looking and is a good plain cook, washer and ironer. Her moral
                    character is good.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Jane</persName> is about thirty-two years of age,
                    bright mulatto, quite tall, she is an excellent cook, washer &#38; ironer, she
                    is a good pastry cook, she is sound in body and mind, and of good general
                    health. Her character is good; she is hired to Mrs. <persName>Walker</persName>
                    at $10&#8212;pr. month.</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten">Male infant, about two months old, not named, quite
                    healthy.</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00387.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">by marriage with <persName>Sidney Wrightman</persName>,
                        who inherited said person from her Mother, <persName>Sarah Syles</persName>,
                        of <placeName>Prince George Co.</placeName>
                        <placeName>Md</placeName>.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">nine thousand five hundred
                        &#38; fifty</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot"
                        xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">And your petitioner further avers that he knows of no
                        infirmities or defects, which impair the value of petitioner's claim, <hi
                            rend="underline">except</hi> those already stated, and he believes that
                        none exist.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg
                        type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into
                    the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del>held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    value of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                    United States, in conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Edw. H. Edelin</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00387.005.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Edward H. Edelin</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Edwd. H. Edelin</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-09">
                            <seg type="handwritten">9th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Chas. Walter</persName> J P seal</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>387</ab>
                <ab>Petition of <persName>Edward H. Edelin</persName></ab>
                <ab>Presented by <persName>Jno B. Peyton</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-22">May 22, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Joseph Beasely</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
