<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00332">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Gabriel Coakley, 20 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00332</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Gabriel Coakley, 20 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-20">May 20, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Gabriel Coakley, 20 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-20">May 20, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Gabriel Coakley</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Nicholas Callan</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-05-07" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-03-24" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00332.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">

                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Gabriel
                        Coakley</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington
                            DC</placeName>.</seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition
                    in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a
                    person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of
                    the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor
                    against <seg type="handwritten">the following named</seg> person<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg
                        type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Anne M
                            Coakley</persName>, <persName>Mary Coakley</persName>, <persName>Mary
                            Ann Coakley</persName>
                        <persName>Sophia Coakley</persName>, <persName>Veronica Coakley</persName>,
                            <persName>Genova Coakley</persName>, <persName>Sarah Coakley</persName>,
                        &#38; <persName>Gertrude Coakley</persName>.</seg> for and during the life
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons.</seg> and that by said act of Congress
                    said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Ann M</persName> was of the age
                        of 39 years. <persName>Mary</persName> was of the age of 34 years.
                            <persName>Mary Ann</persName> was 11 years. <persName>Sophia</persName>
                        was 9 &#189; years <persName>Veronica</persName> was 7 years
                            <persName>Genova</persName> was 5 &#189; years
                            <persName>Sarah</persName> was 3 years &#38;
                            <persName>Gertrude</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg
                        type="handwritten">1 &#189; years.&#8212;</seg> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Ann M Coakley</persName>. is of a Brown complexion about
                            five feet two inches high.</item>
                        <item><persName>Mary</persName> is a Bright Mulatto, about five feet four
                            inches high.</item>
                        <item><persName>Mary Ann</persName>. is of a yellow complexion, is eleven
                            years old.</item>
                        <item><persName>Sophia</persName> is of a yellow complexion is about nine
                            and a half years old</item>
                        <item><persName>Veronica</persName> is of a yellow complexion is about seven
                            years of age.</item>
                        <item><persName>Genova</persName> is of a yellow complexion is about five
                            and a half years old</item>
                        <item><persName>Sarah</persName> has also a yellow complexion is about three
                            years old</item>
                        <item><persName>Gertrude</persName> has a yellow complexion is about one
                            &#38; a half years old.</item>
                    </list>
                    <seg type="handwritten">There are no marks on either of the above persons except
                            <persName>Mary Anne</persName>, who has a scar (produced by a fall) on
                        her chin also one on the right wrist produced by a cut with a knife.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00332.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">That is to say, He purchased <persName>Mary</persName>
                        from <persName>W W W Bowie</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                            <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice> of <placeName>Maryland</placeName> before she was married to
                            <persName>Coakley</persName>, by the name of <persName>Mary
                            Calloway</persName>, all the children were born since her marriage to
                            <persName>Coakley</persName>.</seg></p>
                <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Ann M. Coakley</persName> was bought from Mr
                        <persName>John Larcum</persName>. The original</ab>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">3.300</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName>Ann M.</persName> is an excellent nurse and chambermaid and
                            at this time hired by Dr <persName>J C Riley</persName> of this city at
                            $8 per month in his family. She is a moral, and a well behaved servant,
                            stout &#38; healthy.</item>
                        <item><persName>Mary</persName> does all my cooking washing and ironing
                            together with all my house-work moral industrious and temperate</item>
                        <item><persName>Mary Ann</persName> is a good childs nurse and is employed
                            in my family</item>
                        <item>All the rest of the above named servants are living in my family and I
                            know of no moral, mental or bodily defect in either of them to
                            depreciate their value</item>
                    </list></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten"
                        >his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg
                        type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer>(Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>G
                            Coakley</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00332.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Paid $0 75</ab>
                    <ab><persName>John Larcombe</persName><lb/> to<lb/>
                        <persName>Gabriel Cokely</persName></ab>
                    <ab>Received <date when="1857-06-18">18th June 1857</date></ab>
                    <ab>To be Recorded and the same day was recorded in Liber JAS No 136. folios
                        142. &#38; 143. One of the Land Records for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        and Examined by</ab>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Jno A Smith</persName><lb/>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                                <expan>Clerk</expan>
                            </choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00332.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents That I <persName>John Larcombe</persName> of
                        the <placeName>City and County of Washington</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, for and in consideration of
                        the sum of one dollar, to me in hand paid by <persName>Gabriel
                            Coakley</persName> of said city, the receipt of which I do hereby
                        acknowledge, have given, granted, bargained, sold, aliened, released, and
                        confirmed; and by these presents do give, grant, bargain, sell, alien,
                        release, and confirm unto the said <persName>Gabriel Coakley</persName>, a
                        negro girl called <persName>Ann. Mahala Coakley</persName>, the daughter of
                            <persName>Nancy Coakly</persName> and <persName>Gabriel
                            Stevens</persName>, together with all the right, title, interest, claim,
                        property, possession, and demand, whatsoever of me, my executors or
                        administrators, of, in and to the said <persName>Ann Mahala
                            Coakley</persName>, To have and to hold the said negro girl, and all and
                        singular the premises above mentioned unto him the said <persName>Gabriel
                            Coakley</persName>, and his assigns forever</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof the said <persName>John Larcombe</persName> hath set his
                        hand and affixed his seal the <date when="1857-06-10">10th day of June
                            1857</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>John Larcombe</persName>, seal</signed><lb/>
                        Signed, sealed and delivered in presence of
                        <signed><persName>J H Goddard</persName></signed>
                        <signed>F. I. Murphey</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00332.005.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName> to wit.</dateline>
                    <p>On this <date when="1857-06-12">12th day of June 1857</date>, before the
                        subscriber a Justice of the Peace in and for the county and District
                        aforesaid, personally appeared, <persName>John Larcombe</persName>, and
                        acknowledged the foregoing instrument of writing to be his act and deed for
                        the purposes therein expressed.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>J. H. Goddard</persName> J.P. seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00332.006.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab><unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#kk">Borne</unclear></ab>
                    <ab>332</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00332.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="evidence" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents that I <persName>Walter W. W. Bowie</persName>
                        of <placeName>Prince George's County</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, for and in consideration of the sum of one hundred
                        and fifty Dollars, current money to me in hand paid and also of <choice>
                            <sic>promisory</sic>
                            <corr>promissory</corr>
                        </choice> notes amounting to three hundred and fifty Dollars, bearing
                        interest from their dates, and payable at different times hereafter, to me
                        delivered, by <persName>Southey L. Parker</persName>, <persName>W. E.
                            Spalding</persName>, and <persName>Gabriel Cokely</persName> all of
                            <placeName>Washington City</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, at and before the sealing and delivery of these
                        presents, the receipt whereof I do hereby acknowledge have granted bargained
                        and sold and by these presents do grant bargain and sell unto the said
                            <persName>S. L. Parker</persName>, <persName>W. E. Spalding</persName>,
                        and <persName>Gabriel Cokely</persName>, their executors, administrators and
                        assigns, servant girl <persName>Mary</persName> a slave for life, and the
                        said <persName>Mary</persName> being the same servant girl who belonged
                        heretofore to <persName>Mary Weems</persName> late of <placeName>Prince
                            George's County Maryland</placeName>, to have and to hold the said
                        servant girl <persName>Mary</persName> as above bargained and sold to them
                        the said purchasers their Executors administrators and assigns forever, and
                        I the said <persName>Walter W. W. Bowie</persName> for myself my executors,
                        administrators and heirs, title to the said <persName>Mary</persName> as a
                        slave for life, unto the said Purchasers, their Executors, administrators
                        and assigns against me the said <persName>W. W. W. Bowie</persName> my
                        executors administrators and against all and every person or persons
                        whatsoever shall and will warrant and defend by these presents.</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal this <date
                            when="1850-03-01">first day of March in the year of our Lord eighteen
                            hundred and fifty</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Walter W. W. Bowie</persName> Seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00332.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>Washington D.C.</placeName><lb/><date when="1861-12-20"
                            >December 20th 1861</date>.</dateline>
                    <p>For value received we and each of us by these presents transfer and assign
                        set over and deliver unto <persName>Gabriel Coakley</persName> his executors
                        administrators and assigns All our right title and interest in and to the
                        within named <persName>Mary</persName> a slave for life</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Southey S. Parker</persName> seal</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Wm E. Spalding</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Acknowledged before me this <date when="1861-12-20">20th day of December
                            1861</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>N Callan</persName> JP seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00332.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Gabriel Coakley</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>G
                                    Coakley</persName></seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-14"><seg
                                type="handwritten">14th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten"
                                >May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>N.
                                    Callan</persName> JPeace</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>332</ab>
                <ab><persName>Gabriel Coakley</persName>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-20">May 20, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>S. S. Parker</persName>, <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice><lb/>
                    <persName>W. E. Spaulding</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice>.</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
