<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00406">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of George M. Sothoron, 23 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
            <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00406</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of George M. Sothoron, 23 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-23">May 23, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of George M. Sothoron, 23 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-23">May 23, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>George M. Sothoron</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Robert White</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values @ facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2013-01-24" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
         <change when="2012-10-23" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00406.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress entitled "an Act for
                    the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>".</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <persName>George M. Sothoron</persName> of <placeName>Georgetown
                        D. C.</placeName> by this his petition in writing, represents and states,
                    that he is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName> who at the
                    time of the passage of the said act of Congress held a claim to labor and
                    service against one person of African descent of the name of <persName>Basil
                        Gross</persName> for and during the life of the said <persName>Basil
                        Gross</persName>, and that by said Act of Congress said <persName>Basil
                        Gross</persName>, was discharged and freed of and from all claim of your
                    petitioner to such service or labor: that at the time of said discharge said
                        <persName>Basil Gross</persName> was about the age of thirty nine years and
                    of the following personal description viz: about five feet five inches high of a
                    dark brown color nearly black, scar on left wrist and perfectly sound and
                    healthy: that your petitioner acquired his claim to the aforesaid service or
                    labor, of said <persName>Basil Gross</persName>, in manner following, the said
                        <persName>Basil Gross</persName>, was owned by my father the late Dr.
                        <persName>A. Sothoron</persName>, who died possessed of him, and was
                    inherited by my brother <persName>John W. Sothoron</persName>, and
                    myself,&#8212;and <persName>Jno. W. Sothoron</persName>'s conveyance to this
                    petitioner of all his right in and to the said <persName>Basil Gross</persName>,
                    is duly recorded in the land records of this <placeName>County of
                        Washington</placeName>, in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>:
                    that your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Basil
                        Gross</persName> was, at the time of his said discharge therefrom of the
                    value of One thousand two hundred dollars in money&#8212;that your petitioner is
                    unaware of any mental, moral or physical defect in said <persName>Basil
                        Gross</persName>, who was always healthy and was a sound able-bodied man in
                    Every respect.</p>
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that he bears true and faithful allegiance to the
                    Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has not
                    borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                    rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto: and he also further
                    states and alleges, that he has not brought said <persName>Basil
                        Gross</persName> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since
                    the passage of said act of Congress; and that at the time of the passage of said
                    act, said <persName>Basil Gross</persName> was then held to service and labor
                    therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                    labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states that said claim to the service and labor of said
                        <persName>Basil Gross</persName> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00406.002.jpg"/> any manner aided or sustained the present
                    rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>:
                    Wherefore your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and
                    determine the validity of his said claim to the service or labor of said
                        <persName>Basil Gross</persName> hereinbefore<!-- sic --> set forth: and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value
                    thereof in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to said act of
                    Congress.</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="underline">Geo M. Sothoron</hi>
                 </persName>
               </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
               <lb/>
                    <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> to wit:</dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>George M Sothoron</persName> being duly sworn do depose and say
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition as of my own knowledge are true in substance and
                        fact, and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated as from the information of others I believe to be true in
                        substance and fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                     <persName>Geo M. Sothoron</persName>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to &#38; subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-23">23d day of
                            May A. D. 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                     <persName>Robert White</persName> Justice Peace seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Witnesses for Claimant&#8212;<lb/>
                        <persName>John W. Sothoron</persName>.</ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00406.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>406</ab>
                <ab>Claim of <persName>
                  <hi rend="underline">Geo. M. Sothoron</hi>
              </persName>
               <lb/> one slave.<lb/>
                    <persName>
                  <hi rend="underline">Basil Gross</hi>
              </persName>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-23">May 23, 1862</date>
            </ab>
                <ab>Jones &#38; Ashford<lb/> for Petitioner</ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>John W. Sothoron</persName>
               <lb/> Dr. <persName>J. S. Lauck</persName>
               <lb/>
                    <placeName>Georgetown, D. C.</placeName>
            </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>