<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00515">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Christopher Grammer, 28 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
               <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
               <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00515</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Christopher Grammer, 28 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Christopher Grammer, 28 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Christopher Grammer</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>John S. Hollinghead</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-01-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-09" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-10-05" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2011-05-02" who="#rv">checked</change>
         <change when="2011-01-13" who="#bj">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00515.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main">
                    <seg type="handwritten">Statement</seg>
                    <lb/>
                </head>
                <p>To the Commissioners under the Act of Congress, approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April 1862</date> entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>
                <p>The undersigned <persName>Christopher Grammer</persName> of the city of
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName> and <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> Executer of the late <persName>Gottlieb C.
                        Grammer</persName> late of said City, by this his statement in writing
                    represents and states that he is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who at the time of the passage of the said Act of
                    Congress, held a claim to service or labor against a female person of African
                    descent of the name of <persName>Lucretia Leonard</persName> for and during the
                    life of the said <persName>Lucretia</persName> and that by said Act of Congress
                    said <persName>Lucretia</persName> was discharged and freed of and from all claim
                    of the undersigned, to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <persName>Lucretia</persName> was of the age of fifty eight years as the
                    undersigned is informed and believes; and of the personal description following:
                    a mulatto, rather low of stature and well-set, her height being five feet one
                    inch nearly; face freckles; she has a wart or mole (small &#38; not
                    noticeable unless she is closely observed) under the right eye; her deportment
                    and manner is sedate, respectful &#38; civil. That the undersigned acquired
                    his claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said
                        <persName>Lucretia</persName> in manner following: the said
                        <persName>Lucretia</persName> was the slave for life of the Father of the
                    undersigned, the said <persName>Gottlieb C. Grammer</persName> who purchased her
                    for the term of

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00515.002.jpg"/>
                    
                    of her life at the sale that was made sometime in the year <date when="1839">1839</date> of the slaves of the late <persName>Joseph Kent</persName>
                    formerly Governor of <placeName>Maryland</placeName> and a senator therefrom of
                    the <placeName>United States</placeName>, by the Executor of the said
                        <persName>Joseph Kent</persName>; that undersigned has been informed and
                    believes that the said <persName>Lucretia</persName> was born a slave in the
                    family of said <persName>Joseph Kent</persName> and had continued as such
                    therein until the date of said sale; that the said facts of her servitude as
                    aforesaid, and the legal sale of her as aforesaid, together with the fact of her
                    age as herein stated are within the knowledge recollection of Mr. <persName>DeWitt Kent</persName> a son of the said <persName>Joseph Kent</persName>, now
                    a clerk in the Land Office in this City who will testify to the truth thereof,
                    if summoned; that the undersigned knows of his personal knowledge that his said
                    Father went to said sale in order to purchase some family servants; and that he
                    returned with the said <persName>Lucretia</persName> and that since then he had
                    held &#38; claimed her as his slave for life until his death which
                    occurred on the <date when="1857-01-14">14th day of January 1857</date>; the
                    undersigned further states that he has made diligent search among his Father's
                    paper for written evidence of said sale and purchase, but such, if it ever
                    existed has been lost. the undersigned further states that his said Father by
                    his last will and Testament duly proved in the Orphans Court of the
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> in said
                        <placeName>District</placeName> on the <date when="1857-01-26">26th and 28th
                        of January 1857</date> appointed the undersigned and his brother
                        <persName>Julius E. Grammer</persName> (now a citizen of
                        <placeName>Columbus, Ohio</placeName>) his Executors; that Letters
                    Testamentary were granted to them accordingly

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00515.003.jpg"/>
                    
                    on the <date when="1857-01-26">26th day of January 1857</date>, and which
                    undersigned is ready to exhibit when thereto required</p>
                <p>&#8212;That the claim of the undersigned to the service or labor of the said
                        <persName>Lucretia</persName> was at the time of said discharge therefrom of
                    the value of Four Hundred Dollars (400$) which estimate is based upon the
                    following facts: the said <persName>Lucretia</persName> possesses a sound
                    constitution and excellent heath; and looks in the opinion of the undersigned
                    much younger than the age herein stated; is free, so far as the undersigned
                    after inquiring, &#38; from his own observation, known, from all maladies,
                    excepting some liability to rheumatism&#8212;the only severe attack of which, that the undersigned knows or has be informed
                    of, did not disable her from her
                    work &#38; duties except for a few days; that the said
                        <persName>Lucretia</persName> was at the time of said discharge an
                    experienced, faithful, honest, trustworthy, efficient, and affectionate
                    &#38; respectful family servant identified with and valued and regarded by
                    all of them for these qualities that she was a very good cook and very good and
                    experienced nurse; that for the last two years she has been hired out &#38;
                    obtained wages varying from six to Eight Dollars per month; and the undersigned
                    knows of no moral or mental or physical defects other than the above stated to
                    impair the value of his claim to her service or labor.</p>
                <p>The undersigned hereby declares that he bears true faithful allegiance to the
                    Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName> and that he has not borne
                    <choice><sic>arms arms</sic><corr>arms</corr></choice> against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                    rebellion nor in any way given aid

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00515.004.jpg"/>
                    or comfort thereto.</p>
                <p>And the undersigned further states and alleges that he has not brought the said
                        <persName>Lucretia</persName> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of the said Act of Congress and that
                    at the time of the passage thereof said <persName>Lucretia</persName> was held
                    to service or labor therein under and by virtue of the undersigned's claim to
                    such service or labor.</p>
                <p>The undersigned further states and alleges that his said claim to the service or
                    labor of the said <persName>Lucretia</persName> does not originate in or by
                    virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided
                    or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                <p>And the undersigned asks that the said Commissioners will investigate and
                    determine the validity of his said claim to the service or labor of the said
                        <persName>Lucretia</persName> herein before set forth; and that if the
                    same be found to be valid that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName> in conformity to the provisions of
                    said Act of Congress&#8212;</p>
                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Christopher Grammer</persName> <choice><abbr>Exr</abbr><expan>Executor</expan></choice> of late
                                <persName>Gottlieb C. Grammer</persName>
                 </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00515.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName> to wit:</dateline>
                <p>
                    I <persName>Christopher Grammer</persName>, the party on a
                    king the foregoing statement &#38; signing the same, being duly sworn do
                    depose and say that all the several mattes and things which are set forth and
                    stated in the foregoing Statement as of my own knowledge are true in substance
                    and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated as from the information of others, I
                    believe to be true in substance and in fact</p>
                <closer> 
                    <signed><persName>Christopher Grammer</persName></signed>
                </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-28">28th day of
                            May 1862 AD 1862</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>John S. Hollingshead</persName><lb/>
                                Notary public</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                <p>I, <persName>DeWitt Kent</persName>, the person named in the
                    foregoing Statement of <persName>Christopher Grammer</persName> being duly sworn
                    do depose and say that I have carefully read his said statement: that I know the
                    mulatto woman <persName>Lucretia</persName> therein named and described, 
                    perfectly well and have recently seen her in this city both before and since the
                    passage of the said act of <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date> and
                    since the sale and purchase of her by the said <persName>Gottlieb C.
                        Grammer</persName> of my Father's Executor and the manner set forth in the
                    foregoing statement I have known her as the slave of the said <persName>Gottlieb
                        C. Grammer</persName> and his legal representation and I so further depose
                    and say that the other facts therein set forth as being within my personal
                    knowledge and recollection are true and that I will testify to the truth thereof
                    before any Court or commission whenever summoned; and I further offer and
                    say that in my judgment the estimate of Four Hundred Dollars

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00515.006.jpg"/>
                    is a fair and just estimate of her value</p> 
                  <closer>
                      <signed><persName>DeWitt Kent</persName><lb/>
                      Notary</signed>
                  </closer>
                </div2>
            
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me a Notary Public in and for the county
                    aforesaid, this <date when="1862-05-28">28th day of May A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>John S. Hollingshead</persName><lb/>
                            Notary Public</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>515<lb/>
                    Statement of <persName>Chr. Grammer</persName> <choice><abbr>Exr</abbr><expan>Executor</expan></choice>. of <persName>G C
                        Grammer</persName> in the matter of <persName>Lucretia Leonard</persName> an Emancipated Slave under the act of <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>DeWitt Kent</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Wm B. Todd</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>