<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00890">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Joseph S. Wilson, 11 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00890</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Joseph S. Wilson, 11 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Joseph S. Wilson, 11 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Joseph S. Wilson</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Isaac Nesbitt</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-12-18" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00890.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date
                        when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <persName>Joseph S. Wilson</persName> of <placeName>Washington
                        City D.C.</placeName> by this, his petition, in writing, represents, and
                    States that he is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service, or labor against a female person of African descent of the name of
                        <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> for, and during the life of said
                        <persName>Mary Harrison</persName>, and that by said act of Congress, said
                        <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> was discharged, and freed of and from all
                    claim of your petitioner to such service or labor, that at the time of said
                    discharge said <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> was of the age of about
                    Eighteen, and of the personal description following:&#8212;of dark color and
                    ordinary height, healthy and robust.</p>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired his claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said
                        <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> in manner following:&#8212;by purchase
                    from <persName>Wm. H. Hager</persName> of <placeName>Maryland</placeName> in
                        <date when="1855">1855</date>, for the consideration of $350, (three hundred
                    and fifty dollars) as shown by the copy Bill of sale hereto annexed.</p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Mary
                        Harrison</persName>, was to him at the time of said discharge therefrom, of at
                    least of the value <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00890.007.jpg"/> of $750.
                    (seven hundred and fifty dollars) in money, which he regards a low valuation
                    estimating her worth according to the value of her services, or the cost of
                    hired labor of the same character&#8212;that said <persName>Mary</persName> was
                    to the best of his knowledge and belief sound and vigorous at the date of her
                    emancipation, although petitioner had heard it mentioned by a member of his
                    family, that there was a supposed cast or defect in one of her eyes; yet the
                    said petitioner never heard the said <persName>Mary</persName> complain of it,
                    nor does it according to his belief injure the value of her services, for had
                    the petitioner at any time within the last eighteen months preceding the said
                    act been desirous of disposing of his claim to the services of the said
                        <persName>Mary</persName> he would not have done so at as low a valuation as
                    now presented</p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that he bears true and faithful allegiance to the
                    Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has not
                    borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                    rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that he has not brought said
                        <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> was
                    held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim
                    to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that his said claim to the service or
                    labor of said <persName>Mary Harrison</persName>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00890.003.jpg"/> does not originate in or by
                    virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided
                    or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, the purchase by him having been made
                    years before the commencement of the said rebellion</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of his said claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Mary
                        Harrison</persName> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be
                    valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and
                    report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said act of
                    Congress.</p>

                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Jos. S Wilson</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>Joseph S. Wilson</persName> being duly sworn, do depose and say,
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in
                        fact; and that all the the several matters and things therein set forth and
                        stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance
                        and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Jos. S Wilson</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-11">11th day of July A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Petitioner refers in proof of facts set forth to Mr <persName>Jos W Nairn</persName> <address><addrLine>corner Pennsylvania Avenue &#38; 9 Street</addrLine></address></ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00890.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <fw>Copy</fw>
                    <p>Know all men by these presents, that I <persName>William H. Hager</persName>
                        of <placeName>Hagerstown</placeName>, <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, of the first part, for and in consideration of the
                        sum of Three hundred and fifty dollars, lawful money of the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName>, to me in hand paid, at or before
                        the ensealing and delivery of these presents, by <persName>Joseph S.
                            Wilson</persName> of <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, and
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, of the second part, the
                        receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged, have bargained and sold, and by
                        these presents, to grant and convey, unto the said party of the second part,
                        his executors, administrators and assigns, one colored girl, a Slave, named
                            <persName>Mary Harrison</persName>. To have and To hold the said
                            <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> unto the said party of the second
                        part, his executors, administrators and assigns, for ever.&#8212;And I do
                        for myself and my heirs executors and administrators, covenant and agree, to
                        and with the said party of the second part, to warrant and defend the sale
                        of the said <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> hereby sold, unto the said
                        party of the second part, his executors, administrators and assigns, against
                        all and every person and persons whomsoever.&#8212;In witness whereof I have
                        hereunto set my hand and seal this <date when="1855-10-04">fourth day of
                            October one thousand eight hundred and fifty five</date>.&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>(Signed) <signed><persName>Wm. H. Hager</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Signed sealed and delivered in presence of</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>J. Cook</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Jno. L. Smith</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, <placeName>Washington
                        County</placeName> to wit,</dateline> <p>Be it remembered, and it is hereby certified
                        that on this <date when="1855-10-04">4th day of October 1855</date>, before
                        the Subscribers, Two Justices of the peace of the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>, in and for the said County, personally appeared
                            <persName>William H. Hager</persName>, he being known to us of our own
                        knowledge to be the person who is named and described as and professing <pb
                            xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00890.005.jpg"/> to be a party to the
                        foregoing Bill of Sale and doth acknowledge the said indenture or instrument
                        of writing to be his act and deed&#8212;In Testimony whereof, we hereunto
                        subscribe our names on the day and year aforesaid.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>J. Cook</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Jno. L. Smith</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, <placeName>Washington
                        County</placeName>. To Wit:</dateline> <p>I hereby certify that <persName>J.
                            Cook</persName> &#38; <persName>Jno. L. Smith</persName> <choice><abbr>Esqres</abbr><expan>Esquires</expan></choice> before whom the above acknowledgement was made, and who have
                        thereunto subscribed their names, were at the time of so doing two Justices
                        of the Peace of the <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>, in and for
                        said county, duly elected, commissioned and sworn.&#8212;</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof, I hereunto Subscribe my name, and affix the seal of the
                        Circuit Court for said County, this <date when="1855-10-04">4th day of
                            October A.D. 1855</date>.&#8212;</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Isaac Nesbitt</persName> <choice><abbr>Clk</abbr><expan>clerk</expan></choice><lb/>
                            seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00890.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>890</ab>
                <ab>Petition of <persName>Jos. S. Wilson</persName> in the case of
                        <persName>Mary Harrison</persName> before the Commissioners under Act of
                        <date when="1862-04-16">16th April 1862</date>, Entitled "an act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-11">11 July 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
