<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00025">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Fanny B. Ewell, 5 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
<name xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</name>
               <name xml:id="am">Adam
                    Minakowski</name>
               <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
               <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00025</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Fanny B. Ewell, 5 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-05">May 5, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Fanny B. Ewell, 5 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-05">May 5, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775&#8211;1978, National Archives and
                                        Records Administration</orgName>
<note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                                microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>
                    Fanny B. Ewell
               </persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>
                    John D. Clark
               </persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-01-20" who="#jc">revised schema declaration</change>
          <change when="2012-04-06" who="#jc">blessed</change>
          <change when="2012-04-01" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-02-15" who="#el">automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
<change when="2012-02-14" who="#el">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary</change>
          <change when="2011-08-22" who="#bj">checked</change>
          <change when="2011-07-08" who="#rv">checked</change>
          <change when="2010-11-01" who="#am">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00025.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p>To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">April 16, 1862</date>, entitled "an act for the release of
                    certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <persName>Fanny B. Ewell</persName> of the <placeName>city of
                        Washington &#38; District of Columbia</placeName> respectfully showeth,
                    that at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, she held a claim to
                    the service or labor against the following persons of African descent to wit:
                        <persName>Fanny Martin</persName>, <persName>Davy Martin</persName>,
                        <persName>Moses Martin</persName>, <persName>Louisa Curtis</persName>,
                        <persName>Francis Curtis</persName>, <persName>Margret Curtis</persName>,
                        <persName>George Curtis</persName>, and <persName>Mary Curtis</persName>,
                    for and during the life of said persons &#38; that by the said act of
                    Congress the said persons were discharged &#38; freed of and from all claim
                    of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of the said
                    discharge of the said persons, they were of the ages and description, to wit: </p>
                <p>
               <persName>Fanny Martin</persName> is a small woman of light color and about the
                    age of 60 years. well &#38; active</p>
                <p>
               <persName>Davy Martin</persName> is a small man, dark color, a very efficient
                    porter and has been employed by <persName>Mr. W. Orme</persName> for the past
                    eight years receiving good wages; he is 58 or 59 years of age. </p>
                <p>
               <persName>Moses Martin</persName> is a man of bright countenance and pleasing
                    manner, is employed as chief cook at the <placeName>Elliott House</placeName>,
                    receiving good wages; he is 24 years of age</p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00025.002.jpg"/>

                <p>
                  <persName>Louisa Curtis</persName> is a small bright woman, a smart and efficient
                    servant and has been recently sick but is now quite improved in health; she is
                    89 years of age. <persName>Frances Curtis</persName>, is a girl of light color, lively and
                        pleasing manners, good disposition and character and a very good servant; she is
                        17 years of age. <persName>Margret Curtis</persName>, is a girl of light color, a very capable and
                        efficient servant; she is 15 years of age. <persName>George Curtis</persName> is a small boy for his age but uncommonly
                        smart &#38; useful; he is 11 years of age. <persName>Mary Curtis</persName> is a girl of dark color, healthy and smart; she
                        is 7 years of age. That she acquired title to the service of the aforesaid persons by descent from
                        her parents <persName>Jesse</persName> &#38; <persName>Mildred
                            Ewell</persName> of <placeName>Prince Wm Co Va</placeName> in <date when="1848">1848</date>.
            </p>
                    
                    <p>That the service or labor of the aforesaid persons was at the time of this
                        discharge by the said act of Congress of the value of six thousand dollars to
                        wit: <persName>Fanny</persName>, three hundred, <persName>Davy</persName>, eight
                        hundred, <persName>Moses</persName>, two thousand, <persName>Louisa</persName>,
                        four hundred, <persName>Francis</persName>, nine hundred,
                        <persName>Margret</persName>, seven hundred, <persName>George</persName>,
                        six hundred, and <persName>Mary</persName>, three hundred dollars.</p>
                    <p>That your petitioner has been loyal to the Government of the United States, and
                        that she has not borne arms against the United States in the present rebellion,
                        nor given aid 
                        
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00025.003.jpg"/> or comfort to the
                        enemy.</p>
                    
                    <p>Your petitioner further represents that sometime during the winter of <date when="1851">1851</date>, she came from <placeName>Virginia</placeName> to
                        reside in the <placeName>city of Wasington DC</placeName> and removed at the
                        same time, the aforesaid persons to the latter place, where she had them
                        registered according to law in the clerks office of the Circuit Court for the
                        District of Columbia when they remained domiciled to the time of the passage of
                        the said act subject to &#38; by virtue of your petitioners claim to such
                    </p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further represents that her claim to the service or labor of said
                                persons does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by
                                any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion
                                against the <placeName>United States</placeName> Government.</p>
                            
                            <p>And your petitioner therefore prays the said commissioners to investigate and
                                determine the validity of her said claim to the service or labor of said persons
                                herein above mentioned, and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise
                                &#38; apportion the value of said claim in money and report the same to the
                                Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions
                                of said act of Congress.</p>
                            
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName>Fanny B. Ewell</persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00025.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>Fanny B. Ewell</persName> of the <placeName>city of
                            Washington</placeName> being duly sworn according to law, do depose and
                        say, that all the several matters &#38; things which are set forth
                        &#38; stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true
                        in substance and fact; and all the other matters and things coming to me
                        from others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>Fanny B. Ewell</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to &#38; subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-03">3rd day
                            of May 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>John D. Clark</persName>
                        </signed> JP </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>25</ab>
                <ab>To the commissioners under the act of Congress to release certain
                    persons held to service or labor in the District of Columbia<lb/>
            </ab>
                <ab> Petition of <persName>Fanny B Ewell</persName>
               <lb/>
            </ab>
                <ab>
               <persName>Carl C. W. Davis,</persName>
               <lb/> Baltimore, Md.<lb/>
            </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-05">May 5, 1862</date>
            </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
