<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.02517">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Our Washington Correspondence</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <editor role="co-editor">R. J. Weir</editor>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Elizabeth Lorang</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bw">Becca Weir</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.02517</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>
                        <email>cdrh@unl.edu</email>
                    </addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2015</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington and R. J. Weir, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="letter">
                    <analytic>
                        <author ref="#sgb">S. G. B.</author>
                        <title level="a">Our Washington Correspondence</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The Anglo-African</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1863-11-28">28 November 1863</date>                    
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="pp">[2]</biblScope>                    
                    </monogr>           
                </biblStruct>
                
                <biblStruct xml:id="issue">               
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>                  
                        </imprint>              
                    </monogr>                   
                </biblStruct>                        
            </sourceDesc>       
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc> 
            <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName xml:id="sgb">Brown, Solomon G., 1829?-1906</persName>
                <persName xml:id="rh">Hamilton, Robert</persName>
                <persName xml:id="th">Hamilton, Thomas</persName>
                <date when="1863">1863</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-US">modern American English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <classCode scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov">
                    <term xml:id="sh2009113992">African American soldiers--History--19th century</term>
                    <term xml:id="sh2009113967">African Americans--Civil rights--History--19th century</term>
                    <term xml:id="sh2009114063">African Americans--Washington (D.C.)</term>
                    <term xml:id="n83192912">Brown, Solomon G., 1829?-1906</term>
                    <term xml:id="n96115353">Casey, T. L. (Thomas Lincoln), 1831-1896</term>
                    <term xml:id="n82214557">Ross, John, 1790-1866</term>
                    <term xml:id="no2012113158">United States. Army Headquarters Area Command. Office of the Provost Marshal</term>
                    <term xml:id="n93053256">United States. Colored Troops.</term>
                    <term xml:id="sh2007100004">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Participation, African American</term>
                </classCode>
                <classCode scheme="http://civilwardc.org">
                    <term>Fellows, Stark</term>
                    <term>Todd, Henry B.</term>
                </classCode>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-04-07" who="#ak">corrected</change>
            <change when="2015-03-31" who="#el">checked and corrected transcription and encoding; updated TEI header, including keywords</change>
            <change when="2015-03-30" who="#ak">added keywords</change>
            <change when="2015-02-24" who="#ak">checked, corrected, updated xml:id</change>
            <change when="2014-11-12" who="#ak">checked transcription, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <facsimile corresp="#issue">
        <surface xml:id="pp1">
            <graphic url="aa.18631128.pp1.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp2">
            <graphic url="aa.18631128.pp2.jpg"/>
            <zone xml:id="pp2_cropped" corresp="#letter">
                <graphic url="aa.18631128.pp2_cropped.jpg"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp3">
            <graphic url="aa.18631128.pp3.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp4">
            <graphic url="aa.18631128.pp4.jpg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    
    <text corresp="#letter #pp2_cropped">
        <body>
            
            <head type="main" subtype="authorial" rend="center">OUR WASHINGTON CORRESPONDENCE.</head>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="medium-bar"/>
            
            <opener>
                <dateline rend="right"><emph rend="smallcaps">Washington</emph>, D. C., Nov. 15, 1863.</dateline>
            </opener>
            
            <div>
                <p>
                    <emph rend="smallcaps">We</emph> take the following from the Washington<lb/>
                    Sunday <hi rend="italic"><title level="j">Chronicle</title></hi> of Nov. 15th.</p>
                
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <p><emph rend="smallcaps">"Review Of The 2d United States Colored <lb/>Troops By Major-General Casey</emph>.&#8212;The 2d<lb/>
                            regiment United States colored troops, <choice><orig>Lieute-<lb/>nant-Colonel</orig><reg>Lieutenant-Colonel</reg></choice> S. Fellows commanding, were <choice><orig>re-<lb/>viewed</orig><reg>reviewed</reg></choice> yesterday afternoon at Meridan Hill by <lb/>Major-General Casey.  The day was very fair, <lb/>and all that could be desired for such a <choice><orig>pur-<lb/>pose</orig><reg>purpose</reg></choice>, except that it was rather dusty.  The <lb/>2d colored troops were raised in and around <lb/>this city, and it is the second colored regiment <lb/>raised in the District.  For some time past <lb/>they have been stationed at Camp Chase, <lb/>about three miles across the Long Bridge. <lb/>They have been an organization nearly two <lb/>months.  The regiment left their camp about <lb/>10 o'clock, a. m., six hundred strong, and <choice><orig>com-<lb/>menced</orig><reg>commenced</reg></choice> the march for the Hill, which, from <lb/>their encampment, is in the neighborhood of <lb/>six miles distant.  All but one company took <lb/>up the line of march.  This company remained <lb/>behind to take care of the camp.  The roads <lb/>were very dusty, and before they had gone any <lb/>distance they were covered with dust, but <choice><orig>un-<lb/>mindful</orig><reg>unmindful</reg></choice> of this, they kept on and reached <lb/>Meridan Hill at 1&#189; o'clock.  Upon their <lb/>arrival at this point, a large crowd both white <lb/>and black, including not a few ladies, were in <lb/>waiting, eager to witness them in their <choice><orig>evolu-<lb/>tions</orig><reg>evolutions</reg></choice>.  Among the visitors we noticed John <lb/>Ross, the celebrated Indian Chief of the <choice><orig>Chero-<lb/>kee</orig><reg>Cherokee</reg></choice> nation, who appeared to take a lively <choice><orig>inter-<lb/>est</orig><reg>interest</reg></choice> in the man&#339;uvres of the troops.  Gen. <lb/>Casey appeared on the ground in a carriage, <lb/>accompanied by a portion of his family and <choice><orig>sur-<lb/>rounded</orig><reg>surrounded</reg></choice> by a number of his staff.  The ground <lb/>was also covered with a host of line officers, <lb/>from the various regiments quartered in the <lb/>vicinity.  The troops were then put in a <choice><orig>posi-<lb/>tion</orig><reg>position</reg></choice> for going through the manual of arms. <lb/>After a fatiguing march of six miles we would <lb/>not think they would be in a good condition to <lb/>drill, but they went through the whole manual <lb/>like veterans.  As we said before, they have <lb/>only been under instruction for the past two <lb/>months, yet every movement was promptly <lb/>and beautifully executed with scarcely a fault. <lb/>The regiment was man&#339;uvered by <choice><orig>Lieutenant-<lb/>Colonel</orig><reg>Lieutenant-Colonel</reg></choice> Fellows, who handled them as if he <choice><orig>un-<lb/>derstood</orig><reg>understood</reg></choice> his business.  They marched and <lb/>countermarched, formed into a hollow square <lb/>and formed in line of battle and other <choice><orig>move-<lb/>ments</orig><reg>movements</reg></choice> incidental upon the battalion drill, which <lb/>elicited both surprise and pleasure from the <lb/>lookers on, particularly the soldiers belonging <lb/>to the Invalid corps, who were present in large <lb/>numbers.  After going through the evolutions <lb/>for about two hours they passed in review <lb/>around the carriage of General Casey, headed <lb/>by a band of music which discoursed some <lb/>spirited airs.  General Casey was much <choice><orig>sur-<lb/>prised</orig><reg>surprised</reg></choice> at their aptness and precision in the <lb/>drill, and expressed himself as extremely <choice><orig>satis-<lb/>fied</orig><reg>satisfied</reg></choice> with their behavior, and had no doubt if <lb/>they should ever get into battle that they <lb/>would stand up to the work like heroes, and <lb/>never desert the old flag until the last man had <lb/>shed his life-blood in its defence.</p>
                        
                        <p>After passing in review before the General, <lb/>they filed out into the road and took up the <lb/>march for camp, the large crowd following. <lb/>When near the city the dust was somewhat <lb/>settled by a shower of rain, which also <choice><orig>fur-<lb/>nished</orig><reg>furnished</reg></choice> the men with a bath before reaching <lb/>their tents.  The men are composed of fine <choice><orig>ma-<lb/>terial</orig><reg>material</reg></choice>, and look as if they would render <choice><orig>excel-<lb/>lent</orig><reg>excellent</reg></choice> service for their country.  Some of the <lb/>non-commissioned officers we noticed <choice><orig>particu-<lb/>larly</orig><reg>particularly</reg></choice> were splendid models of the soldier.  The <lb/>commissioned officers were all men of <choice><orig>educa-<lb/>tion</orig><reg>education</reg></choice> and refinement, and before being placed <lb/>in their positions passed through a thorough <lb/>and rigid examination.  They are true men <lb/>and tried.  At the conclusion of the drill and <lb/>review, the large crowd of visitors returned to <lb/>the city, satisfied that the colored troops, if <lb/>opportunity offered, would faithfully perform <lb/>their duty.</p></body>
                </floatingText>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>CITY PASSENGER CARS FOR COLORED PERSONS.</head>
                
                <p>The cars now running up and down <choice><orig>Pennsyl-<lb/>vania</orig><reg>Pennsylvania</reg></choice> Avenue for the accommodation of colored <lb/>persons are entirely inadequate to the wants <lb/>of the colored public. There are but seven <lb/>cars on where we should have twenty, for one <lb/>has to wait from twenty to twenty-five minutes <lb/>for a passing car and when it reaches you it is <lb/>full.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head type="main" subtype="authorial" rend="cente">BURGLARY.</head>
                
                <p>We are quite sorry to record the fact that <lb/>Mrs. Susan Tenny's house was robbed one <lb/>evening last week of $150 in money.  Mrs. <lb/>Tenny is an industrious, respectable lady, and <lb/>has amassed a little property.  She is an <choice><orig>ac-<lb/>tive</orig><reg>active</reg></choice> member of the Union Relief Association <lb/>and is generally forward in all good works. <lb/>We hope this heartless thief may be <choice><orig>appre-<lb/>hended</orig><reg>apprehended</reg></choice>.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head type="main" subtype="authorial" rend="center">THE PROVOST MARSHAL'S OFFICE.</head>
                
                <p><title level="j" rend="italic">The Daily Republican</title> of this city in its issue <lb/>of Nov. 4th has an article headed as above.  In <lb/>it the editor speaks of the excellent and <choice><orig>busi-<lb/>ness-like</orig><reg>business-like</reg></choice> manner the affairs of the office are <lb/>conducted and in conclusion says: "We have <lb/>thus endeavored to give an idea as to how <lb/>things are done.  To the many of our readers <lb/>who have business in the department, we hope <lb/>it may be of some benefit.  From the captain <lb/>to the humblest clerk are perfect gentlemen&#8212; <lb/>polite and affable to all who come to them."</p>
                
                <p>Now, Mr. Editor, I do not think that the <lb/>editor of <title level="j" rend="italic">The Republican</title> would knowingly <lb/>misrepresent this department, but in the <choice><orig>afore-<lb/>said</orig><reg>aforesaid</reg></choice> article he has greatly misrepresented it. <lb/>If any one would take the pains to go to this <lb/>office and observe how persons of color are <lb/>treated they could not agree with <title level="j" rend="italic">The <choice><orig>Republi-<lb/>can</orig><reg>Republican</reg></choice></title> that the officers are polite and affable.  If <lb/>a colored gentleman or lady has any business <lb/>with the Provost Marshal or any one of his <lb/>officers, he or she is made to stand at the <choice><orig>door-<lb/>way</orig><reg>doorway</reg></choice>, along the pavement or sidewalk in the <lb/>rain or sun, or whatever the weather may be, <lb/>for hours at a time, or until some <choice><orig>ungentle-<lb/>manly</orig><reg>ungentlemanly</reg></choice> orderly <choice><orig>choses</orig><reg>chooses</reg></choice> to admit them by the <lb/>guard who paces the street door in pomp, and <lb/>when this consequential orderly <choice><sic>choses</sic><corr>chooses</corr></choice> to come <lb/>down, he does it in a most disrespectful <choice><orig>man-<lb/>ner</orig><reg>manner</reg></choice>, demanding your name, age, residence, <lb/>occupation and desire, all of which he has no <lb/>right to know.  Very often the questions are <lb/>put to cause merriment for those hanging <lb/>about the door.  He will them admit just whom <lb/>he pleases.  When you get in you are made to <lb/>stand around the far corner of a rail jammed <lb/>up as close as you can get to each other, for <lb/>fear that you may touch the hem of some white <lb/>person's garment and defile it.  The officers <lb/>then begin their rough overhauling and should <lb/>you want a pass, you are put through the mill <lb/>in a very rough manner.  At length your pass <lb/>is ready and shoved at you and you leave the <lb/>office vexed and entertaining very hard <choice><orig>feel-<lb/>ings</orig><reg>feelings</reg></choice> against those men for thus using you only <lb/>on account of your complexion.</p>
                
                <p>It matters not how important your mission, <lb/>if your skin is dark, you are thus treated, <lb/>whilst all white persons, or those supposed to <lb/>be white, are admitted with bows and scrapes. <lb/>If a female, she is invited within the bar, a soft <lb/>seat handed her and has two or three clerks <lb/>bowing around her, all anxious to do her honor, <lb/>secessionist though she may be, while the true, <lb/>the loyal, the faithful black is subject to the <lb/>treatment described above.  We do not mean <lb/>to say that Capt. Todd is a party to this mean <lb/>conduct, for we have ever found him a <choice><orig>gentle-<lb/>man</orig><reg>gentleman</reg></choice> of the highest stamp and we feel sure that <lb/>should this meet his eye he will have the abuse <lb/>corrected.</p>
                
                <closer>
                    <signed rend="right">S. G. B.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>  
    
