<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00836">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Joseph Holt, 2 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00836</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Joseph Holt, 2 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-02">July 2, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl><title>Petition of Joseph Holt, 2 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-02">July 2, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Joseph Holt</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Nicholas Callan</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-19" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-14" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-09-25" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00836.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">

                <p>To The Honorable <persName>R. Goodloe Horatio King</persName> &#38;
                        <persName>John M. Brodhead</persName> Commissioners under the act of Congress
                    approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April 1862</date>, entitled "An
                    act for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Your Petitioner <persName>Joseph Holt</persName>, who has resided for the last
                    five years and still resides in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    respectfully represents &#38; states that he is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor a against a negro man of
                    African descent, of the name of <persName><hi rend="underline">Alfred
                        Allen</hi></persName> for and during the life of the said
                        <persName>Alfred</persName> and that by said act of Congress said
                        <persName>Alfred Allen</persName> has been discharged &#38; freed of and
                    from all claim of your Petitioner to such service or labor. That said
                        <persName>Alfred Allen</persName> at the time of the passage of said act of
                    Congress resided in the family of your Petitioner in the District aforesaid
                    &#38; had so resided since the <date when="1857">spring of 1857</date>&#8212;that he was thirty four
                    years of age in the <date when="1862-03">month of March last (1862)</date> &#38; is of the personal
                    description following: to wit, height about 5 feet, 8 or 10
                    inches&#8212;complexion black, health &#38; constitution good and sound. He has
                    served your Petitioner during the last five
                    
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00836.002.jpg"/>
                    years as coachman &#38; <choice><sic>gardiner</sic><corr>gardener</corr></choice> &#38; as such has been a faithful &#38; efficient servant.</p>
                
                <p>Your Petitioner acquired his title to the aforesaid service or labor of the said <persName>Alfred Allen</persName> in manner following: viz. The mother &#38; brother (<persName>Thomas</persName>) of your Petitioner were the owners of the said <persName>Alfred</persName>, &#38; also of a woman who was the wife of a man slave named <persName><hi rend="underline">Richard</hi></persName>, the property of your Petitioner, &#38; on your Petitioner's removal to <placeName>Washington</placeName> in the <date when="1857">spring of 1857</date>, for the purpose of enabling the said <persName>Richard</persName> to remain with his wife he exchanged him with his mother &#38; brother aforesaid, for the said <persName>Alfred</persName>&#8212;They, then transferring absolutely the said <persName>Alfred</persName> to your Petitioner &#38; he transferring to them in the same manner the said <persName>Richard</persName>&#8212;</p>
                <p>Your Petitioner states that his claim to the service or labor of the said <persName>Alfred Allen</persName>, was at the time of said discharge therefrom, as he believes of the value of from nine hundred to a thousand dollars in money.</p>
                <p>Your Petitioner hereby declares that he bears true &#38; faithful allegiance to the government of the <placeName>United States</placeName> &#38; that he has not borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                <p>And your Petitioner further
            

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00836.003.jpg"/>
            
                states and alleges that he has not brought said <persName>Alfred Allen</persName>
                    into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said
                    Act of Congress and that at the time of the passage thereof, said
                        <persName>Alfred Allen</persName> was held to service or labor therein under
                    &#38; by virtue of your Petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>
                <p>Your Petitioner further states &#38; alleges that his said claim to the service or
                    labor of said <persName>Alfred Allen</persName> originated and was perfected
                    more than five years ago, since which time his said claim has been complete
                    &#38; undisputed; that your Petitioner's mother &#38; brother by whom as already
                    stated, the said <persName>Alfred Allen</persName> &#38; the claim to his service
                    or labor were transferred, were at the time of said transfer loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, and your Petitioner has no knowledge
                    that they have in any manner since aided or sustained the present rebellion
                    against the government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>
                <p>And your Petitioner prays the said commissioners to investigate &#38; determine the
                    validity of his said claim to the service or labor of the said <persName>Alfred
                        Allen</persName> herein above set forth, &#38; if the same be found to be
                    valid that they appraise &#38; apportion the value of said claim in money, &#38;
                    report the same to the Secretary of the
                
                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00836.004.jpg"/>
                Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said Act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> <signed><persName>J. Holt</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
                 
                 <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">                     
                <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me <date when="1862-07-01">first day of July AD
                    1862</date></p>
                     <closer><signed><persName>N Callan</persName> JPeace</signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>836<lb/>
                    <persName>Joseph Holt</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-01">July 2, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
