<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00503">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Oliver H. P. Clark, 28 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="rr">Rhiannon Root</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00503</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Oliver H. P. Clark, 28 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Oliver H. P. Clark, 28 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-01-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-09" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-10-18" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2011-05-12" who="#rr">checked</change>
            <change when="2011-03-16" who="#bj">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00503.001.jpg"/>

                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Richard
                            Proctor</persName> a</seg> person of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName> has been</seg> discharged and freed of
                    and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time
                    of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">thirty seven years</seg> and of the personal description
                        following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">that is to say, the said <persName>Richard
                            Proctor</persName> is of a dark copper color, about five feet and eleven
                        inches in height &amp; weighs about one hundred and eighty pounds, wears
                        large whiskers and has a smiling pleasant countenance, had prominent
                        knuckles, otherwise no particular marks, and no scars that are remembered.
                        He is not known to have any physical defects. He is a valuable farm hand and
                        a good gardener, and a skillful driver of a team. His moral character is
                        excellent, he is honest, sober and industrious, quite intelligent and has
                        some education. He is not know to have any mental infirmity or defect.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00503.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Richard Proctor</seg>
                    in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state
                        how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Your Petitioner acquired said claim by purchase from
                            <persName>Agnes Clark</persName> and <persName>Charles H.
                            Clark</persName> in the division of the personal estate of
                            <persName>Henson Clark</persName> deceased, on the <date when="1855-05-10">10th day of May 1855</date>. amongst other property
                        not particularly named in the Bill of Sale from the said
                            <persName>Agnes</persName> and <persName>Charles H.</persName> bearing
                        the state last aforesaid, and here exhibited by your petitioner as his <gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word" quantity="9" unit="chars"/>
                        of title, the consideration for the whole of said property in said division
                        being $1200.—that the said <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>in said
                        division cost your petitioner about eight hundred dollars.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">one thousand</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">your Petitioner knows of no other facts touching the
                        said <persName>Richard Proctor</persName> except those above stated, save
                        that at the time of the passage of the said act of emancipation he was
                        getting one hundred and fifty dollars hire per annum for the said
                            <persName>Richard Proctor</persName> and his boarding &amp; clothing
                        found him. Your Petitioner knows of no defects mental or physical in the
                        said <persName>Proctor</persName>
                    </seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress;
                    and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any
                    person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against
                    the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    value of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Richard Proctor</persName>
                    </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>

            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00503.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Rec'g Paid p: 75 cts.</ab>
                    <ab><persName>Agnes Clark</persName> and <persName>Charles H.
                        Clark</persName><lb/> To<lb/>
                        <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName><lb/> Bill of Sale—</ab>
                    <ab><choice>
                            <abbr>Rec'd</abbr>
                            <expan>Received</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <date when="1855-05-29">29th May 1855</date></ab>
                    <p>To be recorded and the same day was recorded in Liber J.G.H. No 4 folios 354
                        one of the Land Records of the Circuit Court for <placeName>Montgomery
                            County</placeName> &amp; examined per</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Jas. G. Hening</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                                <expan>Clerk</expan>
                            </choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>


                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00503.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">

                    <p>Know all men by these presents, that we, <persName>Agnes Clark</persName> and
                            <persName>Charles H. Clark</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery
                            County</placeName> in the State of <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, for,
                        and in consideration of the sum of twelve hundred dollars, current money, to
                        us equally in hand paid, by <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName> of said
                        county, at, and before the sealing, and delivery of these presents, the
                        receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged, have granted, bargained, and sold,
                        assigned, <choice>
                            <sic>transfered</sic>
                            <corr>transferred</corr>
                        </choice>, and set over, and by these presents, do grant, bargain, and sell,
                        assign, release transfer, and set over unto the said <persName>Oliver H. P.
                            Clark</persName>, his executors, administrators, and assigns, all of our
                        joint, and several right, title, estate, interest, use, trust, benefit,
                        property, claim and demand whatsoever, both at law, and in equity, of, in
                        and to the personal property, and personal estate of <persName>Hanson
                            Clark</persName> lat of said County deceased; and of, in, and to the
                        personal property and personal estate of <persName>William Lemuel
                            Clark</persName>, late of said county, deceased; and we do further
                        agree, and obligate ourselves severally to the said <persName>Oliver H. P.
                            Clark</persName>, to pay, and indemnity, to him the two thirds part, of
                        all, and every debt, claim, or demand, and costs, and charges, whatsoever,
                        which now may be, or hereafter may arise against the said estates, or either
                        of them; or against the said property on account of any outstanding or
                        unsettled claim, or demand against the said estates, or either of them, in
                        any manner whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof we have hereunto set our respective hands, and seals
                        this <date when="1855-05-10">tenth day of May in the year eighteen hundred,
                            and fifty five</date></p>

                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Agnes Clark</persName> seal</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Charles H Clark</persName> seal </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00503.005.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>State of <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, <placeName>Montgomery
                            County</placeName> Sct:</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered, and it is hereby certified that on this <date when="1855-05-10">tenth day of May in the year of our Lord eighteen
                            hundred and fifty five</date> before the subscriber, a Justice of the
                        Peace of said State in and for the Fifth Election District of said County
                        personally appeared <persName>Agnes Clark</persName> and <persName>Charles
                            H. Clark</persName>, they being known to me to be the persons who are
                        named and described as and professing to be the parties to the forgoing bill
                        of sale, and the said <persName>Agnes Clark</persName> and <persName>Charles
                            H. Clark</persName> severally acknowledged the said bill of sale to be
                        their respective act and deed; and the said <persName>Oliver H. P.
                            Clark</persName> made oath that the consideration mentioned in said bill
                        of sale is true and bona fide as therein set forth. In testimony whereof I
                        have hereunto subscribed my name on the day and year first above written</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Issac P Maers</persName> JP </signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p><date when="1855-05-29">1855 May 29th</date>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>Rec'd</abbr>
                            <expan>Received</expan>
                        </choice> one dollar the stamp duty in this bill of sale</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>James G. Hening</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                                <expan>Clern</expan>
                            </choice></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00503.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Oliver H. P. Clark</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-28">
                            <seg type="handwritten">28th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>. </p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>F. I. Murphey</persName> J.P.</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>503</ab>
                <ab><hi rend="underline"><persName>Oliver H.P. Clark</persName></hi><lb/> Petition
                    for Compensation for <hi rend="underline"><persName>Richard
                        Proctor</persName></hi><lb/> a person held to service by &amp; <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">from</unclear> &amp; emancipated by
                    the act of congress of <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Jno E. Morris</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Atty</abbr>
                        <expan>Attorney</expan>
                    </choice></ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>George P. Smith</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Jedediah Gittings</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
