<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00125">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Berhard W. Reed, 9 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
               <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
               <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00125</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Berhard W. Reed, 9 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-09">May 9, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 2</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Berhard W. Reed, 9 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-09">May 9, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Berhard W. Reed</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Nicholas Callan</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-01-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-09" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-11-09" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2012-10-09" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
         <change when="2012-09-24" who="#kk">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00125.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>B. W. Reed</persName>
               </seg> of
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                  <placeName>Washington City D. C.</placeName>
               </seg>
                    by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the United
                    States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a
                    claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">the following named
                        &#8212;</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of
                    the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Lucy Jones</persName>,
                            <persName>Rebecca Henson</persName> and <persName>Jack
                        Jones</persName>.</seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Lucy Jones</persName>. <persName>Rebecca
                            Henson</persName> and <persName>Jack Jones</persName>.</seg> and that by
                    said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Lucy
                            Jones</persName>. <persName>Rebecca Henson</persName> and <persName>Jack
                            Jones</persName>. were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim
                    of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge
                    said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Lucy Jones</persName>. <persName>Rebecca
                            Henson</persName> and <persName>Jack Jones</persName>
                        <choice>
                            <sic>wer</sic>
                            <corr>were</corr>
                        </choice>
               </seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">twenty seven or twenty eight. twenty one or twenty two
                        and eight or nine. respectively.</seg> and of the personal description
                        following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note>
                
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item><persName><hi rend="underline">Lucy Jones</hi></persName> is of a copper complexion with no particular marks except a small scar on the right arm below the elbow, (a scar of a burn). about five feet six inches high.</item>
                        <item><persName><hi rend="underline">Rebecca</hi></persName> aged about twenty one or two, is of a light copper complexion, with no marks of any description about five feet-five inches high.</item>
                        <item><persName><hi rend="underline">Jack</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Jones</hi></persName>. is a bright mulatto with straight hair with no scratch or mark of any description about three feet. ten inches high.</item>                        
                    </list>
                    </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00125.002.jpg"/>
                    
                    <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his&#8212;</seg> claim
                        to the aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and
                            for what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence
                            of title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the
                            same may be found.</note>
                        <seg type="handwritten">That is to say: The said <persName>Lucy
                                Jones</persName>. and <persName>Rebecca Henson</persName> were
                            bequeath to the wife of your petitioner by the last will and testament
                            of <persName>Richard
                            Piles</persName> late of
                                <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>, in the <placeName>State of
                                Maryland</placeName> a copy of which is hereto annexed.
                                <persName>Jack Jones</persName> is the son and child of
                                <persName>Rebecca Henson</persName> and was born since his mother
                            became the property of your petitioner.</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Lucy</persName>
                            <persName>Rebecca</persName> &#38; <persName>Jack</persName>
                  </seg> was,
                        at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">2.500&#8212;</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                            there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                            labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if
                            any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of
                            said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                            service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                            petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                            impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and
                            that he believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such
                            infirmity or defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim
                            should conclude with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such
                            infirmity or defect.</note>
                  <seg type="handwritten">That is to say:
                                <persName>Lucy</persName> is valued at $1000
                                <persName>Rebecca</persName> $1000 &#38; <persName>Jack</persName>
                            $500 all of said persons were domestics in the family of your petitioner
                            and were familiar with all the duties of house servants
                                <persName>Rebecca</persName> was an excellent cook and washer and
                            attended to her duties as such most faithfully.
                                <persName>Lucy</persName> was a first rate chamber-maid and attended
                            generally to all the house work of your petitioner who has for years
                            past been in the habit of renting out the rooms in his large
                            establishment <placeName>corner of F &#38; 14th Street</placeName> all
                            these rooms were kept in order by said <persName>Lucy</persName>. Both
                            said servants were strictly honest and free from any bodily moral or
                            mental infirmities or defects other than the scar already mentioned and
                            your petitioner believes none other to exist. <persName>Jack
                                Jones</persName> is a smart, active &#38; remarkably intelligent boy
                            and very useful in and about the house.</seg>
               </p>

                    <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears
                        true and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and
                        that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United
                        States in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort
                        thereto.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Lucy</persName>, <persName>Rebecca</persName> &#38;
                                <persName>Jack</persName>
                  </seg> into the District of Columbia since
                        the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage
                        thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">servants.</seg> w<del>as</del>
                  <seg type="handwritten">ere</seg> held to service or labor therein under and
                        by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                    <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of
                        any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or
                        sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the United
                        States.</p>

                    <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine
                        the validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service
                        or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants.</seg> herein above set
                        forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                        apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the
                        Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                        provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>R. W. Reed</persName></seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00125.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Will of <lb/>
                  <persName>Richard Pile</persName>
                  <lb/>
                  <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>
                    </ab>
                    <ab>$400 $705</ab>
                    <ab>
                  <hi rend="underline">No</hi>11&#8212;</ab>
                    <ab>tax<lb/>
                    355<lb/>
                    327<lb/>
                    426<lb/>
                    355<lb/>
                    1463</ab>
                    <ab>75000<lb/>
                    5000</ab>
                </div2>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00125.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline>
                  <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> Sct:<lb/>
                  Orphans Court <date when="1828-01-17">Jany. 17th 1828</date>
               </dateline>

                    <p>In the name of God Amen. I <persName>Richard Pile</persName> of
                            <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> and State
                            of<placeName>Maryland</placeName> being in perfect health of body and of
                        sound disposing mind memory and understanding, considering the certainty of
                        death and the uncertainty of the time thereof and being desirous to settle
                        my worldly affairs and thereby be the better prepared to leave this world
                        when it shall please God to call me hence do therefore make and publish this
                        my last will and testament in manner and form following that is to say: <lb/>First
                        and principally I commit my soul into the hands of Almighty God and my body
                        to the Earth to be decently buried at the discretion of my Executrix
                        hereinafter named and after my debts and funeral charges are paid I devise
                        and bequeath as follows.</p>
                    <p>I give and <choice><sic>bequeth</sic><corr>bequeath</corr></choice> <persName>Ann Maria
                            Clark</persName>. <persName>Mary Louisa Read</persName> all that tract
                        or parcel of land called <placeName>Magruder's and Bealls</placeName> Honesty
                        lying and being in <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>
                        containing two hundred acres more or less to be divided between them share
                        and share alike to them, their heirs, and assigns forever.</p>
                    <p>I give and bequeath unto <persName>Ann Maria Clark</persName> one negro boy
                            <persName>Charles</persName> and negro girl named
                            <persName>Caroline</persName> to her and her heirs and assigns
                        forever.</p>
                    <p>I give and bequeath unto <persName>Maria Louisa Read</persName> one negro boy
                        named <persName>Abraham</persName> and one negro girl named
                            <persName>Lucy</persName> and one negro girl named
                            <persName>Rebecca</persName> to her and her heirs and assigns
                        forever.</p>
                    <p>I give and bequeath unto <persName>William Henry Piles</persName> one negro
                        boy named <persName>Lukes</persName> and one negro boy named
                            <persName>John</persName> and one negro girl named
                            <persName>Harriott</persName> and one bed, bedstead and furniture unto
                        him the said <persName>William Henry Pile</persName> his heirs and assigns
                        forever</p>


                    <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00125.005.jpg"/>
                    <p>I give and bequeath unto my dear wife <persName>Rachel Pile</persName> the
                        following negroes to wit. <persName>Federick</persName>,
                            <persName>Dennis</persName>, <persName>Thomas</persName>,
                            <persName>Daniel</persName>, <persName>Henry</persName>,
                            <persName>Sophia</persName> and <persName>Alley</persName> to her heirs
                        and assigns forever and also I give and bequeath unto my wife
                            <persName>Rachel Pile</persName> all my stock of every description and
                        farming utensils to divided between my son <persName>William Henry
                            Pile</persName> and herself</p>
                    <p>And lastly I do hereby constitute and appoint my dear wife <persName>Rachel
                            Pile</persName> to be sole Executrix of this my last will and testament
                        revoking and annulling all former wills by me heretofore made satisfying and
                        confirming this and none other to be my last will and testament.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal the
                            <date when="1844-12-04">fourth day of December in the year of our Lord
                            one thousand eight hundred and forty four</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed>his X mark <persName>Richard Pile</persName> signed</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                    <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Signed, Sealed, published and declared by <persName>Richard Pile</persName>
                        the above named testator as and for his last Will and testament in the
                        presence of us who at his request, in his presence and in the presence of
                        each other have subscribed our names as witnesses thereto</ab>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName>Josiah Harding</persName></signed>
                            <signed><persName>Ninian M Perry</persName></signed>
                            <signed><persName>Br Perry</persName></signed>
                        </closer>                    
                    </div2>                
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>State of <placeName>Maryland</placeName>
                        <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> Sct:</dateline>
                    <p>In testimony that the aforegoing is truly taken from the Records of the
                        Orphan Court of said County I have hereunto subscribed my name &#38; affixed
                        the seal of said Court this <date when="1848-01-17">17th day of Jany.
                            1848</date></p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Henry Harding</persName>
                     <lb/>Register of
                            Wills.</signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>



            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00125.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
               <lb/>
                  <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>B. W. Reed</persName> of said
                            county</seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several
                        matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition,
                        as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the
                        several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>B. W.
                                    Reed</persName>
                     </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-09">
                     <seg type="handwritten">9</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg>
                            A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>N Callan</persName> JP</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            
             <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>125<lb/>
                    <persName>Berhard W. Reed</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-09">May 9, 1862</date></ab>
                 <ab><persName>Abraham Butler</persName><lb/>
                     Dr. <persName>Robt K. Stone</persName><lb/>
                     " <persName>Jno C. Rily</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Wm J Stone Jr</persName><lb/>
                </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>