<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e10856">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Cox, G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e10856</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">225</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>fatal cases of primary amputation in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>bloated appearance of habitual drinker</term>
     <term>shot wound in thigh</term>
     <term>wound of entrance on outer side of thigh above its middle, no wound of exit</term>
     <term>femur badly shattered</term>
     <term>thigh amputated near upper third</term>
     <term>femur shattered more than six and a half inches</term>
     <term>ball entered outer thigh, passed behind and partially around femur, entering femur at
      inner aspect, lodging in medullary canal</term>
     <term>entrance wound small, as if by pistol ball</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage from external circumflex artery</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 439.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private <hi rend="italic">G. Cox</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 1st North
     Carolina Cavalry</name>, aged 27 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="106">Brandy
     Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-06-09">June 09, 1863</date>. He was admitted to
    a field hospital of the Fifth Corps, whence <name type="person" key="930">Assistant Surgeon B.
     Howard</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, reported the following
    history: "The patient was a man of usual good health but had the bloated appearance of a
    habitual drinker. He was shot in the right thigh, and was brought to <name type="place">Kelly's
     Ford</name>, a distance of about three miles, in an ambulance. On examination I found a wound
    of entrance on the outer side of the thigh, a little above its middle, but there was no wound of
    exit. The wound of entrance was very small, as if made by a pistol ball. The femur was badly
    shattered. The patient complained of having lost a good deal of blood on his way to <name type="place">Kelly's Ford</name>. I <date type="operation" when="1863-06-09">immediately</date>
    proceeded to amputate near the upper third by the circular mode. The patient suffered
    considerably from shock, but rallied comfortably, and was transported eight miles <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-10">the next morning</date> in an ambulance, and thence by cars
    to <name type="place">Alexandria</name>. On examination of the amputated leg the femur was found
    to be shattered more than six and a half inches, but not comminuted as finely as often happens
    in fractures by a minié rifle ball, this fracture being more vitreous in appearance and
    furnishing but one small fragment, all the others being large ones. The ball had entered the
    outer side of the thigh, passed behind and partially around the femur, entering at its inner
    aspect, and lodging in the medullary canal. The interesting point in the case is the relation of
    the extensiveness of the fracture to the weight and the diminished velocity of the ball; that
    the bone should have been so extensively shattered by a pistol ball, which, when subsequently
    weighed, did not exceed five scruples and six grains, and that the mischief was all done, too,
    after the ball had been so much deflected from its original course." <name type="person" key="307">Surgeon T. R. Spencer</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
    reported the patient's admission to <name type="hospital" key="202">Prince Street
     Hospital</name>, and the result of the case as follows: "On June 19th and 23d,
    hæmorrhage occurred from the external circumflex artery, for which compression and cold
    applications were made. The loss of blood amounted to six ounces. The patient looked
    anæmic, and there was considerable sloughing of the stump. Death followed on <date type="death" when="1863-06-24">June 24, 1863</date>." The amputated portion of the femur
    was contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="930">the operator</name>, and is numbered 1233, <hi rend="italic">Surg. Section</hi> (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 179). </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001582.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 179.—Comminution of middle third of right femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1233.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
