<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e27374">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Demmuth, Jacob</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e27374</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">733-734</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>reflex paralysis, the result of shot wounds</term> 
     <term>shot wounds</term>
     <term>fragment of shell struck thigh at junction of upper and middle thirds, directly over femoral artery</term> 
     <term>paralyzed and defective sensation in right arm and both legs</term> 
     <term>partially paraplegic.</term>
     <term>shooting pains from wound, burning sensations in feet</term>
     <term>difficult, painful micturition</term>
     <term>hyper&#230;sthesia of muscles of both legs</term>
     <term>electric treatment</term>
     <term>purple and blue mottled spots, possible due to frostbite</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE II.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Flesh Wound of Right Thigh, without wound of any large nerve; complete paralysis of all four limbs; speedy recovery
   of the left arm, tardy recovery of the other limbs, subsequent analgesia of the right side.</hi></p>
   <p>"<name type="person" key="1472">Jacob Demmuth</name>, aged 21, Swiss, enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1861-07">July, 1861</date>,
      <name type="organization" key="228">company 'D,' 108th New York Vols.</name>, a man somewhat
     below the average standard of height, of lymphatic temperament and moderate intelligence.
     Reports himself as healthy up to the date of his wound, which took place at <name type="BATTLE"
      key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13,
      1862</date>. He was marching at double-quick, when a fragment of shell as large as a musket
     ball struck his right thigh at the junction of the upper and middle thirds, directly over the
     femoral artery. The fragment did not enter deeply, but merely lodged in the leg, and was
     removed <date type="operation" when="1862-12-14">a day later</date> without injury to the vessel.   <hi rend="italic">Effect of
     wound.</hi>&#8212;He fell half conscious, and although aware that he was wounded, he could not
     fix on the site of the injury until he had examined the limb. He felt instantly a burning pain
     in both feet, in front of the right chest and in the right arm, and in the right thigh about
     the wound. At first he was entirely powerless, but after a few minutes the power of the left
     arm returned, leaving him paralyzed as to motion in the right arm and in both legs. He lay on
     the field twenty-four hours, the weather being very cold. Sensation was defective in all the
     parts paralyzed as to motion. He had no pain in the back, but the burning pains alluded to
     above continued for a long time, and were always eased by cold applied to the wound. While the
     wound was healing he had headache and difficult, painful micturition. The wound closed in four
     weeks. During this period he regained the power to move the right arm, feebly and slowly,
     although perfectly as to extent. The pain in the side and feet also diminished, and the former
     disappeared altogether at a later period. He could not stand, however, or lift his legs from
     the bed at the time the wound healed, but there was then no headache or difficulty with the
     bladder or rectum. <date type="transfer" when="1863-01-28">January 28, 1863</date>, he was sent
    to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where he improved so as to be able to walk with the help of a cane. His
    subsequent transfer to <name type="place">West Philadelphia</name> caused a relapse; the pains returned, the paralysis
     increased, and he walked with difficulty on crutches. <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-04">June 4</date>, entered Christian Street Hospital.   <hi rend="italic">Present state: Movement.</hi>&#8212;The patient is partially paraplegic. He has
     some power to move the thighs when lying down, but cannot lift the legs from the bed. Below the
     knee all motion is lost, except a slight power of flexing the smaller toes in both feet. Pressure upon the cicatrix causes feeble twitching of the
     anterior muscles of the right thigh; both legs are subject to cramp and twitchings, which
     increase at night. The left arm is strong, the right arm has all the normal movements, but all
     are slowly and feebly executed.   <hi rend="italic">Sensation.</hi>&#8212;He has shooting pains,
     which start from the seat of the wound and dart down the thigh to the knee. No other pain
     exists at present, but there is still a good deal of burning sensation in both feet alike.
     Localizing sensibility perfect everywhere. Tactile sensation normal, or very nearly so, in all
     parts of his body; no loss of sense of pain in the skin. Pressure or pinching of the muscles
     gives him more than the usual pain, so the muscles (of both legs, especially below the knees)
     may be regarded as affected with hyper&#230;sthesia of common sensation. The left arm is in all
     respects normal; the right arm is also free from lesions of sensibility.   <hi rend="italic">Nutrition.</hi>&#8212;There is no special atrophy of individual groups of muscles, but both
     legs are slightly wasted, the right arm not at all so. The legs below the knees are relaxed and
     cold; the feet are congested, but not swollen to any marked extent. Along the edges of both
     soles there are singular purple and blue mottled spots, which he says existed from the time
     his boots were first taken off, twenty-four hours after he was wounded. It is possible that
     these marks are due to frostbite. The muscles of the legs are about equally irritable to
     induced electric currents. Unfortunately, no very perfect electric examination of their
     condition was made at this period.   <hi rend="italic">Treatment.</hi>&#8212;Regarding the case
     as one of reflex paralysis chiefly, he was ordered to have rough frictions, with cold to the
     spine, and to take the twentieth of a grain of strychnia three times a day. Under this
     treatment the cramps and twitchings increased, so that after three weeks the strychnia was
     abandoned. Every future attempt to repeat its employment caused the same increase of annoyance,
     without correspondent benefit, so that it was finally laid aside as useless or worse. About the
     middle of August a blister was placed on the cicatrix, with the effect of greatly relieving the
     burning in both feet. At the same time he was ordered to use the hot and cold douche to the
     spine alternately, and faradized daily. The electricity was persistently employed during two
     months, and a month later he was also treated with iron and quinine, porter and liberal diet.
     The electric treatment caused a rapid amelioration of his case, so that he soon left his bed
     and began to walk on crutches. Early in November he ceased to improve, and the treatment was
     abandoned. At this time he could use his right arm well and quickly, and walked unaided,
     although with a little unsteadiness of gait. No close examination was made as to his sensibility until December 3, 1863,
     because during this time he had been able to give aid in the wards, and made no complaint,
     except of more or less constant aching in the dorsal and lumbar regions of the spine. About
     December 3d he was closely inspected for discharge, when the following notes were taken:   <hi
      rend="italic">Motion.</hi>&#8212;Good in left arm; not so perfect in right arm. Both legs
     somewhat weak, so that he shuffles a little in walking, the worst movement being that of
     extension in the toes of the right foot.   <hi rend="italic">Sensation.</hi>&#8212;Tactile
     sensibility feeble in the right leg and right arm, but nowhere entirely lost; it is normal in
     the left leg and left arm. The sense of touch is first found to be feeble below the navel on
     the right side. It lessens in perfection to the knee, and is better below that part, especially
     on the inside of the calf, being worse in the foot. Tickling the sole causes no sensation of
     tickling on either side.   <hi rend="italic">Pain.</hi>&#8212;There is absolute loss of sense of
     pain in the right leg, belly, chest and arm, with somewhat lessened sensibility to pain on the
     left side also. In many localities he was able instantly to tell by the altered sensibility
     when the needle point crossed the median line; in others, this was more difficult. So complete
     was this analgesia that the most intense faradization of the nails of the right hand or of the
     right nipple caused not the least sensation. The penis remained sensitive, but all over the
     right side he could be cut or stuck full of needles without evincing the least consciousness of
     anything but a touch. The sense of temperature was good in the left leg, confused and uncertain
     at the upper third of the right thigh, and lost below the knee, where a heat of 110&#176; Fahrenheit
     was felt as a touch only when the sponge wetted with hot water was applied. On the foot of the
     right side this degree of heat was unfelt in any form. Higher heat caused reflex movements,
     which did not tend to remove the limb from the irritant, but were merely convulsive in their
     character. Intense cold also gave rise to these irregular movements.   <hi rend="italic">Electric
      examination.</hi>&#8212;There was some difficulty in determining the state of the muscles as
     to their electric sensibility, owing chiefly to the want of intelligence in the patient and to
     the fact that he spoke an impure German patois, which made it no easy task to obtain from him a
     clear statement of his feelings. The electro-muscular contractility is slightly diminished in
     the right leg and arm; it is much impaired in the extensors of the toes on both sides;
     everywhere the muscles respond slowly. The patient was discharged <date type="servicedischarge"
      when="1863-12-14">December 14, 1863</date>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
