<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e23037">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Weeks, W. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e23037</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">597-598, 597, 596-597</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>primary amputations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>successful primary amputations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>ball passed through ankle joint</term>
     <term>Pirogoff's amputation at ankle joint, removed articulating surfaces of tibia and <choice>
       <orig>calcaneum</orig>
       <reg>calcaneus</reg>
      </choice>, bringing cut extremities into apposition</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>pus in stump</term>
     <term>metastatic abscesses along anterior tibial lymphatic glands</term>
     <term><choice>
       <orig>calcaneum</orig>
       <reg>calcaneus</reg>
      </choice> and tibia held in position by adhesive straps</term>
     <term>icteroid hue, especially conjunctiv&#230;, exceedingly yellow</term>
     <term>os calcis united to tibia</term>
     <term>wearing artificial foot</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ak" when="2014-10-08">proofed figure encoding, added figure</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding for figure 346 and 355</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 873.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1386">Lieutenant W. C.
     Weeks</name>,&#178; <name type="organization" key="169">Co. I, 5th Michigan Cavalry</name>,
    aged 28 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="58">Five Forks</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1865-04-01">April 1, 1865</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which passed
    through the left ankle joint. Assistant <name type="person" key="290">Surgeon C. A.
    Leale</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported: "He was immediately
    conveyed to hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name>, where <name type="person" key="xx"
     >Surgeon A. K. St. Clair</name>, <name type="organization" key="169">5th Michigan
     Cavalry</name>, performed Pirogoff's amputation at the ankle joint <date type="operation"
     when="1865-04-01">the same day</date>, removing the articulating surfaces of the tibia and <choice>
     <orig>calcaneum</orig>
     <reg>calcaneus</reg>
    </choice> and bringing the cut extremities into apposition. On <date type="transfer"
     when="1865-04-16">April 16th</date> the patient was transferred to <name type="hospital"
     key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name> at Washington, where he was admitted in a very feeble
    condition. Erysipelatous inflammation extended from the stump several inches above the knee
    joint. Extensive suppuration had taken place, and, although fifteen days had elapsed since the
    operation, the rough edges of the calcaneum could be rubbed against the denuded end of the
    tibia, proving that no union existed. The integumentary flap had partially united, thus
    confining a large quantity of pus in the stump, which prevented the bones from being kept in
    apposition. Metastatic abscesses had commenced to form along the course of the anterior tibial
    lymphatic glands, and every symptom prognosticated an unfavorable termination, the only hope
    being based on the remarkable strong constitution of the patient. The abscess at the stump was
    freely evacuated, and the metastatic abscesses were freely opened as soon as fluctuation could
    be detected; the calcaneum and tibia were held in proper position by means of adhesive straps
    after the limb had been thoroughly cleansed with liquor of chloride of zinc. Large linseed
    poultices were applied over the lower third of the tibia and lead and opium wash over the
    remaining part of the limb as far as the erysipelas extended; stimulants and beef tea were
    administered. The patient gradually improved until April 28th, when he had a chill, which was
    soon followed by others. Quinine and tincture of chloride of iron was then prescribed and an
    ounce of brandy was given every two hours. By May 2d the patient had the peculiar sweet odor of
    breath and the well-marked icteroid hue, especially in the conjunctiv&#230;, which were
    exceedingly yellow. Several chills occurred each day and were followed by considerable febrile
    movement and great prostration; but by the frequent administration of stimulants and the
    constant application of artificial heat the patient rallied, after which beef tea was given in
    quantities as large as could be tolerated. From May 6th he improved, the chills occurring at
    longer intervals and with less severity until May 12th, when they ceased. A slight diarrh&#339;a
    at this time was checked by starch and opium injections, after which the patient convalesced
    rapidly. By June 26th he had entirely recovered, the os calcis having united to the tibia and
    the wound having closed, leaving a solid, firm stump." A plaster cast of the stump, Specimen
    2298 of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, is shown in <hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 346, and a photograph of the patient is copied in <hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGURE <hi rend="initialcap">I</hi> of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE
     <hi rend="initialcap">LXXV</hi>, opposite page 596. <name type="person" key="1386">Lieutenant
     Weeks</name> was mustered out of service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-20">July
     20, 1865</date>, and pensioned, after which time he commenced to wear the "Palmer" artificial
    foot. In a subsequent report, dated <date type="pension" when="1866-06-28">June 28, 1866</date>,
     <name type="person" key="290">Dr. Leale</name> furnished the following information in regard to
    the case: "I have just received a communication from <name type="person" key="1386">Lieutenant
     Weeks</name> (residing at <name type="place">Allegan, Michigan</name>), in which he states:
    &#39;I am able to do anything that most men can do; my patent foot works like a charm. I am at
    present engaged in a large flour mill, and my stump has never troubled me but once since I left
    the hospital, and then it was caused by an accident, which loosened a small splinter of bone.
    This I had removed at Chicago, since which time it has done well. I adjusted my false foot on
     <date type="pension" when="1865-10-01">October 1, 1865</date>, and never take it off except
    when I go to sleep. I can easily walk without a cane.&#39;" The pensioner was paid <date
     type="pension" when="1881-09-04">September 4, 1881</date>.</p>
   <p>&#178; <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, War Department, S. G. O., 1865, p. 47. <hi
     rend="initialcap">S</hi>MITH (<hi rend="initialcap">S.</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Amputations at
     the Ankle Joint in Military Surgery</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">U. S. Sanitary Commission
     Memoirs</hi>, New York, 1871, Surgical Volume II, p. 116, 132.</p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001838.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 346.&#8212;Stump after <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>IROGOFF'S
     amputation at ankle joint. [From a plaster cast.]
    </head>
   </figure>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001824.001"/>
    <head>
     PLATE LXXV. AMPUTATIONS AT THE ANKLE JOINT. Fig. 1. Case of <name type="person" key="1386"
     >Lieut. W. C. Weeks</name>, Pirogoff's Operation.
    </head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
