<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5930">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Machlin, F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5930</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">110</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>ball entered buttock, emerged below and within anterior superior spinous process of
      ilium</term>
     <term>neck of femur comminuted and shaft uninjured</term>
     <term>surgeon in charge confined to bed by illness</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-20">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 258.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private F.
     Machlin</name>,&#185; <name type="organization" key="xxx">11th Pennsylvania</name>, a robust
    man, was wounded at the <name type="battle" key="127">second battle of Bull Run</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>. He laid on the field several days, and
    was then transported thirty miles in a wagon to the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Warehouse
     Hospital, Georgetown</name>, D. C., where he was received on <date type="admit"
     when="1862-09-08">September 8th</date>. A musket ball had entered the right buttock and emerged
    an inch and a half below and within the anterior superior spinous process of the ilium. The limb
    was shortened, and the foot was everted; any movement gave excessive pain. A thorough
    examination was made under the influence of chloroform, and showed that the neck of the bone was
    comminuted and the shaft uninjured. The case was considered to be a particularly favorable one
    for the operation of excision of the broken fragments, and the general condition of the patient
    was such as to offer some hopes of its success, and it was determined to do the operation on the
    following day. But the surgeon in charge of the hospital was confined to his bed by illness, and
    was unable to see the patient for five days. On September 13th the general condition of the
    latter was less favorable. His pulse was 130, quick and weak, and his tongue was dry. He was
    placed under very careful nursing, and beef essence, brandy, eggs, and milk, and other
    concentrated nourishment and stimulants were administered <hi rend="italic">ad libitum</hi>. By
    September 20th this treatment had produced slight improvement, and though he was still in a very
    unfavorable condition for an operation, it was determined, on consultation, that an excision
    might afford the patient relief from the constant pain he suffered, and that it could not
    greatly depress him. At noon on <date type="operation" when="1862-09-20">September 20th</date>,
    accordingly <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon B. A. Clements</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, assisted by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr.
     George K. Smith</name>, of <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, and the surgical staff of the
    hospital, performed the operation. An incision five inches in length was made from a point two
    inches behind and an inch below the anterior superior process of the ilium, downward over the
    prominence of the trochanter major. The incision exposed the parts freely, and the muscular
    insertions being divided, and several small loose fragments of bone removed, the irregular
    broken extremity of the shaft, at its junction with the neck and the tip of the great
    trochanter, were excised by a chain saw. The remnant of the capsular ligament and the round
    ligament were now cut, the joint being opened from below and in front with a probe-pointed
    bistoury. A blade of a long bullet forceps was then introduced as a lever and the head was
    disarticulated by gently prying it out of the cotyloid cavity. These steps in the operation were
    facilitated by rotating the trochanter outward, and by lifting the extensor muscles by a
    metallic retractor. A small vessel was tied at the upper end and another at the lower end of the
    wound. The wound was well washed out by means of a syringe and a few stitches were applied, the
    middle portion of the wound being left open. The limb was suspended in a Smith's anterior wire
    splint. The patient appeared to rally from the operation satisfactorily. At 9 o'clock P. M. he
    was free from pain; his pulse was 136, and the skin was cool and natural. He had slept
    tranquilly. On the following day, September 21st, his pulse was 120 and very feeble. The
    discharge from the wound was dark and thin, and copious. His countenance was placid, the
    pinched, distressed expression it had worn having disappeared. But in the afternoon he sank
    rapidly, and died in the evening, thirty-six hours after the operation, <date type="death"
     when="1862-09-21">September 21, 1862</date>. The specimen is No. 329 of the Surgical Section of
    the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, and is represented in the
    accompanying wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 66).&#8212;(<hi rend="italic"
     >Circular</hi> 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 64; <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> 2, S. G. O., 1869, pp.
    37, 135.) </p>

   <p> &#185; <hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>ATES (<hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap"
     >P</hi>.) (<hi rend="italic">History of Pennsylvania Volunteers</hi>, 1861-5, Harrisburg, 1869,
    Vol. I, p. 30) records the name of this patient as Philip Mechling, Co. I, 11th Pennsylvania
    Volunteers. </p>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001540.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 66.&#8212;Excised head of right femur. <hi rend="italic"
     >Spec</hi>. 329.</head></figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
