<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e15706">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Sarvis, I. N.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e15706</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">380-381</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term>
     <term>fatal cases of shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball perforated patella of leg, passed through knee, exited nearly opposite in popliteal
      space</term>
     <term>crepitant and sibilant rales through both lungs</term>
     <term>crucial ligaments destroyed by ball in passage through joint</term>
     <term>pus beneath muscles of lower third of thigh</term>
     <term>py&#230;mia, lung complication of multiple or metastatic abscess</term>
     <term>inferior lobes of lungs consolidated and studded with abscesses, effusion in the pleural
      cavity</term>
     <term>wound of shoulder involving joint</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2014-07-03">corrected typo in figure head</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 571.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1167">Private I. N.
     Sarvis</name>, <name type="organization" key="468">Co. C, 131st Pennsylvania</name>, was
    wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury"
     when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>, and was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="165"
     >Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-12-17">four days
     afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="1165">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. C. Wyer</name>
    forwarded the pathological specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 234) and reported the
    following detailed history: "Sarvis received his wound by a ball perforating the patella of the
    left leg, passing through the knee and making its exit at a point nearly opposite in the
    popliteal space. When admitted his whole constitution was suffering from the effects of the
    injury; the pulse quick and frequent, denoting irritability; the skin dry and hot; appetite
    poor; sensibility of the joint extreme, the patient shrieking on account of the pain occasioned
    by the slightest motion of the limb. The discharge from the wound consisted of synovia and thin
    unhealthy pus. There was nothing peculiar about the aspect of the limb except a general
    tumefaction. The tongue was furred lightly, and the expression anxious; bowels constipated. On
    the tenth day after admission he was attacked with a severe chill, which was followed by fever,
    and from this period the hectic flush began to appear upon the cheeks periodically. Subsequently
    there were recurrences of the rigors. Occasionally the mind wanders. The features are pinched,
    the skin is sallow, and countenance exhibits the icteroid appearance always present in
    py&#230;mia. There is great thirst, and the respiration is quick and irregular. On December
    28th, he was attacked with a cough, the expectoration being tough, gelatinous, and streaked with
    blood. Auscultation revealed crepitant and sibilant rales through both lungs. On the 5th of
    January, 1863, <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, visited the hospital and his attention was
    called to the case. At this period the case was one of well-marked py&#230;mia; the lung
    complication Dr. Brinton pronounced as multiple or metastatic abscess. 6th, no abatement in any
    of the symptoms. 7th, rales and rhonchi still audible through the lungs; pulse continues 120
    beats in the minute; skin dry and hot; tongue dry and fissured; appetite much impaired; patient
    lies drowsy and dull most of the time. The discharge from the knee is profuse, ichorous, and of
    a sickening odor. From the 8th to 13th the symptoms have continued the same: respiration quick,
    pulse 130; tongue dry and crusty; discharge from the knee ichorous and extremely offensive;
    expectoration rusty and gelatinous. Has had slight rigors. Rales and rhonchi still present.
    Complains of pain on the least motion of his body. Urine scanty and turbid; bowels constipated;
    loss of appetite. Continues in a semi-comatose, dull condition. 14th: This morning he is unable
    to protrude his tongue; the features are pinched and sunken; pulse very feeble and rapid; deep
    hectic flush. Evening: has been moaning all day and refused his stimulants. The peculiar odor is
    very evident. Died at 4.30 A. M. on <date type="death" when="1863-01-15">January 15,
    1863</date>. Autopsy eight hours after death: Rigor mortis was still present; emaciation
    extreme. The thorax being laid open revealed the superior lobes of the lungs apparently healthy,
    but upon removing them the inferior lobes were found to be consolidated and studded with
    abscesses varying in size from a pea to larger ones, the diameter of which measured about half
    an inch. The consolidation and effusion extended also to the dependent portions of the superior
    lobes. There was considerable effusion in the left pleural cavity. The heart was perfectly
    normal; no deposit upon the valves. A small clot was discovered in the right ventricle; there
    was also some of the separated fibrin; no effusion in the pericardium. The inferior lobes of
    both lungs sank readily in water. On making the incision to resect the knee joint, pus escaped
    from beneath the muscles of the lower third of the thigh. There was a good deal of
    disintegration of the tissues. The extremities of the femur and tibia were entirely separated,
    the crucial ligaments having been destroyed by the ball in its passage through the joint and the
    capsule ulcerated through at several points. The patella was perforated about its <choice>
     <orig>centre</orig>
     <reg>center</reg>
    </choice>, dividing it into several fragments, which, however, were retained in position by the
    ligamentum patell&#230;. The internal condyle of the femur was crumbled into small fragments,
    and a deep furrow marked the course of the ball." In addition <name type="person" key="1165">Dr.
     Wyer</name> remarks that "at no period since his admission has an operation been admissible,"
    also that the patient had likewise a wound of the right shoulder, involving the joint. The
    specimen consists of the bones of the injured knee. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001609.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 234.&#8212;Bones of the left knee. Patella and condyles of
     femur perforated. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 700.></head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
