<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16670">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">H——, J. C.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16670</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">264</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>trephining practiced, fatal termination</term>
          <term>conoidal ball entered lower occipital bone, fractured and depressed inner table,
            lodged in diploë, plugged lateral sinus on right side of brain</term>
          <term>symptoms of compression, convulsions caused by depressed portion of bone and
            pressure of ball on brain</term>
          <term>autopsy</term>
          <term>disorganized pulpy condition of posterior lobe of brain, emitted offensive
            odor</term>
          <term>fracture extended from entrance to foramen magnum. The </term>
          <term>ball found in posterior lobe of cerebrum</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Corporal J. C.
          H——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. E, 2d New Jersey
          Volunteers</name>, aged 37 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="3">Spottsylvania Court-house, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-14">May
          14th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the lower part of the occipital bone,
        fractured and depressed the inner table, and lodged in the diploë, plugging up the
        lateral sinus on the right side of the brain. He was admitted on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-14">the same day</date> to the hospital of the 1st division, Sixth Corps,
        and thence, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-19">the 19th</date>, sent to the <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C. On <date type="operation" when="1864-05-21">the 21st</date>, the parts were in a healthy condition,
        with a moderate amount of suppuration, and the patient's constitutional condition was
        remarkably good. <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, applied the trephine, but did not remove
        the ball, for fear of hæmorrhage from the lateral sinus and immediate death. The
        patient did not exhibit any symptoms of compression until <date type="operation" when="1864-05-26">the 26th</date>, when he was seized with convulsions, caused by the
        depressed portion of bone and the pressure of the ball on the brain. The trephine was again
        applied, and the depressed bone was removed, but the ball had receded from sight, and could
        not be found. After the operation, the convulsions ceased, a passive delirium supervened and
        continued until the <date type="death" when="1864-06-04">4th of June, 1864</date>, when
        death occurred. The autopsy revealed a disorganized pulpy condition of the posterior lobe of
        the brain, emitting an extremely offensive odor. The fracture extended from orifice of
        entrance to the foramen magnum. The ball was found in the posterior lobe of the cerebrum, at
        the depth of about two inches. The specimen is a large section of the cranium with a
        conoidal ball suspended in a perforation of the occipital bone. The opening measures one
        inch by one and one-fourth inches, and is partly caused by the operation of trephining. A
        fissure passes down ward and inward to the foramen magnum. The specimen and history were
        contributed by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name> ,<name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> and are further illustrated in the Surgical
        Photograph Series, A. M. M., Volume VII, page 1. </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001415.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 128.—Section of the occipital bone, with a
          musket ball, which plugged the lateral sinus. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3040, Sect. I,
          A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
