<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31225">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Tarbell, J. M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31225</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="bt">Ben Tomjack</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">887</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint</term> 
       <term>excisions at the elbow joint for shot injury</term>
       <term>secondary excisions at the elbow</term> 
       <term>recoveries after secondary excisions at the elbow</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of arm, severely injured elbow joint</term>
       <term>resected elbow joint</term> 
       <term>portion of lower extremity of humerus removed by <choice><orig>exsection</orig><reg>excision</reg></choice></term>
       <term>humerus two and one-half inches shorter than the other</term>
       <term>complete loss of rotation of hand</term>
       <term>forearm cannot be extended completely</term>
       <term>Disability total</term>        
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#bt" when="2011-02-25">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1822.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. M. Tarbell</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 2d U. S. Sharpshooters</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-06">May 6, 1864</date>, and was admitted into a field hospital of the Second Corps, and thence sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and received into <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-26">the 26th</date>. <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, noted:  &#34;Gunshot wound of the right arm, severely injuring the elbow joint. On admission, the parts were considerably swollen and inflamed, and the constitutional state of the patient was very poor. The arm was kept quiet, and cold applications with general constitutional treatment employed until <date type="operation" when="1864-06-18">June 18th</date>, when an operation was deemed necessary, which was performed, on that day, by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who resected the elbow joint. The patient improved in health after the operation, and, at this date, December 26, 1864, the wound has entirely healed and the patient is about to be discharged from service. He has no ability to flex the right arm, which is about two inches shorter than the left, but in other respects useful. Splints, simple dressings, and supporting treatment.&#34;  The photograph from which the cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 644) is taken, together with the specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 643), was contributed by <name type="person" key="158">the operator</name>. The specimen consists of two fragments of carious bone, representing the condyles of the humerus, the olecranon, and head of the radius, excised from the right elbow. <name type="person" key="xxx">Tarbell</name> was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-12-31">December 31, 1864</date>, and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner C. L. Allen</name>, of <name type="place">Vermont</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1873-08-03">August 3, 1873</date>:  &#34;A portion of the lower extremity of the humerus was removed by <choice><orig>exsection</orig><reg>excision</reg></choice>. The right humerus is two and one-half inches shorter than the left. The right arm and forearm measure respectively, one and a quarter, and one and a half inches less than the left in circumference. There is complete loss of rotation of the hand except from the shoulder joint, the forearm can be extended, but can be flexed only to an angle of about one hundred and ten degrees; there is fair use of the hand. The forearm is evidently not strong, especially in pushing. The hand cannot be brought near enough to the head to be of any use in eating. Disability total.&#34;  This pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1874-03-04">March 4, 1874</date>.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001721.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 643.&#8212;Excised portions of the right elbow joint after caries from shot injury.     <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3602.</head>
   </figure>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001722.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 644.&#8212;Appearance after a secondary excision of the elbow for shot injury.    [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
