<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41178">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ball, Peter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41178</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">177</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>pia mater ecchymosed, lateral sinuses full of blood</term>
       <term>heart substance flabby, surrounding adipose tissue abundant</term>
       <term>c&#230;cum and ascending colon ulcerated</term>
       <term>ulcers more numerous in transverse colon</term>
       <term>ulcers in transverse colon penetrated to peritoneum</term>
       <term>ulcers in sigmoid flexure irregular and covered with shreddy lymph</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863, then <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 396.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Peter Ball</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company H, 66th New York volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-12-29">December 29, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears on the register of the regimental hospital of the 66th New York volunteers, admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-12-08">December 8th</date>&#8212;intermittent fever&#8212;sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1863-12-11">December 11th</date>. No subsequent account of him is found prior to his admission to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name>.]  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-01-24">January 24, 1864</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-01-26">forty-eight hours after death</date>: Height five feet eight inches; the body was much emaciated. The brain weighed fifty-three ounces; the subarachnoidal fluid was abundant; the pia mater was ecchymosed in spots; the lateral sinuses were full of blood. The right lung weighed thirty-two ounces; it was congested and marked, especially on its upper lobe, by streaks of black pigment corresponding to the ribs; the left lung weighed twenty-two ounces and a half; it also was congested and marked with pigment in the same manner as the right lung; the lower lobe appeared to be consolidated, but did not sink in water. The bronchial glands were black; some of them were hardened and contained calcareous deposits. The heart weighed six ounces and a quarter; its substance was flabby, the surrounding adipose tissue abundant; there was a large fibrinous clot in the left auricle; the aorta was reddened internally. The liver weighed forty-nine ounces and a half; its substance was finely mottled; the gall-bladder contained a little light-colored bile. The spleen weighed three ounces and a quarter. The pancreas weighed two ounces. The right kidney weighed six ounces, the left kidney six and a quarter. The mucous membrane of the upper part of the jejunum was congested and softened; the valvul&#230; conniventes were not prominent, and disappeared in the lower part of the jejunum, so that the ileum was quite smooth. The c&#230;cum and ascending colon were ulcerated; the ulcers were more numerous in the transverse colon, where they penetrated to the peritoneum; they were generally grouped in rows corresponding to the longitudinal muscular bands; the ulcers in the sigmoid flexure were irregular and covered with shreddy lymph. The rectum was irregularly congested.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
