<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e21035">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Grant, L. V.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e21035</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">546</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot injury</term> 
     <term>recoveries after secondary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>ball entered inner malleolus posteriorly, penetrated base of tibia, remained embedded on semi-cylindrical face of <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice></term> 
     <term>aortic direct murmur of heart, considerable hypertrophy and labored heart action</term> 
     <term>propped up in bed to allow rest</term>
     <term>amputation performed below knee</term>
     <term>symptoms of heart disease modified after operation</term>     
     <term>artificial limb applied</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>   
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 796.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1319">Private L. V.
      Grant</name>, <name type="organization" key="507">Co. M, 8th Illinois Cavalry</name>, aged 23
     years, was wounded in the left ankle, at <name type="BATTLE" key="109">Beverly Ford</name>,
      <date type="injury" when="1863-06-09">June 9, 1863</date>, and entered <name type="hospital"
       key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-06-10"></date>the following day.  <name type="person"
      key="243">Assistant Surgeon J. C. McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who amputated the injured limb, reported as follows: "The wound was caused by the
     ball entering the inner malleolus posteriorly, penetrating the base of the tibia, and remaining embedded on the semi-cylindrical
     face of the <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>. Upon taking charge of the hospital (December, 1863) I found the
     patient's condition as follows: Appetite capricious but well guarded by taking acceptable food;
     constant pain in left breast, accompanied by headache; eyes constantly suffused and face
     flushed, wakefulness, restlessness, and night-sweats; also a strong aortic direct murmur of the heart,
     with considerable hypertrophy and consequent labored heart action. He had to be propped up in bed to allow him any rest, his
     expression being anxious, appetite declining, pain of wound unremitting and excruciating,
     tissues inflamed and &#339;dematous, and the joint immovable and firmly anchylosed, rendering
     it impossible for the patient to put his foot on the ground. He begged again and again to have
     the limb removed. An examination by the probe indicated diseased bone or foreign substance. The
     opinion of <name type="person" key="1318">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. F. Peck</name>&#8212;under
     whose care he had been for some months&#8212;as confirmed by the statement of the patient was that
     the ball had been extracted. Uninfluenced by the patient's constant and urgent solicitation I
     proceeded carefully to examine the case further; and not being satisfied that I had sufficient
     authority to remove the diseased and injured joint by amputation, I delayed for accumulative
     evidence, which was not long in presenting itself. The bad symptoms increasing, it became
     evident that some measure for relief must be promptly taken to save the life of the patient.
      <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon R. Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="190">U. S. A.</name>, under whose care the patient had also been for some time, favored
     immediate amputation, and stated that he had intended to operate before my arrival. <name
      type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, was also present and favored the operation. <name type="person"
       key="1318">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. F. Peck</name> insisted upon removing the limb some time
     before I gave my consent; other medical gentlemen present were satisfied that the removal of
     the limb was called for to rid the patient of a deformity and an encumbrance. Amputation was
     accordingly performed on <date type="operation" when="1863-12-07">December 7, 1863</date>, eight inches below the knee, by circular operation.
     Sulphuric ether was used and the patient reacted promptly. The stump was left laying open on a
     pillow and strapped, when the healing process commenced. Simple water dressings were applied.
     The aggravated symptoms of the heart disease became greatly modified after the operation. The
     patient's appetite improved, his night-sweats ceased, and he was delighted to be able to sleep
     and rest, stating that he had not enjoyed any comfort or relief from pain for months before. He
     obtained an excellent and useful stump. The ligatures came away two weeks after the operation.
     The patient was furloughed <date type="furlough" when="1864-02-11">February 11th</date>, and
     subsequently he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square
      Hospital</name> to have an artificial limb applied." On <date type="servicedischarge"
      when="1864-09-24">September 24, 1864</date>, his term of service expired and he was mustered
     out. He was a pensioner until <date type="death" when="1865-08-21">August 21, 1865</date>, when
     he died. The cause of his death has not been ascertained. The amputated part of the wounded
     limb, longitudinally bisected and exhibiting the place of lodgement of the missile, was
     contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person"
      key="243">the operator</name> and constitutes specimen 1899 of the Surgical Section.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
