<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41427">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Carey, William H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41427</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">192-193</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>liver much enlarged and pale, mottled appearance when cut into</term>
       <term>spleen much enlarged</term>
       <term>small abscesses in medullary portion of kidney</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-18">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 462.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private William H. Carey</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company F, 28th Michigan volunteers</name>; admitted from regimental hospital <date type="admit" when="1865-01-26">January 26, 1865</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1865-02-02">February 2d</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1865-02-03">eighteen hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis very great; body not emaciated, a well-developed muscular subject; slight suggillation posteriorly. The dura mater and pia mater were congested; the whole surface of the brain was coated with recent lymph deposited in the pia mater; the brain-substance was normal; the lateral ventricles contained two drachma of serum. Neck and spinal column not examined. There were no pleuritic adhesions; the pleural sacs contained an ounce of serum. The upper lobe of the left lung was normal, the lower lobe hepatized; the middle lobe of the right lung was hepatized, the lower lobe congested. The pericardium contained half an ounce of serum. The heart and its valves were normal. The omentum was injected and somewhat thickened. Nothing abnormal was observed in either small or large intestine. The liver was very much enlarged and pale; it presented a mottled appearance when cut into; the gall bladder contained two ounces of bile. The spleen was very much enlarged and softened. The pancreas and mesenteric glands were normal. The left kidney was normal, the right apparently softened; in its medullary portion were two small abscesses about the size of small peas; the bladder contained about six ounces of urine.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
