<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41829">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Williams, Frank</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41829</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">258-259</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Freedman's Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>scrofulous ophthalmia</term>
       <term>phthisis pulmonalis</term>
       <term><choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion beneath clavicle</term>
       <term>copious expectoration with profuse h&#230;morrhage</term>
       <term>lungs adherent to pleura costalis and lobes interadherent</term>
       <term>fluid in pleural cavity</term>
       <term>lungs filled with crude tubercles and vomic&#230;</term>
       <term>large vomica in upper lobe filled with coagulated blood</term>
       <term>bronchial glands much enlarged</term>
       <term>pericardium contained fluid</term>
       <term>liver fatty and congested, presented nutmeg appearance, contained tubercles</term>
       <term>spleen filled with tubercles</term>
       <term>mesenteric glands much enlarged</term>
       <term>tubercular ulcers in ileum near ileoc&#230;cal valve</term>
       <term>solitary follicles enlarged in c&#230;cum</term>
       <term>in ascending colon large tubercular ulcer involved mucous and muscular coats, numerous tubercles on peritoneal surface opposite ulcer</term>
       <term>large ulcer in transverse colon</term>
       <term>abdominal cavity filled with serum, intestines adherent to abdominal peritoneum</term>
       <term>omentum contained large number of minute tubercles</term>
       <term>dark mulatto</term>
       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>One of eight cases observed at the <name type="hospital" key="440"><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>REEDMAN'S <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., during 1865, 1866, and 1867.&#8432;  In none of them were the patients soldiers. Five are of interest as examples of tubercular ulceration of the intestines. Besides the specimens from these cases, several other examples of tubercular ulceration of the intestines are preserved at <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, which were obtained from autopsies of colored women who died at the same hospital during the period mentioned. . . . In all of them extensive tubercular deposits were found in the lungs and other organs. Most of the specimens are portions of the ileum with tubercular ulcers of the mucous membrane and miliary tubercles on the peritoneal surface opposite:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 863.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Frank Williams</name>; dark mulatto; age 14; admitted <date type="admit" when="1865-05-24">May 24, 1865</date>, suffering from scrofulous ophthalmia. Symptoms of phthisis pulmonalis were first noticed about <date type="injury" when="1864-10">the middle of October</date>. There was marked <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion on the left side beneath the clavicle and over the second, third and fourth ribs; expectoration very copious during the last four weeks; h&#230;morrhage occurred very profusely for the first time, <date type="death" when="1866-02-04">February 4, 1866</date>, about 5 P. M.  The boy died in three or four minutes.  Treatment: Cod-liver oil, whiskey, nourishing diet, milk-punch, etc. His diarrh&#339;a was not troublesome except during the two or three days preceding death.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1866-02-05">twenty-two hours after death</date>: Body well formed; height four feet nine inches; some emaciation; rigor mortis well marked; weight about 80 pounds. The brain weighed forty-four ounces; its membranes were congested, its substance firm; there were two ounces of fluid in the posterior foss&#230; of the cranium. The right lung was firmly adherent to the pleura costalis, filled with crude tubercles and vomic&#230;, and weighed fifteen ounces; there were three ounces of fluid in the right pleural cavity; the left lung was firmly adherent at all points, its lobes interadherent; it weighed twenty-three ounces; in the upper lobe of the left lung was a large vomica the size of a goose egg, which was filled with coagulated blood; tubercles and smaller vomic&#230; were scattered throughout the lungs. The left pleural cavity contained an ounce of fluid. The bronchial glands were very much enlarged. The heart was small, slightly fatty, and weighed five ounces; all its valves were thickened. The pericardium contained eight ounces of fluid. The liver weighed forty-one ounces, was adherent at all points, its anterior surface coated with lymph; on section it was found to be very fatty and congested, presenting the nutmeg appearance, and contained some tubercles. The spleen weighed four ounces, was adherent at all points, and filled with tubercles. The pancreas and kidneys were normal; the latter weighed three ounces each. The mesenteric glands were very much enlarged. The stomach was normal. Two large tubercular ulcers were found in the ileum near the ileoc&#230;cal valve. The rest of the small intestine was normal. In the c&#230;cum a few of the solitary follicles were enlarged. A large tubercular ulcer, involving the mucous and muscular coats, was found in the ascending colon; on the peritoneal surface opposite this ulcer there were numerous minute tubercles; a similar but much larger ulcer was found in the transverse colon; with these exceptions the large intestine was normal. The abdominal cavity was filled with serum, and the intestines were slightly adherent to the abdominal peritoneum. The large intestine was three feet and a half long, the small intestine nineteen feet. The <choice><sic>urino-genital</sic><corr>uro-genital</corr></choice> organs appeared healthy.&#8212;<name type="person" key="3420">Hospital Steward Samuel S. Bond</name>.   [Nos. 720 and 721, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  No. 720 is a portion of the transverse colon, showing a number of minute follicular ulcers; near the middle of the piece is a large tubercular ulcer running obliquely to the axis of the gut. On the peritoneal surface opposite the ulcer are a considerable number of minute tubercles; a few others are scattered on other portions of the peritoneal surface.  No. 721 is a portion of the omentum containing a large number of minute tubercles.]</p>
   <p>&#8432; During this period two of the hospital stewards on duty in <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, <name type="person" key="3421">D. S. Lamb</name> and <name type="person" key="3420">S. S. Bond</name>, were frequently sent to the <name type="hospital" key="440">Freedman's Hospital</name> for the purpose of making autopsies. A considerable number of specimens illustrative of the diseases of the freedmen were thus obtained.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
