<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e25172">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Buob, F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e25172</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">651</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>miscellaneous injuries</term> 
     <term>simple and compound fractures</term>
     <term>fracture of the femur caused by a fall from a bridge</term>
     <term>mental condition, chronic dementia</term> 
     <term>lameness of hip, fall from bridge</term> 
     <term>trochanter flattened and approximated to anterior superior spinous process of ilium</term> 
     <term>shortening limb, inversion of foot</term>
     <term>pulmonary tuberculosis, death</term>
     <term>impacted fracture of neck of femur</term>
     <term>hemoptysis, pleuritic and pneumonic inflammation</term> 
     <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change> 
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 971.—<hi rend="italic">Fracture of the femur caused by
      a fall from a bridge.</hi>—<name type="person" key="1428">Private F. Buob</name>, <name type="organization" key="539">Co. C, 108th Ohio</name>, aged 36 years, was admitted to the
      <name type="hospital" key="161">Government Hospital for the Insane</name> near Washington on
      <date type="admit" when="1865-05-16">May 16, 1865</date>, his condition being described by the superintendent, <name type="person" key="1429">Dr. C. H. Nichols</name>, as follows:  "The patient's
     mental condition was that of slight chronic dementia. He was not able to walk up stairs to the
     ward on account of a lameness of the left hip, the sergeant in charge of him stating that this
     was caused by a fall from a bridge, which had occurred <date type="injury" when="1865-04">between two and three weeks previous to
     his admission</date>. His own statement was that in marching across the bridge at night he was
     accidentally crowded off the side and fell down some distance, striking upon his left hip. As
     he laid upon his back the injured limb appeared shortened and the toes, turned toward the other
     foot. By measurement the shortening was found to be three-fourths of an inch. The trochanter
     was flattened and approximated to the anterior superior spinous process of the ilium. On
     rotating the limb no point of false motion was discovered and no crepitation. The arc of the
     movement of the trochanter was less than that of the sound side. When the patient stood erect
     there was the same shortening and the same inversion of the foot. He could limp about a little
     by the aid of a chair, bearing considerable of his weight upon the injured limb. The diagnosis
     of the case was that of an impacted fracture of the neck of the femur. The limb improved
     rapidly, and in a few weeks the patient walked without inconvenience excepting what arose from
     the shortening. The general appearance of the man, however, led to the suspicion of pulmonary
     tuberculosis, and a physical examination of the chest confirmed this suspicion. The
     tuberculosis advanced with the ordinary phenomena of cough, expectoration, some hemoptysis, and
     occasional pleuritic and pneumonic inflammation. From this disease the patient died <date type="death" when="1866-01-28">January 28, 1866</date>. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi>
     examination of the body proved the correctness of the diagnosis respecting the lung disease.
     Nothing peculiar was noticed about the acetabulum of the injured side except that the
     ligamentum teres and the cushion of fat at the bottom were more vascular than on the sound
     side. The femur presented unmistakable evidence that the injury was an impacted fracture of the
     neck of the bone, the line of it being partly within and partly without the capsular ligament.
     By comparison with the sound femur a shortening of three-fourths of an inch was shown, and the
     impaction was found to be greater anteriorly than posteriorly, thus causing the inversion of
     the foot. The union of the bone appeared to be firm and sound."  Both the injured and the sound
     femur were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="1429">the reporter of
     the case</name> and constitute specimen 2376 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>. </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
