<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e13014">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Scholl, Simon B.</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e13014</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">182</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term> 
                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the skull</term>
                    <term>balls splitting on the cranial bones</term>
                    <term>musket ball fractured frontal bone in median line and to left, then split into two parts, , the </term>
                    <term>part of ball lodged beneath right scalp</term>
                    <term>part of ball splintered crista galli and lodged over ethmoidal cells, roof of which partially destroyed</term>
                    <term>fatal result attributed to rudimentary state of the frontal sinus, pre-existing anatomical variation</term>
                    <term>left pupil contracted, right pupil widely dilated, both insensible to light</term>
                    <term>large abscess in lower part of anterior right hemisphere</term>
                    <term>spiculæ of bone penetrated membranes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0233">            
                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="1553">Sergeant Simon B. Scholl</name>, <name type="organization" key="331">Co. E, 82d Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="250"><choice><orig>Spottsylvania</orig><reg>Spotsylvania</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05">May, 1864</date>, by a musket ball which penetrated and
                    fractured the frontal bone a little to the left of and involving the median
                    line, making an opening three-fourths by one-half inch; then split into two
                    parts, one of which lodged beneath the scalp at a corresponding point on right
                    side, the other splintered the crista galli in its course and lodged just over
                    the ethmoidal cells, the roof of which it partially destroyed.  The patient was
                    insensible a short time previous to being admitted to the 3d division of the Sixth Corps Hospital.  On <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-24">May 24th</date> he
                    was sent to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>,
                    Washington, and on <date type="operation" when="1864-05-30"><date type="transfer" when="1864-05-30">May 30th</date></date> to
                    <name type="hospital">Cuyler Hospital, Philadelphia</name>.  On admission to the latter hospital he was much
                    exhausted and depressed, becoming towards evening feverish, with pain in head. A
                    portion of the ball was removed from beneath the scalp by counter opening.  For
                    two weeks the only prominent symptoms were headache, constipation, and vomiting,
                    followed afterward by insomnia and great jactation.  On June 18th the patient
                    became almost completely comatose. He could be aroused only with difficulty and
                    relapsed almost immediately. The left pupil became contracted, while the right
                    was widely dilated, both being insensible to light.  He died <date type="death" when="1864-06-18">June 18th, 1864</date>.  At the autopsy the membranes were
                    found to contain a fine arterial injection, the venous trunks also being
                    considerably engorged. The brain presented a moderate degree of interstitial
                    congestion. A large abscess was found in the lower part of the anterior lobe of
                    the right hemisphere, containing about three ounces of greenish, flocculent pus,
                    mingled with broken-down brain substance. Several spiculæ of bone were found
                    penetrating the membranes, and a small clot of coagulable lymph showed at once
                    the original seat of injury, and the point at which suppuration had begun. A
                    point of interest in this case was the rudimentary state of the frontal sinus,
                    an anatomical variation from the customary condition, to which may probably be
                    attributed the fatal result, since the portion of the ball which in this case
                    penetrated the cranium, would in an ordinary skull have lodged in the frontal
                    sinus.   The case is reported by <name type="person" key="374">Assistant Surgeon Henry S. Schell</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
