<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31356">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Mortimer, J. L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31356</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="hf">Heather Furrow</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">870</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term> 
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>excisions at the elbow joint for shot injury</term> 
       <term>intermediary excisions at the elbow</term>
       <term>recoveries after intermediary excision at the elbow</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of upper extremity</term> 
       <term>compound comminuted fracture involving elbow joint</term>
       <term>ball entered outer side of elbow, emerged internal to and above olecranon, fractured external condyle</term>
       <term>articular surface of humerus removed by saw, ulna and radius gouged</term>
       <term>anchylosis of elbow</term>
       <term>arm wasted and deformed, disability total</term>            
       <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#hf" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1801.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. L. Mortimer</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 67th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 40 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="58">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-25">March 25, 1865</date>, and was treated in the depot hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name>, thence transferred to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-02">April 2d</date>.  <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, the operator, noted: &#34;Admitted with gunshot wound of the right upper extremity, compound comminuted fracture, involving elbow joint; ball entered at the outer side of the bend of the elbow and emerged one inch internal to and above the olecranon, fracturing the external condyle.  On <date type="operation" when="1865-04-05">April 5, 1865</date>, the patient was anaesthetized by equal parts of ether and chloroform and an incision was made from the outer border of the bend of the elbow, posteriorly, to the inner border. The articular surface was removed by the saw; of the ulna and radius by gouging with forceps. Four ligatures were applied to small branches. There was considerable oozing from the bone. At the time of operation the forearm and hand were &#339;dematous, the swelling extending above the elbow; the wounds had an unhealthy appearance and an unhealthy pus exuded from them; the general health was good. The after-treatment consisted of simple cold-water dressings, and afterward lead and opium wash; tonics, stimulants, and nourishing diet. The wound healed rapidly, and the patient was transferred to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>.&#34;  He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Mower Hospital</name> <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-18">May 18, 1865</date>, and thence discharged the service, with anchylosis of the elbow, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-06-29">June 29, 1865</date>, and pensioned.  The specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 625), consisting of the articular extremity of the right humerus sawn just above the condyles and excised for fracture of the external condyle, was contributed by the operator.  In <date type="pension" when="1873-09">September, 1873</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner W. J. Mullin</name>, of <name type="place">Shellsbury</name>, reported: &#34;The arm is wasted and badly deformed; disability total.&#34;  Pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1874-03-04">March 4, 1874</date>.</p>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001740.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 625.&#8212;Excised condyles of humerus, shattered by shot.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 72.    &#8531;</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
