<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31629">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Marker, Allen J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31629</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="nm">Nate Mattison</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">91</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>gunshot wound of side and arm</term>
       <term>ball passed through side between ninth and tenth ribs, lodged between transverse processes of third and fourth lumbar vertebr&#230;, fractured tenth rib</term>
       <term>f&#230;cal matter discharged by back wound</term>
       <term>ball extracted from fourth lumbar vertebra</term>
       <term>entrance wound in eight intercostal space, lodgement between apophyses of second and third lumbar vertebr&#230;, ninth rib fractured</term>
       <term>escape of f&#230;cal matter from anterior opening for fourteen days</term>
       <term>preternatural anus in loin discharged of f&#230;ces seven months</term>
       <term>free suppuration from wounds in arm and hypochondrium</term>
       <term>stercoraceous matter escaped from lumbar wound</term>
       <term>ball penetrated lower third of arm and fractured humerus, indicated by cicatrices and irregularity of surface of bone</term>
       <term>arm weakened, dexterity of arm injured, hand weakened in power of grasping</term>
       <term>side weak and painful, general exhaustion, back weak, side slightly paralyzed</term>
       <term>bowels constipated</term>
       <term>sphacelated colon</term>
       <term>total disability</term>
       <term>reduced general strength, loss of weight</term>
       <term>f&#230;cal fistula persisted</term>
       <term>false passage existed after receiving wound, from which excrements escaped</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#nm" when="2011-02-24">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 276.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Allen J. Marker</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 4th Maine</name>, aged 18 years, was wounded near <name type="place">Centreville</name>, at the battle of <name type="battle" key="48">Chantilly</name>, <date type="injury" when= "1862-09-01">September 1, 1862</date>,&#185; and was taken to the regimental hospital, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon G. W. Martin</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">4th Maine</name>, recorded his injury as a "gunshot wound of the side and arm."  The wounded man was conveyed to <name type="place">Washington</name>, and entered <name type="hospital">Epiphany Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-02">September 2d</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. N. P. Monroe</name> states, without describing the wound of the arm, that "the ball passed through the left side between the ninth and tenth ribs, fracturing the latter, and lodged between the transverse processes of the third and fourth lumbar vertebr&#230;, whence it was extracted, as I was informed, on <date type="operation" when= "1862-09-01">the previous day</date>."  <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, saw the patient, and notes the entrance wound as in the eight left intercostal space, and the lodgement as between the apophyses of the second and third lumbar vertebr&#230;, and the ninth rib as fractured. The missile was placed in <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="288">Dr. Brinton</name>, and is represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 58). The missile is said to have lain subcutaneously, and as soon as a counter-incision was made for its extraction, f&#230;cal matter was discharged by this wound. From the anterior opening a number of bone splinters were extracted. A slight escape of f&#230;cal matter from this opening lasted for fourteen days. From the preternatural anus in the loin a free discharge of f&#230;ces persisted for nearly seven months.  On <date type="operation" when= "1862-09-05">September 5th</date>, a portion of sphacelated colon presented at the posterior orifice, and was removed with scissors by the ward surgeon.  On <date type="operation" when= "1862-09-10">September 10th</date>, a piece of omentum, "twelve inches long and two inches wide" (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>), is said to have been removed. Notwithstanding the free suppuration from the wound in the arm and hypochondrium, the general condition of the patient was encouraging. He was sustained by a nourishing diet, with porter and tonic medicines.  <date type="photo" when="1862-10">Late in October</date>, <name type="person" key="878">Hospital Steward Stauch</name> prepared, under <name type="person" key="288">Dr. Brinton</name>’s supervision, an excellent water-color drawing of the subject. This is preserved in the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Series of Drawings</hi>, A. M. M., as No. 15. A reduced copy of the drawing is presented in the accompanying wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 59).  On <date when= "1862-11-01">November 1st</date>, it is noted that the boy had a steady, hearty appetite, and maintained tolerable health, and that the dejections had taken place by the natural channel, on that day, for the first time since the reception of the injury. The lad was preparing to go to his home.  On <date type="servicedischarge" when= "1862-11-21">November 21st</date>, though stercoraceous matter still escaped from the lumbar wound, the patient, at his own desire, was discharged from service by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon James Bryan</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>  The f&#230;cal fistula persisted until May, 1863, when the discharge from the wounds became sero-purulent. A month afterward, both wounds healed up soundly, and the patient went to his home at <name type="place">Belfast, Maine</name>. He was pensioned.  On <date type="pension" when="1864-09-15">September 15, 1864</date>, his condition was so satisfactory that his pension was reduced. He applied for an increase, and, on <date type="pension" when= "1870-08-27">August 27, 1870</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner Charles N. Germain</name>, of <name type="place">Rockland, Maine</name>, made the following report in the case: "A musket ball penetrated the lower third of the left arm, fracturing the humerus, as indicated by cicatrices and by irregularity of the surface of the bone. Arm weakened thereby, so that it is with difficulty he can raise more than thirty pounds. The natural dexterity of the arm is injured, and the hand weakened in its power of grasping. Disability one-half.  Secondly, there exists a large depressed cicatrix on his left side, between the ninth and tenth ribs, where a musket ball entered; another large (two by four inches) callused cicatrix, between the third and fourth lumbar vertebr&#230;, where a ball was cut out.  In the wound of his side, a false passage existed for three or four months after receiving the wound, from which the excrements of his body escaped. The seat of the wound is now subject to periodical attacks soreness and pain. By reason of injury to the spine, his back is weak, and his side is slightly paralyzed. If he attempts to perform manual labor his back becomes so weak and lame that he cannot stand erect; his side also becomes weak and painful, producing general exhaustion. If he inclines forward his back becomes painful and weak; his bowels are constipated, requiring the constant use of purgatives; he is reduced in general strength; loss of weight, twenty-five pounds. For this disability, I rate him one-half; for both disabilities, total."</p>    
   <p>&#185; See <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the Adjutant General of the State of Maine for the year</hi> 1862, p. 51, for particulars of the part the regiment bore in this engagement.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001775.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 58.&#8212;Conoidal ball, battered by contact with the ninth rib and the transverse processes of the lumbar vertebra.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 6248.</head>
   </figure>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001776.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 59.&#8212;Preternatural anus in the lumbar region, from a shot perforation of the colon.    <hi rend="italic">Surg. Drawings</hi>, A. M. M., No. 15.</head>
   </figure>  
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
