<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e29169">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Donnelly, Reuben</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e29169</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">721</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>shot wounds</term>
     <term>effect of missiles and projectiles on bony structure</term>
     <term>perforations of bone</term>
     <term>shaft of femur perforated in centre</term>
     <term>longitudinal fissure on anterior surface of femur extends into joint and also upward,
      ends in transverse fissure</term>
     <term>oblique fracture on posterior surface of femur runs upward</term>
     <term>wound of thigh</term>
     <term>ball entered front of thigh above patella, passed directly through limb front to rear,
      divided condyles and split bone up the shaft</term>
     <term>amputation of thigh at junction of lower and middle thirds</term>
     <term>suppuration in medullary canal of bone</term>
     <term>femoral shaft split longitudinally in anterior surface and posteriorly obliquely</term>
     <term>femoral condyles separated by fissure</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-26">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1067.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Reuben
     Donnelly</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. A, 25th Ohio</name>, was wounded at
     <name type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30,
     1862</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas C. Barker</name>
    reported: &#34;He entered <name type="hospital" key="193">King Street Hospital</name>, <name
     type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, on <date type="admit" when="1862-09-03"
     >September 3d</date>, suffering with a wound of the right thigh. A round ball entered the front
    part of the thigh just above the patella and passed directly through the limb from front to
    rear, dividing the condyles and splitting the bone up the shaft several inches. On <date
     type="operation" when="1862-09-05">September 5th</date>
    <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. E. Summers</name>, <name type="organization" key="190"
     >U. S. A.</name>, amputated the thigh at the junction of the lower and middle thirds by the
    antero-posterior flap operation. The case progressed favorably. Union had taken place throughout
    the whole of the flaps, with the exception of one point, about one-eighth of an inch in
    diameter, over the end of the bone, which lay at a depth of three-fourths of an inch below the
    orifice of the aperture. Patient's health, appetite, and general vigor had been good up to the
    night of October 3d, when, during a cold rain, he was attacked with a severe chill. The next
    day, in the afternoon, he had another chill, and although tonics and stimulants were sedulously
    used with him, he sank in general vigor and his appetite failed. Absorption of the new
    granulations took place around the aperture which had remained ununited, and the opening
    increased to nearly an inch in diameter, the integuments retracting and leaving the end of the
    bone nearly on a level with the external surface. Suppuration occurred in the medullary canal of
    the bone. Emaciation was extreme; debility was rapidly increasing, with indisposition and
    incapacity of taking and retaining food, or even stimulants to any appreciable amount; and the
    patient gradually sank, and died of exhaustion and debility <date type="death" when="1862-10-20"
     >October 20, 1862</date>.&#34; The specimen, consisting of the lowest third of the right femur,
    perforated by a round ball directly through the centre of the shaft, just below the upper margin
    of the patella, was forwarded to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name
     type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Barker</name>, and is represented in the wood-cuts (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGS. 403, 404). The shaft is split longitudinally in its anterior
    surface for four inches, and posteriorly obliquely for the same distance. The condyles are also
    separated by a fissure.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001676.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 403.&#8212;Shot perforation of right femur; anterior view.
      <hi rend="italic">Sp</hi>. 319.</head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001677.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 404.&#8212;Posterior view of the same specimen.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
