<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e5026">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Gold, George</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e5026</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">84</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds of the scalp</term> 
                    <term>py&#230;mia, pyemia</term>
                    <term>secondary hemorrhage from wounds of scalp</term>
                    <term>successfully treated by ligating wounded vessel</term>
                    <term>fatal termination</term>
                    <term>musket ball struck scalp, passed backwards, lay bare skull and denuded pericranium</term>
                    <term>in middle of wound space sagittal suture passed and met coronal suture at anterior border</term>
                    <term>left chest pain resembling pleurisy</term>  
                    <term>dullness on percussion over right lung</term>
                    <term>yellow serum in left pleura, none in right</term>
                    <term>lower lobe of left lung in gray hepatization</term>
                    <term>upper lobe of left lung and lower lobe of right lung in red hepatization</term>
                    <term>circumscribed deposits of pus in both lungs</term>
                    <term>pus along coronal and sagittal sutures, dissecting scalp from bone</term>
                    <term>pus between bone and dura mater</term>                 
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>            
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0034">            
                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="335">Private
                        George Gold</name>, <name type="organization" key="148">Co. I, 155th
                        Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>, aged 23 years, was admitted to <name
                        type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name> on <date type="admit"
                        when="1864-10-07">October 7th, 1864</date>. He had been wounded at <name type="battle" key="xx">Poplar
                            Grove Church</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1864-09-30">September 30th</date>, by
                    a musket ball, which struck the scalp, passing from before backwards, tearing up
                    a portion about three inches in length by one inch in breadth, laying bare the
                    skull and denuding it of its pericranium for the space of three inches in length
                    and one inch in breadth, through the middle of which space the sagittal suture
                    passed, meeting the coronal at the anterior border.  The patient was carefully
                    watched for symptoms indicative of cerebral or meningeal inflammation; but none
                    were manifested up to the moment of his death, unless a slight drowsiness,
                    which, at the time, was attributed to the administration of eight grains of
                    Dover's powder, might be so regarded.  He was up and about the ward, complaining
                    of nothing except the wound in the scalp, and receiving no treatment, except
                    simple dressings, until the morning of October 18th, when he spoke of a slight
                    pain in the left side of the chest, over the lower lobe of the lung. There was
                    some dullness on percussion over the part complained of, but no marked physical
                    signs of inflammatory mischief.  On October 19th, the patient was worse. The pain
                    in the left chest was more severe, resembling that of pleurisy; the pulse was
                    full and frequent; the tongue brown and rather dry; there was very little cough,
                    and no expectoration. On percussion, the right side was very dull over the lower
                    lobe, less so over the upper lobe. The respiratory murmurs were nearly if not
                    quite normal, over the whole of the right lung. Examination by auscultation
                    unsatisfactory, on account of the turbulent action of the heart and the catching
                    character of the respiration. There was no cephalic or nervous symptoms.  On
                    October 20th, the patient appeared more comfortable in the early part of the
                    day, the respiration less labored, and pulse more quiet, and tongue more moist;
                    towards the latter part of the day, however, the symptoms increased in severity.
                    Great dullness over whole of left side of chest was noticed, and greatly
                    diminished resonance on the right side. The vesicular murmur was heard over a
                    small portion of the superior lobe of the left lung only. Moist friction sounds
                    over nearly the whole of the left lung could be heard, together with bronchial
                    respiration, and, at some circumscribed parts, a very coarse crepitation. On the
                    right side the vesicular murmur was rather faint, and greatly obscured by
                    bronchial respiration.  On October 21st, there was less pain and
                    dyspn&#339;a, very little cough, with a soft infrequent pulse, pale
                    countenance, and increasing dullness on percussion over the right side. Towards
                    the latter part of the day there was less drowsiness.  The patient died at
                    half-past eight o'clock, on <date type="death" when="1864-10-22">October 22d, 1864</date>. He was perfectly sensible and rational within ten minutes of
                    his death.   A <hi rend="italic">post mortem</hi> examination was made <date type="autopsy" when="1864-10-22">three hours
                    afterwards</date>. Cadaveric rigidity was strongly marked; the skin of the chest and
                    face was of a deeply jaundiced hue. On making an opening into the chest, about
                    twenty ounces of yellow serum was found in the left pleura, none in the right.
                    The pleural cavities of both sides, but particularly the left, were covered to a
                    considerable extent with coagulable lymph of considerable firmness. The left
                    costal and pulmonary pleural were bound strongly together by broad, thick bands,
                    the result of some former disease. There were also a few much less firm
                    attachments on the right side. The lower lobe of the left lung was in a state of
                    gray hepatization, the upper lobe in that of red hepatization, and in both, at
                    various points, were found circumscribed deposits of pus, containing from
                    one-half a drachm to a drachm each. The lower lobe of the right lung was in a
                    state of red hepatization, and the middle and upper lobes were greatly
                    congested. In the lower lobe were found two or three purulent deposits, which
                    appeared to form centres of inflammation, or metastatic foci. The wound along
                    the scalp appeared as during life. Pus was found along the coronal and sagittal
                    sutures, throughout the whole extent, dissecting the scalp from the bone, to the
                    breadth of one inch. The skull was roughened, and deprived of pericranium to
                    that extent. The portion of the wound which had been originally denuded had
                    begun to exfoliate, a line of separation being visible around it. On removing
                    the calvaria, a thin layer of pus was found between the bone and dura mater,
                    extending along the sagittal and coronal sutures to the same extent as on the
                    external surface, the amount of pus within the skull being less than one drachm.
                    There was a narrow strip of the dura mater each side of these sutures which was
                    inflamed; at other parts this membrane was healthy. The arachnoid and pia mater
                    were perfectly normal. The brain and its ventricles, the cerebellum, medulla
                    oblongata, and roots of all the cerebral nerves, were carefully examined, and no
                    lesions were discovered. The heart and its valves, the vena cava and azygos, the
                    pulmonary veins and arteries, the jugulars, and the blood-vessels of the brain,
                    were in a normal condition. The liver was apparently healthy.   <name
                        type="person" key="336">Acting Assistant Surgeon Cobb</name> recorded the
                    case. </p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
