<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10987">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Sullivan, Denis</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e10987</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">148-149</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term>
                    <term>gunshot fractures of the inner table of the skull</term>
                    <term>fractures of the vitreous table of the skull without fracture or
                        depression of the outer table</term>
                    <term>trephining performed</term>
                    <term>depressed fracture of the inner table and vitreous plate</term>
                    <term>abscess in substance of cerebral hemisphere</term>
                    <term>musket ball denuded and contused frontal bone below coronal suture to left
                        of median line</term>
                    <term>paroxysms of ague daily</term>
                    <term>pneumonia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2014-07-03">corrected typo in figure head</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding,
                edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-30">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0185">
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 17.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1430">Private <hi
                        rend="italic">Denis S</hi>&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization"
                    key="788">Co. E, 2d Virginia Cavalry</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded, in an
                engagement at <name type="place">Harper's Farm</name>, near <name type="place"
                    >Appomattox Court House</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1865-04-06">April
                    6th, 1865</date>, by the oblique impact of a musket ball which denuded and
                contused the frontal bone a little below the coronal suture and to the left of the
                median line. Being taken prisoner, he was placed in a field hospital where a water
                dressing was applied, the hair being shaved off to a suitable extent. A few days
                subsequently, he was sent to the rear, and he reached <name type="place"
                    key="#Washington">Washington</name> a fortnight after the reception of his
                wound, and was placed in <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name> on
                    <date type="admit" when="1865-04-19">April 19th</date>. He had a chill soon
                after his admission, and reported that for some days he had suffered from two
                paroxysms of ague daily. He had no pain in the head, nor any symptom to excite
                apprehension as to the condition of the brain, except the chills, which were
                ascribed to malarial influence. They proved, however, not to be amenable to quinia,
                which was freely administered, for several days, without advantage. On April 24th, a
                slight congestion of the lower lobe of the right lung was noticed. The next day
                pneumonia was fully developed here, and on the 26th the greater portion of the right
                lung was involved, and there was acute pain in the cardiac region, with a souffle
                accompanying the first sound of the heart and a murmur of regurgitation the second
                sound. The pulse rose rapidly to 156; but fluctuated greatly in frequency and force.
                At ten in the evening of <date type="operation" when="1865-04-26">this day</date>
                the patient became comatose. Shortly afterwards, <name type="person" key="158"
                    >Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
                    Vols.</name>, applied the crown of a small trephine on the right of the space in
                which the pericranium was removed. When the outer table was passed, pus began to
                exude from the cells of the diplo&#235;. When this was penetrated a depressed
                fracture of the inner table was discovered. Another perforation was now made to
                obtain space to remove the depressed fragments of vitreous plate. A small fragment
                and another measuring nine by six lines were found completely detached, and were
                removed by common dissecting forceps. The operation had no influence upon the
                profound coma, that persisted until the patient's death, which took place on the
                following morning, <date type="death" when="1865-04-28">April 28th, 1865</date>. At
                the autopsy, a large abscess was found in the substance of the right cerebral
                hemisphere. A segment of the frontal bone, with the two disks and the larger
                fragment of the inner table, removed at the operation, were forwarded to the <name
                    type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> by <name type="person"
                    key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U.
                    S. V.</name>, and are represented in the accompanying wood-cut, (<hi
                    rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 61.) A view of the interior of the specimen is given
                in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. I, of the Catalogue of the Surgical Section of
                the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, (p. 6.) and in the
                Surgical Report in <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 11, <hi
                    rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 6, and a photograph of the patient, taken a few
                hours prior to the operation, is preserved at <name type="hospital" key="431">the
                    Museum</name>, as No. 58, Vol. I, of the Series of Contributed Photographs of
                Surgical Cases. The lower figure in Plate III, opposite page 105, is copied from the
                photograph, and represents the appearance of the patient after the graver symptoms
                of compression of the brain had set in. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001380.001"/>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 61.&#8212;Segment of a cranium trephined for a
                    depressed fracture of the inner table. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4344, Sect.
                    I, A. M. M.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001364.001"/>
                <head>Plate III. GUNSHOT SCALP WOUNDS AND CONTUSIONS OF THE SKULL. 4. Private Denis
                    Sullivan, 2 Virginia Cavalry.</head>
            </figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
