<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e24665">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Private J. M. Granger</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e24665</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted:  
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">643-644</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>miscellaneous injuries</term> 
     <term>contusions and sprains</term>
     <term>injured by falling of heavy piece of timber on shoulder, striking upon superior and posterior aspect over spine of scapula</term>
     <term>almost total inability to use arm, rupture of <choice><orig>musculo-spiral</orig><reg>radial</reg></choice> nerve</term> 
     <term>shoulder swollen, greatest tumefaction directly over supra-spinous region</term> 
     <term>general contusion of shoulder, followed by inflammatory action</term> 
     <term>inability to prove origin of injury in line of duty, claim for pension rejected</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 945.—<hi rend="italic">Contusion of the
      shoulder.</hi>—<name type="person" key="1418">Private J. M. Granger</name>, <name type="organization" key="534">Co. F, 141st New York</name>, aged 26 years, entered Central Park Hospital, <name type="place">New York City</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-17">December 17, 1862</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon B. A. Clements</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, forwarded the following
     report:  "In <date type="injury" when="1862-10">October, 1862</date>, the patient was injured
     at <name type="place">Annapolis</name> by the falling of a heavy piece of timber on his right shoulder, striking upon the
     superior and posterior aspect over the spine of the scapula. The blow was so severe as to knock
     him down. He was immediately taken to hospital, where the hand and arm swelled largely and he
     became unable to use them without great suffering.  <date type="transfer" when="1862-11">Five weeks afterwards</date> he entered <name type="hospital" key="67">Trinity Hospital</name> at Washington, whence he was transferred here
     <date type="transfer" when="1862-12">two weeks later</date>.  On examination the patient was found to be well nourished and in general good
     condition, but his face had an anxious expression, or that of suffering. The right shoulder was
     swollen, the greatest amount of tumefaction being directly over the supra-spinous region. The
     whole arm and hand were also swollen and of a purplish color, and the patient was unable to
     raise them except to a limited degree. By an assistant the arm could be moved with difficulty
     and the hand might be placed on the top of the head. The patient underwent a variety of
     treatment, including colchicum, iodide of potassa, liniments, etc., without any appreciable
     benefit, the condition of the shoulder and arm remaining unchanged, the hand swollen and cold,
     and the arm quite stiff and useless. When he received his discharge from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-12-23">December 23, 1863</date>, his general health was not as
     good as formerly."  He subsequently made application for pension, and received the following certificate from <name type="person" key="xx">Examining Surgeon W. M. Chamberlain</name>, of <name type="place">New York City</name>: "There has
     been a general contusion of the shoulder, followed by inflammatory action about the joint. Depression of the shoulder and almost total inability to use the arm is dependent perhaps upon
     rupture of the <choice><orig>musculo-spiral</orig><reg>radial</reg></choice> nerve."  Owing to the applicant's inability to prove the origin of
     the injury in the line of duty his claim for pension was rejected.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
