<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41908">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Brooks, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41908</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">446</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>acute dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in acute dysentery</term>
     <term>diphtheritic inflammation</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>colon thickened and ulcerated after separation of pseudomembrane</term>
     <term>upper rectum swollen and infiltrated, irregularly coated with pseudomembrane</term>
     <term>in lower rectum diseased coats separated by sloughing</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-31">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and
    encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p>The sloughing which attacks the parts entangled in the diphtheritic exudation may be a gradual
    process, in which the necrosed tissue separates in little shreds; or portions of the surface of
    considerable size may be thrown off. The plate facing this page, which is a reproduction of a
    nature-size photograph of No. 703, Medical Section, illustrates one variety of the former of
    these processes. The following is a brief history of the case:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 893.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Wm.
     Brooks</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company H, 2d United States colored
     troops</name>; enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1865-03-11">March 11, 1865</date>. From this
    time till December 31, 1863, he appears on the muster-rolls of his company as present for duty,
    except during September and October, when he was on detached service. With the exception of
    these two mouths he served in Florida, and was under treatment by the regimental surgeon in June
    for constipation, and in July and August for jaundice. About <date type="injury" when="1865-12">the middle of December</date> he was taken sick with dysentery, and <date type="transfer" when="1866-01">in January</date> was sent north for treatment. He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., <date type="admit" when="1866-01-12">January 12, 1866</date>, having at that time been sick four weeks. He had the
    usual symptoms of acute dysentery, and died <date type="death" when="1866-01-20">January
     20th</date>. Was not much emaciated at the time of death. The treatment consisted of
    astringents, opiates and supporting measures. <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> The small
    intestine appeared to be quite normal. The colon was thickened and ulcerated in many places
    throughout. The rectum as in the specimen. The condition of the other organs is not
     recorded.—<name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> [No. 703, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, is from this case.]</p>
   <p>The specimen represented by the plate is from the rectum of this patient. In the upper part of
    the piece the mucous and submucous tissues are swollen and infiltrated; the surface is
    irregularly coated with tough pseudomembrane. In the lower part of the piece the diseased coats
    are separating by sloughing, the sloughs adhering by one extremity and hanging down as
    string-like shreds, for the most part only a quarter to half an inch in length, but a few much
    longer. Higher up in the colon, it would appear from the report of the autopsy, the sloughs had
    completely separated in many places, leaving numerous ulcers.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001501.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XVI. RECTUM WITH SLOUGHING PSEUDO-MEMBRANE. No. 703.
     MEDICAL SECTION.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
