<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31381">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Rand, C. F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31381</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">529</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
       <term>decapitations of the humerus for shot injury</term>
       <term>primary decapitations of the humerus for shot injury</term>
       <term>successful cases of primary decapitation of the humerus</term>
       <term>bleeding from wound on the field</term> 
       <term>head of humerus excised</term>
       <term>arm hangs by muscles and ligaments, little use of hand</term>
       <term>arm of no use for manual labor</term> 
       <term>three inches shortening of limb</term>
       <term>resection of shoulder necessitated by shot wound</term>       
       <term>studied medicine, became a practitioner in Washington</term>    
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-23">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change> 
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1500.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant C. F. Rand</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 12th New York</name>, aged 24 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="22"><choice><orig>Gaines's</orig><reg>Gaines'</reg></choice> Mill</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-06-27">June 27, 1862</date>. There is no hospital record of the case until the patient's arrival at <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>; but, twelve years subsequently, the injured man stated that: &#34;He laid on the field all that night, and was carried to the general field hospital at <name type="place">Savage's Station</name> <date type="admit" when="1862-06-28">the next morning</date>. There was free bleeding from the wound. At <name type="place">Savage's Station</name> the head of the humerus was excised either by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">12th New York</name>, or by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. Swinburne</name>.  From this station, he was sent to <name type="place">Richmond</name>.&#34;  He complained of the road and river transportation. After discharge from the prison hospital he stated that he was exposed at the dock until the arrival of the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">transport Daniel Webster</name>, on which he was conveyed to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>. He entered <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Satterlee Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1862-07-30">July 30, 1862</date>, and was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1862-08-30">a month subsequently</date> and pensioned, <name type="person" key="137">Surgeon I. I. Hayes</name> certifying: &#34;Resection of shoulder, necessitated by shot wound.&#34;  This pensioner re-enlisted in the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserves</name>, and was appointed in <date type="enlist" when="1863-11"><date type="promotion" when="1863-11">November, 1863</date></date>, a second lieutenant, and assigned, in May, 1864, to duty at <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>.  <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, had prepared a photograph, which is copied in Figure 4 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XIV</hi>, opposite page 529, and furnished a copy to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> with the following memorandum: &#34;This officer can use his arm at table, and plays well on the banjo.&#34;  On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1868-01-01">January 1, 1868</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant Rand</name> was discharged. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner John Root</name>, of <name type="place">Batavia, New York</name>, in <date type="pension" when="1869-06">June, 1869</date>, reported: &#34;The arm hangs by the muscles and ligaments, and for manual labor is of no use;&#34; and, in <date type="pension" when="1873-09">September, 1873</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. O. Stanton</name> reported: &#34;About three inches of shortening of the limb. Cannot raise the arm. Has little use of the hand.&#34;  This pensioner was paid in <date type="pension" when="1874-09">September, 1874</date>.  He availed of the opportunities afforded by his assignment to hospital duty to study medicine, and, receiving a diploma from one of the medical colleges in Washington, became a practitioner there.  In addition, he occupies a responsible position in the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Post Office Department</name>.  The result of the primary excision in this case is very satisfactory.</p> 
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001715.001" />
    <head>PLATE  XIV.   RESULTS  OF  EXCISIONS  OF  THE  HEAD  OF  THE  HUMERUS.    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.  IV.    Lieut. C. T. Rand.</head> 
   </figure> 
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
