<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9770">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Private Jonathan Wallace</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9770</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">204-205</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>excisions in the continuity of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary excisions in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>fatal cases of primary excision in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>missile entered external surface of thigh at lower portion of middle third, fractured
      femur through middle third, emerged on internal surface above wound of entrance</term>
     <term>injured limb shortened one inch</term>
     <term>femoral vein contained blood clots</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>py&#230;mia</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 415.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1059">Private <hi
      rend="italic">Jonathan Wallace</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="424">Co. F, 21st
     Georgia</name>, aged 38 years, was wounded by a conoidal ball, in the charge on <name
     type="FORT" key="xx">Fort Steadman</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-25">March 25,
     1865</date>. The missile entered on the external surface of the left thigh at the lower portion
    of the middle third, passed obliquely upward and inward, fractured the femur through the middle
    third, and emerged on the internal surface an inch above the wound of entrance. He was taken to
    the field hospital of the 2d division, Ninth Corps, where <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon
     G. W. Snow</name>, <name type="organization" key="425">35th Massachusetts</name>, reports that
    "resection at the middle third of the femur was performed by <name type="person" key="xx"
     >Surgeon G. R. Sullivan</name>, <name type="organization" key="426">39th New Jersey</name>, and
    anterior splints applied." On <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-10">April 10th</date>, he was
    admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington.
     <name type="person" key="424">Acting Assistant Surgeon George K. Smith</name> reports "that the
    injured limb was shortened one inch; extension was applied (Buck's method) with a weight of
    eleven pounds, after which there was no shortening. Patient did remarkably well until June 8th,
    when he was attacked with diarrh&#339;a, which was arrested at the end of three days. On June
    23d, the bone appeared to be firmly united with half an inch shortening, and, on July 2d,
    extension was removed, and the patient rode about the ward in an invalid chair. July 28th, it
    was discovered that the limb had shortened two and one-fourth inches; extension was reapplied
    with a weight of sixteen pounds, and, on August 5th, it measured three-fourths of an inch
    shorter than its fellow. On <date type="photo" when="1865-08-15">August 15th</date>, a
    photograph of the patient was taken [No. 92 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Photograph
     Series</hi> of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, a reduced copy
    of which is represented in the wood-cut, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 164]. On <date
     type="transfer" when="1865-08-17">August 17th</date>, the wound had nearly healed, his
    condition was remarkably good, and the bone had apparently united." On this date he was
    transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, to the
    care of <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon W. F. Norris</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who reports: "The wound was still open and
    discharging a small quantity of matter, but there was firm union of the broken femur, and the
    patient could without assistance raise his leg from the bed. His general health seemed to be
    improving, and he daily rode about the ward in a wheeled chair, the limb being supported in an
    extended position. <date type="operation" when="1865-08-26">August 26th</date> several small
    loose fragments of bone were removed. August 28th, had a severe chill; on the 29th, had an
    attack of erysipelas in the thigh, and, on the following day, a loose piece of necrosed bone,
    one and a half inches in length, was removed. On September 2d, erysipelas had spread down to
    ankle joint. 11th, erysipelas had disappeared; another small sequestrum was removed from the
    posterior wound. 16th, had two chills, diarrh&#339;al passages, and vomiting. 21st, he steadily
    grew weaker; the wound had almost ceased to discharge. There was slight icterus; the countenance
    was pinched and anxious and the breathing labored. 22d, he had pain in chest and abdomen, and
    was unable to pass his urine. These symptoms continued until the evening of the <date
     type="death" when="1865-09-23">23d</date>, when death ensued from py&#230;mia. At the autopsy,
    fifteen hours after death, the brain appeared healthy; but there was a large amount of serous
    subarachnoid effusion. Both lungs were adherent and thickly studded with py&#230;mic patches,
    most of which were dark colored and hardened, a few only having softened, and containing pus.
    There was considerable serous effusion in the left pleural sac. The spleen was enlarged but not
    softened; the other thoracic and abdominal viscera appeared healthy. The fractured femur [which
    is represented in the adjoining wood-cut, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 165] was removed and
    sawn longitudinally; above the fracture the marrow and interspaces between the cancelli
    presented a reddish chocolate hue, below, it appeared reddened and inflamed; it had not, in
    either locality, any gangrenous odor. The femoral vein [represented in <hi rend="initialcap"
     >P</hi>LATE XXX, opposite] was found to contain old and partially disintegrated blood clots,
    and in some portions also a quantity of healthy looking creamy pus; its walls were much
    thickened. It continued to present the same appearance up to about two inches below its junction
    with the internal iliac vein; here the clots ceased, and the coats of the vein, although of
    reddish hue, did not appear much thickened. The pus was carefully examined with the microscope
    and presented its usual round corpuscles, which under the application of acetic acid exhibited
    distinctly their characteristic double and triple nuclei. The femoral artery appeared to be
    healthy." </p>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001572.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 164&#8212;Appearance five months after excision in middle third
    of femur. [From a photograph.]</head></figure>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001573.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 165&#8212;Ends of fractured left femur united six months after
    shot injury. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1354.</head></figure>
   <p>PLATE XXX. &#8212; OBSTRUCTED FEMORAL VEIN</p>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
