<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10795">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Hatch, David G.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e10795</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">748</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases attributed to non-miasmatic exposures</term>
                                        <term>diseases of the respiratory organs</term>
                                        <term>diphtheritic inflammation of the fauces, etc.</term>
                                        <term>doubt diphtheria was constitutional disease from specific poison</term> 
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>diphtheria</term>  
                                        <term>could not swallow</term>  
                                        <term>chest dull on percussion, bronchial breathing heard</term>
                                        <term>respiration painful and difficult</term>
                                        <term>admitted with typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>acrid discharges from nose, sordes on teeth</term>
                                        <term>fibrinous mass, grayish-white in larynx and red in trachea</term>
                                        <term>bronchial tubes occluded with plugs of white fibrinous lymph</term>
                                        <term>lower lobe of lung consolidated, middle lobe partially carnified, upper lobe generally consolidated</term>
                                        <term>cheesy and calcareous degeneration of bronchial glands</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches congested and spotted</term>
                                        <term>suprarenal capsules enlarged</term>
                                        <term>diphtheritic layer coated posterior surface of soft palate and under surface of epiglottis, notably at rima glottidis</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches congested and spotted, valvul&#230; irregularly congested</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>  
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>                        
                        <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 20.&#8212;<name type="person">Private David G. Hatch</name>, <name type="organization">Co. H, 13th N. H.</name>;
                                age 23; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1862-12-30">Dec. 30, 1862</date>, with typhoid fever.  On
                                <date type="injury" when="1863-02-23">Feb. 23, 1863</date>, he had high fever, pulse 144, and a dry
                                        hacking cough; his throat, lips and tongue were much swollen
                                        and his mouth and fauces dry and inflamed. He continued to
                                        take food till March 1, when he complained that he could not
                                        swallow. At this time the chest was dull on percussion and
                                        bronchial breathing was heard; respiration was painful
                                        and difficult, the pulse low, breath offensive and the
                                        extremities cold; acrid discharges came from the nose,
                                        sordes accumulated on the teeth and the expectoration was
                                        mixed with putrid masses.  He died on <date type="death" when="1863-03-03">the 3d</date>.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The brain was pale and firm. The trachea,
                                        larynx, posterior half of the left side of the fauces, the
                                        pharynx on the line of the nares and the posterior part of
                                        the floor of the nares were covered with a fibrinous mass,
                                        grayish-white in the larynx and red in the trachea.  [<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 7, Med. Sec., <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, shows a
                                        diphtheritic layer coating the posterior surface of the soft
                                        palate and the under surface of the epiglottis; it is
                                        notably present at the rima glottidis.]  The right lung
                                        weighed thirty-nine ounces; its bronchial tubes were
                                        occluded with plugs of white fibrinous lymph, which, when
                                        detached with difficulty, revealed longitudinally striated
                                        mucous membrane, roughened and in places granulated; on
                                        section the tubes appeared as yellowish-white spots; the
                                        lower lobe was almost entirely consolidated; the middle
                                        lobe, shrivelled and partially carnified, had its main
                                        bronchus totally occluded by a large plug; the upper lobe
                                        was generally consolidated, but the bronchial plugs were
                                        less adherent and there were neither stri&#230; nor
                                        granulations in the bronchi. Some of the bronchial glands
                                        were in a state of cheesy and calcareous degeneration. The
                                        heart was pale and contained fibrinous clots in both sides;
                                        nineteen drachms of brownish serum were found in the
                                        pericardium. The duodenum was stained; Peyer's patches
                                        were much congested and spotted; the valvul&#230; were thin and
                                        irregularly congested and the mucous membrane of a livid
                                        flesh-color. The large intestine was normal. The liver,
                                        fifty-nine ounces, was mottled, pale and softened; the
                                        spleen, seven ounces and a quarter, was mottled of a
                                        light-purple color, its trabecul&#230; distinct and firm and its
                                        substance pulpy; the pancreas firm and purple; the kidneys
                                        reddish flesh-colored and firm; the suprarenal capsules
                                        enlarged, straw-colored and of natural consistence.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="244">Ass't Surgeon Geo. M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi> </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
