<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41932">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Manchester, A. L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41932</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">519</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>morbid anatomy</term>
     <term>chronic inflammation of the intestines accompanied by follicular or other ulcers</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>measles</term>
     <term>measles and enteritis</term>
     <term>small intestine inflamed near ileoc&#230;cal valve</term>
     <term>large intestine inflamed and ulcerated</term>
     <term>descending colon exhibited small, oval follicular ulcers, also irregular ulcers with
      overhanging edges</term>
     <term>tormina and tenesmus</term>
     <term>bloody stools</term>
     <term>catarrhal ulcers</term>
     <term>diphtheritic inflammation</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>The extreme dimensions of the erosions, which occasionally result from the extension of
    follicular ulcers, are well illustrated by the plate facing page 526, which is a reproduction of
    a photograph of No. 195, Medical Section. The following is an account of the case:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 904.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant A. L.
     Manchester</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 152d New York
     volunteers</name>; age 23; was enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1862-09-27">September 27,
     1862</date>, and continued to do duty with his company until March, 1863. During much of this
    time he had diarrh&#339;a, which, however, did not prevent him from remaining on duty. <date
     type="injury" when="1863-03-02">March 2d</date>, being then on duty as one of the guard at
     <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., he was attacked by
    measles, with dry skin, pulse 110, and dark tongue. At the time of this attack he was a good
    deal broken down by the disorder of his bowels, and when, on the <date type="admit"
     when="1863-03-05">5th of March</date>, he was transferred to a bed in the hospital, the entry
    in the register was "measles and enteritis." The stools had been comparatively painless, but,
    March 7th, tormina and tenesmus supervened and they became bloody; they did not, however, exceed
    ten in twelve hours. These symptoms gradually abated under the use of a chalk mixture with
    opiate suppositories, and by the 12th of March the stools were reduced to four in the
    twenty-four hours, and were no longer bloody; skin moist; tongue cleaner; pulse 70, but quite
    feeble; the patient began to eat, and was now free from tenesmus and abdominal pain. March 20th:
    Is much better; pulse 84 and stronger; he sits up; has milk and eggs for diet; the remedies
    employed seem to control the tendency to pain and straining; the latter symptom appears to be
    kept in check by the use of the suppositories mentioned above. March 22d: Appetite better; only
    three painless passages in the last twenty-four hours; pulse 84; skin natural; tongue coated;
    slight tenderness on pressure in the left inguinal region. March 28th: Not so well; pulse 110;
    skin natural; has had about four stools daily for the last few days; they are dark-colored and
    stringy; tongue coated with a brownish fur; increased tenderness in left inguinal and lumbar
    regions. March 29th: Pulse 125; skin dry; tongue coated, but not so thickly as yesterday.
    Ordered quinia and milk punch. March 30th: Continual bilious vomiting set in, which was somewhat
    relieved by creasote, but it recurred from time to time, and death ensued <date type="death"
     when="1863-04-01">April 1st</date>. Stimulants, beef tea, &#38;c., had been freely used during
    the last week of life. <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> The small intestine near the
    ileoc&#230;cal valve was inflamed; higher up it was healthy. The large intestine was extensively
    inflamed and ulcerated.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Henry L. W.
     Burritt</name>. [Nos. 194 and 195, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army
     Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.]</p>
   <p>The plate represents a portion of descending colon, which exhibits a number of the small,
    oval, characteristic follicular ulcers, but shows besides a number of large irregular ulcers
    with overhanging edges. The largest of these are more than an inch in diameter. It is probable
    that follicular ulceration had existed in this case for some time before the patient was
    attacked by measles, and that in consequence of the adynamic condition induced by that disease
    the ulcers rapidly extended. This seems to have been effected by a simple ulcerative process
    quite independent of any diphtheritic inflammation, and the specimens afford an excellent
    illustration of the great size to which catarrhal ulcers sometimes extend. No. 194, Medical
    Section, is taken from higher up the same colon, and exhibits similar lesions but in a less
    marked degree.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001509.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XXXIV. COLON WITH IRREGULAR ULCERS. No. 195. MEDICAL
     SECTION.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
