<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41915">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Glascow, Taylor W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41915</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">449</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>acute dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in acute dysentery</term>
     <term>diphtheritic inflammation</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
     <term>typhoid fever</term>
     <term>dysentery</term>
     <term>chronic flux</term>
     <term>colon extensively ulcerated</term>
     <term>condition of other organs not recorded</term>
     <term>ulcers do not penetrate muscular coat, but do invade submucous connective tissue
      deeply</term>
     <term>acute diphtheritic dysentery, in convalescence from typhoid fever</term>
     <term>small intestine not examined for traces of typhoid fever</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and
    added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p>Somewhat similar is the character of the ulcers shown in the chromo-plate facing page 454. The
    following is a history of the case:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 897.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Taylor W.
     Glascow</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company H, 110th Pennsylvania
     volunteers</name>; age 34; admitted to <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory hospital</name>,
    Washington, D. C., <date type="admit" when="1863-10-17">October 17, 1863</date>. Chronic
    diarrhœa. This man enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1862-09-25">September 25,
    1862</date>, and is reported on the muster-rolls of his company as present until March, 1863.
    Some time <date type="injury" when="1863-04">during April</date> he was taken sick and sent to
    division hospital. <date type="admit" when="1863-06-14">June 14, 1863</date>, he was admitted to
    the <name type="hospital" key="500">1st division Alexandria hospital</name>. Diagnosis, typhoid
    fever. He was, however, now in a convalescent condition, and was returned to duty with his
    regiment, <date type="duty" when="1863-08-11">August 11th</date>. Shortly after he was attacked
    with dysentery, for which he was finally admitted to <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory
     hospital</name>, as above stated. His disease now presented the aspect of a chronic flux. He
    was treated at first with pills of camphor and opium, but as the discharges from the bowels
    continued unabated, he was put to bed on the 21st, and tannic acid and opium substituted. Light
    diet. The diarrhœa was checked for a few days, but again grew worse about November 1st,
    when a chalk mixture was prescribed and a diet of boiled milk and toast. November 5th, he
    complained of pain in the abdomen. The diarrhœa was about the same. Substituted Parrish's
    camphor mixture and laudanum. November 11th, the patient complained of being unable to sleep.
    The diarrhœa remains about the same. Ordered mercury with chalk, and Dover's powder at
    night. November 16th, is worse. Stools more frequent. The patient appears much debilitated.
    Ordered pills of acetate of lead, opium and ipecacuanha; stimulants. Under this treatment he was
    again temporarily better, but again became worse about the 25th, when calomel and opium were
    substituted. December 3d, is much weaker; the diarrhœa unchecked. Stopped the pills;
    continued the stimulants. December 4th, at the request of the patient, procured him some
    blackberry brandy, which he seemed to relish; but in a few days discontinued its use, as it
    seemed to nauseate him. December 8th, is considerably emaciated, greatly prostrated and growing
    rapidly weaker. The stools are very frequent and tinged with blood. Ordered beef tea, brandy and
    a laudanum injection at night. Died, <date type="death" when="1863-12-13">December 13th</date>.
     <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> The colon was considerably thickened and extensively ulcerated.
    [The condition of the other organs is not recorded.]—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting
     Assist. Surgeon W. H. Combs</name>. [No. 115, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Army Medical Museum</name>, is from this case.]</p>
   <p>A portion of the descending colon from this case was brought to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> immediately after the autopsy, and a water-color drawing
    made by <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Hermann Faber</name>, of which the chromo-plate is a
    reproduction. The piece presents a number of ulcers, some of them of considerable size, which
    for the most part do not penetrate to the muscular coat, but invade the submucous connective
    tissue more or less deeply. The general surface of the mucous membrane between the ulcers is
    cream colored, with bluish and greenish streaks and patches. There are also a number of reddish
    patches in which the congested condition of the small veins is recognizable with the unaided
    eye. The bases of the ulcers are for the most part quite smooth, and similar in tint to the
    mucous membrane itself, but two of them are stippled with minute granulations; their edges are
    bevelled or rounded, not overhanging. This case, like the last, is to be interpreted as one of
    acute diphtheritic dysentery, which, in this instance, occurred not long after convalescence
    from typhoid fever. The precise duration of the disease is not shown by the record. It clearly
    commenced some time after the 11th of August, when the patient had sufficiently recovered from
    typhoid fever to be returned to his regiment for duty; but it cannot have commenced very long
    afterwards, for when admitted to <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory hospital</name> the
    disease had already so far advanced as to present the characters of a chronic flux. The duration
    of his last illness must therefore have probably been somewhere between three and four months, a
    sufficient time to permit the complete separation of all the diphtheritic sloughs, but the
    resulting ulcers were too numerous and extensive to permit recovery. The physician who made the
    autopsy was unacquainted with the fact that the patient had previously suffered from typhoid
    fever, and does not appear to have examined the small intestine for traces of that disease.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001503.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XX. ULCERATION OF THE COLON. No. 115. MEDICAL
     SECTION.</head>
   </figure>
   <p/>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
