<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19886">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Grothenn, Henry</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e19886</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">545</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>ligations</term>
          <term>ligations of the subclavian</term>
          <term>traumatic <choice>
              <orig>aneurism</orig>
              <reg>aneurysm</reg>
            </choice></term>
          <term>circumscribed <choice>
              <orig>aneurism</orig>
              <reg>aneurysm</reg>
            </choice> from gunshot injury</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
          <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>

      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 21.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant Henry
          Grothenn</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 5th United States
          Cavalry</name>, aged 28 years, was admitted into the <name type="hospital">McClellan
          Hospital, Philadelphia</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-23">June 23d,
          1863</date>, from <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington,
        with an <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> of the right axillary artery, the result of a gunshot wound received at <name
          type="battle">Beverly Ford, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-06-09">June
          9th, 1863</date>. The ball had passed in on the anterior part of the arm, near the
        shoulder-joint, and was cut out at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>
        an inch below the interior angle of the scapula. In a report of the case in the <hi
          rend="italic">American Journal of Medical Sciences</hi>, Vol. XLVII, p. 128, N. S., <name
          type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Isaac Norris</name> says: &#34;When I
        took charge of the ward, on July 26th, the patient was absent. He returned on the 28th, and
        after making a careful examination of the arm, the true nature of the disease became
        manifest, as the pulsation of the tumor at that time about the size of a large
        horse-chestnut was very apparent, and, upon auscultation, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> thrill could be distinctly heard, corresponding with the contraction of the left
        ventricle of the heart. My predecessor had had made an apparatus composed of a compress of
        lead with screws so arranged that by tightening them any amount of pressure desired could be
        placed upon the part. The apparatus was adjusted, but after a trial of some thirty hours, it
        was abandoned on account of the pain it gave the patient, and a padded bandage was
        substituted, in the faint hope that it might be of use. This was worn for nearly ten days,
        but it was finally left off, and the treatment was reduced to keeping the arm, as nearly as
        possible, at perfect rest. On <date type="injury" when="1863-08-16">the 16th of
          August</date> last, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> became much larger, and from the pressure upon the axillary plexus of nerves,
        caused him great pain. The following evening it was decided to operate and tie the
        subclavian, despite the hazard attending it. The <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> broke, unfortunately, early the next morning, before the operation could be
        performed, and the patient lost from thirty to forty ounces of blood. The h&#230;morrhage
        finally ceased of its own accord, but he was so weakened and exhausted from the great loss
        he had sustained, that it was the opinion of the medical staff of the hospital, upon
        consultation, that, if anything was attempted then, he would die under the operation, and
        that his life might be prolonged for a few hours more by keeping up digital compression upon
        the artery. This was accordingly done, and the assistants appointed, relieved each other
        every hour or two, until the arrival of <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon R. H.
          Coolidge</name>, medical inspector of <name type="organization" key="190">the Army</name>,
        on a chance visit to the hospital, who at once became interested in the case, and thought
        the subclavian should be tied without delay; the temporary absence of <name type="person"
          key="xxx">Dr. Taylor</name>, the surgeon in charge, being the objection to its
        performance. As the patient seemed to be rallying each hour, <name type="person" key="xxx"
          >Dr. Coolidge</name> decided to return to the hospital <date type="operation"
          when="1863-08-18">in the afternoon</date>, and operate, if no objection then existed. Upon
        his return, the h&#230;morrhage again having commenced, he proceeded to ligate the
        subclavian in the third part of its course. I here give the account of the operation as
        furnished by the Doctor: &#39;The patient came easily under the influence of the chloroform,
        and the operation was performed carefully and deliberately. The loss of blood amounted to a
        few drops only, h&#230;morrhage from the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> having been completely arrested by a tourniquet. Chloroform was not administered
        after the operation began. The artery, on being exposed, was found closer to the brachial
        plexus than usual, and it was also quite deeply seated, the patient being a large muscular
        man. An armed artery needle having been passed beneath the vessel from below upward and
        outward and withdrawn, it was found by the operator, and his assistants also, that the
        inferior cord of the brachial plexus was included in the ligature, a result attributed in
        part to the want of sufficient curve in the needle. Another one, having a more abrupt curve,
        being armed and passed beneath the artery, it was elevated by the first ligature, and care
        taken to exclude the nerve above mentioned. The first ligature was then withdrawn, and
        several of the medical officers present, having examined the parts, and satisfied themselves
        that nothing but the artery was embraced in the ligature, the knot was tied, the lips of the
        incision drawn together, and the patient placed in bed.&#39; Everything seemed to do well
        until about eight o'clock P. M., when the patient complained of considerable pain in the
        region of the wound. Morphia was given to him freely, and repeated the following hour, but
        without the effect of quieting him. The patient, from that time, grew rapidly worse,
        suffering with great dyspn&#339;a, and <date type="death" when="1863-08-18">at
          midnight</date> expired, six hours after the operation. The <hi rend="italic"
          >post-mortem</hi> revealed the unexpected fact that a nerve of considerable size, lying
        immediately posterior to the artery, had been included in the ligature despite the care that
        had been taken to prevent it. It is to be regretted that this nerve was not traced to its
        origin and termination; all that can now be said, is that it was followed as a single cord
        down to and upon the posterior wall of the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice>. It was certainly neither of the two cords of the brachial plexus, and its
        situation was, beyond doubt, abnormal, as the nerve included in the ligature was directly
        opposite the knot, and cannot be seen when the artery was placed in its proper position. It
        is scarcely necessary to add that no writer on anatomy has described such a nerve, nor has
        any dissection on record shown the existence of one, previous to this. At the time the
        ligature was tied, the patient was but slightly under the influence of chloroform, and no
        pain was manifested until several hours afterwards. The preparation is an exceedingly
        instructive one, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> sac being very large, and the course of the artery well shown. The infiltration of
        blood also into the surrounding cellular tissue was very great.&#34; The specimen,
        consisting of the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> sac and the subclavian, with a ligature on the third portion, is represented in
        the accompanying wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 250.) It was contributed, with
        the notes of the case, as subsequently published by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting
          Assistant Surgeon Isaac Norris, <choice>
            <orig>jr.</orig>
            <reg>Jr.</reg>
          </choice></name>
      </p>

      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001476.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 250.&#8212;Traumatic <choice>
            <orig>aneurism</orig>
            <reg>aneurysm</reg>
          </choice> of the right axillary, with ligation of the subclavian. <hi rend="italic"
            >Spec</hi>. 2609, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
