<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e8659">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Doyle, W. S.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e8659</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">381-382</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the ileum or small intestine only affected</term>                                           
                                        <term>ulcerated Peyer's patches, one perforated, peritoneum formed base of one</term>
                                        <term>peritoneal surface bright crimson, small intestine glued together with lymph</term>
                                        <term>abscess in walls of œsophagus</term>
                                        <term>agminated glands near ileo-cæcal valve formed elliptical ulcerated patches</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00156">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 156.—<name type="person" key="691">Private W. S. Doyle</name>,
                                                <name type="organization" key="687">Co. H, 3d Mich.
                                                Cav.</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-06-11">June 11, 1863</date>; died <date type="death" when="1863-10-15">October 15</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination:
                                        Sudamina were observed, especially on the abdomen and arms.
                                        The brain-substance was very firm; the lining membrane of
                                        the ventricles was roughened, especially over the corpora
                                        striata and the descending crura of the fornix, where the
                                        roughness seemed like an exudation of lymph, but it could
                                        not be detached without destroying the cerebral substance;
                                        there was no meningitis. The trachea, dark purplish-red in
                                        color, presented numerous minute whitish points of exudation
                                        on the surface of the mucous membrane at its upper part. The
                                        œsophagus was of a pale purple color superiorly and
                                        of a brownish hue below; an abscess the size of a chestnut
                                        was found in its walls. Both lungs were congested; the right
                                        weighing sixteen ounces and one-quarter, the left twelve
                                        ounces and a half. The heart contained fibrinous clots in
                                        both sides. The liver was firm, its capsule easily torn, its
                                        acini distinct; the spleen was pultaceous. The stomach was
                                        mottled and filled with liquid greenish fæcal-like
                                        matter. The intestines were distended with air; patches of
                                        the peritoneal surface were of a bright crimson color and
                                        the coils of the small intestine were glued together with recent lymph; the
                                        duodenum was of a dark color, its villi softened and readily
                                        detached; the ileum was passively congested, its solitary
                                        glands enlarged, its agminated glands elevated and whitish,
                                        those near the ileo-cæcal valve forming elliptical
                                        ulcerated patches with high thickened walls and smooth pale
                                        bases, in many instances covered by a whitish adherent
                                        exudation, while in one instance the peritoneum formed the
                                        base and in another perforation had taken place; the large
                                        intestine was healthy. The kidneys were
                                                normal.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. H.
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
