<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3912">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Way, Sidney D.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e3912</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">238-239</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term> 
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>tenderness and tympanites of the bowels</term> 
                                        <term>muscular twitchings</term>
                                        <term>sudamina</term> 
                                        <term>pneumonia</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-06-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00087">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 87.—<hi rend="italic">Headache, dizziness, deafness, delirium and
                                                muscular twitchings; relaxation, tenderness and
                                                tympanites of the bowels; pneumonia; no rose-colored
                                                spots.</hi>—<name type="person" key="545">Private Sidney D. Way</name>, <name type="organization" key="87">Co. I, 2d Vt.</name>;
                                        age 18; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-09-27">Sept. 27, 1861</date>, having been taken <date type="injury" when="1861-09">three
                                                        weeks before</date> with intermittent fever, cough and pain in the
                                        breast. The case was diagnosed typhoid fever. The patient
                                        was weak, his cheeks flushed, countenance anxious, pulse
                                        quick, 120, skin hot and dry; he had some pain in the head
                                        and chest, with deafness and muscular twitchings; there was
                                        anorexia with a moist white tongue, and relaxed bowels with
                                        much tympanites and general abdominal tenderness. Small
                                        doses of blue-pill and opium were given on the 28th and
                                        turpentine emulsion on the 29th. During the next four days
                                        his condition was but little altered; the deafness
                                        increased, and delirium, dizziness and aphonia were
                                        manifested; three or four passages from the bowels were
                                        recorded every twelve hours; the cough occasionally became troublesome, and
                                        was accompanied with a mucous expectoration; the
                                        respirations were at one time as high as 36 per minute. On
                                        the morning of October 2 the patient, having slept well
                                        during the previous night, was found with the skin of natural
                                        temperature and bathed in perspiration, sudamina on the right
                                        side and over the abdomen, the tongue moist and slightly
                                        coated yellow, and the pulse 95 but strong and quick; two
                                        stools had been passed during the night and a little blood
                                        expectorated, after which the cough became less troublesome;
                                        respiration 28, with much crepitation anteriorly on the left
                                        side and a little on the right side. Next day, however, the
                                        pulse was again accelerated, 113, and the skin hot and more
                                        or less dry, the other symptoms continuing as already
                                        described until the 6th, when with a freely perspiring skin
                                        the pulse fell to 90, and the patient had less cough and
                                        some improvement in the voice. After this the pulse again
                                        rose to 105, the skin becoming hot and dry, but the tongue
                                        remaining moist and yellow-coated; the cough and
                                        expectoration of mucus and blood continued, with <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice>
                                        over the lower lobe of the right lung posteriorly and mucous
                                        and submucous râles above, and with crepitation over the
                                        left lung posteriorly; the diarrhœa and abdominal
                                        tenderness continued as already reported. By the 11th the
                                        pulse had risen to 118, and the patient was quite deaf and
                                        complained of headache. On the 12th the tongue, still
                                        continuing moist and yellow-coated, became red at the tip
                                        and edges; some sordes formed upon the lips, and tormina
                                        accompanied the diarrhœal passages. From this time
                                        to the end of the month the condition varied little from day
                                        to day, but a gradual alleviation of the symptoms of the
                                        lung and bowel complaints was observed. A free perspiration
                                        which occurred on the 20th was followed by a reduction of the
                                        pulse on the 21st and the manifestation of some appetite.
                                        The abdominal tenderness became lessened and the passages
                                        less frequent until the 31st, when, for the first time, the
                                        daily record shows that no stool was passed during the
                                        previous twenty-four hours. On November 1 the pulse was 80
                                        and feeble, the skin natural, the tongue pale, the appetite
                                        good; the cough was less troublesome and there had been but
                                        one stool. His condition had not changed materially on 
                                                <date type="servicedischarge" when="1861-11-09">the 9th</date>, when he was discharged from the service
                                        on account of debility; the cough persisted with occasional
                                        relaxation of the bowels and abdominal tenderness, but with
                                        a good appetite and natural skin. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
