<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20368">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">S&#8212;&#8212;, Jesse</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e20368</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">628</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>complications of injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>abscesses in the lung</term>
          <term>gunshot wound of knee-joint</term>
          <term>fractured inner condyle</term>
          <term>knee-joint and thigh inflamed and discharged pus</term>
          <term>knee-joint suppurating</term>
          <term>pus extending up and down leg, gastrocnemius to muscles of middle of thigh</term>
          <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal Jesse
          S&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B, 4th Ohio Volunteers, 3d
          division, Second Corps</name>, was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">McVeigh
          Branch of the 3d division general hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria,
          Virginia</name>, on <date type="admit" when="1863-12-05">December 5th, 1863</date>, with a
        gunshot wound of the knee-joint, received near <name type="battle" key="xxx">Mine Run,
          Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-27">November 27th</date>. A conical
        ball struck the knee of the right leg just below the patella, on its inner and anterior
        aspect, fracturing the inner condyle and opening the joint, passed downward and forward, and
        was extracted about four inches from the point of entrance. At the time of the patient's
        admission to the Alexandria hospital, the joint and thigh were very much inflamed and
        discharged pus copiously, and the man was much prostrated and terribly anxious as to the
        result of his wound; but after being washed and fed, and otherwise cared for, he appeared
        much recruited. On <date type="operation" when="1863-12-08">December 8th</date>, the
        operation of excision of the knee-joint was performed by <name type="person" key="134"
          >Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>; one
        inch of the femur, and about one inch arid a half of the tibia bones being removed. The
        h&#230;morrhage was slight, but the condition of the tissues was not very satisfactory. The
        patient endured the operation well, and the reaction was good. On <date type="injury"
          when="1863-12-08">the 9th</date>, the patient complained of severe pain on the right side
        of the chest over the lung, which continued for several days; no pain else where. On the
        night of December 10th, he had a severe chill, which was followed by two still more severe
        attacks on the 11th. Stimulants were freely given, with raw eggs well beaten up and beef
        essence for diet. He continued to have chills till the night of the 13th, when he was seized
        with a very severe chill, from which he never rallied, and died on the morning of <date
          type="death" when="1863-12-14">December 14th, 1863</date>. The <hi rend="italic"
          >post-mortem</hi> examination, eighteen hours after death, showed no attempt at
        reparation, and there was considerable sloughing, while upon the inside of the thigh there
        were numbers of small abscesses. The heart and left lung were healthy, but the right lung
        was infiltrated with pus, and a single large abscess appeared upon the surface of the
        inferior lobe. There was no pus nor abscesses found in the liver, but it was very much
        softened. The stomach, kidney, and intestines were perfectly healthy. The preparations in
        the case were sent to the Curator of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
          Museum</name>, <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>, <name
          type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who made the following memorandum of the
        appearances in the limb: &#34;Whole joint is one suppurating mass; pus extending up and
        down, far down under gastrocnemius, and up between the muscles of the thigh on the inside; a
        long abscess in the sheath of the vessels; extending up to the middle of the thigh. Small
        clot in femoral artery, three inches long and thin; none in femoral vein. Surrounding
        tissues of vessels in some places hardened, where pus had not reached. Lining membrane of
        femoral vein dirty gray and softened.&#34; Clot in <choice>
          <orig>suphena</orig>
          <reg>saphenous</reg>
        </choice> vein. <name type="person" key="288">Dr. Brinton</name> added the following notes
        of the preparation of the lung, represented in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi
          rend="initialcap">XIII</hi>, received at <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>
        December 15th, 1863: &#34;Apparently a metastatic abscess very circumscribed. When examined,
        found to be a clot, in different degrees of softening, and red blood corpuscles in every
        state of change; but no pus. The greenish mass in each [condyle?] was complete circumscribed
        gangrene of the cancellated bony tissue (coinciding with Virchow's doctrine). See picture
        painted by <hi rend="initialcap">M</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>TAUCH.&#34; The picture
        is very accurately copied in the chromo-lithograph opposite,&#185; <hi rend="initialcap"
          >P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XIII</hi>. </p>

      <p> &#185;The preparation of the lung was preserved in the <name type="hospital" key="431"
          >Army Medical Museum</name> and numbered 1910 of the surgical series, but became so much
        decomposed after exposure by the draughtsman, that it was discarded, and the number 1910 was
        assigned to another specimen. There is a partly finished drawing of the femoral vessels by
        M. Stauch, which has been copied and elaborated by Mr. Fabre, with a view to its
        reproduction in chromo-lithography. The excised fragments of the knee-joint were not
        preserved. The adjacent portions of the diaphyses of the femur and tibia are numbered 1909,
        Sect, I, A. M. M., and are figured in the Catalogue, p. 336, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
        115. See, for a note of the case, the surgical report in Circular No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, p.
        59. </p>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001498.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XIII</hi>. &#8212; METASTATIC FOCUS
        IN THE LUNG.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
