<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41506">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wyatt, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41506</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">195</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Third Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>abdominal tenderness, occasional colicky pains</term>
       <term>little appetite for food, no power to assimilate nutriment</term>
       <term>patches of inflammation in ileum, no enlargement or ulceration of glands of Peyer</term>
       <term>intussusception in lower ileum</term>
       <term>omentum atrophied and <choice><sic>bloodvessels</sic><corr>blood vessels</corr></choice> injected</term>
       <term>mesenteric glands enlarged</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-21">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>   
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">T</hi>HIRD <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:&#8432;</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 482.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx"> Private John Wyatt</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company B, 75th Ohio volunteers</name>; admitted from the hospital of the 11th Corps, <name type="place">Fairfax Court-House, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-01-22">January 22, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a of long standing.  The patient was at first able to sit up and walk around a little, but soon grew feeble, and was confined to bed. He was somewhat emaciated. At the date of admission the discharges from the bowels were watery, more or less yellowish, and varied in frequency from half a dozen to a dozen in the twenty-four hours; they were attended with some little pain and tenesmus; there was more or less abdominal tenderness, and occasional colicky pains, which, however, were not severe; the stomach was irritable, and there was considerable nausea, especially after taking food, drink, or medicine; he had but little appetite for food, and complained of constant thirst; the pulse was small, frequent and feeble; the respiration unembarrassed.  Treatment: Various astringents, especially acetate of lead, sulphate of copper, and tannic acid, were successively employed in combination with opium; occasionally a small dose of castor oil was administered; cod-liver oil in moderate doses was given as an analeptic; it was administered in peppermint-water, and was tolerated by the stomach better than any other medicine tried; rubefacients were applied to the abdomen. Milk, eggs, and farinaceous articles were mainly employed as food, and gum-water, toast-water, and tea for drink; but there seemed to be no power to assimilate nutriment, and the patient gradually sank, his intellect remaining clear to the last.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-02-13">February 13th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-02-17">ninety hours after death</date>: Body extremely emaciated. The thoracic viscera were normal. The stomach was healthy. There were patches of inflammation in the ileum, but no enlargement or ulceration of the glands of Peyer; there was a well-marked intussusception about an inch long in the lower part of the ileum. The omentum was atrophied, its <choice><sic>bloodvessels</sic><corr>blood vessels</corr></choice> injected. The mesenteric glands were enlarged. The liver was healthy.  [There is no record of the condition of the large intestine.]</p> 
   <p>&#8432; It is to be regretted that, in most instances, the records of this hospital do not show by whom the autopsies were made. It is known that many of them were made by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Bentley</name> himself, or under his immediate supervision, but it is only possible to distinguish these from the others in a few cases.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
