<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e9283">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Nelson, Jos. S.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e9283</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>                                        
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">385-386</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>    
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>gangrenous abscess adjacent to anus, extending deeply into buttock</term>
                                        <term>severe hemorrhage from abscess</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of epiglottis, larynx, and thyroid cartilage ulcerated</term>
                                        <term>no flatus or excrementitious matter escaped during life</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches and lower portion of small intestine ulcerated</term>
                                        <term>large intestine ulcerated and of stone-gray hue alternating with dull lardaceous appearance</term>
                                        <term>circumscribed pleuritic effusion</term>
                                        <term>bronchial tubes gave feel of cirrhosed liver</term>
                                        <term>posteriorupper lobe of lung &#339;dematous</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                        
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00185">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 185.&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="713">Private Jos. S.
                                                Nelson</name>, <name type="organization" key="531">6th Me. Bat'y</name>; age 45; was admitted <date
                                                type="admit" when="1863-10-19">Oct. 19, 1863</date>,
                                        with typhoid fever, and died <date type="death"
                                                when="1863-11-24">Nov. 24</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-11-25">next day</date>: Body greatly
                                        emaciated. The brain was healthy. The epiglottis was lined
                                        on the posterior surface with an exudation and ulcerated on
                                        either side of the free border, the ulceration being
                                        confined to the mucous membrane, which was of a palish pink
                                        color and thickened around the edges of the ulcers; an
                                        irregular ulcer, with pinkish walls, was seen on the left
                                        side of the larynx immediately below the vocal cord and a
                                        smaller ulceration of similar appearance in the angle of the
                                        thyroid cartilage. The posterior portion of the pharynx
                                        opposite the epiglottis was the seat of a superficial ulcer;
                                        the &#339;sophagus was pale and filled with a whitish
                                        curd-like mass, at first supposed to be a retained portion
                                        of ingesta, but on careful examination found to be a true
                                        exudation. The right lung weighed twenty-seven ounces; the
                                        posterior part of its upper lobe was quite
                                        &#339;dematous, its bronchi prominent, feeling like
                                        millet-seed under the fingers, and their mucous lining
                                        everywhere of a dark-purple color; the posterior surface of
                                        the lobe was coated to the extent of an inch and a half with
                                        a thick whitish membrane; the lower lobe posteriorly was
                                        much compressed by a circumscribed pleuritic effusion
                                        measuring fourteen ounces. The weight of the left lung was
                                        thirty-two ounces; its upper lobe presented the same general
                                        appearance as that of the right side; the bronchial tubes
                                        were everywhere prominent, in some parts giving the feel of
                                        a cirrhosed liver; the lower portion of the lung was of a
                                        dark-purple flesh-color, friable and heavier than water. The
                                        heart contained but little clot in its right side and none
                                        in its left. The liver was dark and tolerably firm, weighing
                                        fifty-seven ounces; the gall-bladder was very prominent and
                                        contained twenty drachms of thin brown bile; the spleen
                                        weighed seven ounces and was of a dark mahogany color and
                                        quite firm. Peyer's patches and the lower portion of the
                                        small intestine were ulcerated; the large intestine was also
                                        ulcerated and of a stone-gray hue alternating with patches
                                        of a dull lardaceous appearance; the ulceration was of the
                                        punctated form. A large gangrenous abscess was found on the
                                        right of the anus extending deeply into the right buttock;
                                        its external opening was small. Just before death a severe
                                        hemorrhage had taken place from this abscess; several very
                                        large, firm, blackish clots were found in its cavity. It was
                                        supposed from the examination that this communicated with
                                        the rectum, but the passage to that gut was obtained with
                                        some difficulty, and it is not improbable that the force
                                        used in manipulation produced the communication. No flatus
                                        or excrementitious matter had escaped during life.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name
                                                  type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. Harrison
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
