<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11298">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">B&#8212;&#8212;, George W.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  </edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e11298</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor>
                                                  <name>Center for Digital Research in the
                                                  Humanities</name>
                                                  <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                                  </distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl>
                                                  <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                                                  <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                                                  <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                                  <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                                  <date when="1870">1870</date>
                                                  <biblScope type="page">161</biblScope>
                                                  </bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term> 
                                                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the skull</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the cranium without depression</term>
                                                    <term>injury to bone slight, not recognized until after death</term>
                                                    <term>violent pain in head near wound, chills, delirium</term>
                                                    <term>circular depressed fracture of external table of left parietal bone behind coronal suture</term>                                                    
                                                    <term>insensibility of right side of body</term>
                                                    <term>autopsy performed</term>
                                                    <term>canister shot tore scalp over left parietal bone behind coronal suture</term>
                                                    <term>violent pain in head</term>
                                                    <term>purulent liquid between dura mater and cranium</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>     
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text>
                                <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0190">                                                
                                                  <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                  key="1436">Private George W. B&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name
                                                  type="organization" key="554">Co. A, 10th
                                                                  Pennsylvania Reserves</name>, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date
                                                  type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th,
                                                  1862</date>, by a canister shot which tore the
                                                  scalp for an inch in extent over the left parietal
                                                  bone, just behind the coronal suture.  He was
                                                  conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, and <date
                                                  type="admit" when="1862-12-14">next day</date> was
                                                  admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>.  The injury was regarded
                                                  as slight, there being no evidence that the bone
                                                  or structures beneath were seriously involved.
                                                  With the exception of a slight headache, the case
                                                  progressed well until the morning of <date type="injury" when="1862-12-22">the 22d</date>, when
                                                  he was seized with violent pain in the head in the
                                                  vicinity of the wound. He became restless and
                                                  painfully sensitive to sound. On the evening of
                                                  the 23d, and again on the morning of the 24th,
                                                  chills supervened, attended with delirium. A few
                                                  hours later insensibility of the right side of the
                                                  body was noticed. A blister was applied over the
                                                  nucha, and free purgations produced by cathartics.
                                                  In the afternoon the patient was rational, and
                                                  full sensibility in the body was restored. The
                                                  chills being regarded of a <choice><orig>malarious</orig><reg>malarial</reg></choice> character,
                                                  liberal doses of quinine were administered, and
                                                  none occurred after the 25th of the month. On the
                                                  30th he fell into a semi-comatose state, and death
                                                  ensued on the <date type="death" when="1863-01-04">4th of January, 1863</date>, no convulsions
                                                  having occurred at any time.  The autopsy revealed
                                                  a circular depression of the external table of the
                                                  left parietal bone, just behind the coronal
                                                  suture, half an inch in diameter, the surrounding
                                                  bone being cribriform. The inner table was found
                                                  irregularly fissured and depressed half a line.
                                                  About an ounce and a half of a sanguine, purulent
                                                  liquid had collected between the dura mater and
                                                  the cranium. The brain itself, however, appeared
                                                  healthy.   The pathological specimen is No. 628,
                                                  Sect. I, A. M. M., and was contributed, with the
                                                  history, by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon
                                                  John A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization"
                                                  key="132">U. S V.</name>   It is quite remarkable to
                                                  observe that several of the fragments of the
                                                  vitreous plate are very firmly re-united, the
                                                  patient having survived the injury only
                                                  twenty-three days.</p>                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
