<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e15185">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Gray, N.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e15185</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">371</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball entered in middle of internal condyle above inferior margin, passing in obliquely
      and downward, hole one inch deep</term>
     <term>femur found surrounded with pus, bone yet covered with periosteum</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>joint and leg weakened and atrophied, walks quite lame</term>
     <term>impaired motions of hamstrings</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 549.—<name type="person" key="1125">Private N.
     Gray</name>, <name type="organization" key="442">Co. H, 4th Maine</name>, aged 24 years, was
    wounded in the right knee joint, at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-05-26">three weeks
     afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, contributed the following history: "The ball
    entered in the middle of the internal condyle three-fourths of an inch above the inferior
    margin, passing in an oblique direction inward and downward. At the <date type="operation" when="1864-05-26">time of his admission</date> the general state of his health was good and
    color of skin normal; knee joint a little swollen. The patient complained of a fixed pain right
    below the centre of the patella, which was increased by pressure upon the patella. The thigh was
    swollen, especially on the inner side, about five inches upward, and fluctuating. On enlarging
    the opening upward a quantity of pus was discharged and the ball was discovered and removed. The
    hole made by the ball was one inch deep; its direction inward and downward. An ice bag was
    applied to the joint. On <date type="operation" when="1864-06-02">June 2d</date>, an incision
    was made in the fossa poplitea three inches long, and the lower third of the posterior side of
    the femur was found to be surrounded with pus, but the bone was yet covered with periosteum. The
    discharge was free and copious; the ice was still kept on. On July 20th, there was œdema of
    the right leg, which was bandaged from the toes to the knee joint; discharge healthy and
    copious. Solution of chlorinate of sodæ was now used in the dressing. By <date type="furlough" when="1864-09-01">September 1st</date>, the wound was doing well, discharging
    but little, and the incision in the fossa poplitea being healed. Exudation below the patella had
    disappeared, and the movements of the knee joint were perfectly free and painless. The patient
    went on furlough, and returned on September 14th. Small pieces of bone were coming from the
    wound in the condyle; movement of the joint perfect. On December 1st, erysipelas of the right
    leg commenced below the patella, attended with high fever, vomiting, and headache. For this ten
    drops of muriated tincture of iron were given every three hours. By December 10th, the
    erysipelas had disappeared and the patient was doing well. The process of exfoliation was going
    on slowly on January 1, 1865. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-02-13">February 13,
     1865</date>, the patient was discharged from service, the process of exfoliation not yet having
    terminated, but the knee joint being of normal size and color, and its movements perfectly free
    and painless in every direction." <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner I. H. Harding</name>,
    of <name type="place" key="xx">Ellsworth, Maine</name>, <date type="pension" when="1867-02-01">February 1, 1867</date>, certified to the injury and added: "The joint and leg are weakened
    and atrophied so much that he walks quite lame." The <name type="organization" key="xx">Boston
     Examining Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1875-09-13">September 13,
     1875</date>: "There are two large adherent cicatrices in the popliteal space, which impair the
    motions of the hamstrings." The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-12-04">December 4, 1879</date>. The wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 222) is a copy of a
    photograph contributed by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon Bontecou</name> (<hi rend="italic">Card Photographs</hi>, Vol. 3, p. 22). </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001605.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 222.—Shot fracture of internal condyle of right femur.
     [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
