<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e25220">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Howrigan, T. M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e25220</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">652</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>miscellaneous injuries</term> 
     <term>simple and compound fractures</term>
     <term>fracture at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>horse frightened and fell with him, foot caught under horse and fractured</term> 
     <term>fracture and tibia partially dislocated at ankle</term> 
     <term>motion and strength of foot and ankle impaired</term> 
     <term>fracture of tibia and fibula, dislocation of internal malleolus</term>
     <term>osseous deposit close to femur and femoral vessels at upper third of thigh</term>
     <term>osseous deposit interfered with circulation and mobility of limb</term> 
     <term>limb atrophied and partially paralyzed</term> 
     <term>varicose veins of entire limb</term>     
     <term>confined to bed</term> 
     <term>unable to do manual labor</term> 
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 975.—<hi rend="italic">Fracture at the ankle
      joint.</hi>—<name type="person" key="1443">Captain T. M. Howrigan</name>, <name type="organization" key="101">Co. H, 1st Michigan Cavalry</name>, aged 37 years, suffered a
     fracture at the left ankle joint while passing through <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-11-11">November 11, 1862</date>. The accident was occasioned by his horse becoming
     frightened and falling with him, causing his left foot to be caught under the horse and to be
     fractured. He was discharged for disability <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-06-30">June 30,
      1863</date>, but re-entered his regiment as Major <date type="enlist" when="1863">several months afterwards</date>, and remained in
     service until ultimately mustered out <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-06-19">June 19,
      1865</date>, since which date he has become a pensioner.  <name type="person" key="xx">Examining Surgeon J. A. Brown</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Detroit,
        Michigan</name>, <date type="pension" when="1869-08-11">August 11, 1869</date>, certified to the fracture and to the tibia being partially
     dislocated at the ankle, and added that "motion and strength of the foot and ankle are
     considerably impaired." The <name type="organization" key="xx">Kansas City Examining
      Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-04">September 4, 1873</date>: "Upon careful examination we find fracture of the tibia and fibula and
     dislocation of the internal malleolus, it being projected inward and downward, with tumefaction
     and pain. Close to the femur and femoral vessels at the upper third of the thigh there is found
     an osseous deposit about six and a half or seven inches long, one and a half inches wide above
     and tapering off in a wedge-shape below, and one-half inch thick, and just above this there is
     a smaller deposit, being two inches long and one inch wide. These deposits interfere materially
     with the circulation and mobility of the limb, which is atrophied and partially paralyzed.
     General health bad." <name type="organization" key="xx">The same board</name> on <date type="pension" when="1877-09-08">September 8, 1877</date>, reported the existence of " large
     varicose veins of the entire limb. He is feeble, very nervous, and quite lame, being compelled
     to support himself by a cane in walking. He is much more feeble now than two years ago, and
     unable to do manual labor." <date type="pension" when="1878-09">One year later</date> the board reported that the pensioner "is now
     confined to his bed and has not been able to walk for several months. He has to have constant
     attendance and is not able to help himself."  The pensioner died <date type="death" when="1879-05-02">May 2, 1879</date>. His attending physician, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. A. B. Sloan</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Kansas City</name>, testified
     that death was caused by "exhaustion induced by ossification of the arteries in the lower limbs
     and the deposit of bony masses in his left thigh, resulting from the injury and exposure in the 
     army." </p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
