<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19611">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Hillard, Thomas N.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e19611</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted:
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">505</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term> 
                                                                  <term>gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
                                                                  <term>penetrating gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
                                                                  <term>treatment by hermetically sealing</term>
                                                    <term>ball entered right thorax below clavicle, emerged to right of spinal column</term>
                                                    <term>fractured second rib near sternum</term>
                                                    <term>superior surface of fifth rib shattered at angle</term>
                                                    <term>ball passed directly through lung</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                  <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant Thomas N. Hillard</name>,
                                    <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. H, 70th New York Volunteers</name>, aged 22 years,
                                    was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Manassas Gap, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-07-23">July 23d,
                                                  1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the right
                                                  side of the thorax, one inch below the clavicle
                                                  and three and a half inches to the left of the
                                                  acromion process, fractured the second rib near
                                                  its sternal extremity, passed directly through the
                                                  lung, and emerged one inch to the right of the
                                                  spinal column, opposite the spine of the scapula.
                                                  The fifth rib was shattered at its superior
                                                  surface, near its angle, but its continuity was
                                                  not severed. He was taken to the hospital of the
                                                  2d division. Third Corps, where the wound was
                                                  hermetically sealed by <name type="person" key="930">Assistant Surgeon B. Howard</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>  On <date type="transfer" when="1863-07-30">July 30th</date>, he was transferred
                                    to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington. When admitted,
                                                  the wounds had partially opened, and were ragged
                                                  from the tearing out of the sutures. The patient
                                                  coughed incessantly, and spat up large quantities
                                                  of frothy sputa, more or less mixed with blood.
                                                  Respiration was 46 per minute, and labored with
                                                  extreme orthopnœa. The pulse was 96, and small.
                                                  Every fit of coughing was accompanied by a profuse
                                                  discharge of dark sanguinous fluid through either
                                                  wound. It was evident that the attempt to
                                                  permanently close the orifice had proven a
                                                  failure. Acting under instructions from the
                                                  Medical Director of the department the treatment
                                                  already inaugurated was continued. An attempt was
                                                  made to renew the coating of collodion, which was
                                                  accomplished after some difficulty; but before
                                                  the ether had had time to evaporate, a profuse
                                                  discharge of the pleuritic fluids took place which
                                                  rendered every effort at restoration
                                                  impracticable. By August 5th, the discharge from
                                                  the posterior wound had almost entirely ceased,
                                                  while that from the anterior one continued to be
                                                  large in quantity and of a purulent character. The
                                                  discharge of this fluid was invariably accompanied
                                                  with coughing, and always followed by an
                                                  amelioration of all the rational symptoms. The
                                                  hope was therefore entertained, that the
                                                  accumulation of pus in the pleural cavity would be
                                                  prevented, and that recovery would eventually take
                                                  place; but as the necessity for repeated effort
                                                  to throw off the pus became more frequent, the
                                                  strength of the patient became proportionately
                                                  exhausted. On the evening of <date type="death" when="1863-08-12">August 12th</date>, he was
                                                  seized with an unusually severe paroxysm of
                                                  coughing, followed by a copious discharge of pus,
                                                  which flooded his person and the bedding, and
                                                  reduced him to a state of syncope from which he
                                                  was imperfectly aroused under the administration
                                                  of stimulus, but expired in a short time. The
                                                  necropsy revealed extensive deposit of lymph over
                                                  the entire right lung, and one-half pint of thick
                                                  empyemic fluid in the cavity. The track of the
                                                  wound was closed anteriorly. The upper portion of
                                                  the right lung was permeable to air. Only part of
                                                  the first and the whole of the second and third
                                                  lobes were impermeable and compressed. The left
                                                  lung was well filled with air and weighed thirteen
                                                  ounces; right lung eighteen ounces. The case is
                                                  reported by <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
