<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41373">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Stewart, George</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41373</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">189</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>both kidneys had small abscesses in cortical substance</term>
       <term>ureter filled with purulent fluid</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon inflamed and dark colored, rectum thickened and extensively ulcerated</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-13">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 447.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private George Stewart</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company F, 4th New York artillery</name>; age 45; admitted from the field <date type="admit" when="1864-10-21">October 21, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears upon the register of the depot hospital of the 2d Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-10-06">October 6th</date>&#8212;chronic diarrh&#339;a&#8212;sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-20">October 20th</date>.]  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-11-01">November 1st</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-11-03">fifty-two hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis very slight; body emaciated; slight suggillation posteriorly. Head, neck and spinal column not examined. The left pleural cavity contained about an ounce of fluid. The left lung was normal; the apex of the right lung was adherent posteriorly to the costal pleura; the lobes of the lung interadherent; the lower lobe hepatized posteriorly. The pericardium contained two drachms of fluid. The heart was normal. The spleen, pancreas and liver were normal; the gall-bladder contained about an ounce of bile. The left suprarenal capsule was enlarged and softened. The left kidney, dark externally, congested internally, had six small abscesses in its cortical substance. The right suprarenal capsule was softened. The right kidney was similar to the left, except that it had only two small abscesses in its substance; its pelvis was congested, and the corresponding ureter filled with a purulent fluid. The bladder was full of urine; its mucous coat seemed thickened. The mucous membrane of the stomach was dark colored; that of the small intestine congested in patches; that of the colon inflamed and very dark colored; that of the rectum very much thickened and extensively ulcerated.&#8212;<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
