<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e14176">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Capps, E. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e14176</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">312-313, 314-315</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>fatal cases of secondary amputation in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>ball entered leg below the patella, passed through anterior portion of leg, fractured
      spine of tibia, emerged on inner side of limb</term>
     <term>head of tibia pierced by ball</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>pyarthrosis of knee joint, popliteal abscess</term>
     <term>py&#230;mia</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ak" when="2014-10-08">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 488.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1106">Captain <hi
      rend="italic">E. W. Capps</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="458">Co. C, 15th
     Virginia Cavalry</name>, aged 35 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="107">Brandy
     Station, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-10-11">October 11, 1863</date>. He was
    admitted, on <date type="admit" when="1863-10-21">October 21st</date>, into <name
     type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington. <name type="person" key="245"
     >Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>,
    reported:&#185; "A conoidal ball entered the right leg, from without inward, about one and a
    half inches below the patella, passed through the anterior portion of the leg, fractured the
    spine of the tibia, and emerged on the inner side of the limb. On admission a bandage was found
    applied tightly to the affected part. Upon its removal the joint was discovered to be greatly
    swollen from effusion, and the wounds presented an inflamed appearance. Cold-water dressings
    were applied. No constitutional symptoms were present. After the effusion in the joint had
    subsided a thorough examination of the wound was made. The head of the tibia was found pierced
    by the ball. No stellation existed, nor was the joint involved. A seton of tow was thrust
    through the wound and withdrawn, bringing away several small fragments of bone. On <date
     type="operation" when="1863-10-21">October 21st</date>, a small abscess was opened in the
    popliteal space. The patient, from this time, did remarkably well, and all thought him to be out
    of danger. On January 26, 1864, however, when he was walking, with the assistance of crutches,
    from one ward to another, he stumbled, and, in order to preserve his balance, bore his weight
    upon the injured limb. The following day an erysipelatous inflammation set in about the joint,
    which became enormously swollen. He was restless and uneasy, his skin hot and dry, tongue coated
    with a thick whitish fur; he had severe pain in the head; pulse 140; anorexia and constipation
    present. On January 29th, a sense of decided fluctuation was felt in the joint, and it was
    thought at the time that pyarthrosis of the knee joint was present. He had little or no fever.
    His pulse averaged 120 beats per minute, soft, compressible. Face very pale, mind clear. The
    swelling in the course of a week had gone down completely from the limb below and above the
    joint; but around the seat of injury and joint a dull purplish red color lingered. By judicious
    pressure pus could readily be made to exude through the internal wound. Pus had burrowed a very
    little distance in the parts connected with the popliteal abscess above mentioned. No sinus of
    any extent existed. It was now evident that the case was one demanding amputation, and, the
    patient's condition being favorable, the circular operation was performed by <name type="person"
     key="243">Assistant Surgeon J. C. McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S.
     A.</name>, in charge, on <date type="operation" when="1864-02-08">February 8th</date>. The
    joint, which gave evidence of the presence of pus of long standing, the cartilages being denuded
    and partially destroyed, was sent to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
     Museum</name> (<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 2036 of the Surgical Section). The patient did
    well until February 12th, when he had a severe chill which lasted forty minutes. This was
    followed by a profuse diaphoresis. The skin became cold and clammy, the pulse 120 and feeble. On
    the following day he had another chill, and, on the 15th, two more, one in the morning at six,
    the other at four o'clock in the afternoon. Another exacerbation occurred on the morning of the
    16th. In other respects the constitutional symptoms of what was evident to all to be py&#230;mia
    were remarkably slight. His tongue remained clean. His appetite continued the same. There was no
    vomiting, no fever of any consequence followed the chills; his pulse varied from 120 to 140,
    rapid and weak. His appearance at this time was that of a man who was suffering from a severe
    h&#230;morrhage; his an&#230;mic condition was startling; his sclerotica were pearly white, his
    lips and gums pale, his finger nails blue. He had a slight cough, though no expectoration. His
    most distressing symptom was the colliquative sweatings, which came on during the night, and
    which were not apparently connected with the chills. The limb looked well, and there was no
    unusual amount of pain in it. The flaps were granulating finely. On February 18th the sixth
    chill took place, and, on the next day, the seventh, followed by vomiting. He now rapidly sank,
    and died on <date type="death" when="1864-02-20">February 20th</date>, at four o'clock A. M.
    Autopsy: Rigor mortis marked. Adipose tissue abundant. Limb much swollen and of a tallow color.
    Upon dissecting out the vessels the tissues of the thigh were found greatly indurated,
    especially along the course of the Hunterian tract. The interior of the femoral vein was filled
    with a solid black clot, which was firmly adherent to the walls of the vein. No disintegration
    noticed. The lower third of the vessel, that which had lain in contact with the suppurating
    surface of the stump, was stained by a purulent fluid for about two inches from the patulous
    opening. A curious appearance was observed in one of the small branches of the profunda vein in
    the upper third of the thigh. It presented the same general aspect seen in the patulous end of
    the femoral, and was filled with pseudo-pus." A drawing (made by <name type="person" key="878"
     >Hospital Steward E. Stauch</name>, and copied in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi
     rend="initialcap">XXIII</hi>, opposite) of the upper two-thirds of the femur, removed at the
     <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi>, shows the separation of the periosteum in osteomyelitis.
    Upon a longitudinal section of the femur (<hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap"
     >XLIX</hi>, opposite p. 314) the medulla throughout was found to be of a grayish-yellow color,
    which was more intense at the region of the trochanter than elsewhere. Numerous small abscesses,
    more or less elliptical, were arranged lineally down the central portion of the medulla. The
    bone was not thickened or vascular. The periosteum, however, was inflamed, and, at the lower
    two-thirds of the specimen, was readily stripped from the bone, where it presented the
    appearance of having been pulled away from the femur by the fibres of the muscles inserted upon
    it.</p>
   <p>&#185; A condensed abstract of this case was published by Dr. <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LLEN
    in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Medical Sciences</hi>, 1865, Vol. XLIX, p. 39, in
    connection with his <hi rend="italic">Remarks on the Pathological Anatomy of Osteomyelitis, with
     Cases</hi>.</p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001836.001"/>
    <head>
     SEPARATION OF PERIOSTRUM IN OSTEOMYELITIS
    </head>
   </figure>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001837.001"/>
    <head>
     PLATE XLIX __ MEDULLARY ABSCESSES OF THE FEMUR. Case of <name type="person" key="1106">Captain
     E. W. Capps</name>, <name type="organization" key="458">15th Virginia</name>
    </head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
