<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e15008">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Stuck, Peter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e15008</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">370</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>missile entered at inner border of patella, escaped external to center of popliteal space</term>
     <term>ball grooved articular surface of internal condyle, passed through intercondyloid notch</term>
     <term>limb bandaged to double-inclined plane splint</term>
     <term>deposit new bone, patella firmly anchylosed to femur</term>     
     <term> leg atrophied, including thigh and hip</term>
     <term>knee joint anchylosed, leg flexed upon thigh</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 547.—<name type="person" key="1124">Private P. Stuck</name>,¹ <name type="organization" key="336">Co. E, 116th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 18
     years, was wounded in the right knee, at <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice><orig>Spottsylvania</orig><reg>Spotsylvania</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-12">May 12, 1864</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-05-18">six days afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="214">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. Gibbons, <choice><sic>jr.</sic><corr>Jr.</corr></choice></name>, described the case as follows: "The missile, probably a minié ball, entered at the inner border of the patella and escaped a little external to the center of the
     popliteal space, going directly through the joint and grooving the articular surface of the
     internal condyle, but passing mainly through the intercondyloid notch. The patient was a man of
     delicate organization. He had but little constitutional disturbance and not much inflammation
     in the joint, which, however, was somewhat swollen. Simple water dressings were applied. The
     discharge was free, abundant, and thin, the pus being mixed with synovial fluid.  On June 9th, there was some loss of appetite, with small, frequent pulse, and the patient complained of pain
     in the knee, which was swollen considerably. Flaxseed poultices, applied for two or three days,
     procured a free discharge from the posterior wound (the anterior wound having healed), when the
     symptoms immediately abated. In the latter part of August the patient began to walk about on
     crutches, the leg being flexed at an angle of about 135° with the thigh. The discharge was now
     not so copious, nor the pain at all severe; his appetite was fair, bowels regular, sleep
     refreshing, etc., as had indeed been the case during the greater part of the time.  In the
     latter part of October, in order to reduce the flexion, the limb was bandaged to a
     double-inclined plane splint, which resulted in almost entire extension without occasioning any
     bad symptoms in the joint or confining the patient to his bed.  For the following eight months nothing of special interest
     occurred, though there were several inflammatory attacks, moderate in degree and readily
     subdued by poulticing. On these occasions abscesses sometimes formed on the posterior thigh.
     The case is doubly interesting from the fact that the wound only received the ordinary dressing
     of cold water on cloths, with charpie to absorb the discharge. Tincture of iodine and
     poultices, or hot fomentations with flannel covered with oiled silk, were used when signs of inflammation showed themselves. No ice was
     used in the treatment.  A photograph (<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 63, A. M. M.) of the patient, taken
     <date type="photo" when="1865-07-09">July 9, 1865</date>, is represented in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 2 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXVIII</hi>.  The soldier was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-13">July 13, 1865</date>, in good health, the posterior wound being still open
     and permitting the introducing of a probe for three inches. There was also a large deposit of
     new bone, and the patella was firmly anchylosed to the femur. Some motion of the joint
     remained."  <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner H. Brubacker</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Somerset, Pennsylvania</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1867-09-23">September 23, 1867</date>:
     "The knee is very much enlarged, and the muscles of the thigh are gradually shrinking away. The
     wound is still discharging pus very freely, and there is evidently some disease of the bones about the joint,
     which keeps up the discharge." In <date type="pension" when="1876-01">January, 1876</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">the same examiner</name> reported: "The joint is
     completely anchylosed and the leg flexed upon the thigh, so that the heel cannot be made to
     touch the ground. He walks on the front of the foot. The ball of the foot behind the great toe
     is enlarged, hardened, and tender, which renders walking very difficult. The leg, including the
     thigh and hip, is becoming atrophied. His condition is gradually growing worse."  The pensioner
     was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-03-04">March 4, 1880</date>.</p>
   <p>¹ <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, War Department, Surgeon General's Office, Washington, 1865, p. 37.</p> 
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001821.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  LXVIII. __ RESULTS  OF  SHOT  INJURIES  OF  THE  KNEE - JOINT.      2.  Case of <name type="person" key="1124">Private Peter Stuck</name>,   <name type="organization" key="336">116 Pennsylvania</name>.</head>
   </figure>    
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
