<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e23996">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Jennings, C. E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e23996</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">622</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
     <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered inner side of foot, passed through three cuneiform bones and cuboid, exit wound on external and upper surface of foot</term> 
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>wounds discharging unhealthy sanious pus</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 906.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Shot fracture of tarsal bones; death.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="1400">Captain C. E. Jennings</name>, <name
      type="organization" key="528">Co. G, 26th New York</name>, was wounded in the foot, at <name
      type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30,
       1862</date>, and was conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>.  <name type="person" key="938">Surgeon C. L.
      Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported:  "The patient was
     a man about thirty years of age, of a sanguine temperament, and apparently of good constitution
     and fair health previous to being wounded; while he was at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, on his way to
     <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, a surgeon had declared the necessity of amputation; but before the operation could be performed the patient was taken to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>. The
     ball had entered on the inner side of the foot and passed through the three cuneiform bones and
     the cuboid, the wound of exit being upon the external and upper surface of the foot. On
     September 27th the foot was enormously swollen, and there were five or six openings besides the
     original wounds discharging large quantities of unhealthy sanious pus. The leg and even the
     thigh were very much swollen and &#339;dematous, and the lower third of the leg was marked by
     several long cicatrices, said to be the results of incisions made early in the case for
     erysipelatous inflammation. His general condition was that of marked hectic and his emaciation
     was great. He had also considerable dyspn&#339;a and complained of pain in his chest, for which
     sinapisms were being applied. Compound tincture of cinchona and tincture of cantharides, with
     brandy and liberal allowance of beef-essence, etc., were now immediately ordered for the
     patient, hoping but not expecting to raise him to a condition to sustain amputation of the leg.
     Although crowding the nourishment and stimulants to the utmost he continued to sink, and died
     on <date type="death" when="1862-10-01">October 1, 1862</date>.  No <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination was held."</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
