<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40916">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Becker, Philip</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40916</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">152</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Douglas Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>colon and rectum extensively ulcerated</term>
       <term>some ulcers nearly penetrated all coats</term>
       <term>lower Peyer's patches presented appearance of shaved-chin, neighboring solitary glands slightly prominent</term>
       <term>extensive ulcers, fewest in ascending colon, most extensive in descending colon just above rectum</term>
       <term>ulcers penetrate to muscular coat, extended by burrowing in submucous connective tissue</term>            
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="162"><hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>OUGLAS <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from February, 1863, to September, 1864, and after September, 1865:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 315.&#8212;<name type="person" key="224">Private Philip Becker</name>, <name type="organization" key="237">27th New York battery</name>; admitted from the <name type="organization" key="377">army of the Potomac</name> <date type="admit" when="1864-09-09">September 9, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears on the register of the depot hospital of the 9th Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, as admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-08-31">August 31st</date>&#8212;chronic diarrh&#339;a; no disposition recorded.]  He stated that he had been sick a long time; did not know exactly how long, but thought it was <date type="injury" when="1864-06">more than two months</date>. He had lost a great deal of flesh, and was hardly more than skin and bones; had twenty to thirty passages in the twenty-four hours, consisting of yellowish, thin, flocculent matter; his pulse was feeble and about 100. Ordered a pill containing half a grain of nitrate of silver, three times daily, and laudanum enemata. After the first three days he began to improve, and the stools were reduced in number to three or four daily. He died very suddenly and unexpectedly, <date type="death" when="1864-09-17">September 17th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-09-18">eighteen hours after death</date>: The colon and rectum were extensively ulcerated, the mucous membrane hanging in fringes; the ulcers in some places had so nearly penetrated all the coats that they tore in removing the gut, although the greatest care was used. The small intestine was not much diseased. The lower Peyer's patches presented the appearance of the shaved-chin, and the neighboring solitary glands were slightly prominent. The other organs were all examined, but nothing abnormal was observed.&#8212;<name type="person" key="217">Acting Assistant Surgeon David L. Haight</name>.  [Nos. 364 to 366, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case. No. 364 is from the ascending, No. 365 from the transverse, and No. 366 from the descending, colon, just above the rectum. All the specimens present extensive ulcers, which are fewest in No. 364 and most numerous and extensive in No. 366. The ulcers penetrate to the muscular coat, and appear to have extended by burrowing in the submucous connective tissue; as a consequence, the mucous membrane hangs out in more or less extensive fringes, which are especially remarkable in No. 366.]</p>  
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
