<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e1038">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">McLaughlin, Stephen</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e1038</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">136</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>pathology of malarial disease</term>
                                        <term>congestive chills</term>
                                        <term>premature old age, asthma, and debility</term>
                                        <term>&#339;dema and congestion of abdominal viscera regarded as malarial influence</term>
                                        <term>abdomen full, tense and fluctuating</term>
                                        <term>absolute <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> from below nipple to midway between that point and crest of ileum</term>
                                        <term>heart ventricle hypertrophied, middle valve thickened, margins of pulmonary and aortic valves hardened</term>
                                        <term>liver enlarged and softened</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-05-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change> 
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch3.sc4.0093">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 93.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="xxx">Stephen McLaughlin</name>, who was
                                        discharged from <name type="organization" key="xx">2d U. S.
                                                Art'y</name>
                                        <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-17">August 17,
                                                1865</date>, on account of premature old age, asthma
                                        and general debility from twenty years' service, was
                                        admitted <date type="admit" when="1865-09-11">September
                                                11</date>, confused in mind and with tremors of the
                                        limbs and voice; pulse 136; he appeared to have been
                                        drinking to excess. His legs were &#339;dematous; abdomen full,
                                        tense and fluctuating; auscultation disclosed roughness of
                                        the heart-sounds with increased impulse, the sounds being
                                        heard all over the left side; there was absolute <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice>
                                        from a little below the nipple to midway between that point
                                        and the crest of the ileum; the respiratory murmur was
                                        absent at the base of the left lung, puerile at its summit
                                        and on the right side; the left side of the chest was
                                        contracted, the right side enlarged.  At 2 P. M. on the day of
                                        admission he experienced a severe chill, for which brandy
                                        and quinine were given and mustard applied. He recovered,
                                        but the chill recurred at 2.30 P. M. on the <date
                                                type="death" when="1865-09-12">following day</date>
                                        and he died at 7 P. M.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi>
                                        examination <date type="autopsy" when="1865-09-13">seventeen hours after death</date>: Body bloated; skin
                                        of the head dark and livid; a thick greenish liquid flowing
                                        from the mouth. The brain was normal. The right lung was
                                        healthy. The left pleural cavity was partly obliterated by
                                        adhesions, but contained in its sacculi serum and lymph; the
                                        lung was diminished to half its size, the lower lobe being
                                        very friable and having its air-cells filled with a
                                        prune-juice liquid. The pericardium contained four ounces of
                                        serum. The heart weighed fourteen ounces and a half; the
                                        ventricle was hypertrophied, the middle valve somewhat
                                        thickened and the curved margins of the pulmonary and aortic
                                        valves hardened. The liver was enlarged and softened; the
                                        spleen, weighing twenty-two ounces and a half, was pulpy.
                                        The peritoneum was darkly injected and contained ten ounces
                                        of serum. The stomach and intestines, which were much
                                        distended with gas, had their mucous lining congested. The
                                        kidneys were nodulated on the surface and contained several
                                        cysts somewhat larger than a pea.&#8212;<hi
                                                rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D.
                                        C.</hi></p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
