<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18125">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">McNitt, S.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e18125</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">438-439</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>recovery after shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
       <term>ball entered limb posteriorly at junction of upper and middle third, caused compound comminuted fractures of the tibia and fibula, exited anteriorly with fragments of bone</term> 
       <term>h&#230;morrhage</term>        
       <term>accidentally shot in leg in camp</term>
       <term>limb much weakened, convexity marked</term>
       <term>permanent disability</term>
       <term>necrosis and shortening of leg</term>
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-04">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 689.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private S. McNitt</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. D, 4th Delaware</name>, aged 23 years, was accidentally shot in the left leg, while in camp
    near <name type="place">Fairfax Court House</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-10-22">October 22, 1863</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon D. S. Hopkins</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">4th Delaware</name>, reported: &#34;The ball entered the limb posteriorly, at the junction of the upper with the middle third, passed directly through, causing a compound comminuted
    fracture of the tibia and fibula, and came out anteriorly, carrying with it fragments of bone. Comparatively slight h&#230;morrhage
    ensued, and that principally of a venous character. An examination showed that although extensive laceration of the soft parts
    had taken place, yet the arteries were found entire and pulsation at the extremities very perceptible. The leg was, therefore,
    placed in a horizontal position and loose spicul&#230; of bone were removed. Cold-water dressings were applied, and the patient
    was made as comfortable as circumstances would permit. Solution of morphia, two grains to an ounce of water, was administered at intervals of an hour until the patient became quiet. Next morning, <date type="operation" when="1863-10-23">October 23d</date>, his system seemed to have suffered but little from the shock, he being comparatively comfortable. More minute examination revealed the fact that a number of
    pieces of bone still remained in the wound, which it was deemed necessary to remove. Accordingly a longitudinal incision was
    made along the crest of the tibia, the patient being under the influence of chloroform, and several spicul&#230; of bone were taken
    out varying in length from one to two and a half inches. The largest, from the crest of the tibia, included in its thickness much of the cancellated structure of the bone, as was the case with each piece removed; the average breadth was three-fourths of an
    inch. After the fragments had been removed the parts were coaptated, the limb was adjusted in a fracture-box, and cold-water
    dressings were reapplied. The patient was comparatively comfortable during the night.&#34; Some months after the reception of
    the injury the patient was admitted from the field into hospital at <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, and lastly he was transferred to Tilton Hospital,
    <name type="place">Wilmington</name>, where he was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-06-19">June 19, 1865</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon E. I. Baily</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, certifying to the shot fracture resulting in &#34;necrosis and shortening of the leg.&#34; The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Wilmington Examining Board</name>, in describing the injury,<date type="pension" when="1871-12-06">December 6, 1871</date>,
    reported: &#34;Large and irregular cicatrices in front and rear of the limb; unnatural condition of skin; shortening of leg by an
    inch and a half. On account of occasional suppuration and exfoliation the limb has become much weakened and the convexity
    of it more marked. The disability is permanent in its present degree.&#34; After another inspection <date type="pension" when="1873">two years later</date> the pensioner
    was exempted from further examinations. He was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-09-04">September 4, 1880</date>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
