<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11603">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Sands, William</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e11603</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">867</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>on certain local diseases</term>
                                        <term>cardiac diseases</term>
                                        <term>rupture of the heart</term>
                                        <term>considered phenomenal, only recorded case</term> 
                                        <term>flesh-wound of thigh</term>
                                        <term>ball impinged on femur without fracturing it</term>
                                        <term>half an inch opening extended through anterior wall of right ventricle and adherent pericardium</term>   
                                        <term>post-mortem examination only</term>
                                        <term>heart of large size, underwent fatty degeneration</term>
                                        <term>opening in wall of ventricle in direction of muscular fibres</term>
                                        <term>rupture of the heart not following violent exertion</term>
                                        <term>gradual effusion of blood compressed lungs</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body>                        
                        <p> <name type="person">Private William Sands</name>, <name type="organization">Co. A, 147th Pa.</name>, was admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-05-07">May 7,
                                1863</date>, with a flesh-wound of the thigh, received at
                                <name type="BATTLE" key="257">Chancellorsville</name> on <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">the 3d</date>. The patient seemed in good
                                        condition and complained of nothing apart from his wound.  On
                                        the morning of <date type="death" when="1863-05-15">the 15th</date>, <name type="person"><hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>r. <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">W</hi>ILLIAMS</name> having been
                                        called to see him, found him so near death by asphyxia that
                                        no opportunity was afforded to examine the chest during
                                        life. At the evening visit on the previous day the patient
                                        had some fever and complained of restlessness, for which an
                                        opiate was administered. About midnight his mind wandered
                                        somewhat, but not more than might be attributed to the
                                        opiate. After this the nurse on duty noticed that his
                                        breathing was short and somewhat labored; but as he was
                                        quiet and made no complaint the attending surgeon was not
                                        called.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The ball, which had
                                        impinged on the femur without fracturing it, was removed
                                        from the wound, which showed nothing unusual. On elevating
                                        the sternum the thoracic cavity was found filled with black
                                        blood. The lungs adhered to the walls of the thorax and the
                                        diaphragm; the pericardium to the pleura and the diaphragm;
                                        these adhesions were firm and extensive. The heart,
                                        enveloped in its pericardium, was carefully removed; the
                                        pericardium was firmly adherent to the heart. An opening
                                        nearly half an inch in length was found extending through
                                        the anterior wall of the right ventricle and its adherent
                                        pericardium. On stripping off the pericardium the heart,
                                        which was of large size, appeared paler than natural, having
                                        evidently undergone fatty degeneration; the opening in
                                        the wall of the ventricle was in the direction of the
                                        muscular fibres and was rendered valvular by the intrusion
                                        of one of the fleshy columns. Every point in the case shows
                                        that the cause of death was rupture of the heart not
                                        following any violent exertion. The nurse's statement that
                                        he noticed the short breath of the patient some hours
                                        before death, and his asphyxiated appearance when <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>r.
                                <hi rend="initialcap">W</hi>ILLIAMS saw him, indicate that death was caused by the
                                        gradual effusion of blood compressing the lungs. The man
                                        probably lived four or five hours after the rupture of the
                                        heart, the columna carnea at the base of the opening
                                        preventing an immediately fatal hemorrhage. The opening in
                                        the pericardium and heart could scarcely have been made by
                                        the knife of the dissector without inflicting injury on the
                                        fleshy column at the base of the opening, which, it will be
                                        observed, was uncut; nor would the chest have been suddenly
                                        filled with blood by a <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> cut in the right
                                        ventricle, in which was found a large soft clot.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="905">Ass't Surgeon Alexander Ingram</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="169">St. Aloysius Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi>  </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
