<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e21135">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Bussler, D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e21135</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
    </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">546-547</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot injury</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of secondary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>compound comminuted fracture of fibula</term> 
     <term>ball entered outer aspect above external malleolus and emerged at inner aspect above internal malleolus</term> 
     <term>amputation of leg at junction of middle and lower thirds</term>
     <term>great pain in stomach, symptoms of gastritis</term>
     <term>gangrene</term>
     <term>pyæmia</term>
     <term>metastatic abscesses of liver and spleen</term>
     <term>medulla of upper third of femur inflamed</term>     
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>   
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 797.—<name type="person" key="1317">Private D.
      Bussler</name>, <name type="organization" key="508">Co. K, 93d Pennsylvania</name>, aged 19
     years, was wounded near the left ankle during the engagement near <name type="BATTLE" key="104">Fort Fisher</name>, before <name type="BATTLE" key="58">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-25">March 25, 1865</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon S. F.
      Chapin</name>, <name type="organization" key="509">139th Pennsylvania</name>, reported his
     admission to the field hospital of the 2d division, Sixth Corps.  <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the pathological specimen, numbered 195 of the Surgical Section, A. M. M., with the following
     description and result of the injury: "The wound consisted of a compound comminuted fracture of
     the fibula; a conoidal ball had entered the outer aspect four inches above the external
     malleolus, and emerged at the inner aspect one and a half inches above the internal malleolus.
     The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>,
     Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-01">one week after receiving the injury</date>. Circular amputation of the leg was performed
     by <name type="person" key="876">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. Craft</name>, on <date type="operation" when="1865-05-06">May 6th</date>, at the
     junction of the middle and lower thirds. Eight ligatures were applied and sulphuric ether was used. At the time of the operation the leg
     presented a large open surface on the posterior region, extending from one inch below the ankle
     joint to the junction of the middle and lower thirds of the limb. Several spiculæ had been
     removed previously and there had been gangrene; the patient had lost his appetite and was very
     weak; pulse small. Reaction came on slowly. On the evening of May 9th he had a severe chill;
     suppurative process not yet established; stump dark looking and flaps somewhat discolored; two ligatures now came away.
     Tincture of chloride of iron, with stimulants and nourishing diet, were prescribed, also a
     camphor and opium pill every liquid stool. On the following day there was another chill,
     followed by profuse cold sweat; previous treatment continued, and one-half drachm of
     bi-sulphate of soda dissolved in water was given every two hours. There was very little
     discharge from the stump, which was dressed with solution of bromine. On May 11th there were
     two chills and the treatment was continued. In the evening the bi-sulphate of soda was stopped, but resumed the next morning. Several rigors
     occurred during the night and a slight chill on the morning of May 13th, when the patient had
     great pain in the stomach, and the bi-sulphate of soda was again stopped and morphia
     prescribed. In the afternoon the doses of bi-sulphate of soda were again resumed. He suffered
     great pain in the stomach through the night, and the next day the remedy was again stopped.
     There were now symptoms of gastritis and the patient was gradually sinking. The slough had all
     separated from the stump, which looked quite healthy. Poultices of charcoal, flaxseed, yeast,
     and creasote had been used for several days. On the morning of May 15th the patient was very
     low and in a dying condition, and all medicines except stimulants and beef-essence were stopped. Death, caused by pyæmia,
     supervened at 3 P. M. on <date type="death" when="1865-05-15">May 15, 1865</date>. At the
     autopsy the thoracic viscera were found to be normal with the exception of old adhesions of the
     right lung. The left lobe of the liver and the spleen contained metastatic abscesses; other
     abdominal viscera were normal. The stump was in a gangrenous condition. The medulla of the upper third of the femur was greatly inflamed,
     particularly so about one inch below the great trochanter; cancelli of upper part of femur very
     vascular; cancellous structure of tibia slightly vascular."  The specimen consists of the
     amputated portion of the fibula, showing the seat of the injury without any attempt at repair.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
