<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41109">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">McCann, Edward</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41109</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">172</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a and hepatic abscess</term>
       <term>liver contained purulent deposits, appeared on external surface as whitish circular spots</term>
       <term>large intestine from c&#230;cum down extensively ulcerated, mucous membrane between ulcers dark stone-gray color, ulcerated patches exposed muscular coat</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863.</p>                
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 375.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Edward McCann</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company G, 69th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 34; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-09-12">September 12, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a and hepatic abscess.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-09-27">September 27th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-09-28">fourteen hours after death</date>: Height five feet ten inches; some rigor mortis. The brain weighed fifty-two ounces; it was somewhat soft. The mucous membrane of the trachea was generally pale, the spaces between the rings slightly purplish. The right lung weighed nine ounces and a half; it was pale and an&#230;mic except the lower lobe, which was somewhat congested posteriorly; the left lung weighed eight ounces, and presented the same appearances as the right; both lungs were peculiar from the absence of the frothy bronchial secretion usually seen on section. The pericardium contained six drachms of fluid. The heart weighed eight ounces; in the right auricle there was a large fibrinous clot which extended upward into the descending vena cava, downward into the ventricle, and thence into the pulmonary artery; the left side of the heart also contained a fibrinous clot, but of smaller dimensions than that in the right. The liver measured eleven by eight by five inches; it contained a number of purulent deposits; these appeared on the external surface as whitish circular spots, about an inch and a half in diameter, surrounded by a purple areola; some of them had a little fibrinous lymph adhering over them; between them the surface of the liver was mottled with yellow and red; on section the parenchyma was pale except immediately around the deposits, where it was congested. The spleen was firm and dark colored; it weighed five ounces and a half. The right kidney was healthy, and weighed four ounces and a quarter; the left kidney was markedly congested, and weighed four ounces and a half. The small intestine appeared to be perfectly healthy. The large intestine, from the c&#230;cum down, was extensively ulcerated; the mucous membrane between the ulcers was of a dark stone-gray color, and not covered by any exudation; the ulcerated patches, however, had a thin diphtheritic coating on the exposed muscular coat.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>&#8432;</p>
   <p>&#8432; September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief &#34;<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>,&#34; to which the reader is referred.&#8212;(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
