<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e21217">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Nash, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e21217</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">550-551</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
       <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term> 
       <term>secondary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term> 
       <term>secondary amputations in the lower third of the leg for shot injury</term> 
       <term>recoveries after secondary amputations in the lower third of the leg for shot injury</term>
       <term>compound fracture of tarsus</term> 
       <term>leg amputated at lower third</term> 
       <term>necrosis of tarsus bone</term>       
       <term>aid of artificial limb</term>
       <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 800.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. Nash</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 187th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 19 years, was wounded in the right foot, before <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-18">June 18th, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon C. N. Chamberlain</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported his admission to the field hospital of the 4th division, Fifth Corps, with &#34;severe injury to the bones of the foot, caused by a mini&#233; ball.&#34; From the field hospital the wounded man
    passed to <name type="place">City Point</name> thence to hospital at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, and subsequently to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon T. C. Brainerd</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of <name type="hospital">Broad and Cherry Streets Hospital</name>, described the injury as &#34;a compound fracture of the tarsus, followed by necrosis of bone, pain in the foot, and free discharge, for which the leg was amputated at the lower third by circular method, on <date type="operation" when="1865-05-08">May 8th</date>, by <name type="person" key="1071">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Bellows</name>. At the time of the operation the patient had become much exhausted from the profuse and continued discharges from the wound. He reacted promptly, ether having been used as an anaesthetic. Dry dressings were applied.&quot;  <name type="person" key="1071">The operator</name> subsequently communicated that the stump only required three weeks to heal perfectly. The patient afterwards passed through various hospitals, and was ultimately mustered out at the expiration of his time of service, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-03">August 3, 1865</date>, and pensioned.  Several years later, when seen and examined by <name type="person" key="1071">the operator</name>, the pensioner was found in general good health and with a good, round, and entirely healed stump, he being able to walk satisfactorily with the aid of an artificial limb. In his application for commutation, in <date type="pension" when="1870">1870</date>, the pensioner described the stump as being &#34;not in the best condition;&#34; but in his subsequent statements, <date type="pension" when="1875">five</date> and <date type="pension" when="1880">ten years</date> later, he reported its condition as &#34;good.&#34; The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-09-04">September 4, 1880</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
