<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40897">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Taylor, Obed E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40897</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">151</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Douglas Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>pneumonia of lower lobe of lung, lobular pneumonia in first stage</term>
       <term>large intestine ulcerated and coated with pseudomembrane from ileoc&#230;cal valve to rectum</term>
       <term>liver fatty</term>
       <term>Peyer's patches enlarged and injected</term>
       <term>one kidney abnormally small</term>
       <term>tormina and tenesmus</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="162"><hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>OUGLAS <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from February, 1863, to September, 1864, and after September, 1865:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 309.&#8212;<name type="person" key="215">Private Obed E. Taylor</name>, <name type="organization" key="233">company F, 106th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 35; admitted from the <name type="organization" key="377">army of the Potomac</name> <date type="admit" when="1864-02-01">February 1, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [It appears from the register of the regimental hospital of the 106th Pennsylvania volunteers that this man was treated in that hospital for diarrh&#339;a in <date type="admit" when="1863-11">November, 1863</date>, and again in <date type="admit" when="1864-01">January, 1864</date>.]  This man had been <date type="injury" when="1863-10">sick about four months</date>. He was very weak, greatly emaciated, and in a very filthy condition. The stools were frequent, very thin, and of an ash-gray color; had severe tormina and tenesmus. A grain of opium was administered at once, with an ounce of whiskey, and a blister applied to the abdomen.  February 2d: Slept very little last night; had several involuntary evacuations.  &#8478;. Acetate of lead two scruples, opium ten grains, ipecacuanha one scruple; make forty powders. Take one three times daily; also a laudanum enema three times daily. Stimulants and milk diet.  He continued about the same until <date type="injury" when="1864-02-07">February 7th</date>, when symptoms of pneumonia of the lower lobe of the left lung set in, for which a blister was applied to the chest and fluid extract of seneka given internally. Milk-punch and beef-tea were freely administered.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-02-10">February 10th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-02-11">six hours after death</date>: Body emaciated; rigor mortis well marked. The left lung presented lobular pneumonia in the first stage. The liver was fatty. Peyer's patches were enlarged and injected. The large intestine was ulcerated and coated with pseudomembrane from the ileoc&#230;cal valve to the rectum. The right kidney was abnormally small.&#8212;<name type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon Carlos Carvallo</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
