<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7142">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Farnham, Noah L.</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e7142</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">109-110</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term> 
                    <term>contusion of the skull without fracture</term>
                    <term>chronic irritability of the brain, or mental aberration</term>
                    <term>musket ball made superficial forward wound over parietal</term>
                    <term>external wound superficial</term>
                    <term>fell from horse</term>
                    <term>grave cerebral symptoms, hemiplegia, coma and death</term>
                    <term>abscess at seat of injury, directly beneath wound of scalp</term>
                    <term>extravasation of blood into sulci of brain</term>
                    <term>extravasation of blood beneath visceral arachnoid membrane into pia mater</term>
                    <term>contusion of brain or spinal cord</term>
                   <term>concussion and irritation of brain</term>
                    <term>concussion, complicated with contusion cerebrum</term>
                    <term>meningo-cerebral inflammation and cerebral abscess</term> 
                    <term>extravasation of blood in brain</term>     
                    <term>hemiplegia</term>
                    <term>cerebral disturbance</term>
                    <term>ill before wound, unfit to perform duty at the time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>   
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-06-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>            
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change> 
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0090">            
                <p><name type="person" key="365"><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>ARNHAM, <hi
                            rend="initialcap">N</hi>OAH <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>.</name>,
                    Colonel, <name type="organization" key="589">11th New York Volunteers (1st Fire
                        Zouaves)</name>, was wounded, at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="322">Manassas</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-07-21">July 21st,
                        1861</date>, by a musket ball, which made a superficial forward wound over
                    the left parietal. He was much stunned, and fell from his horse.  He was conveyed
                    to the <name type="hospital" key="154">E Street Infirmary</name>, Washington,
                    and placed under the care of <name type="person" key="366">Assistant Surgeon W. J. H. White</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>  The
                    wound healed promptly, and his condition was hopeful until <date type="injury" when="1861-08-10">August 10th</date>, when
                    grave cerebral symptoms appeared, terminating in hemiplegia, followed by coma
                    and death on <date type="death" when="1861-08-14">August 14th, 1861</date>.  At
                    the autopsy, made by <name type="person" key="287">Assistant Surgeon J. W. S. Gouley</name>, <name type="organization"
                        key="190">U.S.A.</name>, an abscess, the size of an English walnut, was
                    found at the seat of injury, with extravasation of blood in the neighboring
                    sulci of the brain. The following description of this case was prepared by<name
                        type="person" key="70"> Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>,   <name
                            type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>:&#8432;</p>                
            <p> &#42;    &#42;    &#42;    &#34;It cannot be doubted that, in at least some instances, this ecchymosis,
                    this extravasation of blood beneath the visceral arachnoid membrane into the
                    meshes of the pia mater (connective tissue), denotes a genuine contusion of the
                    brain or spinal cord, as the case may be; and that, in this way, a positive
                    pathological lesion, perceptible to the unaided vision, is superadded to the
                    concussion. These cases of concussion, complicated with contusion of the nerve
                    tissue, when the cerebrum happens to be the part involved, exhibit a marked
                    tendency to the occurrence of meningo-cerebral inflammation and cerebral
                    abscess. The following case strongly corroborates this statement:    &#42;    &#42;    <name type="person" key="365">Colonel Farnham</name>, of the <name type="organization" key="589">New York City Fire Zouaves</name>, was wounded, at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="322">Manassas</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-07-21">July 21st,
                        1861</date>, by a spent ball, which hit his head and knocked him off his
                    horse. He was picked up insensible. The wound was small in size, superficial in
                    character, and situated on the left side of the head, three inches above the
                    meatus auditorius. It healed without any difficulty. The principal symptoms in
                    his case, until near the close, were referable to concussion and irritation of
                    the brain.  He died on the evening of <date type="death" when="1861-08-14">August 14th</date>, twenty-four days subsequent to the infliction of the injury. It
                    was thought that he would recover, until about four days before death. He was
                    partially paralyzed on the right side (hemiplegia) toward the last. He was
                    comatose in the last moments.  At the autopsy, made <date type="autopsy" when="1861-08-15">August 15th</date> by <name
                        type="person" key="287">Doctor Gouley</name>, <name type="organization"
                        key="190">U. S. A.</name>, we found that the external wound was superficial; that the skull was not injured; that there was copious subarachnoidian
                    effusion; that there was an unusual quantity of yellow-colored serum in the
                    ventricles, and that there was an abscess of the cerebrum, situated directly
                    beneath the wound of the scalp. This abscess was about the size of an English
                    walnut, superficial in situation, and surrounded by softened cerebral tissue.
                    The visceral and parietal arachnoid over the abscess were glued together, to
                    some extent, by adhesive inflammation, so that, in endeavoring to turn back the
                    dura mater while making the autopsy, though it was carefully done, the abscess
                    was torn open. There were also traces of an extravasation of blood, three or
                    four weeks old, in the sulci of the brain, beneath the visceral arachnoid
                    membrane over the seat of the abscess, and likewise at the anterior extremity of
                    the left cerebral hemisphere. There was a flattened clot of blood, black in
                    color, and apparently three or four weeks old, in the fossa, at the base of the
                    middle lobe of the left cerebral hemisphere. The dura mater, in relation with
                    it, was somewhat thickened, roughened, and opacified.&#34;    &#42;    &#42;    &#42;</p>                
            <p><name type="person" key="367">Medical Inspector F. H. Hamilton</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, has described this case as follows:&#8224;</p>
            <p>&#34;First, I would remark, that you may have an injury of the scalp of an exceedingly trivial character, which may, in the
                    end, prove fatal. A ball may simply tear off the hair of the scalp, and create a very slight abrasion of the skin, yet, the bone
                    being so near, and the brain so close to the bone, it is very probable that serious mischief has been done. The bone in that
                    situation may be so injured as to lead to necrosis, or a sufficient shock may be given to the brain and its envelopes to bring on
                    inflammation. I will mention a very remarkable illustration of this fact.  <name type="person" key="365">Colonel Farnham</name>, after the death of <name type="name" key="xx">Colonel
                        Ellsworth</name>, took command of the <name type="organization" key="589">1st Zouave Regiment</name>. At the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="253">Bull Run</name>, <date type="battle" when="1861-07-21">July 21st, 1861</date>, he received an injury of the character referred to, and which I examined myself. It was a very slight and superficial wound, which seemed to have taken
                off very little more than the hair.  He was transferred from the field to the <name type="hospital" key="428">Washington Infirmary</name>, where he was reported as
                    doing very well, the wound being considered as a very slight and insignificant one; but, notwithstanding all this, he kept his
                    bed. He did actually seem to be improving until about the ninth day after the reception of the wound, when grave symptoms
                    suddenly supervened, and, in a day or two after, he died. I should notice that, during all the time he was in the hospital, he
                    was very easily disturbed by visitors, and it was his desire to be left alone, showing that there was some cerebral disturbance.
                    I ought also to mention that he was ill before he received the wound, and was unfit to perform duty at the time the battle took
                    place; but, being a gallant officer, he was determined to lead his regiment to the charge. But his previous condition I do not
                    think had much, if anything, to do with his death, which, in my opinion, and in the opinions of many other surgeons who saw
                    him, was due directly to the apparently slight wound which he received during the fight.&#34;   &#42;   &#42;   &#34;Next, I called your attention
                    to those injuries of the scalp produced by smaller missiles; for example, where a rifle ball had slightly impinged upon the
                    surface of the scalp, producing a slight abrasion of the integument, which accident is usually accompanied by some degree of
                    concussion, either to the skull, to the meninges of the brain, or to the brain itself, and which I have said you are not to regard
                    as trivial accidents. Although the patient may not seem to have suffered any severe injury, you are to anticipate that sooner or
                    later there may be an ulceration along the track of the ball, or that there may result necrosis, or meningitis, or cerebritis, and
                    that the patient may ultimately die. And I cited, as an illustration of injuries of this class, the case of <name type="person" key="365">Colonel Farnham</name>,
                    who assumed command of the Ellsworth Zouaves after the death of <name type="person" key="xx">Colonel Ellsworth</name>. He received an injury of such a
                    character, which was exceedingly slight and superficial. I saw him myself, and examined him particularly, and all that was
                    visible was a very trivial scalp wound. He was taken into a hospital in <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and there I saw him again, at the
                    expiration of seven or eight days. He was then very irritable, and had been quite ill, but still his friends all thought that his
                    recovery was certain. Three or four days after this, if I remember correctly, the symptoms became more grave, and he died, evidently from the injuries which his brain had received.&#34;    &#42;    &#42;    &#42;</p>
            <p> &#8432; <hi rend="italic">American Journal of the Medical Sciences</hi>, vol. xlviii, p. 323.</p>
            <p> &#8224; <hi rend="italic">American Medical Times</hi>, vol. viii, pp. 73-85.</p>           
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
