<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18413">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ferguson, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e18413</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">443-444</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>bullet passed through upper third of calf of leg in downward and outward direction</term> 
     <term>typhoid symptoms</term> 
     <term>persistent hæmorrhage, femoral artery ligated</term>
     <term>gangrene</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage from lower popliteal artery</term>
     <term>popliteal artery opened by ulceration</term>     
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 700.—<name type="person" key="1254">Corporal J.
      Ferguson</name>, <name type="organization" key="146">Co. G, 142d Pennsylvania</name>, was
     wounded in the right leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. He remained at a First Corps field
     hospital for <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-20">one week</date> and was then transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="159">Patent Office Hospital</name>, and subsequently to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton
      Hospital</name>, Washington. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter, described the case as
     follows: "The wound was produced by a bullet, which passed through the calf of the leg in the
     upper third in a downward and outward direction. The wound did well until the middle of
     January, when the granulations assumed an unhealthy appearance and the discharge became thin and serous. The patient also exhibited typhoid
     symptoms, having a hot skin, frequent pulse, and dry red tongue, watchfulness, and no appetite.
     This went on until the morning of <date type="injury" when="1863-01-23">January 23d</date>, when hæmorrhage occurred unexpectedly from
     the external orifice behind the fibula. The bleeding was readily controlled by application of
     pressure by bandage and ice, the patient having lost about ten ounces. Throughout the day and
     the night following the loss of blood by oozing was very little, but on the following morning
     hæmorrhage recurred from the internal orifice, behind the tibia this time. This amounted
     to from four to six ounces, and was also readily controlled by the application of persulphate
     of iron, lint, ice, and bandaging. In the meantime the typhoid symptoms became more marked. The
     patient also complained of great tenderness throughout the leg and thigh; the inguinal glands
     were somewhat swollen and tender, and there was dusky redness, with soreness in the track of
     the long saphenous vein. His skin was now pale and yellow. On the morning of January 25th,
     another slight bleeding occurred from the internal wound and was readily controlled by
     pressure. A marked increase of the swelling was now noticed, extending from the leg to the
     thigh, especially over the external and internal condyles and the popliteal space, and infiltration with blood was suspected. The patient was now very pale and
     expressed a great deal of anxiety, his pulse being 120, quick and weak. The first day the
     hæmorrhage was thought to come from the peroneal artery, the next day from the posterior
     tibial, but now we were uncertain in regard to the source of the bleeding, and the case
     presented an unpromising appearance on account of the debility from the loss of about eighteen
     ounces of blood superadded to his typhoid condition. We then decided to tie the femoral artery
     at the apex of Scarpa's space as affording the best chance of benefit, which operation <name type="person" key="70">I</name>
     performed without any difficulty on the afternoon of <date type="operation" when="1863-01-25">January 25th</date>, forty-three days after the
     reception of the wound. On the following morning the patient appeared brighter; pulse 130;
     tongue more moist; leg getting warmer down to the ankle. The plugs being removed some dark
     offensive blood flowed away. In the evening his foot was cold, leg cooler, and blackness was
     extending across the leg in the track of the wound. Patient had a slight chill; somewhat
     delirious; pulse 130 and weak; tongue dry. On the morning of January 27th the patient looked
     better; pulse 132 and stronger; leg warm and blacker; foot pale and swelled; serous
     infiltration and discoloration extending up the thigh. The next day the patient presented a
     pale yellow hue; blackness of limb deepening and extending, having reached the lower end of the
     incision made for the ligation; odor gangrenous.  Death supervened on the
     evening of <date type="death" when="1863-01-29">January 29, 1863</date>. The autopsy showed
     that the bleeding did not come from the posterior tibial or peroneal artery, but from the lower
     part of the popliteal, which had been opened to a large extent by ulceration. Some loose
     splinters of bone were also found, the ball having grazed the hind part of both the tibia and
     fibula. On the proximal side of the ligature the clot was firm, closely attached to the walls
     of the artery, and about three-fourths of an inch long, with its apex pointing upward towards
     the heart. There was also a firm clot on the distal side, adherent to the walls of the artery,
     but much smaller than the proximal one." A piece of the femoral artery, about four inches long
     and embracing the seat of the ligature, was contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon Lidell</name>, and constitutes specimen
     1140 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>. </p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
