<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40868">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Armstead, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40868</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">149</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Harewood Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic dysentery, contracted on duty in Florida</term>
       <term>hæmorrhage from bowels</term>
       <term>enlarged solitary follicles of ileum, deposits of black pigment in patches of Peyer and in summits of villi</term>
       <term>colon ulcerated, coated with pseudomembrane between ulcers</term>
       <term>solitary follicles enlarged, villi hypertrophied</term>           
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-22">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="173"><hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>AREWOOD <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon Reed B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 300.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private William Armstead</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company C, 2d United States colored troops</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1866-01-17">January 17, 1866</date>.  Chronic dysentery, contracted while on duty with his regiment in Florida.  At the time of admission the patient was in a dying condition, and had profuse hæmorrhage from the bowels; this was controlled by astringent injections, and supporting measures were employed, together with opiates and astringents.  He rapidly sank, however, and died <date type="death" when="1866-01-23">January 23d</date>.  Autopsy: The solitary follicles of the ileum were enlarged, and there was a deposit of black pigment in the patches of Peyer and in the summits of the villi. The colon was thickened, ulcerated, and coated with pseudomembrane between the ulcers.—Surgeon Reed B. Bontecou.  [Nos. 704 to 706, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case. No. 704 is a portion of the ileum, taken near its middle, in which the solitary follicles are enlarged and the villi hypertrophied. When fresh, the extremity of each villus presented a black pigment deposit. No. 705 is the lower extremity of the ileum, with the ileo-cæcal valve and a small portion of the cæcum. The last Peyer's patch is somewhat thickened; the surrounding mucous membrane presents the same lesions as No. 704. No. 708 is a portion of the descending colon, which is considerably thickened and ulcerated. The ulcers are fringed with pseudomembrane, which hangs in shreds from their edges.]</p>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
