<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31461">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ford, James</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31461</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">165</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the kidney</term> 
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of shoulder</term>
       <term>fracture of clavicle</term> 
       <term>ball entered over outer portion of clavicle, passed through lung of same side, lodged in region of kidney, was extracted</term>
       <term>h&#230;maturia, h&#230;moptysis</term>
       <term>respiration feeble or absent over injured lung posteriorly, subcrepitant r&#226;les and sibilant ronchi</term>
       <term>urine contains albumen, granular tube-casts, blood corpuscles, and pus globules</term>
       <term>suffers pain in shoulder, partial paralysis of arm</term>         
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-27">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 513.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private James Ford</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. G, 10th Infantry</name>, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>. He was treated in the field till <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-09">May 9th</date>, then was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="152">Finley Hospital</name>; on <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-20">June 20th</date>, to Christian Street Hospital, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>; on <date type="transfer" when="1863-08-04">August 4th</date>, to Turner's Lane Hospital; and, on <date type="transfer" when="1863-09-18">September 18th</date>, to the Citizens Volunteer Hospital.  The case appears upon the records of these different hospitals as a &#34;gunshot wound of the left shoulder,&#34; and, at Turner's Lane, a fracture of the left clavicle is noted.  On <date type="transfer" when="1863-09-26">September 26th</date>, the patient was transferred to St. Joseph's Hospital, <name type="place">Central Park</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>, where the following notes appear in the case book: &#34;The ball entered, while he was stooping, over the outer portion of the left clavicle, passed through the lung of the same side, and lodged in the region of the left kidney. It was extracted on the tenth day, together with fragments of fractured bone.  After the injury occurred he had h&#230;maturia, which continued eight or ten days. He has had cough and h&#230;moptysis from the beginning.  The examination made on admission to this hospital reveals the following facts: &#39;<choice><orig>Dulness</orig><reg>Dullness</reg></choice> and tenderness on percussion on the left side; respiration feeble all over the left lung posteriorly, and, at some situations, is entirely absent; over the anterior portion of the lung there is heard an occasional subcrepitant r&#226;le and sibilant ronchus. No distinct evidences of a cavity present themselves; the urine contains albumen, granular uriniferous tube-casts, and blood corpuscles and pus globules in abundance.&#39;  October 10th, the h&#230;moptysis continues; the patient is failing in strength and becoming more emaciated. The treatment while in this hospital was quinine and aromatic sulphuric acid.&#34;  This soldier was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-10-16">October 16, 1863</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner F. F. Burmeister</name>, of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1866-06-18">June 18, 1866</date>: &#34;A mini&#233; ball fractured the left clavicle and passed out on the left side of the back. The pensioner suffers with pain in the shoulder and partial paralysis of the left arm, interfering with its use.&#34;  He was last paid in <date type="pension" when="1873-06">June, 1873</date>.</p>     
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
