<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41197">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Foster, Greenleaf P.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41197</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">178</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>delirium tremens</term>      
       <term>firm adhesions at apex of lung</term>
       <term>pleural sac contained forty-eight ounces of serum</term>
       <term>pericardium contained fluid</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of large intestine of dirty light-bluish color</term>
       <term>liver friable and capsule readily separated</term>      
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 399.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Greenleaf P. Foster</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company K, 18th Massachusetts volunteers</name>; age 36; admitted from the field <date type="admit" when="1864-02-03">February 3, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-03-04">March 4th</date>, of delirium tremens.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-03-05">eighteen hours after death</date>: Height five feet six inches; rigor mortis well marked; body not much emaciated. The brain weighed forty-five ounces, and was apparently healthy; very little fluid was found in the ventricles. The lining membrane of the trachea was very much congested. There were numerous firm adhesions at the apex of the right lung; the lung weighed twenty-one ounces; it was very much congested throughout; in the posterior portion of its upper lobe there was a circumscribed patch about the size of a walnut, which was of a dark-mulberry color and sank in water; the left lung weighed twenty-one ounces; nearly the whole of its surface was coated by recent lymph, and the pleural sac contained forty-eight ounces of serum; the upper lobe of the left lung was congested, purple on section, and exuded a large amount of frothy fluid; the lower lobe was carnified. The pericardium contained an ounce and a half of fluid. The heart was apparently healthy, weight nine ounces; a large fibrinous clot was found in the right ventricle, and a very small venous clot in the left ventricle. The mucous membrane of the &#339;sophagus was very pale. The stomach was well distended; its mucous membrane very soft and of a dusky-brown color. The intestines were much distended with gas; the mucous membrane of the duodenum and jejunum was of a very light color, nearly white; for about a foot of the upper part of the ileum, and about two feet of the lower portion, the mucous membrane was of a pinkish hue; the mucous membrane of the large intestine was of a dirty light-bluish color. The liver weighed seventy-one ounces; it was very friable; its capsule readily separated; its color a little lighter than natural. The pancreas was healthy, weight three ounces. The spleen weighed five ounces, was very firm, and of a light color. Both kidneys were healthy; the right weighed six ounces, the left seven ounces.&#8212;<name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
