<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31241">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Perkins, A. N.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31241</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="bt">Ben Tomjack</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">891</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint</term> 
       <term>excisions at the elbow joint for shot injury</term>
       <term>secondary excisions at the elbow</term> 
       <term>fatal secondary excisions at the elbow</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of elbow</term>
       <term>excision of elbow joint</term> 
       <term>ball entered near external condyle of humerus, lodged in joint</term>
       <term>elbow joint discharged pus</term>
       <term>outer condyle and head of radius fractured and removed</term> 
       <term>articular surfaces of excised bones destroyed by suppuration</term>
       <term><choice><orig>exsected</orig><reg>excised</reg></choice> lower part of humerus and upper radius and ulna each</term>       
       <term>fatal case accompanied by necroscopical record</term>
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#bt" when="2011-02-25">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1827.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private A. N. Perkins</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 2d Connecticut Heavy Artillery</name>, aged 35 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-01">June 1, 1864</date>, and admitted to the field hospital of the 1st division, Sixth Corps, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon R. Sharpe</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">15th New Jersey</name>, noted:  "A gunshot wound of the left elbow."  On <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-07">June 7th</date>, the wounded man entered <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, and <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-11">four days afterward</date> he was transferred to Patterson Park Hospital, <name type="place">Baltimore</name>, where he underwent excision of the elbow joint. <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. W. Fay</name>, who performed the operation, furnished the minutes of the case as follows:  "The ball entered near the external condyle of the humerus and lodged in the joint. The missile was removed soon after admission.  <date type="operation" when="1864-06-30">June 30th</date>, patient suffers very much from great swelling and inflammation of arm, and has a bed-sore over the sacrum. Made an incision in the arm near the elbow, which discharged about a pint of pus. Applied bread and milk poultice, and prescribed tincture of muriate of iron, fifteen drops three times a day.  <date type="operation" when="1864-07-16">July 16th</date>, the swelling and inflammation is so much diminished as to admit of an operation. Administered chloroform, and <choice><orig>exsected</orig><reg>excised</reg></choice> from lower part of humerus two and a half inches, and from the radius and ulna each one and a half inches. Made a vertical incision about seven inches long.  August 1, patient suffers much from bed-sore, which is more weakening than the wound itself. The incision is nearly healed. Patient has stealthily procured and eaten unripe pears, causing pain and vomiting followed by diarrhœa.  August 3d, had two chills to-day, one in the forenoon and the other past noon. Prescribed two grains of sulphate of quinine thrice daily.  August 9th, chills are arrested; there is now pain in right side of chest, with a cough. Prescribed a mixture with squills.  August 11th, pain in right breast continues; dullness on percussion over right lung; pulse rapid; cough. Expectorates a thick tough mucus. Ordered a prescription of sulphate of morphia two grains, diluted hydrocyanic acid ten drops, syrup of squills one-half ounce, and mucilage of gum arable two ounces, to be given in teaspoonfuls every four hours.  August 12th, patient very feeble; former symptoms continue; alternate cold sweats and paroxysms of fever; administered stimulants.  <date type="death" when="1864-08-13">August 13th</date>, patient died.  Autopsy: On opening the chest, the right pleural cavity was found to contain about thirty-four ounces of yellowish serum. The lower lobe of the right lung was congested, and a large ulcer near its apex had discharged pus into the thoracic cavity. There was also a small ulcer at the apex of the left lung. The examination of the arm at the seat of operation disclosed that the lower end of the humerus had become deprived of periosteum, subsequent to the operation, for a space of about one and a half inches. This part had become encased with an osseous substance, which completely protected it from the soft parts. In other respects all parts adjacent to the operation had healed favorably."  The excised bones of the elbow joint were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="xxx">the operator</name>, and show (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 3, <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LI</hi>, <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi> p. 872) the articular surfaces to be destroyed by suppuration. The line of section in the shafts of the bones of the forearm are very oblique. The outer condyle and head of radius had been fractured and were removed. In the specimen the olecranon has been divided.—<hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1860, p. 156, <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3466.</p>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001725.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE  <hi rend="initialcap">LI</hi>.   BONES  OF  ELBOW,  EXCISED  FOR  SHOT  INJURY.     SURGICAL  SECTION,  ARMY  MEDICAL  MUSEUM.     Fig. 3.  Specimen 3466.</head>  
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
