<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e15454">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Pomroy, H. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e15454</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">379</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered inner border of patella, exited posteriorly at central popliteal space, in line with inferior border of condyles</term>
     <term>extremity rigid, knee joint permanently anchylosed, region of knee joint much swollen</term>
     <term>surgeons desired amputation, patient refused to give consent</term>
     <term>case treated conservatively</term>
     <term>walks with cane, flexing the body on opposite thigh to swing injured limb forward, not flexing knee</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 566.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1162">Private H. W.
      Pomroy</name>, <name type="organization" key="423">Co. F, 1st Maine Heavy Artillery</name>,
     aged 36 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="55">Laurel Hill</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-19">May 19, 1864</date>, and entered <name type="hospital"
      key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-05-22">three days afterwards</date>. <name
      type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, reported: "The wound was apparently through the knee joint. A conoidal ball
     entered at the inner border of the right patella and made its exit posteriorly at the external
     central part of the popliteal space, on a line with the inferior border of the condyles. The
     progress of the case has been imperfectly recorded. All that can be ascertained is to the
     effect that the patient was bed-ridden for eight weeks; that <date type="operation" when="1864-06">in the third week</date> two pieces of bone were removed from the
     posterior wound, and <date type="operation" when="1864-06">in the fifth week</date> two others were taken out; also that he suffered
     greatly, and according to his account had marked rigors. The patient came under my notice in
     January, 1865, when presenting himself for discharge. At this time the appearance of the limb
     was as follows: The entire extremity was rigid, the knee joint permanently anchylosed, and the
     region of the joint much swollen: all original contour of the outline was destroyed, and the
     integuments were semi-&#339;dematous up to the hip joint. The skin was of a dead purplish red
     color and extremely sensitive, especially around the knee joint. The surgeons at the field
     hospital were desirous of amputating the limb, but the patient refused to give his consent, and
     the case was then treated conservatively. The patient was discharged from service <date
      type="servicedischarge" when="1865-01-26">January 26, 1865</date>, and asserted, prior to his
     departure for his home, that should the limb continue to be so excessively painful he would
     have it amputated. Thus it is shown that, should conservative treatment be successful in this
     class of cases, the limb resultant of months of suffering is apt to be worse than useless."
     <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner R. K. Jones</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Bangor</name>, <date type="pension" when="1866-10-08">October 8, 1866</date>, certified: "The wound is healed and he retains the power of flexing the leg
     slowly and feebly to an angle of 135°. He walked with crutches till the fall of 1865. He now
     walks with one cane, flexing the body on the left thigh and swinging with much effort the right
     limb forward&#8212;not flexing the knee. The foot and leg swell much after use and are now
     &#339;dematous. The outside of the leg and foot are numb. He suffers much from pain after use,"
     etc.  Subsequent examiners substantially show the same disabling effects, and the <name
      type="organization" key="xx">Bangor Board</name> in <date type="pension" when="1876-09">September, 1876</date>, described the exit wound
     as very tender, and stated that a solid substance like a buckshot or a spicula of bone could be
     felt under the cicatrix. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. </p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
