<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41041">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Allerdist, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41041</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">165</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>German</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a and anasarca</term>
       <term>pericardium contained moderate quantity of fluid</term>
       <term>whitish cheesy tubercles in both lungs, surrounded with melanic matter in apices of upper lobes</term>
       <term>cortical substance of kidneys ash-colored, bases of pyramids deep-blood color, capsules separated readily</term>
       <term>suprarenal capsules greenish-yellow internally, several loose yellowish bodies of fibrinous appearance in interior</term>
       <term>ileum dilated, walls thin, patches of Peyer congested and dotted with black points</term>
       <term>descending colon, sigmoid flexure, and rectum ulcerated</term>
       <term>solitary glands in colon had dark spots in centres</term>
       <term>ascending colon presented deep-purple color, farther up deep-ash color with purple spots</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 355.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private William Allerdist</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 20th New York volunteers</name>; German; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-01-02">January 2, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a and anasarca.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-03-16">March 16th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-03-17">twenty hours after death</date>: Height five feet four inches; body slightly emaciated; apparent age 28. The brain weighed fifty ounces and a quarter; there was some effusion in the subarachnoid space; in other respects the brain was healthy. The heart was small; it had very little adipose tissue about it; the valves were normal; the right side was filled with black clots. The pericardium contained a moderate quantity of fluid. Both lungs contained a considerable number of whitish cheesy tubercles; in the apices of their upper lobes these were surrounded with a considerable quantity of melanic matter; the lower lobes were congested and purplish on section. The bronchial tubes were congested and dilated; the larger tubes filled with a frothy mucoid serum. The right lung weighed twenty-two ounces and a quarter, the left twenty-three ounces and three-quarters. The liver weighed forty six ounces and a half; it was firm, full of blood, very finely mottled and smooth purplish-brown. The spleen weighed three ounces and a half; it was firm, full of blood, its trabecul&#230; distinct. The left kidney weighed eight ounces and a half, the right seven ounces; the cortical substance of the kidneys was ash-colored, the bases of the pyramids of a deep-blood color, the capsules separated readily. The suprarenal capsules were large, greenish-yellow internally, and very friable. In the interior of the left suprarenal capsule were several loose yellowish bodies of a fibrinous appearance. The pancreas was normal and weighed two ounces and a half. The stomach was large, its fundus congested. The mucous membrane of the duodenum was thin and soft; that of the jejunum was of a yellowish-ash color in its upper portion, purplish lower down; the ileum was dilated, its walls quite thin; all the patches of Peyer except the first were congested and dotted with black points. The c&#230;cum was dilated and congested; the ascending colon at first presented a deep-purple color; farther up it was greatly contracted, of a deep-ash color with purple spots; the solitary glands had dark spots in their centres; the transverse colon was also much contracted; the descending colon, sigmoid flexure, and rectum were ulcerated; in the descending colon the ulcers were chiefly grouped along one of the longitudinal bands; they were of moderate size and had indistinct edges; in the sigmoid flexure they appeared as little pits, with indistinct edges, and were irregularly scattered over the mucous membrane; in the rectum they were of larger size, and quite irregular in shape.&#8212;<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
