<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e24124">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Barbin, T.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e24124</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">625</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
     <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>excisions in the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>secondary excisions in the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>bone carious, removal of os calcis</term>
     <term>lame in gait, otherwise not injured</term>     
     <term>furnished with shoe filled with hair at heel</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 919.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1404">Sergeant T. Barbin</name>, <name type="organization" key="382">Co. C, 81st Pennsylvania</name>, aged 18
     years, was wounded in the right foot, at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. <name type="person"
      key="1315">Assistant Surgeon C. R. Greenleaf</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the following report of the injury: "He received the wound from a
     conoidal ball, which passed directly through the boot and entered the heel, passing through the
     os calcis in an oblique direction from behind forward and from above slightly downward.
     Considerable h&#230;morrhage attended the wound, and after an attempt at walking the man was
     carried to a house near by, where a bandage was applied.  <date type="admit" when="1862-12-15">Two days afterwards</date> he was taken to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount
      Pleasant Hospital</name>, where cold-water dressings were applied. <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-23">Eight days later</date> he was
     transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Mower Hospital, Philadelphia</name>, where, on
     examination, the bone was found to be carious, and poultices were ordered. From this date until
     the time of the operation several pieces of bone were discharged and some small abscesses were
     opened. As no improvement was observed and the probe could be passed entirely through the bone,
     showing a considerable loss of substance, it was finally determined to remove the os calcis. On
     <date type="operation" when="1863-05-16">May 16th</date> I proceeded with the operation, being assisted by <name type="person" key="xx">Drs. J.
      H. B. McClellan</name> and <name type="person" key="xx">C. R. McLean</name> (Acting Assistant
     Surgeons), and the patient being freely under the influence of chloroform. An incision was
     commenced a little in front of the articulation between the cuboid and calcis and carried
     around the heel, parallel with the long axis of the calcis, to a point just posterior to the
     posterior tibial artery; another was made at right angles to this, about two and a half inches
     in length, through the tendo-achillis. The flaps were then dissected back and disarticulation was effected in the manner
     recommended by <name type="person" key="xx">Mr. Erichsen</name>, the operation being completed
     in thirty minutes and no artery requiring ligation being cut. Monsell's solution was used to
     control the h&#230;morrhage from the smaller arterial twigs and veins. The flaps were
     accurately brought together and retained in position by silver-wire sutures, an opening being
     left posteriorly for the escape of fluids. Cold-water dressings were used. One-half grain of
     morphia was given, and some little febrile action during the next two days was controlled by
     spirits mindereri. On May 18th, Smith's anterior splint was applied to the leg and adhesive strips from the toes to a point near the
     incision. The incisions on the inner side of the foot healed by first intention and the sutures
     were withdrawn on May 20th, and a sponge tent was ordered to keep open the posterior point of
     exit, which had closed by granulations. On May 22d all the sutures were removed and adhesive
     strips re-applied. Large quantities of grumous pus were being discharged. The patient continued
     to improve, and on the 24th, the splint was removed, a sling made from a sheet being
     substituted. After this the patient improved rapidly and left his bed on June 12th, the wound
     having healed with the exception of a slight track at the junction of the two incisions, from
     which a little healthy pus was being discharged. By June 17th the patient could bear his weight
     on the foot, the sinus having closed. The contour of the foot was not materially altered, the
     sole being a little flatter than its fellow. He was in excellent health and fine spirits, and
     felt no pain when bearing his weight on the foot, but said that it felt very springy."   In
     addition to the history, <name type="person" key="1315">Dr. Greenleaf</name> also stated that
     as soon as the parts had become a little hardened and accustomed to their new position, a shoe
     filled with hair at the heel was to be furnished to the patient. The subsequent records of the
     hospital show that the patient was able to wear his shoe by <date type="injury" when="1863-07-10">July 10th</date>, and could walk without
     crutch. Afterwards he was allowed to stay at his home in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> on furlough, getting
     stronger every day and his foot being entirely healed.  On <date type="servicedischarge"
      when="1863-11-30">November 30, 1863</date>, he was discharged from service and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xx">Examining Surgeon W. Jewell</name>, of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, <date type="pension" when="1866-09-14">September 14, 1866</date>, certified that "the removal of the os calcis has left the pensioner lame in his gait but
     not otherwise injured. Other examiners report nothing additionally important. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-09-04">September 4, 1880</date>. The excised <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice>, contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the  Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="1315">the operator</name>, and exhibiting general caries, constitutes specimen 1286 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical
     Section</hi>.&#185;</p>
   <p>&#185; A detailed account of this case by Surgeon <hi rend="initialcap">C. R.</hi> <hi rend="initialcap">G</hi>REENLEAF, <hi rend="initialcap">U. S. A.</hi>, will be found on page 389 of Vol. XLVI of the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of the
    Medical Sciences</hi>, Philadelphia, 1863.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
