<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18268">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Ward, Rowland</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e18268</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">373-374</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the face</term>
          <term>plastic operations</term>
          <term>cheiloplastic operations</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the face</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the facial bones</term>
          <term>fracture of lower maxilla</term>
          <term>fragment of shell destroyed inferior maxillary bone and soft parts</term>
          <term>destroyed chin and soft parts down the neck to level of hyoid bone</term>
          <term>destroyed floor of mouth</term>
          <term>tongue protrudes and hangs down on neck</term>
          <term>deglutition and articulation impossible</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-20">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-11-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private Rowland
          W&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization">Co. E, 4th New York Heavy
          Artillery</name>, aged 46 years, was wounded at <name type="battle">Ream's Station,
          Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-08-25">August 25th, 1864</date>, by a
        fragment of shell, which destroyed and completely carried away the inferior maxillary bone
        and soft parts, commencing two inches anterior to the angle on the right side, carrying away
        the chin and all the soft parts down the neck, on a level with the hyoid bone, destroying
        tho floor of the mouth completely, allowing the tongue to protrude and hang down on the
        neck; deglutition and articulation were impossible. Three of the right lower incisor teeth,
        with the corresponding alveoli loosely connected with the tissue, remained, and were allowed
        to stay in that position until the healing process took place, as they gave a partial
        support to the tongue and submaxillary gland, which was not injured. The wound extended
        across to the left side, carrying away all the teeth and jaw bone, except those previously
        mentioned, to a point as high up as the angle of the inferior maxillary on the left side. He
        was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, <date
          type="admit" when="1864-08-28">August 28th, 1864</date>. His general health was bad from
        scurvy. The patient did well, and improved rapidly. On <date type="furlough"
          when="1864-12-09">December 9th</date>, he was furloughed for thirty days, and, at the
        expiration of his furlough, he was readmitted to hospital in good condition. On <date
          type="operation" when="1865-01-20">January 20th, 1865</date>, an operation was performed
        to construct a floor for the mouth&#8212;no anaesthetic was used. Preliminary to the
        operation, two molar teeth were extracted from the right-hand fragment of the lower jaw. An
        incision was made two and a half inches in length down the median line of the neck,
        terminating one inch above the thyroid cartilage. Two lateral incisions, one upon each side,
        of equal length, right-angled to the vertical incision, these incisions corresponding to the
        base of the jaw. These flaps were then carefully dissected up, brought together at the
        middle incision, and secured by three hare-lip needles, the parts being supported by
        adhesive straps. Frequent application of dry lint was made to protect the parts from the
        injurious effects of the saliva, which was being constantly secreted. The healing proceeded
        rapidly, the parts uniting by first intention. Power of articulation and degustation was
        much improved. The needles were removed <date type="operation" when="1865-01-23">on the
          third day</date>. On <date type="operation" when="1865-04-22">April 22d, 1865</date>, the
        parts being in a favorable condition, ether was administered, and a second operation was
        performed. Two incisions, one on the right and one on the left, parallel to the inferior
        border of the inferior maxillary bone, each three inches in length, severed both the facial
        arteries, which were secured by ligatures. The upper flaps were carefully dissected up, as
        far back as the angle of the jaw upon each side. The anterior edges of these flaps were
        freely incised, as well as the superior edge of the parts remaining after the first
        operation. The flaps were then brought into apposition and retained by four hare-lip
        needles, two in the upper flap forming the lip, and one upon each side, uniting the lower
        edge of the flap to the freshened edge of the parts after the first operation. Dry lint
        dressings were applied, and the patient was fed through a gum catheter. The hare-lip pins
        were removed from the longitudinal incision on the third day, the others being removed <date
          type="operation" when="1865-04-26">on the fourth day</date>, at which time the remaining
        pins, together with all the sutures, were removed, the parts being supported throughout the
        remainder of the treatment by straps of adhesive plaster. On the morning of the <date
          type="operation" when="1865-04-27">27th of April</date>, secondary h&#230;morrhage
        occurred from the left facial artery, which was readily controlled by digital compression.
        Owing to the constant secretion of saliva from the sublingual gland, which was carefully
        preserved during the operation, a slough was produced at the junction of the inferior angle
        of the flaps. This was checked by the application of a <choice>
          <sic>week</sic>
          <corr>weak</corr>
        </choice> solution of nitric acid. On <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1865-06-23">June
          23d</date>, the patient was discharged at his own request. A fistulous orifice, one-fourth
        of an inch in diameter, only remaining, in consequence of the constant secretion of saliva,
        from the sublingual gland, which prevented the parts from closing by granulation. He is able
        to articulate quite plainly, which he has hitherto been unable to do since the date of his
        injury. Until the completion of this operation the patient was compelled to assume a
        recumbent position to receive his nourishment, or even a swallow of water. He can now take
        his food and drink without any difficulty, in an erect posture. By the use of a rubber
        button, properly adjusted to the fistulous orifice, the secretion of saliva was prevented
        from making its exit externally. The appearance of the patient, both before and after
        operation, is shown by photographs Nos. 167, 168, 169, 170 and 186, <hi rend="italic"
          >Surgical Series</hi>, A. M. M. The photographs were printed from negatives prepared at
          <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, under the direction of <name
          type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization"
          key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who was the operator in this case. On <date type="pension"
          when="1869-11-08">November 8th, 1869</date>, <name type="person">Ward</name> forwarded a
        letter to the <name type="person">Surgeon General</name> in reference to a pension. He wrote
        that he was obliged to live on milk diet. The letter, with photographs and a history of his
        case, was forwarded to the <name type="organization">Pension Office</name>. He is a
        pensioner. </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001437.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 165.&#8212;Gunshot laceration of chin. (From
          photograph 186, S. S. A. M. M.)</head>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001438.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 166.&#8212;Successful cheiloplastic operation for
          gunshot injury. (From photograph 170, S. S. A. M. M.)</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
