<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e12295">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">S&#8212;&#8212;, Henry</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e12295</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">174-175</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term> 
                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the skull</term>
                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the cranium with depression</term>
                    <term>gunshot fracture of cranial bones accompanied by hemiplegia or paraplegia</term>
                    <term>conoidal musket ball fractured and depressed skull between frontal eminences</term>
                    <term>profuse diarrh&#339;a</term>
                    <term>mental faculties obscured, paralysis of motion, hyper&#230;sthesia of whole surface, convulsions</term>
                    <term>fracture of inner table with depression, fissure extended into frontal sinus</term>                    
                    <term>depressed fractures of frontal bones</term>
                    <term>convulsions of epileptic character</term>
                    <term>meninges presented evidence of high degree of inflammation</term>
                    <term>surfaces of right hemisphere bathed with pus</term>
                    <term>pus filled longitudinal fissure and near ethmoid plates</term>
                    <term><term>autopsy performed</term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0213">            
                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1527">Private
                        Henry S&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="441">Co. E, 118th Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>, aged 38, was wounded at the battle of 
                    <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness, Virginia</name>,
                        <date type="injury" when="1864-05-09">May 9th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal
                    musket ball which fractured and depressed the skull between the frontal eminences.  He was sent to the hospital of the 1st division, Fifth Corps, and on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-15">May 15th</date> transferred to
                    <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, and admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount
                        Pleasant Hospital</name>. So far, simple dressings only had been applied.  On
                        <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-27">May 27th</date> he was transferred
                    to the <name type="hospital">Satterlee Hospital, Philadelphia</name>. The day following his admission, he was
                    attacked with a profuse diarrh&#339;a, and complained of pain in the head;
                    was dull and drowsy, and at times delirious.  On <date type="injury" when="1864-06-01">June 1st</date> his mental faculties
                    were completely obscured, and paralysis of motion on the left side was observed,
                    though there was hyper&#230;sthesia of the whole surface.  Convulsions of an epileptic
                    character occurred on the 2d, and it was observed that the muscular power of the
                    left side was now restored, and that the right was paralyzed. The pupils, which
                    had hitherto been dilated, were now somewhat contracted; the tongue was dry; the
                    lungs full of coarse r&#226;les.  Repeated convulsions recurred on the 4th, exhibiting
                    the same remarkable features heretofore mentioned in respect to the side
                    paralyzed. No control over the sphincters remained.  Death occurred in the
                    afternoon of <date type="death" when="1864-06-04">June 4th, 1864</date>.  At the
                    autopsy the fractured portion of bone was found to be ovoid in shape and
                    corresponding in dimension to the external wound. There was a fracture of the
                    inner table with depression of a portion near the longitudinal sinus to the
                    depth of two lines, and a fissure extended into the frontal sinus. Beneath was a
                    black slough of the dura mater, measuring two inches in length by one in width.
                    The anterior and lateral surfaces of the right hemisphere were bathed with pus,
                    which also filled the great longitudinal fissure and the parts in the region of
                    the ethmoid plates. At the base of the brain was an effusion of serum. The
                    meninges on this side presented evidence of a high degree of inflammation, and
                    could be easily separated in large patches from the convolutions, which were
                    slightly softened, one containing a large abscess. The membranes of the other
                    side were little more than congested. Further than this the brain was healthy.   The pathological specimen, an extraordinarily thin <choice><orig>calvaria</orig><reg>calvarium</reg></choice>, is No. 2758, Sect.
                    I, A. M. M., and was contributed, with the history, by <name type="person"
                        key="1526">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. W. Keen, <choice><orig>jr.</orig><reg>Jr.</reg></choice></name></p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
