<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6034">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Woodworth, Henry</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6034</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">118</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary excisions</term>
     <term>ball entered thigh below trochanter major, grooving femur anteriorly at level of lesser
      trochanter, lodging under sartorius muscle</term>
     <term>pus burrowed about articulation</term>
     <term>periostitis</term>
     <term>cotyloid cavity ulcerated</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 270.—<name type="person" key="961">Private Henry
     Woodworth</name>, <name type="organization" key="197">Co. A, 4th Vermont</name>, aged 18 years,
    was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice>
      <orig>Spottsylvania</orig>
      <reg>Spotsylvania</reg>
     </choice> Court House</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1864-05-11">May 11, 1864</date>, by
    a conoidal musket ball, which entered the left thigh, just below the trochanter major, passed
    inward and forward, grooving the femur anteriorly at the level of the lesser trochanter, and
    lodging under the sartorius muscle. The patient was conveyed to the field hospital of the 2d
    division of the Sixth Corps, where the ball was removed through an incision at the edge of the
    sartorius. <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-18">A week subsequently</date>, he was placed on
    one of the trains for the <name type="place">Rappahannock</name>, and was transferred from <name type="place">Fredericksburg</name> to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>,
    where, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-25">May 25th</date>, he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>. His condition on admission was very
    unpromising; his pulse was quick and feeble; he was anæmic, and without appetite. He was
    placed upon a tonic regimen, but he did not improve. The wound discharged profusely; there was
    much pain in the joint, pain aggravated by the slightest movement, and pus had burrowed in every
    direction about the articulation. <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, decided that an excision of the head of the femur offered
    the only possible chance of saving life, and, on <date type="operation" when="1864-07-01">July
     1st</date>, the patient having been anæsthetized by sulphuric ether, <name type="person" key="158">Dr. Bontecou</name> proceeded to perform the operation. A curved incision, with its
    concavity forward, embracing the trochanter, readily exposed the joint. The muscular attachments
    were divided, and the head was easily disarticulated, the joint being disorganized and the round
    ligament destroyed. The continuity of the bone being uninterrupted, the upper extremity was
    readily turned out and sawn just below the point of impact of the ball. On examination of the
    portion of bone removed, it was found that much of the head had been absorbed, and that the
    remainder was carious. The specimen is represented in the accompanying wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 75). The neck and trochanters are covered with traces of the
    effects of periostitis. The cotyloid cavity was ulcerated. The wound was drawn together by
    adhesive strips, and the limb was dressed in a fracture apparatus with moderate extension. Every
    means of supporting the patient's strength was adopted, but he did not rally from the operation,
    and, sinking gradually, expired on <date type="death" when="1864-07-02">July 2, 1864</date>. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001544.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 75.—Excised upper extremity of left femur with a conoidal
     ball. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3049. ¼</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
