<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40983">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Fenstermaker, David</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e40983</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">158-159</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a, sick one month</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of small intestine reddened, valvul&#230; conniventes very distinct</term>
       <term>transverse colon presented small ulcers, descending colon appeared same as transverse colon, ulcers of sigmoid flexure and rectum larger and more numerous</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-30">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 339.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private David Fenstermaker</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company K, 48th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 26; admitted from the hospital of the 2d Division, 9th Corps, <name type="place">Windmill Point, Aquia Creek, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-02-08">February 8, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a, contracted at Fredericksburg.  He had been sick a month, was emaciated, and had twelve to fifteen evacuations daily. His tongue was dry and brown, his features shrunken, and there was slight tenderness over the abdomen.  &#8478;. Mercury with chalk, ten grains, tannic acid two grains, quinine six grains; make eight pills. Take one every two hours. Half an ounce of brandy every hour.  February 9th: Much the same; diarrh&#339;a slightly less.  February 10th: diarrh&#339;a worse again; stools involuntary.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-02-11">February 11th</date>.  In this case the use of beef-tea seemed to aggravate the diarrh&#339;a.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Daniel Weisel</name>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-02-11">two hours after death</date>: Height five feet ten inches; no rigor mortis; body somewhat emaciated. The brain weighed forty-eight ounces and a half; it was light-colored and soft; the pia mater was somewhat congested. The right lung weighed thirty-five ounces and a quarter, the left forty-eight ounces and a half; the right lung was congested throughout and presented a number of isolated hepatized lobules; the central portion of the upper lobe of the left lung and an irregular area in the lower lobe were also in the state of red hepatization; the rest of the lung was congested; the bronchial tubes on both sides were inflamed, the bronchial glands large and black. The heart weighed eight ounces and a quarter; its muscular tissue was firm and red; there was but little surrounding adipose tissue; the right cavities contained black clots which weighed an ounce and a quarter. The pericardium contained an ounce of serum. The liver weighed fifty-nine ounces and a half; it was firm, finely mottled, and generally congested; the gall-bladder contained a small quantity of light-yellow viscid bile. The spleen weighed eleven ounces and a quarter; it was of a dark-purple color, very firm and congested, its trabecul&#230; indistinct, The pancreas weighed two ounces and three-quarters; it was light-red and firm. The suprarenal capsules were normal. The right kidney weighed nine ounces, the left nine ounces and a half; the cortical substance of both kidneys had a peculiar light flesh color; their capsules were very readily torn off. The stomach was rather large, its mucous membrane soft. The mucous membrane of the small intestine was reddened; the valvul&#230; conniventes very distinct. The ascending colon was dark colored; its mucous membrane soft; its glands distinct and slightly enlarged; the transverse colon was contracted; its mucous membrane slate-colored, thin, soft, and presented a number of small ulcers; the descending colon was dilated; but, with this exception presented the same appearances as the transverse colon. In the sigmoid flexure and rectum the ulcers were still larger and more numerous.&#8212;<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
