<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e11085">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Crawford, J. A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e11085</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">241</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the lower third of the femur</term>
     <term>recoveries after primary amputations in the lower third of the femur</term>
     <term>wounded through knee joint</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>amputated at lower third of thigh</term>
     <term>h&#230;morrhage</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>tubular sequestrum and involucrum removed from stump of femur</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 444.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal J. A.
     Crawford</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 6th Wisconsin</name>, aged 24
    years, was wounded through the knee joint, at <name type="BATTLE" key="2">Gettysburg</name>,
     <date type="injury" when="1863-07-01">July 1, 1863</date>. He was admitted to the Seminary
    Hospital, whence <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. M. Welch</name> made
    the following report: &#34;The limb was amputated at the lower third of the thigh on <date
     type="operation" when="1863-07-02">the day following the injury</date>. The patient, came under
    my care on August 15th, at which time the stump was granulating slowly and there was a free
    discharge of healthy pus; but the flaps had sloughed, leaving the end of the femur bare. A
    roller bandage was applied to prevent retraction of the muscles, and warm-water dressings with
    disinfectants were used, iron and stimulants being given internally. The patient's general
    health was disturbed, though his appetite was tolerably fair. He improved gradually, and was
    transferred to <name type="place" key="xx">Camp Letterman</name> on <date type="transfer"
     when="1863-09-02">September 2d.</date>&#34; <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon H.
     C. May</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">145th New York</name>, continued the history
    as follows: &#34;The patient came under my charge on October 12th, being very feeble and
    troubled with profuse and obstinate diarrh&#339;a, having no appetite, and suffering from hectic
    fever and much pain, also an abscess along the course of the lower end of the bone. The stump
    was conical shaped, with the end of the femur exposed, and the granulations were pale and
    flabby. Astringents and tonics were administered. On <date type="operation" when="1863-10-30"
     >October 30th</date>, the diarrh&#339;a was almost controlled, but great pain and irritation
    was felt about the stump, and, chloroform having been given, a sequestrum four and a half inches
    long, and consisting of a complete section of the lower end of the bone, was removed by forcible
    traction. The surfaces of the bone were found to be very rough and surrounded with a wall of
    callus. The patient did well after the operation; the abscesses ceased to discharge, and the
    cavity in the stump filled with healthy granulations. By November 6th, he had regained a good
    appetite, the diarrh&#339;a was entirely checked, and his general appearance and condition were
    rapidly improving.&#34; On <date type="transfer" when="1863-11-07">the next day</date> the
    patient was transferred to Newton University Hospital, <name type="place">Baltimore</name>,
    where the following described operation was performed on <date type="operation"
     when="1864-02-02">February 2, 1864</date>, by <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon C. W.
     Jones</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge: &#34;The end of
    the femur being necrosed, an incision six inches in length was made on the anterior aspect of
    the thigh and four inches of bone removed. Thirty-six hours afterwards h&#230;morrhage to the
    amount of four ounces occurred, when the sutures were removed and a large clot of blood was
    taken out, after which the bleeding ceased. After this the patient's constitutional condition
    continued to improve and the flaps approximated. By March 24th, the stump had entirely healed
    with a good cushion.&#34; The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge"
     when="1864-05-03">May 3, 1864</date>, and pensioned. He was paid <date type="pension"
     when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. The sequestrum was contributed to <name type="hospital"
     key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon E. A.
     Koerper</name>, and is represented in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGURE 180, and an involucrum
    of new bone, removed at the last operation, is shown in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGURE
    181.</p>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001583.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 180.&#8212;Tubular sequestrum removed from stump of the right
    femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1971.</head></figure>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001584.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 181.&#8212;Involucrum, 4 inches in length, from stump of right
    femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2153.</head></figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
