<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e35007">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Jordan, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e35007</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">839-840</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>hospital gangrene</term>
     <term>struck by fragment of shell</term>
     <term>shell passed across right thigh below Pouparts ligament, through scrotum, destroying right testicle, behind left thigh</term>
     <term>febrile disturbance, anorexia</term>
     <term>yellow fured tongue</term>
     <term>burning pain in thigh</term>
     <term>restless expression of countenance</term>
     <term>ulcer covered with ashy gray slough, discharging a
      thin fetid serum mixed with debris</term>
     <term>severe pain in region of cicatrix of thigh</term>
     <term> gangrene attacked granulating surface of thigh</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-02-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
    and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>In <date type="injury" when="1863-02">February, 1863</date>, a number of cases of hospital
    gangrene occurred at the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D.
    C., and were observed by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who, in a special report to the Surgeon
    General, gives the following interesting account of the pathology and treatment of the cases. In
    several instances later information has been added to the cases cited by <name type="person"
     key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>: <!--<ref xml:id="n01" target="#n48" n="1" /> --></p>

   <p>"On the 26th of December, 1862, about two hundred wounded from the battle of <name
     type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name> were received into the <name type="hospital"
     key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>.</p>

   <p>&quot; CASE VIII.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">John Jordan</name>, Private, <name
     type="organization" key="xxx">Co. H, 2d Maine</name>, aged 20 years, was struck at <name
     type="battle" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December
     13, 1862</date>, by a fragment of shell, which passed across the right thigh below Poupart s
    ligament, through the scrotum, destroying the right testicle, and behind the left thigh,
    producing in its course very extensive but superficial wounds of the anterior portion of right
    and posterior portion of left thigh. He was admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-12-26">December 26, 1862</date>, and placed in ward No.
    5. February 27, 1863, he had febrile disturbance and anorexia, a yellow, furred tongue,
    an anxious, restless expression of countenance, and a burning pain in his left thigh. There was
    on the right thigh a granulating surface three by two inches in dimensions, level with the
    integument, and cicatrizing rapidly. A smaller, equally healthy surface remained unheuled on the
    scrotum, while on the posterior portion of the upper part of the left thigh an ulcer three by
    two inches in extent was found, oval in shape, covered with an ashy gray slough, with its margin
    thickened and everted, surrounded by a livid areola, and, instead of normal pus, discharging a
    thin fetid serum mixed with debris. He was at once removed to the house; the whole diseased
    surface was touched with pure nitric acid and dressed with the creasote lotion; stimulants and
    the best extra diet, with beef essence and milk punch at short intervals, and citrate of iron
    and quinine three times daily, were ordered. March 5th: The attempt to push the
    nutrients and stimulants produced, as it generally does, anorexia, nausea, vomiting, and
    diarrh&#339;a. The tongue became thickly coated with a yellow fur and dry and red at the tip; and so
    great was the gastric disturbance that all medicines were discontinued and the stomach allowed
    to recover its tone by rest, no longer being teased either by drugs or excessive and undesired
    nutriment. No benefit followed the local application, and the ulceration had extended in every
    direction. There was the characteristic margin, preceded by the areoln of livid stasis,
    preparing the tissues for their rapid destruction. The connective tissue beneath the skin had
    been destroyed, so that the skin for one inch from its margin was perfectly movable. The muscles
    separated from each other by the death of their connective tissue lay in the wound bathed in its
    discharge, but rosy and florid, and resisting the advance of the disease. This sore was so
    unmistakably hospital gangrene that several pictures of it were taken by direction of <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon
     Brinton</name>, which represent well the surface of the ulcer dripping with its thin serous discharge,
    mingled with threads of dead connective tissue, its piled-up, thickened, and everted margin
    surmounted by a thin line of vivid redness, and its broad zone of purple congestion shading away
    into a bronze hue, the depth of color in the areola indicating the engorgement of the small
    vessels and its line the feebleness and slowness of the movement of the blood. It was determined
    to try the opium treatment, with hydrochloric acid as a tonic, and this mixture was given in the
    proportion of 16 drops of tincture of opium with four drops hydrochloric acid every three hours.
    The sore was dressed with a stimulating poultice composed of flaxseed, cinchona, and ginger
    mixed with porter. Under the use of the acid internally the tongue has become clean and moist,
    the tone of the digestive apparatus improved, and a fair quantity of food had been taken.
    Porter and ale had been given as the stomach would retain them. But little change had taken
    place in the character of the ulcer, which was eight inches in length by seven in breadth,
    extending to the perineum, and irregularly oval in shape. The muscles exposed (the
    semi-membranosus and biceps) had yielded and were now almost divided. The sores on the right
    thigh and scrotum had not been in the least affected, but were cicatrizing rapidly. The entire
    surface of the gangrenous sore was now thoroughly cleaned, all sloughs and shreds removed with
    forceps and scissors, was well dried with lint and carefully painted with pure nitric acid. The
    brush, charged with acid, was passed beneath the excavated margin in some places more than an
    inch. The patient was etherized, and this acid application was made most carefully and
    completely. This was considered a dernier resort, for although the capacity for taking and
    assimilating food seemed to have been increased by the acid treatment internally, yet his
    strength was daily diminishing from the exhausting discharge and from the absorption of the
    products of the gangrene. On the succeeding day an entire change in the sore was observed; there
    had been no extension of the gangrene, the fetid odor was gone, and the discharge was more
    consistent and less serous. In a few days more all the shreds of dead fascia were removed, and
    the surface was found to be perfectly healthy. The contrast between the ragged, offensive,
    yellow-colored ulcer before the last application of acid, and the florid, perfectly normal
    granulating surface which replaced it, was as gratifying as it was surprising. With the local
    there was also a constitutional improvement. The appetite became voracious, the patient slept
    well; there was no pain, and the process of repair was very rapid. The acid was continued
    internally. April 1st: The sore was now two by three inches in extent and cicatrizing rapidly;
    but a small surface yet remained annealed. The patient was in perfect health, had gained flesh
    very rapidly, and was now on crutches. There was some contraction of the flexors, as the biceps
    and semi-membranoeus were both involved in the destruction. [Jordan was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-06-09">June 9, 1863</date>,
    and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. C. Weston</name> reported, September 11, 1869: &quot;At the biennial
    examination in 1865 atrophy and increased weakness of right thigh and leg had occurred. His gait
    is always affected; he has severe pain in region of cicatrix of left thigh; this cicatrix is
    six by three inches, is depressed, indurated, adherent to muscles, and sensitive on account of
    rigidity and emaciation; he cannot fully extend the leg.&quot; His condition had not improved
    when examined in 1873.] </p>

   <p>&quot;The most remarkable circumstance in this typical case is the fact that when the gangrene
    attacked the granulating surface of the left thigh the equally large granulating surface of the
    right thigh was unaffected; and that while the gangrene was ravaging the left thigh the rapid
    cicatriza tion of the right proceeded uninterruptedly. The discharge from the left thigh was so
    profuse that no precaution would have prevented the virus from coming in contact with the
    excoriated surfaces of the scrotum and right thigh. If, therefore, the disease be propagated by
    inoculation, all the circumstances were favorable; since the proximity of the thighs at their
    upper part, and a denuded surface on the scrotum, that might act as a link, render it certain
    that a portion of the great discharge from the left must frequently have been placed in contact
    with both of the other sores. If, on the other hand, the gangrene be not a local but a
    constitutional disease, why should it spend itself on one granulating surface when there were
    two others equally obnoxious ? The con trast between these sores was marked ; for while the
    tissues of the left thigh were melting away under one s very gaze, the process of repair in the
    scrotum and right thigh was progressing as rapidly as under the most favorable circumstances. In
    its earlier stages this case was twice treated with nitric acid, and perhaps imperfectly, from
    its not having been carried into the recesses of the ulcer. The system of urging nutrients,
    stimulants, and tonics irrespective of the natural desires of the patient is, I am satisfied,
    pernicious. The vital energy being depressed, the digestive organs are enfeebled; and the
    introduction of milk punch, beef essence, eggnog, and with stimu lants porter, ale, etc., into
    an unwilling stomach, simply produces anorexia, nausea, vomiting, and diarrh&#339;a. The tongue
    became furred and dry, and there was a perfect disgust for all food. The hydrochloric acid was
    given to correct this condition ; and whether its action was confined to the stomach in
    rendering soluble the aliment given in very small quantities, or whether its action was
    catalytic or eliminative, I shall not pretend to state, but under its influence the tongue
    became moist and clean and tlie patient made known his desire for food. Nutrients were then
    given more freely as his appetite returned. The recovery of this man is due, firstly, to the
    thorough application of nitrid acid to every portion of the ulcer, which changed its specific
    nature immediately; and, secondly, to the combined effect of acid and opium internally. After
    the last complete application of acid the sore was changed in character, the areola
    disappeared, the surface became clean, the margins lost their elevated appearance, the serous
    discharge became purulent, and the offensive odor was entirely destroyed. An equally marked
    improvement occurred in his general condition. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
