<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9146">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Shillinglaw, R. T.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9146</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">190-191</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recovery after shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball fractured femur obliquely at middle third</term>
     <term>wounded in thigh, both upper extremities, and temple</term>
     <term>made prisoner</term>
     <term>injured limb shortened three inches</term>
     <term>gunshot wound of thigh, arm and elbow, hand and arm, and temple. The bone has united
      crookedly</term>
     <term>compound comminuted fracture of thigh bone</term>
     <term>bone united crookedly, three inches shorter</term>
     <term>nerves of limb affected, constantly suffering</term>
     <term>gunshot wound of elbow joint, ball lodged near joint</term>
     <term>elbow weakened as to be unserviceable for labor</term>
     <term>ball struck parietal bone</term>
     <term>consumption, superinduced by pleuro-pneumonia</term>
     <term>arm pierced by piece of shell, scraping bone</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-04">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 390.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Captain R. T.
     Shillinglaw</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 79th New York</name>, aged 32
    years, was wounded in the left thigh, both upper extremities, and the right temple, at <name type="BATTLE" key="6">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-07-21">July 21,
     1861</date>. The injury of the thigh was caused by a conoidal ball, which fractured the femur
    obliquely at the middle third. He was made a prisoner and conveyed to <name type="place">Richmond</name>, where the fracture was treated at the Alms House Hospital, by a Desault
    splint for one week, and by Smith s anterior splint for twelve weeks subsequently. Slight
    suppuration continued for nearly a year after the injury, with occasional elimination of bits of
    necrosed bone. Having been exchanged on <date type="transfer" when="1861-12-31">December 31,
     1861</date>, he proceeded to his home in <name type="place">New York City</name>, where he was
    treated, for a time, by his family physician. <date type="duty" when="1862">Some months
     afterwards</date> he returned to the field, and served as Acting Aid-de-Camp to <name type="person" key="xxx">General Wilcox</name> until <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-01-20">January 20, 1863</date>, when he resigned the service. In <date type="duty" when="1863-08">August following</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Captain
     Shillinglaw</name> was commissioned in the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve
     Corps</name>, in which organization he remained until <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-02">August 2, 1865</date>, when he was finally mustered out and pensioned. After
    leaving the service he took up his residence in <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington
     City</name>, and obtained employment in the <name type="organization" key="xxx">U. S. Treasury
     Department</name>. The photograph, represented in the annexed cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 152), was obtained in <date type="photo" when="1866-06">June, 1866</date>, when he
    visited the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>. At that time the injured
    limb was shortened nearly three inches, but he could walk briskly and without a limp. He used no
    cane and experienced little or no inconvenience from his wounds. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. Phillips</name> certified, <date type="pension" when="1869-02-06">February 6,
     1869</date>: "Gunshot wound of left thigh, left arm, right hand and arm, and right temple.
    Compound comminuted fracture of thigh bone. The bone has united crookedly, and is about three
    inches shorter than its fellow; the muscles are attenuated, and the nerves of the limb so
    affected that he is constantly suffering. Gunshot wound of left elbow joint; ball lodged near
    the joint, which is now so weakened as to be unserviceable for labor. Flesh wound of right hand
    from piece of shell. The right arm was pierced by a piece of shell, scraping the bone. This
    wound impairs the usefulness of the limb. A ball struck the right parietal bone. He suffers but
    little from this wound." This pensioner died <date type="death" when="1870-04-14">April 14,
     1870</date>, of consumption, superinduced by an attack of pleuro-pneumonia and gunshot wounds. </p>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001568.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 152.—Shot fracture of middle third of left femur. [From
    a photograph.]</head></figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
