<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18145">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Martyn, C. G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e18145</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">439-440</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recovery after shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball entered leg between tibialis anticus and extensor longus digitorum muscles opposite
      centre of tibia, fractured tibia and fibula, exited at anterior-lateral soleus muscle</term>
     <term>contraction of tendo-achillis</term>
     <term>operation cut tendo-achillis and removed fractured bone</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>heart irregular, respiration difficult, circulation feeble</term>
     <term>liver twice normal size</term>
     <term>dropsy</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 690.—<name type="person" key="1248">Lieutenant C. G.
     Martyn</name>, <name type="organization" key="248">Co. A, 2d New York Heavy Artillery</name>,
    aged 29 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="113">Deep Bottom</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-08-14">August 14, 1864</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-08-17">three
     days afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="290">Assistant Surgeon C. A. Leale</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, contributed the pathological specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 267), and the following history of the case: He was wounded by a
    minié ball, which entered the right leg between the tibialis anticus and extensor longus
    digitorum muscles, opposite the centre of the middle third of the tibia, passed through the leg
    transversely, fracturing the tibia and fibula, and made its exit at the anterior lateral aspect
    of the soleus muscle. Immediately after the reception of the injury the patient was removed to a
    field hospital, and on <date type="operation" when="1864-08-15">the following day</date> he was
    placed under the influence of chloroform, when several spiculæ of bone were removed.
    Splints were then applied, and he was transferred to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where the wound was dressed and the limb placed in a fracture-box. The
    general condition of the patient at that time was good. On account of great pain the
    fracture-box was removed on October 7th, and Smith's anterior splint was adjusted, which allowed
    the patient to rest more comfortably. On November 1st the splints were removed, and the limb was
    laid on a pillow and dressed twice a day with simple dressings. The wound had now nearly closed,
    but several sinuses existed and communicated with the bone, and the fracture had not yet united.
    By March 16, 1865, the patient was able to leave his bed and walk on crutches. He first came
    under my charge on <date type="injury" when="1865-04-01">April 1st</date>, when, on an
    examination with the probe, I found the sinuses to communicate with dead bone; the discharge of
    pus was about three ounces per diem; appetite and general condition good. The discharge
    continuing to increase and the patient gradually growing weaker, he was placed under the
    influence of ether on <date type="operation" when="1865-04-25">April 25th</date>, and an
    incision was made nine inches in length over the anterior portion of the tibia, when it was
    found that necrosis extended to within two inches of the ankle joint and nearly to the head of
    the tibia. A sequestrum nine and a half inches long was then removed, also several small pieces,
    and in the operation a longitudinal piece of newly formed bone had to be withdrawn. After the
    removal of the necrosed portion, new bone was found of sufficient thickness to hold the foot in
    its proper position. The loss of blood during the operation amounted to about ten ounces. The
    wound was dressed with charpie and cold water, and the patient took stimulants and an anodyne
    every four hours. On the next day he was very weak and had continued nausea, no appetite, and
    vomited all food as soon as swallowed, not being able to retain brandy even, which increased the
    nausea. Two ounces of beef tea was then given every four hours, but it also was nearly all
    thrown off. On April 27th, he was still weaker and the nausea continued, when two ounces of
    champagne with ice was administered every four hours, and four ounces of beef tea, per enema,
    was given three times a day. This was continued for two days, when the patient had a well-marked
    chill and was sinking fast, his nausea having increased to such an extent that the sight of
    other patient's food caused him to vomit. On April 30th, he was worse in every respect, when
    doses of five grains of oxalate of cerium was ordered to be given whenever the patient felt as
    though he would immediately vomit. By 9 o'clock P. M. he had used six powders, not having
    vomited once since taking the first, and having retained food eaten at noon. The champagne and
    beef tea were continued. By May 6th great improvement was noticed, and, there being no nausea or
    vomiting, the powders were discontinued. The wound was now granulating finely, and the discharge
    consisted of perfectly healthy pus. About June 25th, the patient could leave his bed and sit in
    a chair, the cavity having nearly filled and the wound being healthy and reduced to about half
    the size of the incision. He had perfect use of the ankle joint and the tibialis anticus muscle,
    and there was all probability of a very useful limb. By July 15th, he could bear considerable
    weight on the injured leg. The patient was subsequently transferred to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, where he was discharged from service by special order of the
    War Department, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-10-13">October 13, 1865</date>. In his
    publication¹ of the case <name type="person" key="290">Dr. Leale</name> mentioned <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
     V.</name>, as the operator, and added that he saw the patient again just before he left <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, at which time the limb was in a healthy
    condition and the wound had nearly closed, leaving three small openings, which were prevented
    from closing by the great tension on the newly formed integuments. There was also slight
    contraction of the tendo-achillis, which could be easily overcome, although every possible care
    had been taken to guard against that result. The patient's name was subsequently admitted on the
    Pension Rolls, and afterwards he obtained employment in the <name type="organization" key="xx">New York City Custom House</name>. <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. G. K. Smith</name>, of
     <name type="place" key="xx">Brooklyn</name>, <date type="pension" when="1874-05-11">May 11,
     1874</date>, certified that the patient, <date type="operation" when="1865">after receiving his
     discharge from service</date>, entered Bellevue Hospital, <name type="place">New York
     City</name>, where "<name type="person" key="xx">Professor J. K. Wood</name> performed an
    operation on his leg, cutting the tendo-achillis, and, I think, he also removed a large portion
    of the fractured bone. The wound healed in 1866, but soon broke open again, and continued to
    discharge until the month of <date type="injury" when="1873-06">June, 1873</date>, when it
    finally healed. After leaving Bellevue Hospital he came under my care, and though his health was
    feeble, he performed his duties at the <name type="organization" key="xx">Custom House</name>,
    with occasional loss of time, until the wound healed, in June, 1873. From that date his health
    failed rapidly. His liver began to increase in size, the heart became irregular in its action,
    respiration difficult and circulation very feeble. At length dropsy set in, and he died <date type="death" when="1873-12-01">December 1, 1873</date>. An external examination showed the
    liver to be nearly twice its normal size, and I have no doubt that death was caused by a waxy
    degeneration of the liver, the result of the shot fracture." </p>
   <p>¹ <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>EALE (<hi rend="initialcap">C. A.</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Extensive Necrosis of the Shaft of the Tibia following Gunshot Fracture of the Bone</hi>, in
     <hi rend="italic">United States Sanitary Commission Memoirs</hi>, Surgical Volume I, New York,
    1870, p. 492.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001626.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 267.—A sequestrum, 9½ ins. long, from the right
     tibia. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1489.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
