<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8750">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Gilbert, W. D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8750</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">187-188</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recovery after shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball passed through thigh at junction of middle and lower thirds, comminuting the
      femur</term>
     <term>limb shortened three inches</term>
     <term>ligamentous anchylosis of knee joint</term>
     <term>totally disabled</term>
     <term>limb inflamed, discharging offensive pus</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 382.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. D.
     Gilbert</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 6th Vermont</name>, aged 50 years,
    was wounded in the right thigh at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>. <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-27"
     >Three weeks afterwards</date> he arrived at <name type="place">Alexandria</name> and entered
    the <name type="hospital" key="185">Mansion House Hospital</name>, whence <name type="person"
     key="146">Surgeon C. Page</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, reported
    the injury as a &#34;shot fracture of the middle third of the femur.&#34; Subsequently the
    patient was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="188">Sickels Hospital</name>, and lastly
    to Sloan, <name type="place">Montpelier</name>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H.
     Janes</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter
    hospital, contributed the following history: &#34;The patient, a man of strong constitution, was
    wounded by a mini&#233; ball, which passed through the thigh at the junction of the middle and
    lower thirds, comminuting the femur for several inches. <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-06"
     >The day after the injury</date> he was sent by ambulance to <name type="place"
     >Fredericksburg</name>, no retentive apparatus having been applied, and <date type="transfer"
     when="1864-05-26">two weeks later</date> he was moved by cars and boat to <name type="place"
     >Alexandria</name>, the limb being kept in a fracture-box during the trip. At <name
     type="place">Alexandria</name>, it was put upon an anterior splint and extension was made by
    brick and pulley. <date type="operation" when="1864-06">In June</date> several pieces of bone
    were removed. Suppuration was profuse, and about August 1st his appetite failed and he became so
    much debilitated that his life was despaired of. After this he gradually but slowly improved,
    though not without occasional relapses. On January 1, 1865, the splint was removed and the
    patient allowed to sit at the bedside, and no retentive apparatus was used for more than two or
    three days after that time. About the last of January he could walk about the ward on crutches,
    though unable to bear any weight upon the limb. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-03-17">March
     17th</date> the patient was transferred to this hospital, during which journey the limb became
    considerably inflamed, resulting in his confinement to bed for three days. On <date
     type="operation" when="1865-05-29">May 29th</date> the limb, having again become inflamed and
    discharging very offensive pus, was freely opened for about four inches, and several large
    pieces of necrosed bone, one of which measured one by three inches, were removed. The cavity in
    the callus, which contained these fragments, was found to be large and seemed to extend quite or
    nearly to the cancellated structure of the condyles. After the operation suppuration became
    healthy and the wound mended rapidly for four weeks, when the improvement became checked. On
     <date type="operation" when="1865-09-07">September 7th</date>, the limb was again laid open
    freely and a small piece of bone was removed, after which there was no further interruption in
    the progress of the patient up to <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-10-12">October 12,
     1865</date>, when he was discharged from service. At this time the wound still suppurated to
    the amount of two ounces per day, and a considerable cavity existed between the ends of the
    bone, but no necrosis could be detected by the probe. The limb was shortened three inches, and
    there was ligamentous anchylosis of the knee joint, permitting the patient to move it about ten
    degrees. He was in general good health, able to bear half his weight on the injured leg for a
    short time, and seemed to have a fair prospect of obtaining a useful limb. There had been no
    h&#230;morrhage, gangrene, or diarrh&#339;a since the injury, and his appetite had been good
    nearly all the time, having taken nutritious food freely and stimulants moderately.&#34; <name
     type="person" key="xxx">Examiner W. McCollom</name>, of <name type="place">Woodstock,
     Vermont</name>, <date type="pension" when="1866-11-14">November 14, 1866</date>, certified to
    the injury, and stated: &#34;The bone has united with three inches shortening. Exfoliations are
    thrown off occasionally, and the wound in the soft tissues has not entirely healed. He is
    totally disabled from performing manual labor at present.&#34; <name type="person" key="xxx"
     >Examiner O. W. Sherwin</name> stated, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-04">September 4,
     1873</date>: &#34;There is considerable loss of tissue, and the knee is permanently flexed so
    as to keep the heel two inches from the floor,&#34; and, in <date type="pension" when="1877-09"
     >September, 1877</date>, he reported the following: &#34;During the present year a large
    abscess formed at the seat of the injury, with exfoliation of bone. I attended him during two
    months of confinement in bed from the aforesaid cause.&#34; A card photograph of the patient,
    taken at the Sloan Hospital, was contributed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon
     Janes</name> (<hi rend="italic">Card Photos</hi>, A. M. M., Vol. 2, p. 22), an enlarged copy of
    which, taken at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> (<hi
     rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 130). is represented in the cut (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 150). The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-03-04"
     >March 4, 1879</date>.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001566.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 150.&#8212;Shot fracture of middle third of right femur.
     [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
