<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e12710">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Sailor, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e12710</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">289-290</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of intermediary amputation in the lower third of the femur</term> 
     <term>wounded in leg by conical bullet</term>
     <term>no pulsation in anterior tibial artery</term>
     <term>both tibia and fibula comminuted</term>
     <term>limb amputated in lower third of thigh</term>
     <term>bones comminuted up to head of fibula</term>
     <term>anterior tibial artery divided by bullet, ends separated about one inch</term>
     <term>fatty degeneration of anterior tibial muscles</term>
     <term>bowels confined</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>spleen contained metastatic abscesses</term>
     <term>end of femur in stump necrosed and gangrenous</term>
     <term>purulent infection</term>     
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>   
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 469.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1092">Private W. Sailor</name>, <name type="organization" key="449">Co. E, 119th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 40
     years, was wounded in the left leg by a conical bullet, at <name type="BATTLE" key="15">Rappahannock Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7, 1863</date>.
     <date type="admit" when="1863-11-09">Two days afterwards</date> he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>,
     Washington, whence <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name
      type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, made the following report:  "On examination, it
     was found that the injured leg was much swollen and dark colored on its anterior surface, that
     there was no pulsation in the anterior tibial artery, and that both the tibia and fibula were
     extensively comminuted, with much laceration of the soft parts. His pulse was frequent and
     irritable, and he had a good deal of constitutional disturbance and fever of an irritative
     type.  On <date type="operation" when="1863-11-14">November 14th</date>, the fever had abated, and the general condition much improved; pulse
     fuller and less irritable; appetite better; wound suppurating; discharge thin, dark colored,
     and offensive; leg not improved. There being manifestly no hope of saving, it, the bones being
     broken and the soft parts inflamed nearly up to the knee joint, and comminution very extensive,
     the limb was amputated in the lower third of the thigh. The operation was performed by the
     circular method by <name type="person" key="459">Assistant Surgeon G. A. Mursick</name>, <name
      type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, under sulphuric ether. A dissection of the
     amputated limb showed that the bones were extensively comminuted as high up as the head of the
     fibula. The anterior tibial artery was found to be divided by the bullet a little below where
     it passes through the interosseous membrane, the ends being separated from each other about one
     inch and retracted within the sheath, also closely contracted. The cardiac end was plugged up
     by a firm coagulum about an inch in length. The distal end was also plugged up by a small
     coagulum. The anterior tibial muscles were pale yellow in color, soft and greasy to the touch
     (fatty degeneration). The patient bore the operation well. The stump was dressed with lead
     sutures and adhesive plaster, and a full dose of morphine was administered. He had a good
     night's rest after the operation, and, on the following day, expressed a desire for food, his
     pulse being full, frequent, and quick; bowels confined, for which a dose of rochelle salts was
     ordered.  On November 17th, suppuration commenced, but little of the stump being united by adhesion; general condition good.
     Prescribed moderate stimulation, with whiskey.  18th, edge of posterior flap looked sloughy;
     ordered diluted Labarraque's solution to the stump, and twenty drops of muriated tincture of
     iron every six hours internally.  20th, had a chill in the morning, followed by fever and sweat;
     skin sallow looking; granulations in stump looking well, except on the posterior flap, a small
     portion of which was sloughing. Ordered five grains of quinine every six hours, twenty drops of
     muriated tincture of iron every four hours, and one ounce of whiskey every three hours.  21st,
     had a chill in the afternoon; sallow appearance of skin deepened; pulse irritable; slight subsultus; bowels not moved for two days. Ordered ten grains of aloes and twenty grains of
     rhubarb to be given at once, and continued other treatment.  22d, had chills again in the
     afternoon, with slight delirium. Ordered one-twelfth of a grain of corrosive sublimate, with three grains of iodide of potassa, every four hours, and continued
     the whiskey.  23d, patient vomited in the morning, had also a good deal of fever. Applied
     sinapism to epigastrium.  24th, rigors, etc., in the morning; treatment continued.  25th, rigors, fever, and delirium; skin very yellow.  28th,
     rigors, etc.; urine passed involuntary; bedsores on sacrum. Ordered a water bed.  Patient died,
     exhausted, on <date type="death" when="1863-12-01">December 1, 1863</date>, the seventeenth day
     after the amputation and the eleventh day after the advent of the purulent infection. Autopsy
     twelve hours after death: Rigor mortis well marked; skin yellow; some emaciation; stump swollen
     and &#339;dematous; femoral artery well plugged up in stump; end of femoral vein well sealed up
     in stump; femoral vein empty and collapsed from the end up to the valve at the first
     anastomosing branch, a distance of about six inches; the vein in this situation about as large
     as the artery; the walls of the vein also much thickened, being about as thick as those of the
     artery; the lining membrane looking velvety, wrinkled, and dirty gray in color; no pus in vein.
     From the valve above mentioned up to the mouth of the vena profunda, a distance of about two
     and a half inches, the femoral vein was filled to distension with fetid broken down liquefied
     blood, its lining membrane dirty gray colored in this situation, and its walls somewhat thicker
     than natural; no pus revealed in this locality by the microscope. At the mouth of the vena
     profunda the femoral vein was plugged up with yellowish white<choice><orig>fibrine</orig><reg>fibrin</reg></choice>; vena profunda and many
     of its branches filled and knotted with recent coagulum; femoral vein also filled with recent
     coagulum above the mouth of the profunda to a distance of about two and a half inches; the
     lining membrane of the profunda and part of the femoral vein last mentioned stained dark red,
     and the walls of the vessels somewhat thickened in same locality. A thin dark colored recent
     coagulum, not filling the calibre of the vein, extended the whole length of the external iliac.
     The end of the femur in the stump (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 2, <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XLIII</hi>, opposite) was necrosed to the extent of nearly half an inch, and here the
     periosteum was thickened, varying from a line to one-third of an inch, detached and gangrenous;
     underlying bone white in color; medullary membrane at end of bone gangrenous and dirty grayish
     green in color to the depth of about one-third of an inch; medullary membrane elsewhere more
     vascular than natural, which was well shown by splitting the bone lengthwise with a saw (<hi
      rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 1 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XLIII</hi>, opposite). Three or
     four small superficial abscesses were formed about the right extremity of the spleen; the rest
     of that organ was contracted and indurated. Five or six small superficial abscesses were
     discovered in the lungs, the pulmonary tissue surrounding each of them being consolidated by inflammatory action. The other organs were natural, and the blood did not exhibit
     any abnormity." The femoral artery (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1887) and the femoral vein
      (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1888), together with three inches of bone from the stump (<hi
      rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 1890), and the section of the spleen containing the metastatic
     abscesses (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1889, shown in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 3, <hi
      rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XLIII</hi>, opposite), were contributed to <name type="hospital"
       key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="70">Dr. Lidell</name>.</p>
    
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001815.001" />
    <head>PLATE  XLIII. __ RESULT  OF  OSTEOMYELITIS.     Figs. 1, 2, 3.  Dr. Lidell's Case of Pt. W. Sailor,  Specs. 1889 _ 1890.  A. M. M.</head>
   </figure> 
    
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
