<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31627">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Mallet, J. E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31627</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="jl">James Largen</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">90-91</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>ball entered left of umbilicus, exited to right of spinal column</term>
       <term>missile entered left side, took downward course, tore intestines in its course, lodged against marrow of right thigh-bone</term>
       <term>fancied sparks of fire, curtains of cobwebs wet with dew, sparkling in sun, roar of cataracts</term>
       <term>teeth chattered, blood rushed to eyes, ears, nose, and ends of fingers and toes</term>
       <term>severe colic</term>
       <term>fasting forty-eight hours before wound</term>
       <term>destruction of wall of descending colon</term>
       <term>spinous process of vertebra fractured</term>
       <term>f&#230;cal discharge from wound</term>
       <term>missile entered left side</term>
       <term>large button driven in by ball</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#jl" when="2011-02-20">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 275.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant J. E. Mallet, Adjutant</name> <name type="organization" key="xxx">81st New York</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date when="1864-06-03">June 3, 1864</date>, by a musket ball, which entered three inches to the left of the umbilicus and made its exit a little to the right of the spinal column. The direction of the ball is indicated in the accompanying wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 57), engraved from a photograph on the wood block made at <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> several years ago. <name type="person" key="xxx">This officer</name>, who still survives and holds an important civil office under <name type="organization" key="xxx">the Government</name>, has kindly prepared an account of his case, which is peculiarly valuable because of the rarity with which reliable information of the immediate symptoms produced by severe wounds can be obtained. The authenticity of the facts is unquestionable, and, independently of the officer's own statement, is affirmed by the testimony of the medical attendants: "I was wounded," says this brave officer, "at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, while serving as adjutant of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">81st New York Infantry</name>, or <name type="organization" key="xxx">2d Oswego Regiment</name>, then with the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Army of the Potomac</name>, and attached to the<name type="organization" key="xxx"> first (<name type="person" key="xxx">Marston</name>'s) brigade</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">first (<name type="person" key="xxx">Brooks</name>'s) division</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Eighteenth (<name type="person" key="xxx">Smith</name>'s) Army Corps</name>.  It was at about five o' clock in the morning, and in the assault on the enemy's entrenched lines, I was struck. I fell at the distance of about fifteen paces from the works which our men were charging with uncapped pieces. The missile entered my left side. I distinctly remember the sensations experienced upon being hit. I imagined that a cannon-ball had struck me on the left hip-bone, that it took a downward course, tearing the intestines in its course, and lodged against the marrow of the right thigh-bone. I fancied I saw sparks of fire, and curtains of cobwebs wet with dew, sparkling in the sun. I heard a monotonous roar as of distant cataracts. I felt my teeth chatter, a rush of blood to my eyes, ears, nose, and to the ends of my fingers and toes. These sensations crowded themselves in the instants in which I struggled to stand, and actually fell forward on my face. As I fell, I experienced another sensation as of a sudden and violent blow on the nape of the neck, and then became completely insensible. I was awakened to consciousness by cheering, and fearing to be trampled by the advancing lines, I made a desperate effort to regain my feet; and, doubled up as one with a broken back, with my sword strapped to my right wrist, and the scabbard in the other hand, I dragged myself about forty paces to the right and rear, and entered the skirt of a wood, where I saw men hiding behind trees, which angered me, and I again fell insensible. Later, I remember being put on a stretcher by some men of a Massachusetts regiment, and carried some distance to an ambulance. During the day, some one had given me a piece of sponge cake dipped in wine; but it was at once rejected. It rained during the day, and some one covered me with a rubber blanket, which a passer-by presently carried off, and I had the will but not the power to protest. The pain in the wound in the back was intense. I do not recollect distinctly my arrival at the corps hospital; but I recall the visit of <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon W. H. Rice</name>, and his exploration of my wound, and his instructions to a friend to take my watch and valuables, and my inference that he considered my case hopeless, and that these mementoes were to be sent home.  On the afternoon of June 3d, I was put in an ambulance wagon with <name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant McKinney</name>, and taken as far as <name type="place">Bethesda Church</name>, where we stopped over night. We proceeded on our journey next morning, over very rugged ground. I remember the wounded who could walk, often put their shoulders to the wagon to keep it from upsetting. We arrived at <name type="place">White House Landing</name>, on the <name type="place">York River</name>, late on the afternoon of June 4th. I had suffered much pain from shortness of breath, but was relieved by draughts of water. I was put on a hospital transport, and was laid by the side of the deck, where the breeze could reach me; but it seemed to take away my breath instead of restoring it. I was very faint, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Captain Tyler</name>, of <name type="organization" key="xxx">my regiment</name>, and others, have since told me that I was regarded as a dead man.  I remember nothing further until we reached <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, and finally <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where I asked to be taken to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>; but nearly all the wounded were carried off in ambulance wagons, and I thought I was deserted; but finally they brought a stretcher and carried me to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square</name>, which was nearer the steamboat wharf. I was placed in Ward 1 about midnight. On the morning of <date type="admit" when="1864-06-06">June 6th</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Medical Inspector Coolidge</name> examined me. From memoranda, made soon afterward, I find that I was frequently unconscious during the next week; but that, on June 12th, I could read the leaded headings of newspapers.  On June 15th, I had a distressing pain in the bowels. Gradually my vision improved, and, on June 22d, I began to keep my diary.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Bowen</name> was attending me.  On June 27th, I ate some blackberries, which made me sick, and for the next two days I was feverish and drowsy.  On July 1st, I had severe colic.  On July 3d, <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon Bliss</name> examined me.  On the 5th, I was better, and asked to be sent home.  On July 6th, I sat up in an arm-chair.  On the 12th, some blackberry seeds were found in the lint removed from the wound in the side. On July 17th, I drank a glass of soda-water, which, in about fifteen minutes, began to bubble out at the orifice in the side, forcing off the adhesive plaster and compresses, and soiling my clothing with a copious foetid discharge of a yellowish color.  On <date type="transfer" when="1864-07-27">July 27th</date>, I was taken on a stretcher to the cars, and rode to <name type="place">New York</name>, and thence on a steamer to <name type="place">Albany</name>, and thence by rail to <name type="place">Oswego</name>, where I arrived on the 29th, and was attended by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. C. P. P. Clark</name>, of <name type="place">Fort Ontario</name>. My hospital diet nearly starved me, and I suffered greatly during the dressings. Pieces of shirt and trousers and braces were extracted from the wounds at different times. There was a swelling below the wound, which was very sensitive. Some of the surgeons thought it contained the ball; others that a fragment of the eleventh rib was lodged there.  On August 13th, I walked for the first time.  On August 26th, there was so much pain in the swelling referred to that a surgical consultation was held, and, on <date type="operation" when="1864-08-28">the 28th</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Clark</name> incised the swelling and removed a large button that had been driven in by the ball.  On <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-01">October 1st</date>, I reported at the hospital at <name type="place">Annapolis</name>, and on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-10-31">October 31, 1864</date>, was honorably discharged for wounds received in action, on the recommendation of <name type="organization" key="xxx">the board</name> of which <name type="person" key="xxx">General Graham</name> was president. In 1865 my health improved, so that I was able to do clerical duty, and from that time to this (1873) my health has been comparatively good. I am nevertheless subject to pain in the spine at damp seasons. My left side and arm are weak, and, in walking a considerable distance, my left leg becomes lame. It may be proper to add that at the time of receiving the wound I had been fasting for nearly forty-eight hours."  The principal facts above recited in a connected form, appear, separately, in the reports of <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeons W. H. Rice</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">81st New York</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">H. P. Porter</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">10th Connecticut</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. H. Bowen</name>, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon B. A. Vanderkieft</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>  <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Bowen</name> remarks that the evidence of extensive destruction of the wall of the descending colon was conclusive, and that a spinous process of a vertebra was probably fractured. The evidence of the intestinal lesion consisted in a copious f&#230;cal discharge from the wound, which persisted for several weeks, while the patient was at <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square</name>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Mallet</name> received the brevet of Major of <name type="organization" key="132">United States Volunteers</name> for gallantry.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001562.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 57.&#8212;Cicatrices in a case of shot perforation of the descending colon.    [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>   
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
