<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e19287">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Cavanaugh, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e19287</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">492</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the lower third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>successful primary amputations in the lower third of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shell caused fracture of lower portion of leg, involving ankle joint</term>
     <term>amputation of leg at lower third</term>
     <term>injured leg amputated at field hospital</term>
     <term>abscesses formed in middle third of tibia, left fistulous openings, indicating necrosis
      of shaft of tibia</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>reamputation below tubercle of tibia</term>
     <term>received artificial limb</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>

   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 742.—<name type="person" key="1285">Private J.
     Cavanaugh</name>, <name type="organization" key="229">Co. C, 7th Wisconsin</name>, aged 27
    years, was wounded before <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-18">June 18, 1864</date>, by a shell, which caused a fracture of the lower
    portion of the left leg, involving the ankle joint. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon C. N.
     Chamberlain</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported that the
    injured leg was amputated at the field hospital of the 4th division, Fifth Corps. <name type="person" key="405">Surgeon B. B. Wilson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
     V.</name>, contributed the pathological specimen, No. 1526, <hi rend="italic">Surg. Sect.</hi>,
    A. M. M., shown in the adjoining wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 291), and reported
    the following history of the case: "The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, from <name type="place">City Point</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-07-01">July 1st</date>. He had suffered amputation of the leg at the
    lower third, by the circular method, <date type="operation" when="1864-06-19">the day after he
     was wounded</date>, being, according to his statement, in a high fever at the time of the
    operation. He was treated with stimulants, and ice dressings locally. During the month of
    September the limb became much swollen and abscesses formed in the line of the middle third of
    the bone, which, after discharging, left fistulous openings, clearly indicating necrosis of the
    shaft of the tibia. His term of service having expired, the patient was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-10-05">October 5, 1864</date>, but being unable to leave, he
    was retained as a patient in the hospital. The shaft of the tibia being evidently extensively
    necrosed, I determined to perform another amputation above the diseased portion. This
    operation—though opposed by the medical staff of this hospital and by <name type="person" key="1224">Surgeon A. N. Dougherty</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
    as well as <name type="person" key="1286">Surgeon T. F. Betton</name>, <name type="organization" key="495">1st U. S. V. V.</name>, who saw the case—was preferred by me to that of <choice>
     <orig>exsecting</orig>
     <reg>excising</reg>
    </choice> the sequestrum for the reason that it involved no more danger and would give the
    patient a much better stump (though six inches shorter) for fitting an artificial limb. The
    operation was performed one inch below the tubercle of the tibia, by the circular method, on
     <date type="operation" when="1865-02-25">February 25, 1865</date>, and the stump was treated
    with cold-water dressings. Traumatic erysipelas followed (an epidemic of erysipelas breaking out
    in the hospital the same week), and for a few days fears were apprehended as to the result. The
    patient, however, made a good recovery, and by March 15th the inflammation, which had extended
    to the abdomen, had subsided. Before he finally left the hospital the patient received an
    artificial limb, on which he walked with great ease and comfort. The specimen indicates clearly
    and in a marked degree the efforts of nature in throwing off dead bone and supplying its place
    by new growth. The adventitious process, thrown out to unite the amputated ends of the tibia and
    fibula and thus give the extremities of those two bones firmness and solidity, shows to how
    great an extent the reparative process can be carried. By what agency the want of bony matter at
    this point was perceived and its deposit determined at the proper place and in the proper form
    is beyond the scope of human knowledge at the present time. The fact, however, evidences the
    powers of nature to accommodate herself to circumstances and to repair in a limited degree the
    effects of losses which are irremediable." The specimen, consisting of the re-amputated stumps
    of the bones of the leg joined by osseous deposit at their lower extremities, shows a massive
    involucrum except on the anterior border, where a heavy sequestrum is visible. The patient
    became a pensioner after leaving the hospital. On <date type="pension" when="1874-09-02">September 2, 1874</date>, he was examined by <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. C.
     F.Falley</name>, pension examiner at <name type="place">Lancaster, Wisconsin</name>, who
    certified to the loss of the leg and reported: "The amputation has left rather an irritable
    stump, but, as his cork leg does not press on it, I do not think it any great injury in wearing
    an artificial limb. He can flex and extend the stump freely," etc. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-03-04">March 4, 1880</date>. In his application for an artificial leg
    he reported that <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon D. C. Ayres</name>, <name type="organization" key="229">7th Wisconsin</name>, performed the first amputation. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001637.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 291—Six ins. of the stump of the bones of the left
     leg, showing a massive involucrum. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1526.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
