<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e17241">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Coats, J. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e17241</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">429</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the tibia and fibula</term> 
     <term>shot contusions of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recoveries after shot contusions of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>injury of tibia</term> 
     <term>shell struck shoe without injury, then struck tibia antero-internally in lower third</term> 
     <term>an&#230;mia</term>
     <term>periostitis</term>
     <term>anchylosis of ankle joint</term>
     <term>injured bone necrosed</term>
     <term>wound abscesses</term>
     <term></term>
     <term></term>
     <term></term>
     <term></term>
     <term></term>
     <term></term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 659.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1226">Private J. C.
      Coats</name>, <name type="organization" key="488">Co. I, 5th Vermont</name>, aged 22 years,
     was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. He was conveyed to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, and transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Satterlee, Philadelphia</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-23">December 23d</date>.  <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. W. Keen, <choice><orig>jr.</orig><reg>Jr.</reg></choice></name>, from the latter
     hospital, described the wound as " an injury of the right tibia," and reported: "The man had
     been hit by a fragment of a shell, which struck his left shoe without seriously injuring the
     foot; it then glanced and struck the right tibia antero-internally in the lower third. <date type="operation" when="1862-12-23">On
     admission to the hospital</date> there was a swelling, fluctuating but quite tense, at the point of
     the injury in the leg, which I opened by an incision about three-fourths of an inch long. About
     an ounce and a half of coagulated blood and some pus was evacuated, and poultices were ordered
     to be applied. The wound did well till January 1, 1863, when it began to enlarge and look very
     much like hospital gangrene. I suspected this the more from the prevalence of this disease at
     that time in the ward. The edges of the wound had become everted, its base rather ashy grey,
     and the discharge unhealthy, and a considerable circle of inflammation was around the opening.
     But the characteristic stinging pain being absent, I determined not to treat it as hospital
     gangrene but by the ordinary measures for inflammation. I ordered three compound cathartic
     pills to be taken and tincture of iodine to be applied locally, also a large poultice. On January 6th, the wound had increased to two and one-fourth inches in diameter, but was still
     entirely without the peculiar pain of hospital gangrene, when I ordered a mixture, consisting
     of half an ounce of hydrochloric acid, two ounces of laudanum, and one pint of water, to be
     used locally with lint. The acid wash was gradually diluted, and finally abandoned on January
     25th. The patient being rather an&#230;mic, I ordered two grains of quinine and four ounces of
     milk punch to be given daily.  On <date type="operation" when="1863-01-30">January 30th</date> another abscess was opened, and on <date type="operation" when="1863-02-09">February 9th</date> yet another, each being preceded
     by severe pain, tenderness, and swelling. No doubt they as well as the original one were the
     result of severe local periostitis. They were readily subdued by cathartics and poultices, with
     morphia at night. No bone was at any time discharged, although considerable depression existed
     on the tibia from absorption of the tissue. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-02-20">February
      20th</date>, the patient was transferred to <name type="place" key="xx">Brattleboro'</name>, the wound having almost entirely healed and there being but little
     depression." The man entered the Marine Hospital at <name type="place" key="xx">Burlington</name>, and on <date type="duty" when="1864-03-08">March 8, 1864</date>, was assigned to the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve Corps</name>, and discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-13">July 13, 1865</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xx">Examining Surgeon A. P. Belden</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Whitehall, N. Y.</name>,
     reported the wound as being in an inflamed condition, and added that "it opens at any time the
     limb is much used in standing or walking. There is adhesion of the <hi rend="italic">peroneus longus muscle</hi> and
     ligament, and inflammation produced partial anchylosis of the ankle joint." <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner J. Lambert</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Salem, N. Y.</name>, <date type="pension" when="1878-08-10">August
     10, 1878</date>, reported that "the injured bone is necrosed for about three inches and demands an
     operation." The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-09-04">September 4, 1880</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
