<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e7113">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Francis, Lewis</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e7113</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">154</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the hip joint</term>
     <term>coxo-femoral amputations</term>
     <term>reamputation at the hip joint</term>
     <term>exarticulations at the hip for diseased conditions succeeding previous amputations</term>
     <term>injury from bayonet stab in knee instead of shot injury</term>
     <term>bayonet thrust opened knee joint</term>
     <term>wound of testis, testis removed</term>
     <term>disease of knee with abscesses in thigh</term>
     <term>necrosis of femur</term>
     <term>disease of innominatum, pus from fistulous orifices</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-28">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 331.&#8212;<name type="person" key="977">Private Lewis
     Francis</name>, <name type="organization" key="147">Co. I, 14th New York Militia</name>, aged
    42 years, was wounded <date type="injury" when="1861-07-21">July 21, 1861</date>, at the first
    battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="6">Bull Run</name>, by a bayonet thrust, which opened the
    right knee joint. He received not less than fourteen other stabs in different parts of the body,
    none of them implicating the great cavities. He was taken prisoner, and conveyed to Richmond and
    placed in hospital. One of his wounds involved the left testis, which was removed on <date
     type="operation" when="1861-07-24">July 24th</date>. On <date type="operation"
     when="1861-10-28">October 28, 1861</date>, his right thigh was amputated at the middle, on
    account of disease of the knee with abscesses in the thigh. The double-flap method was employed.
    The stump became inflamed and the femur protruded. An inch of the bone was resected and the
    flaps were again brought together. In the spring of <date type="transfer" when="1862"
     >1862</date> the patient was exchanged and sent to <name type="place">Fort Monroe</name>. <date
     type="transfer" when="1862">Thence</date> he was transferred to a <name type="place"
     key="#Washington">Washington</name> hospital, and thence, in <date type="hospitaldischarge"
     when="1862-03">March, 1862</date>, to his home in <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>. There was
    necrosis of the femur, and in <date type="operation" when="1862-05">May, 1862</date>, its
    extremity was again resected by a civil surgeon. On <date type="admit" when="1863-10-28">October
     28, 1863</date>, <name type="person" key="977">Francis</name> was admitted to the Ladies Home
    Hospital, <name type="place">New York</name>. Necrosis had apparently involved the remaining
    portion of the femur. On <date type="operation" when="1864-05-21">May 21, 1864</date>, <name
     type="person" key="1441">Surgeon A. B. Mott</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
     V.</name>, laid open the flaps and exarticulated the bone. The patient recovered rapidly and
    had a sound stump. He was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-08-12">August 12,
     1864</date>. On October 1, 1865, a photograph, from which the accompanying wood-cut (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 113) was taken, was forwarded by <name type="person" key="1441"
     >Surgeon A. B. Mott</name> to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>.
     <name type="person" key="1441">Dr. Mott</name> reported that the pathological specimen of the
    exarticulated femur was stolen from his hospital. For some months after his discharge <name
     type="person" key="977">Francis</name> enjoyed good health; but then the cicatrix became
    unhealthy, pus was discharged through several sinuses, and there was bleeding from the slightest
    irritation. In <date type="pension" when="1867-03">March, 1867</date>, a messenger was sent to
    his residence, 54 Hamilton Street, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, and found him in very
    poor health. He had been unable to leave the house since November, 1866. On <date type="pension"
     when="1867-04-12">April 12, 1867</date>, he was visited by <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. E.
     D. Hudson</name>, who reported him as then confined to his bed. There was a large ulcer at the
    upper outer angle of the cicatrix, which communicated with extensive sinuses; there was a
    fistula-in-ano also. The pus from the different fistulous orifices was thin, oily, and ichorous.
    There could be little doubt that there was disease of some portion of the innominatum. The
    patient was much emaciated, and had a cough with muco-purulent expectoration. His pulse,
    however, was not frequent, and he had a good appetite. In <date type="pension" when="1867-05"
     >May, 1867</date>, it was reported that his general condition had somewhat improved. In <date
     type="pension" when="1868-03">March, 1868</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">Pension Examiner
     J. C. Burdick</name>, of <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, reported that this pensioner was
    &#34;permanently helpless and required the constant aid of a nurse.&#34; On May 30, 1874
    (Decoration Day), and the day prior, at a preparatory parade of the veterans of his regiment, he
    was particularly active. The day after this unusual exercise, <date type="death"
     when="1874-05-31">May 31, 1874</date>, he died suddenly while at table.&#178; This statement
    from the <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>
    <hi rend="italic">Union</hi>, June 1, 1874, is corroborated by the records of the <name
     type="organization" key="xx">Pension Bureau</name>. </p>

   <p> &#178; <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 49. <hi rend="italic"
     >Circular</hi> No. 7, 1867, pp. 52, 65. <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>AMILTON (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">Treatise on
     Military Surgery</hi>, 1865, p. 629.</p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001555.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 113.&#8212;Cicatrix sixteen months after a reamputation at the
     right hip, succeeding amputation for a bayonet stab through the knee.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
