<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30618">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wistar, Isaac J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e30618</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="nk">Nathan Kumm</persName>  
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">831</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow treated on the expectant plan</term>
       <term>twice severely wounded, then disabled by third wound</term>
       <term>shot flesh wounds of thigh and of neck</term> 
       <term>third wound shot fracture of elbow</term>
       <term>recovered with anchylosed joint</term>
       <term>shot perforation of arm near elbow, not implicating bone</term> 
       <term>ball shattered external condyle of humerus and head of radius, chipped olecranon passing out</term>
       <term>elbow firmly anchylosed at right angle</term>
       <term>pain became constant, at times intense</term> 
       <term>pain of neuralgic character extended over whole arm and forearm</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#nk" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1742.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant-Colonel Isaac J. Wistar</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">71st Pennsylvania</name>, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Ball's Bluff</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-10-21">October 21, 1861</date>.  In his <hi rend="italic">History of Pennsylvania Volunteers</hi>, 1870, Vol. III, page 790, <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Samuel P. Bates</name> reports that:  "<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant-Colonel Wistar</name> was twice severely wounded, but kept his place until he was completely disabled by a third wound." The first two injuries
    were shot flesh wounds of the thigh and of the neck, the third a shot fracture of the right elbow. The case is referred to by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon A. B. Crosby</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> (<hi rend="italic">Appendix to First Part Med. and Surg. Hist. of the War</hi>, p. 11), in his report of the wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Ball's Bluff</name>, and by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, in the same volume of documents, p. 13.  There was little inflammatory reaction for a fortnight, but grave trouble ensued. However, the patient recovered with an anchylosed joint,, and, in <date type="duty" when="1862-08">August, 1862</date>,
    returned to duty as colonel.  At <name type="BATTLE" key="33">Antietam</name> he received a shot perforation of the left arm, near the elbow, but not implicating the
    bone. (See Bates, <hi rend="italic">l. c.</hi>, p. 794.)  Promoted to be brigadier-general, <date type="promotion" when="1862-11-29">November 29, 1862</date>, this officer served until honorably
    mustered out, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-09-15">September 15, 1864</date>. In <date type="pension" when="1875-11">November, 1875</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. George C. Harlan</name>, of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, had the kindness to make the following notes of the injury to the right elbow:  "The ball seems to have shattered the external condyle of the right humerus
    and the head of the radius, and to have chipped the olecranon in passing out. There was no resection, but the wound was
    opened <date type="operation" when="1861-11">about three weeks after the injury</date> and some pieces of bone were extracted.  <hi rend="italic">Present condition</hi>:  The wounds of entrance
    and of exit are united by a broad cicatrix. The elbow is firmly anchylosed at a right angle. The forearm is well developed.
    The hand is in excellent position and its functions are perfect except that slight limitation of flexion interferes with the handling
    of small objects. The other elbow is in good condition, never having received any injury, but there is an adherent cicatrix on
    the inner side of the arm, at about its middle, and some numbness of the little, ring, and middle fingers of the left hand. There
    was occasional pain in the right elbow for two years, after which it became constant, and was at times very intense. There were
    no signs of inflammatory action in the joint—the pain was of a neuralgic character, and extended over the whole arm and forearm. 
    This lasted about two years, when it gradually subsided, and, of late, the General has suffered only occasionally and slightly"  This officer's name is borne on the Pension List as last paid <date type="pension" when="1875-06-04">June 4, 1875</date>.</p>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
