<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41875">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Stearnes, George W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41875</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">300-301</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>acute diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in acute diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>morbid anatomy</term>
     <term>lesions observed in the small intestine</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>lobular pneumonia in lower lobes of both lungs</term>
     <term>evidence of bronchitis</term>
     <term>small intestine inflammation increased toward the ileo-c&#230;cal valve, agminated glands
      thickened and dark-red with inflammation, solitary glands enlarged</term>
     <term>large intestine streaked and spotted with ash-color and dark-red, also spots of
      ecchymosis</term>
     <term>valvuli conniventes and hypertrophy of the villi in ileum</term>
     <term>in ileum solitary follicles enlarged and projected above surface of mucous
      membrane</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-28">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and
    encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>A case of diarrh&#339;a of nearly two months duration:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 880.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal George W.
     Stearnes</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company I, 9th New Hampshire
     volunteers</name>, was mustered into service <date type="enlist" when="1862-08-15">August 15,
     1862</date>, to serve three years. There is no record of the time at which he was first taken
    sick; but he appears on the register of the general field hospital of the 9th Corps, near <name
     type="place">Harper's Ferry, Virginia</name>, as under treatment for diarrh&#339;a <date
     type="admit" when="1862-11-05">November 5th</date>; sent to <name type="place"
     key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>
    <date type="transfer" when="1862-11-12">November 12th</date>. He is borne on the register of the
    convalescent hospital at Fort Ellsworth, near <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria,
     Virginia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1862-11-16">November 16th</date>, general
    debility; no disposition recorded. The register of <name type="hospital" key="214">Fairfax
     Seminary Hospital</name>, near Alexandria, Virginia, shows that he was admitted to that
    hospital <date type="admit" when="1862-12-08">December 8th</date>&#8212;chronic
    diarrh&#339;a&#8212;transferred to Philadelphia, <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-15"
     >December 15th</date>. He is borne on the register of the <name type="hospital" key="xxx"
     >Satterlee hospital, West Philadelphia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1862-12-16"
     >December 16th</date>&#8212;chronic diarrh&#339;a. December 23d, papers were made out for his
    discharge from service by reason of &#34;great debility and emaciation, the result of chronic
    diarrh&#339;a, which is still unchecked.&#34; Pending the approval of these papers by the proper
    authority, he died, <date type="death" when="1862-12-24">December 24th</date>, at 5 A. M. From
    the circumstance that his discharge papers were made out the day before his death it is to be
    presumed the fatal issue was unexpected. The autopsy was made <date type="autopsy"
     when="1862-12-24">during the afternoon of the same day</date> by <name type="person" key="xxx"
     >Professor Joseph Leidy</name>, of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">University of
     Pennsylvania</name>, who forwarded the following statement to the <name type="organization"
     key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> with the specimens: <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi>
    Age about 30. The body was rather emaciated. The chest and abdomen presented a number of faint
    spots of purpura. The brain was healthy. There were no pleuritic attachments, nor was there any
    pleurisy on either side. Lobular pneumonia was observed in the lower lobes of both lungs; the
    inflamed lobules were numerous&#8212;varied from the size of a marble to that of a
    walnut&#8212;and were in the stage of gray hepatization. Evidences of bronchitis were also
    observed. The heart was healthy. The stomach was exceedingly contracted. The liver was
    apparently sound; the gall-bladder enormously distended with green bile; the spleen small but
    healthy; the pancreas and kidneys sound. The intestines were inflamed throughout; in the small
    intestine the inflammation increased in intensity toward the ileo-c&#230;cal valve; the
    agminated glands were slightly thickened and dark-red with inflammation; the solitary glands
    were enlarged, and looked like yellow mustard seeds sprinkled on a red ground. The large
    intestine was streaked and spotted with ash-color and dark-red on a nearly uniform red ground;
    there were also spots of ecchymosis, and the epithelium was softened.</p>
   <p>Nos. 93 to 98, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>,
    are from this case. The specimens are six successive portions of the ileum. In Nos. 93 and 94
    there are well-marked valvuli conniventes, and some hypertrophy of the villi, giving a velvety
    appearance to the surface. The solitary follicles are enlarged to the size of small pin-heads
    and project above the surface of the mucous membrane. In No. 94 there is a small Peyer's patch,
    which is a little more distinct than normal. In Nos. 95 to 98 there are no valvuli conniventes,
    no hypertrophy of the villi is observable, and the intestinal walls are thinner than normal.
    Each of these pieces presents a number of enlarged solitary follicles, which are most
    conspicuous in No. 98. In both 97 and 98 there is a slightly-thickened Peyer's patch. No portion
    of the large intestine was preserved.</p>
   <p>The plate facing this page is a reproduction of a photograph of No. 98, which represents it of
    the natural size. This piece was taken from near the ileo-c&#230;cal valve. Just above its
    middle is a thickened Peyer's patch, which appears as a dark elliptical spot two inches long by
    an inch in transverse diameter near its middle. This is crossed obliquely from above downwards
    by a wrinkle in the mucous membrane, produced accidentally by the method of preparing the
    specimen. The surface of the patch is not materially elevated above the surface of the
    surrounding mucous membrane, yet it is thicker than normal, and, when examined by transmitted
    light, appears more opaque than any of the other patches observed in this subject. The enlarged
    solitary follicles are scattered over the rest of the mucous surface as little pimple-like
    projecting tumors, which are largest and most numerous in the lower half of the piece; the
    largest of them, however, do not exceed pin-heads in size. Owing to the tenuity of the mucous
    membrane, the course of the circular fibres of the muscular coat is plainly indicated by
    numerous transverse lines. For the same reason the arborescent branching of the blood-vessels is
    also indicated in several places.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001500.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE IV. ILEUM WITH ENLARGED SOLITARY FOLLICLES. No. 98.
     MEDICAL SECTION.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
