<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41119">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Clark, Kinkin</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41119</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">173</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>       
       <term>ileoc&#230;cal valve seat of irregular shallow ulceration</term>
       <term>c&#230;cum intensely congested, solitary glands conspicuous and whitish</term>
       <term>small intestine stone-blue color, increased in intensity toward ileoc&#230;cal valve</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 378.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Kinkin Clark</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company C, 44th North Carolina volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-10-20">October 20, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-10-24">October 24th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-10-25">twenty-two hours</date> after death: Apparent age 45; height five feet nine inches; rigor mortis slight; body not much emaciated. The brain was firm, and weighed fifty-one ounces and a half; there was but little fluid in the ventricles. The mucous membrane of the trachea was irregularly purplish in spots, between which it was pale. The lungs were engorged with venous blood, but crepitant throughout; the right lung weighed fifteen ounces and a half, the left fourteen ounces. The pericardium contained nine drachms of fluid. The heart was normal, and contained no clots except a very small one in the right ventricle. The liver weighed seventy ounces and a half; its substance was normal in color and consistence, except at the left extremity of the left lobe, where it was firmer than elsewhere, coated by old exudations, and attached to the spleen; the gall-bladder contained six drachms of bile resembling coffee-grounds. The spleen was firm and weighed twenty-three ounces; it was of a pale grayish-blue externally, and of a dark-mulberry color internally; it was firmly agglutinated to the liver; the adhesion was extremely thick, and cut like cartilage. The pancreas was of normal consistence, and weighed four ounces. The kidneys were large; the right measured five inches by two and a half, and weighed seven ounces and a half; the left measured five inches by three, and weighed eight ounces; the cortical substance of both was pale but injected, the section appearing as if sprinkled with red pepper; the bases of the pyramids were of a very dark-purple color, the capsules readily elevated, the pelves highly injected. The mucous membrane of the small intestine was softened and of a stone-blue color, which increased in intensity toward the ileoc&#230;cal valve; the agminated glands were not elevated or thickened, but presented a few ulcers which varied from the size of a mustard-seed to that of a split-pea; the solitary glands were prominent, but not ulcerated. The ileoc&#230;cal valve was the seat of an irregular shallow ulceration. The c&#230;cum was intensely congested, its solitary glands conspicuous and whitish; the mucous membrane of the rest of the large intestine was softened and of a pale yellowish-slate color.&#8212;<name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>&#8432;</p>
   <p>&#8432; September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief &#34;<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>,&#34; to which the reader is referred.&#8212;(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
