<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19420">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">B——, S.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e19420</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">490</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
          <term>penetrating gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the ribs</term>
          <term>pleuro-pneumonia resulted in empyema</term>
          <term>eleventh and twelfth ribs fractured</term>
          <term>ball entered chest posteriorly over the attachment of eleventh rib, passed
            forward</term>
          <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-20">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private S.
        B——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. A, 83d New York</name>, having been
        wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th, 1862</date>, was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, on <date type="admit" when="1862-12-23">December 23d, 1862</date>. A conoidal musket ball had entered the right chest
        posteriorly, over the attachment of the eleventh rib, and passed forward. The missile was
        extracted on <date type="operation" when="1862-12-26">the 26th</date>, and simple dressings
        were applied. Pleuro-pneumonia ensued, and resulted in empyema. On <date type="operation" when="1863-01-03">January 3d, 1863</date>, a pint of pus was evacuated from the pleural
        cavity. The case terminated fatally on <date type="death" when="1863-01-21">January 21st,
          1863</date>. Nine hours subsequently a <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination was
        performed by <name type="person">Assistant Surgeon G. M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>
        <hi rend="italic">Rigor mortis</hi> was well marked. The brain weighed forty-five ounces and
        two drachms. A healthy fluid was found in the lateral ventricles. The bronchial glands were
        enlarged. The right lung was compressed and crowded into the superior, posterior, and
        internal part of its chamber. It was adherent to the costal parieties by fibrinous bands.
        Anteriorly, inferiorly, and externally, occupying the cavity left by the retreating lung,
        was found a collection of pus, between the two walls of pleura, measuring one pint and a
        half. This cavity was lined by a thick membrane presenting internally a mucoid appearance.
        The left lung showed gray hepatization in the upper and posterior portions, the inferior and
        anterior being congested, and thick, tenacious bronchial secretion exuded from the bronchial
        tubes. Anteriorly, this lung was firmly adherent to the pericardium. The right lung weighed
        fourteen, the left twenty-six ounces. The pericardium was filled with two ounces of
        yellowish fluid. The heart, with the pericardium, weighed ten and a half ounces. Firm
        fibrinated clots existed in both auricles, continuous within the auriculo-ventricular
        openings, and a black clot was found in the left ventricle and aorta. The liver, weighing
        sixty-four ounces, was "nutmegged." Each kidney weighed five and a half ounces. The
        spleen was firm, and weighed seven and a half ounces. The pancreas weighed four ounces. The
        greater omentum extended a short distance below the umbilicus; the intestines were much
        inflated; the lymphatics of the lumbar region and the mesenteric glands were enlarged. The
        stomach and duodenum were normal; patches of congestion were scattered through the jejunum
        and ileum; the mucous membrane of the small intestine was softened; the walls of the large
        intestine were thickened. Portions of the eleventh and twelfth ribs of the right side,
        completely fractured and surrounded at the points of solution with large irregular
        formations of callus, were contributed to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
          Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="131">Surgeon H. Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, and the particulars of the autopsy were
        furnished by <name type="person" key="243">Assistant Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> The specimens are figured in the
        accompanying wood-cuts (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGS. 232 and 233), on a much reduced
        scale, the cut used in <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> 6, and in the <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, being utilized. </p>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001468.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 232.—Right lung collapsed after gunshot wound. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 846, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001469.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 233.—Attempted repair after gunshot fracture of
        floating ribs. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 845, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
