<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7334">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Ivers, Niles</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e7334</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">350-351</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial fever</term>
                                        <term>entered as typho-malarial with or without a record of symptoms to substantiate the diagnosis</term>
                                        <term>condition of Peyer's patches variously stated, but not ulcerated; intestines more or less affected, but no ulceration of the ileum</term>
                                        <term>left pleural cavity contained pint and a half of purulent liquid, right cavity contained six ounces of serum</term>
                                        <term>liquid in pleural cavity, effusion did not embarrass breathing.</term>
                                        <term>pleural cavity contained purulent liquid, compressed lung against spinal column</term>
                                        <term>glands of Brünner and solitary glands of ileum enlarged but not ulcerated</term>
                                        <term>patches of Peyer presented shaven-beard appearance</term>
                                        <term>liver enlarged and contained minute abscesses</term>
                                        <term>spleen enlarged and contained abscesses</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00087">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 87.—<name type="person" key="648">Private Niles Ivers</name>, <name type="organization" key="177">Co. F, 6th
                                        Wis.</name>, was admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-04-21">April 21, 1864</date>, with
                                        typho-malarial fever.  He stated that he had been sick <date type="imjury" when="1864-04-14">for a
                                                week</date> with fever, which began with chills. He was much
                                        prostrated; his bowels were loose and his tongue dry and
                                        brown with red edges. Quinine, stimulants and nutriment were
                                        ordered.  In a few days his respiration became accelerated
                                        and he complained of cough and pain in the side, for which
                                        he was blistered. Under this treatment he gradually
                                        improved, the fever subsiding, but a considerable quantity
                                        of liquid remained in the pleural cavity, for the removal of
                                        which iodide of potassium was given in free doses and an
                                        occasional blister was applied, but without much benefit;
                                        the effusion did not embarrass his breathing. Convalescence
                                        was slow and he was unable to leave his bed, when, about
                                        June 1, symptoms of hectic appeared.  He failed gradually and
                                        died on <date type="death" when="1864-06-23">the 23d</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination
                                        <date type="autopsy" when="1864-06-24">twenty-four hours after death</date>: Body much emaciated; rigor
                                        mortis moderate. The left pleural cavity contained about a
                                        pint and a half of purulent liquid which compressed the lung
                                        against the spinal column; the right cavity contained about
                                        six ounces of serum; the right lung was healthy. The
                                        intestines were distended with gas; the mucous coat of the
                                        stomach and of the intestinal canal was thickened and
                                        softened; the glands of Brünner and the solitary glands of
                                        the ileum were enlarged and prominent but not ulcerated; the
                                        patches of Peyer presented the shaven-beard appearance. The
                                        liver was about one-third  larger than normal and contained a number of minute abscesses; the spleen was
                                        enlarged to three times its normal size and also contained
                                        abscesses; the kidneys were healthy.  [<hi rend="italic">Specimens</hi> 325-6, Med. Sect., <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
                                        Museum</name>, are from the spleen of this
                                                case.]—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="459">Ass't Surg. Geo. A.
                                                  Mursick</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
