<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e14752">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Reams, O. F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e14752</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">363</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
       <term>punctured and incised wounds of the knee joint</term> 
       <term>incised wounds of the knee joint</term>
       <term>amputations in the thigh after incised wounds of the knee joint</term> 
       <term>cut knee joint open with axe, chopping down tree in camp</term> 
       <term>secondary h&#230;morrhage, femoral artery ligated</term>
       <term>py&#230;mic chills</term>      
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-24">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 529.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private O. F. Reams</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B, United States Engineers</name>, aged 23 years, accidentally cut his right knee joint
    open with an axe while in the act of chopping down a tree in camp, on <date type="injury" when="1864-03-12">March 12, 1864</date>. He was admitted to hospital in <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-03-21">March 21st</date>. at which time there was but little suppuration, the external wound having partly healed by first intention,
    so that a probe could not be made to enter the joint. The patient was doing very well and had a good appetite, and hopes were
    entertained that the joint might be saved.  On April 12th, the limb was somewhat swollen and painful, and his appetite began to
    fail.  On <date type="operation" when="1864-04-22">April 22d</date>, fluctuation was distinctly detected, when an opening was made and two ounces of pus escaped.  On <date type="operation" when="1864-04-24">April 24th</date>, the thigh was amputated in the upper third by lateral flaps, by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>  The tissues below the point of amputation were found to be infiltrated with pus and badly disorganized. The patient reacted well, though not very promptly.  Py&#230;mic chills began <date type="injury" when="1864-04-26">two days afterwards</date>, and secondary h&#230;morrhage set in on <date type="operation" when="1864-04-28">April 28th</date>, when the femoral artery was ligated just below Poupart's ligament. The patient died from the effects of py&#230;mia, <date type="death" when="1864-05-01">May 1, 1864</date>. At the autopsy large quantities of serous fluid were found in the pleural cavities and a number of py&#230;mic abscesses in the left lung. One abscess was also discovered in the spleen. The latter organ, together with the bones of the amputated knee, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, with the history, by <name type="person" key="134">the operator</name>, and constitute specimens 2253 and 2234 of the Surgical Section.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
