<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40715">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Pitsley, Henry</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40715</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">106</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from DeCamp Hospital, David's Island, New York harbor</term>
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and pain in side for five months</term>
       <term>emaciated and weak</term>
       <term>cough for four months</term>
       <term>lungs tuberculous, riddled with cavities</term>
       <term>mesenteric glands tubercular</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-09-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>The following case forwarded on medical descriptive lists from the <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>E<hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>AMP <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, <name type="place">David's Island, New York harbor</name>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon J. Sim Smith</name> in charge at the date of the case.</p>       
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 105.&#8212;<name type="person" key="78">Private Henry Pitsley</name>, <name type="organization" key="88">company C, 147th New York volunteers</name>; age 21; admitted <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-29">October 29, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man was admitted to the field hospital of his regiment in the latter part of <date type="admit" when="1863-03">March, 1863</date>, and returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1863">some time after</date>; the date is not recorded. He was re-admitted with dysentery <date type="admit" when="1863-05-15">May 15th</date>, and is reported returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1863-05-18">May 18th</date>.  He was again admitted with diarrh&#339;a <date type="admit" when="1863-10-01">October 1st</date>, and transferred to the field hospital of the 1st Division, 1st Corps, <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-05">October 5th</date>.  <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-11">October 11th</date> he was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, and was admitted on the same day to <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver hospital</name>.  The diagnosis recorded is chronic diarrh&#339;a.  <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-28">October 28th</date> he was sent to <name type="place">New York</name>, and admitted to this hospital next day, as stated above.]  He stated that he was attacked about <date type="injury" when="1863-05">five months ago</date> with diarrh&#339;a and pain in the side. The diarrh&#339;a was profuse and the pain in the side severe, but he was kept with his regiment until about two weeks ago, when he was sent to <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., whence he was transferred to this place. He is now much emaciated and very weak; pulse frequent and feeble; diarrh&#339;a profuse. He has considerable cough, which he says has troubled him for the last four months.  November 3d: The patient appears to be gaining strength; the diarrh&#339;a is somewhat improved, there being but about four passages daily; his appetite also has improved. Ordered half an ounce of whiskey every two hours, and a chalk-mixture containing paregoric and rhatany. Diet: Milk, eggs, and beef-tea.  November 12th: Is about out of doors, and seems to be doing very well. Treatment continued, with the addition of half an ounce of cod-liver oil twice daily.  November 25th: The patient is still doing well. He has gained some flesh, but the cough and diarrh&#339;a continue, though they are less troublesome than at first; his appetite is good, and he sleeps pretty well at night. Treatment continued.  November 30th: For the last day or so the patient has not been so well. He is beginning to lose appetite; his cough is troublesome, and the diarrh&#339;a is again very severe; does not sleep well at night. Directed him to take ten grains of subnitrate of bismuth and one-third of a grain of powdered opium every three hours.  December 3d: The diarrh&#339;a still continues; the patient is very feeble. Ordered a pill of lead and opium every three hours; whiskey. He died <date type="death" when="1863-12-05">December 5th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-12-06">eighteen hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis well marked; body very poorly nourished. The left lung was tuberculous and firmly adherent to the walls of the chest; its upper lobe was nearly solidified, and riddled with cavities, one or two of which measured an inch in diameter; the lower lobe contained tubercles but no cavities; in the right lung some groups of tubercles were scattered here and there, but there were no cavities. The heart was normal. The diaphragm was firmly adherent to the whole upper surface of the liver. The liver and spleen were normal. About the ileoc&#230;cal valve there was marked congestion, and there were deposits of tubercles [?] on the surface of the intestines, but no well-marked ulceration. The mesenteric glands were tubercular; some of them were as large as an inch and a half in diameter. The kidneys were normal.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. Norton Brockway</name>.</p>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
