<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18524">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">L——, John</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e18524</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">417</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the neck</term>                                                                   
                                                                  <term>operations on the neck</term>
                                                                  <term>operations on the air-passages</term>
                                                                  <term>bronchotomy for disease</term>
                                                                  <term>laryngotomy for non-traumatic causes</term>
                                                                  <term>typhoid-pneumonia</term>
                                                                  <term>edema of the glottis</term>
                                                                  <term>pneumonia</term>
                                                                  <term>epiglottis swollen and edematous, closing the passage</term>
                                                                  <term>post-mortem dissection</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-11-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                                <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private John L——</name>, <name type="organization">1st United States
                                                                Volunteers</name>, aged 26 years, was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="injury" when="1865-04-07">April 7th, 1865</date>, suffering
                                                  from an attack of typhoid-pneumonia. He was
                                                  apparently doing well until <date type="injury" when="1865-04-20">the 20th</date>, when he
                                                  complained of sore throat. On examination, the
                                                  posterior wall of the pharynx was found to be a
                                                  little reddened, and covered with an abundance of
                                                  tenacious mucus. At about 2.30 P. M., on <date type="operation" when="1865-04-25">the 25th</date>,
                                                  he was suddenly seized with great dyspnœa;
                                                  respiration stertorous, countenance livid, and
                                                  lips blue. There was complete orthopnœa, with
                                                  great restlessness and jactitation, and entire
                                                  inability to speak above a faint lisping whisper.
                                                  These symptoms continued to increase in severity
                                                  in spite of the administration of an emetic. A
                                                  consultation was held, and it was decided that the
                                                  symptoms were those of œdema of the glottis, and
                                                  that unless relief were promptly afforded the
                                                  patient would die of suffocation. <name type="operation">Laryngotomy</name> was
                                                                thereupon performed by <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon William F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, by plunging a narrow straight
                                                  bistoury into the larynx, just above the cricoid
                                                  cartilage. The relief was almost instantaneous,
                                                  and there was but little hæmorrhage. For want of
                                                  a trachea tube the lips of the wound were kept
                                                  apart by bent copper wires, which were carried
                                                  backward and fastened by a piece of tape behind
                                                  the neck. During the night the patient took sherry
                                                  wine and beef tea through an elastic bougie,
                                                  swallowing small quantities at a time. The
                                                  following afternoon a trachea tube was introduced
                                                  into the larynx, which rendered the patient much
                                                  more comfortable, although it was frequently
                                                  necessary to remove and cleanse the inner tube,
                                                  which became, from time to time, plugged by the
                                                  thick and tenacious mucous which was constantly
                                                  expectorated. On April 28th, there was a feeling
                                                  of oppression in the chest; all the symptoms of
                                                  bronchitis became more marked, and on the
                                                  following day he was attacked with pleurisy in
                                                  the right side. May 1st, well-marked pneumonia of
                                                  the right side; respiration rapid; sputa rusty
                                                  and frothy. Death resulted from pneumonia on <date type="death" when="1865-05-04">May
                                                                  4th</date>. A careful dissection was made, and the lungs,
                                                  larynx, and heart removed together. The larynx was
                                                  pale. The epiglottis, with the edges and upper
                                                  portion of the glottis, was swollen and
                                                  œdematous, almost entirely closing the passage.
                                                  There was a small irregular opening near the vocal
                                                  cord of the left side, through which an abscess
                                                  had evidently discharged. It had previously
                                                  burrowed down to some extent in the cellular
                                                  tissue, outside of the larynx, and had evidently
                                                  been the cause of the sudden and urgent dyspnœa.
                                                  There was well-marked hepatization of the lower
                                                  lobe of the right lung. There was one pint of
                                                  sero-purulent effusion, and numerous recent
                                                  adhesions between the parietal and viscera pleura.
                                                  The pathological specimen is No. 2513, Section I, A. M. M., and was contributed, with a history of
                                                  the case, by <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon William F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
