<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e23698">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Tarrance, D. M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e23698</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">619</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
     <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fracture of the os calcis</term>
     <term>ball entered outside of tendo-achillis, passed through os calcis and fractured bone, emerged at inner margin of sole of foot</term> 
     <term>pus discharged from wounds, symptoms of necrosed bone present</term>
     <term>diseased bone removed</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 892.—<hi rend="italic">Shot fracture of the os
      calcis.</hi>—<name type="person" key="1394">Sergeant D. M. Tarrance</name>, <name type="organization" key="344">Co. B, 1st Pennsylvania Cavalry</name>, aged 24 years, was
     wounded in the right foot, at <name type="place">United States Ford</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-25">May 25, 1863</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-06-15">three weeks afterwards</date>.  On <date type="transfer" when="1863-09-29">September 29th</date> the patient was
     transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Mower Hospital, Philadelphia</name>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon J. Hopkinson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported:  "The patient was wounded by a ball entering outside of the
     tendo-achillis, passing downward, forward and inward through the os calcis, fracturing the
     bone, and emerging at the inner margin of the sole of the foot. The heel became very much
     swollen and painful and pus continued to discharge from both the wound of entrance and exit,
     all the symptoms of necrosed bone being present. Flaxseed poultices were applied; iron and
     quinine with wine was administered. On <date type="operation" when="1863-12-01">December 1st</date>, another examination having been made, it
     was decided to cut down and remove the diseased bone, and a crucial incision was made along the
     internal aspect of the bone, its length parallel with the axis of the bone being three and a
     half inches, in the opposite direction two and a half inches. The loose pieces were then
     removed and the necrosed bone was scraped with the gouge, after which the wound was closed with
     sutures and cold-water dressings were applied. The operation was performed by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. H. Jamar</name>, the patient being in good general condition at the time. He did
     well afterwards. Small fragments of bone exfoliated and were removed at different intervals. By
     <date type="furlough" when="1864-01-20">January 20, 1864</date>, the wound was healing kindly and the patient was allowed to go to his home.
     About the end of February the wound had healed with the exception of a small point, and the
     patient dispensed with his crutches and used a cane.  He was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-07-08">July 8, 1864</date>."  <name type="person" key="xx">Examining Surgeon W. Jewell</name>, of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>,
     certified to the injury <date type="pension" when="1866-04-07">April 7, 1866</date>, and described the wound as still suppurating. The
      pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1871-03-04">March 4, 1871</date>.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
