<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41366">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Caywood, Adelbert</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41366</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">189</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>pleural cavity contained bloody serum</term>
       <term>large intestine thickened and congested from c&#230;cum to rectum, but no ulcers</term>
       <term>bronchi contained muco-purulent matter</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-12">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 445.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Adelbert Caywood</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company A, 24th New York cavalry</name>; age 18; admitted from <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-10-02">October 2, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-10-25">October 25th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-10-26">twenty-four hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis great; body very much emaciated. Head, neck and spinal column not examined. The pericardium contained half an ounce of clear serum. The heart was rather smaller than usual, its structure normal, although a little pale; all the valves closed perfectly, but they were somewhat attenuated; both auricles and ventricles contained small firm clots. The right pleural cavity contained an ounce of bloody serum; there were no adhesions between the pulmonary and costal pleura on either side, but the lobes of the right lung were interadherent. The left lung was pale, its structure normal; the right lung was congested, and portions of its upper and lower lobes, anteriorly, were in the stage of gray hepatization. The bronchi contained some muco-purulent matter, but their mucous membrane was normal; the bronchial glands were healthy with the exception of one, which contained a deposit of calcareous matter. The mucous membrane of the stomach was slightly congested. The duodenum was normal. The small intestine was congested in regions through its whole tract, but not ulcerated. The large intestine was contracted, thickened, and congested from the c&#230;cum to the rectum, but there were no ulcers present. The liver was of medium size, its structure normal; the gall-bladder contained an ounce of very dark bile. The pancreas and spleen were normal. The kidneys apparently healthy in structure, but pale; the bladder contained about eight ounces of urine.&#8212;<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
