<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e28371">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Marks, John C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e28371</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">820-821</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term> 
     <term>tetanus</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of both arms, ball passed through left arm, entered right arm near inner edge of biceps muscle, and passed through obliquely</term> 
     <term>medial nerve included in cicatrix of right arm</term>      
     <term>partial trismus, jaws stiff</term>      
     <term>arm pain caused by compression of nerve by contraction of cicatrix</term>
     <term>operations of resection of cicatrix</term>    
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>amputation of right arm at junction of upper and middle third</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1196.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1507">Private John C.
      Marks</name>, <name type="organization" key="562">Co. D, 149th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 28
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1864-05-10">May 10, 1864</date>. On <date type="admit" when="1864-05-13">May 13th</date>
     he was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington,
     whence <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported:  "Flesh wounds of both arms by a musket ball, which, after
     passing through the left arm, entered the right near the inner edge of the biceps muscle, and
     passed through obliquely, outward and downward. At the end of about six weeks both wounds had
     healed; the cicatrix was firm. The medial nerve was evidently included in the cicatrix of the
     wound of the right arm, as he suffered intense pain in the course of it, especially in the
     fingers, which were stiff and extended. The nutrition of the arm was also impaired. He suffered great nervous irritation. <date type="operation" when="1864-09-16">September
      16th</date>, the pain in the forearm and hand is very severe; he has also partial trismus; his jaws
     are stiff, but he can open them to the extent of about an inch. He has failed in strength and
     appetite and is emaciated."  <name type="person" key="70">Dr. Lidell</name> made an incision
     about two inches in length through the cicatrix down to the nerve, which was loosened and laid
     bare to the extent of the incision. The old cicatrix was also removed. The nerve did not appear
     to be injured in any way. The pain was apparently caused by compression of it by the
     contraction of the cicatrix. The wound was left open to heal by granulation. He had been
     treated to date of operation by subcutaneous injections of morphia, which relieved the pain
     temporarily.  September 17th, pain is slight, trismus lessened; passed a comfortable night.  September 18th, pain continues, trismus subsided. The injections of morphia were continued at
     night, and a grain of sulphate of zinc ordered thrice daily.  September 30th, treatment
     continued to date. The operation has only afforded partial relief. The pain continues quite
     severe.  <date type="operation" when="1864-10-06">October 6th</date>, the wound of the previous operation has entirely healed, but he cannot use
     the hand in consequence of the exalted sensibility of it; the pain in it is very severe, and he
     is suffering much from want of sleep. He has had several paroxysms of severe tetanic
     irritation, with some stiffness of the jaws, one of which occurred this morning. <name type="person" key="459">Assistant Surgeon George A. Mursick</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="132">U. S. V.</name>, made an incision through the cicatrix of the previous operation and
     dissected out the median and excutaneous nerves, which were found lying in close apposition,
     and resected three-fourths of an inch of each of them. They were both involved in the new
     cicatrix. <date type="operation" when="1864-10-19">October 19th</date>, the operation of resection did not avail anything, and his condition is
     as bad as ever. The pain is now so severe as to deprive him of all rest, and the sensibility of
     the hand is so great that he will not allow anything to touch it. His general health is
     suffering severely. His countenance expresses great anxiety and his appetite has failed. <name
      type="person" key="70">Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, administered chloroform and amputated the right arm at the junction of the upper
     with the middle third by anteror posterior flaps. Marks recovered, and was discharged <date
      type="servicedischarge" when="1865-05-27">May 27, 1865</date>, and pensioned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
