<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41209">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Gupton, W. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41209</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">179</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>both lungs adherent to thoracic walls at their apices, considerable tuberculous solidification</term>
       <term>small cavities communicated with bronchial tubes and with each other</term>
       <term>small intestine contained tubercular deposit and extensively ulcerated</term>
       <term>large intestine had several ulcers, many in state of cicatrization</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863, then <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 403.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. H. Gupton</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 44th North Carolina, (Confederate:)</name> age 29; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-12-17">December 17, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-04-21">April 21, 1864</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> Height six feet; body extremely emaciated. Brain not examined. Both lungs were adherent at their apices to the thoracic walls; there was considerable tuberculous solidification in the posterior part of the upper lobe and upper third of the lower lobe of the left lung; on section of the consolidated portion numerous small cavities were seen, which communicated with the bronchial tubes and with each other; they were filled with a yellowish some what fetid, purulent secretion, and were lined by a distinct smooth membrane; the superior lobe of the right lung was almost wholly solidified; at its apex was a cavity the size of a walnut, with several smaller ones communicating with it; these cavities closely resembled those in the opposite lung; the lower lobe was healthy; the right lung weighed twenty-four ounces, the left thirty ounces. The heart was healthy; weight eight ounces. The liver, spleen, pancreas, and kidneys were healthy; weight of liver fifty-three ounces; spleen ten ounces; pancreas two ounces; right kidney five ounces, left five and a half. The small intestine contained a considerable amount of tubercular (?) deposit, and was extensively ulcerated. In the large intestine were several ulcers, many in a state of cicatrization.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Henry E. Paine</name>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
