<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10399">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Minisberger, John</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e10399</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">579-580</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases allied to or associated with</term>
                                        <term>the paroxysmal and continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>cerebro-spinal fever</term>
                                        <term>clinical and post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>resection of elbow joint</term>  
                                        <term>blood and serum within cranium</term>
                                        <term>severe pain between the shoulder-blades</term>
                                        <term>sick at stomach, tried to vomit</term>
                                        <term>profuse perspiration</term>
                                        <term>radial pulse fluttering</term>
                                        <term>pallor of face, lips with lividity of asphyxia</term>
                                        <term>lungs intensely congested with venous blood</term>
                                        <term>subarachnoid effusion over hemispheres</term>
                                        <term>pleural cavities and pericardial sac contained serum</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body>                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 91.—<name type="person" key="832">Private John Minisberger</name>, <name type="organization" key="100">Co. I, 90th
                                        Pa.</name>; age 40; convalescing satisfactorily from a
                                        resection of the left elbow joint, rose on the morning of
                                                <date type="death" when="1864-07-28">July 28,
                                                1864</date>, in his usual good health, dressed
                                        himself and went out to the pump for a drink as was his
                                        daily habit.  About 6 A. M. he was suddenly seized with a
                                        severe pain between the shoulder-blades, the feeling being
                                        as if some one was pressing a bar of hot iron into his back
                                        bone. A mustard plaster gave speedy relief, and after the
                                        attack was over he got up and walked about the ward. An hour
                                        later the pain returned, but was relieved in ten or fifteen
                                        minutes by a reapplication of the mustard. He appeared to be
                                        sick at stomach and tried to vomit; he declined food but had
                                        no thirst. His strength appeared good, but after the attack
                                        he fell into a profuse perspiration and slept an hour or
                                        two.  At 10 A. M. the pain returned with such increased
                                        severity that he cried out in anguish; it also lasted
                                        longer.  At 11 A. M., on raising him up in bed for the
                                        application of cups, he was seized with a fourth paroxysm,
                                        and exclaiming "Oh! such pain!" fell over on the shoulder of
                                        an attendant and immediately became unconscious as if in
                                        syncope, his face deathly pale, eyes fixed, muscular system
                                        relaxed, radial pulse fluttering and breathing interrupted
                                        by long intervals. In a few minutes the pallor of the face
                                        and lips gave place to the lividity of asphyxia; the eyes
                                        were open, fixed and glassy, the left pupil contracted, the
                                        right dilated; the muscles completely relaxed and the pulse
                                        imperceptible at the wrist. He took afterwards only three or
                                        four long sighing inspirations, with long intervals between
                                        them, although ammonia was applied to the nostrils and
                                        Marshall Hall's method of artificial respiration was
                                        faithfully tried.  He died at 11.30 A. M.  There was no thirst
                                        or any unnatural warmth of skin during the five and a half
                                        hours his sickness lasted; nor were petechial or any other
                                        kind of spots visible on the surface.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: On removing the
                                        skull-cap four ounces of blood and serum escaped; the veins
                                        and sinuses of the brain were congested with fluid blood;
                                        there was a moderate quantity of subarachnoid effusion over
                                        the hemispheres and the ventricles contained about an ounce
                                        of serum. The spinal cord and its membranes appeared
                                        healthy. The lungs were intensely congested with venous
                                        blood; the pleural cavities contained eight ounces of serum
                                        and the pericardial sac two ounces; the valves of the heart
                                        were sufficient. All the abdominal viscera were healthy
                                        except the kidneys, which were congested of a bright maroon
                                        color; the urine obtained at the autopsy was
                                        albuminous. The blood remained fluid everywhere; it was dark
                                        in color and flowed freely wherever an incision was made in
                                        the body.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="459">Ass't Surg. Geo. A. Mursick</name>,
                                                  <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton
                                                          Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi>⃰</p>
                        <p>⃰ <hi rend="initialcap">J</hi>OHN <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL, <hi rend="initialcap">U. S. V.</hi>, published this case in an article on <hi rend="italic">Epidemic Cerebro-spinal Meningitis</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">American Jour. Med. Sciences</hi>, June, 1865.</p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
