<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20035">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Bickett, F. E.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e20035</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">562</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>excisions</term>
          <term>excisions of the scapula</term>
          <term>excisions of portions of the scapula</term>
          <term>disability total and permanent</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
          <term>ball splintered scapula extensively</term>
          <term>ball lodged in glenoid cavity</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private F. E.
          Bickett</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 5th Connecticut
          Volunteers</name>, aged 51 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10"
          >Chancellorsville, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3d,
          1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which struck the infra-spinatus fossa of the left scapula
        about midway between its inferior angle and the spine, passed forward, splintered the bone
        extensively, and finally lodged in the glenoid cavity without injuring the humerus. He was
        treated in the field hospital of the 1st division, Twelfth Corps, until <date
          type="transfer" when="1863-05-06">the 6th</date>, when he was sent to <name
          type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington. An operation, for the
        removal of the ball, discovered a large number of shattered fragments lying near the joint,
        which were dissected out from their ligamentous attachment and withdrawn. The lower portion
        of the scapula being now entirely separated from the upper, and, not knowing to what extent
        the inferior portion of the bone had been splintered, it was determined to remove it rather
        than risk the effects of the prolonged discharge from the remnant. Chloroform was
        administered, and the operation performed by <name type="person" key="131">Surgeon H.
          Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> The spine and
        supra-spinous fossa were preserved. The smooth head of the humerus was visible through the
        wound. The patient did remarkably well. No bad symptoms supervened, and he gradually
        regained his strength. The incision made for the removal of the bone filled up without
        sinuses or discharge of exfoliations. On <date type="furlough" when="1863-08-29">August
          29th</date>, he was furloughed for sixty days. Upon returning, the wound had entirely
        healed. The use of the fore-arm and hand were perfect, though the motion of the arm, as was
        anticipated, was impaired by the loss of support of the head in the glenoid cavity. It had
        fallen back slightly from its natural position. The arm, from weakness, was still worn in a
        sling. The patient was enabled to eat, tie his cravat, brush his hair, button his clothes,
        etc., with the affected member, and its strength and usefulness were daily increasing. On
          <date type="transfer" when="1864-01-14">January 14th, 1864</date>, Bickett was transferred
        to <name type="place">Connecticut</name>, and finally discharged from service in <date
          type="servicedischarge" when="1864-03">March, 1864</date>. The pathological specimen was
        contributed, with this history of the case, by the operator. It is figured in the preceding
        cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 259). This man is a pensioner. On <date type="pension"
          when="1867-05-27">May 27th, 1867</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner R.
          Strickland</name> reports that the arm is utterly useless and painful, and rates the
        pensioner's disability as total and probably permanent. </p>

      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001480.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 259.&#8212;Portion of left scapula successfully
          removed after a gunshot injury. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1090, Sect. I, A. M.
          M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
