<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40852">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Benedict, Charles</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40852</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">148</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Harewood Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>debility from fever and chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>countenance hippocratic</term>
       <term>liver fatty</term>
       <term>jejunum lead-colored, portions injected</term>
       <term>solitary follicles in ileum enlarged to size of small shot</term>
       <term>ascending colon injected, showed cicatrices of former ulcers</term>
       <term>rectum with points of ulceration extending upward to sigmoid flexure</term>        
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="173"><hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>AREWOOD <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="156">Surgeon Thomas Antisell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge from October, 1862, to September, 1863:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 293.&#8212;<name type="person" key="191">Private Charles Benedict</name>, <name type="organization" key="207">company C, 17th Connecticut volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-04-21">April 21, 1863</date>.  Debility from fever and chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Treatment at first opium and tannin, then Dover's powder, afterward quinine and iron.  <date type="furlough" when="1863-05-26">May 26th</date>: Was furloughed.  May 29th: Returned from furlough laboring under a relapse. He had twenty thin, yellowish, bloody stools during the day.  Treatment: Decoction of flaxseed with opium internally, enemata of starch and opium, nutritious diet, sinapisms to the abdomen.  On the 30th there were six stools, and hiccough set in; pulse 160; countenance hippocratic; vomiting; profuse cold sweat.  Treatment: Lime-water, pills of opium and camphor, sinapisms to the abdomen and neck.  <date type="death" when="1863-05-31">Died, May 31st</date>, at 5 P.M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> The body was not much emaciated. There were pleuritic adhesions on both sides; firm on the right side, slight on the left. The lungs were pale, but apparently healthy. The heart was rather small, pale, and coated with fat; there was a large, fibrinous, yellow clot in the right ventricle. The liver was mottled and fatty; the gall-bladder distended with greenish bile. The spleen was congested and softened. The stomach and duodenum were injected in patches. The jejunum was lead-colored, portions of it much injected. The ileum was much congested; its solitary follicles were enlarged to the size of a small shot. The ascending colon was much injected, and showed the cicatrices of former ulcers; the transverse colon was pale; the follicles were enlarged slightly, with minute depressions on their summits; the rectum was pale, and dotted with points of ulceration extending as far upward as the sigmoid flexure.&#8212;<name type="person" key="166">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. Hirshfield</name>.</p>  
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
