<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e12982">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Davis, W. E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e12982</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">291-292</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of intermediary amputation in the lower third of the femur</term> 
     <term>gangrene of foot and leg from gunshot wound of leg</term>
     <term>foot and lower portion of leg completely mortified</term>
     <term>injury and obliteration of main arteries</term>       
     <term>tetanus after amputation, hastened fatal issue</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-21">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 471.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1094">Captain <hi
       rend="italic">W. E. Davis</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="451">Co. B, 30th North Carolina</name>, aged 25 years, was wounded in the skirmish at <name type="BATTLE" key="294">Kelly's Ford</name>, Virginia, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7, 1863</date>. He was conveyed to the hospital of the Third Corps, and,
     <date type="transfer" when="1863-11-10">November 10th</date>, was transferred to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>
     and admitted into <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>. <name
      type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon Carlos Carvallo</name> reported that the ball
     entered the anterior external aspect of the right leg about two and a half inches below the
     inferior edge of the patella, one and a half inches external to the median line of the leg, and
     one and a quarter inches below the head of the fibula, where it fractured the bone, and
     descending downward, inward, and backward, emerged in the posterior internal aspect of the leg,
     midway between the inferior edge of the patella and the internal malleolus, internal to the
     bulk of the gastrocnemius muscle. The right foot was cold, of a purple hue, and entirely
     senseless; the leg, from knee to upper portion of lower third, was swollen and emphysematous,
     and the middle third was of a yellow and dark green, intermixed with a brown-purple hue.
     Diagnosis: Gangrene of the foot and leg from gunshot wound of leg, with, most probably, injury
     and obliteration of the main arteries. Amputation was the sole treatment indicated, the foot and lower portion of the leg being completely mortified. <name
      type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W. Thomson</name> amputated the thigh at the lower
     third by the circular method. The femoral was secured by digital compression and the
     tourniquet. Very little arterial blood was lost. A grain of morphia was administered in a half
     ounce of whiskey immediately after the operation, he having readily revived from the ether
     narcosis, and he stated that he had slept undisturbed during the operation, without dreaming,
     and was now entirely free of pain. The cut surface of the stump showed the tissues infiltrated
     and of an unhealthy appearance. Stimulants were administered. The stump was dressed with dry
     charpie. At night the pulse was 130, tongue moist, skin dry. The stump was boggy and crepitant
     to pressure, and a dark discoloration was visible on the external aspect extending to the
     tensor fascia lata.  November 12th, towards evening a line of demarcation was visible of a large
     slough in external side of skin flap, no discharge from stump; tension of the skin caused by
     three sutures, which were removed, followed by gaping of the flap. About 9 P. M., the pulse
     became frequent (145), and there was great paleness of the conjunctiva and skin. The extensive
     sloughing, weak pulse, and an&#230;mic appearance presented a hopeless prognosis. Late in the
     evening, a strong solution of bromine was directly applied to the surface of the stump by means
     of charpie. The application was at first painless, but, after penetrating the mortified tissues
     and coming in contact with sensitive parts, it caused such pain that the patient was fortified
     during the operation by a half ounce of sherry wine in powdered ice and one-half grain morphia.  13th, <name type="person" key="454">Dr. Holly</name> touched the line of demarcation (which was
     very well marked, and extended to the whole circumference of the stump) with pure bromine, by
     means of a flattened stick, in order to facilitate and hasten the efforts of nature. He also
     applied <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson's</name>  solution of bromine (composed of one drachm of pure bromine, three drachms of bromide of
     potassium, and three ounces of water), by means of a glass pipette to all the sinuses beneath the mortified integuments and the sinuses near the
     arteries; besides this application, after carefully washing the stump with "blue wash"
     (solution of permanganate of potassa), and protecting the integuments outside with castor oil
     and the surface of the stump with a thin muslin rag, the vapor of bromine was administered by
     pouring an ounce of solution of bromine on charpie; this was applied to the face of the stump
     and covered with simple cerate spread on sheet lint and inclosed by oil-cloth and a bandage.
     The application of bromine was repeated at 1 and 7 P. M., and the nourishing food and
     stimulants continued. An injection of soap and water caused the first passage since the date of
     the injury and gave great relief.  14th, the effects of the bromine yesterday had hermetically
     sealed the surface of the stump, covering it with a yellowish gray matter, which was removed as
     much as possible, a large amount of mortified integuments being cut away and three loose ligatures removed. Decubitus of gluteal region,
     somewhat to right of sacral bone; bedsore the size of the palm of the hand, with a yellow
     greenish slough, which was partly removed with the assistance of a scissors. India-rubber rings
     employed, and ointment of cinchona bark. Bromine was freely applied four times during the day.
     There was an abundant discharge of thin unhealthy pus, and the removal of a great quantity of
     slough discovered a red granulating surface.  15th, wound dressed with bromine at 9 A. M. and 4 P. M. Doing very well;
     slough removed in large pieces.  17th, large quantity of sphacelated integuments removed and
     vapor of bromine applied. The stump was exposed for an hour to a painter's view.  18th, the
     decubitus is becoming the most painful and prominent feature of his complaint. For the first
     time he had a free passage without adjuvants; slept on his belly.  On the 19th, he was put on a
     water bed, on which he lay much easier. An extensive slough was removed from the inferior
     portion of the flap, as also from the decubitus, which discharges healthy pus in large
     quantity; could see an artery pulsating. Bromine applied to bedsore. Patient felt bright, and
     eat a hearty dinner. In the evening, he complained of a little pain in his throat resembling
     <choice><orig>tonsilitis</orig><reg>tonsillitis</reg></choice>.  20th, on examining the patient's throat, it was found that he could only open his
     jaws enough to show the tip of his tongue. Tetanus diagnosticated. Nutritious diet and
     stimulants were given as usual. At 4 P. M., a laxative was administered. The decubitus was
     dressed with pulverized cinchona. The stump, which had a beautiful red granulating surface,
     with one single ligature, was dressed at night with castor oil. He had had contractions and
     jerking of the stump once in the morning, but had not paid any attention to it until 6 P. M.,
     at which time it became more frequent, recurring nearly every half hour; three ounces of brandy
     and a half grain of morphia were ordered at 10 and 12 P. M. and 2 and 4 A. M.  21st, trismus
     well confirmed. Contractions of glottis muscles and fits of suffocation after taking fluids,
     though administered in small quantities and through a pipette. There was rigidity of the masseters and <choice><orig>sterno-cleido-mastoid</orig><reg>sternocleidomastoid</reg></choice> muscles, and of the muscles of the back of the neck, which were quite hard. The head inclined backward and to the left side; diificulty of articulation. The difficulty of
     swallowing increased and only fluid nourishment could be taken. He gradually sank, and died
      <date type="death" when="1863-11-22">November 22, 1863</date>, of asthenia. A <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination of the stump was made November 24th. There was a
     natural clot of blood at the distal end of the femoral artery. The neurilemma of the sciatic
     nerve appeared thickened, and the fibres of the nerve more gross and coarse than usual. The
     ends of several nerves were strongly attached to the external surface of the stump. The body
     and spine were not opened. A drawing, by <name type="person" key="878">Hospital Steward E.
      Stauch</name>, of the gangrenous stump, is copied in the <choice><orig>chromo-lithograph</orig><reg>chromolithograph</reg></choice>, <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XXI</hi>, opposite.</p>
   
    <figure>
     <graphic url="cww.001816.001" />
     <head>PLATE  XXI.    GANGRENE  OF  A  THIGH  STUMP.    Case of Captain W. E. Davis,  30th North Carolina</head>
    </figure>
    
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
