<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e14556">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Hughes, Patrick</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e14556</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">206-207</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
                    <term>perforating gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                    <term>survived after perforations of craniums by musket balls</term>
                    <term>missiles struck back of head</term>
                    <term>ball entered posterior to junction of coronal and sagittal sutures on
                        median line, passed backward under the scalp and escaped one inch above the
                        occipital protuberance</term>
                    <term>perforation of skull by single conoidal ball</term>
                    <term>ball entered posterior right parietal, emerged at higher point of left
                        parietal, large exit wound</term>
                    <term>compound comminuted fracture of skull</term>
                    <term>paroxysms of giddiness</term>
                    <term>loss of substance of skull</term>
                    <term>loss of hearing</term>
                    <term>sight of right eye impaired</term>
                    <term>unable to see small object placed directly on level and in midline between
                        eyes</term>
                    <term>confused and irritable</term>
                    <term>fungus cerebri</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
            
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-25">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.275">
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="1609">Private Patrick
                    Hughes</name>, <name type="organization" key="675">Co. K, 4th New York
                    Volunteers</name>, aged 23 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="33">Antietam</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-09-17">September 17th, 1862</date>, in <name type="person" key="xxx">Sumner</name>'s
                attack on the right, near <name type="place">Dunker's Chapel</name>. Several special
                reports, at variance in regard to some particulars of the case, have been received.
                In the note book of <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>,
                    <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, it is stated that "two
                missiles had struck the back portion of his head, the one near vertex causing injury
                of greatest extent," and that "he did not entirely lose his consciousness at
                time of injury." But the field report, and the majority of the subsequent
                hospital reports, state very positively that the injury was a perforation of the
                skull by a single conoidal musket ball entering near the inner posterior angle of
                the right parietal, and emerging at a higher point of the left parietal, making,
                after traversing a portion of the brain, a large exit wound. Little is known of the
                early history of the case, except that the patient dragged himself from the field,
                and, after a preliminary dressing from <name type="person" key="">Surgeon G. W.
                    Lovejoy</name> of <name type="organization" key="675">his regiment</name>, was
                conveyed to a field hospital in a barn near <name type="place">Keedysville</name>,
                where he remained until <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-20">the 20th</date>,
                when he was sent to <name type="place">Hagerstown</name>. The regimental surgeon
                reports that the shock and depression from the injury was great, but that the
                patient was conscious and answered questions rationally. There is no report from the
                    <name type="place">Hagerstown</name> hospital, except that the patient was sent
                to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-24">the 24th</date>. On <date type="admit" when="1862-09-25">the
                    25th</date>, he was received at the <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount
                    Pleasant Hospital</name>. The following is an extract from the report of <name type="person" key="1610">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Carroll</name>, who had
                immediate charge of the case, after the patient's admission to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>: "The ball entered half an inch
                posterior to the junction of the coronal and sagittal sutures on the median line,
                passed backward under the scalp and escaped one inch above the occipital
                protuberance, inflicting a wound four inches in length, producing a compound
                comminuted fracture of the skull of the same extent. At the time of his admission to
                the hospital, eight days after the reception of the wound, so much tumefaction of
                the parts existed that it could not be ascertained whether or not the brain or its
                membranes were injured. The general condition of the patient was good; suppuration
                had commenced; no febrile action existed, the pulse was regular, sleep not
                materially disturbed, mind clear and manifesting no signs of compression of the
                brain, or inflammation of its membranes. Little, if any, change was perceptible for
                several days, when the swelling of the scalp and tissues subsided, leaving a
                prominence nearly, if not altogether, one inch in height, and two and a half or
                three inches in length of brain substance, in which the pulsation of the arteries
                could be distinctly observed. From the closest examination that could now be made,
                it was supposed that the membranes of the brain were not lacerated, though this
                supposition was by no means certain, as there was reason to believe the brain itself
                had been penetrated. The chief, and in fact, the only unpleasant symptom complained
                of by the patient, was an occasional paroxysm of giddiness that occurred at
                intervals of from ten to fifteen days; the paroxysms continued to return, though
                less frequently, while he remained in the hospital. Early in December, he was able
                to sit up and walk about the ward, and was never afterwards much confined to bed.
                The protuberance now began to subside, and was soon reduced nearly to a level with
                the skull; numerous pieces of bone were removed as they became detached from the
                tissues, leaving a complete channel in the cranium from the point where the ball
                entered to where it emerged. At the time this man was discharged from the service,
                    <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-01-26">January 26th, 1863</date>, the
                wound was nearly healed. There was but little discharge of pus, and with the
                exception of an occasional recurrence of the paroxysms of giddiness, he suffered but
                slight inconvenience. The treatment consisted simply in cutting the hair short, and
                applying cold water dressing locally, paying strict attention to the diet, and
                administering a cathartic as often as symptoms seemed to indicate its use."
                    <name type="person" key="339">Assistant Surgeon C. A. McCall</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>, furnished a report of
                the case, from which the following extracts are made. "The ball passed from
                about one inch above and to the right of occipital protuberance into the cavity of
                cranium and emerged at a point on the left of the median line, about one and
                three-fourths inches from the point of entry; probably a conoidal ball. From the
                posterior margin of the inferior wound to anterior margin of superior was about four
                inches. At the time of his admission to hospital, eight days after the injury, so
                much tumefaction and hardened clot existed, that it was deemed inadvisable to make a
                very strict examination with a view to determine the extent of lesion. The hair was
                closely shaved, and cold water dressings applied and patient placed in a sitting
                posture. The general condition of patient was promising, although all the brain
                functions appeared clouded, the memory impaired, speech desultory or given in
                fragments, yet being readily aroused and, generally at such times, answering
                promptly and clearly. In a short time healthy suppuration was established, febrile
                action decreased, the pulse became regular, sleep became natural, the mind began to
                show clearness, and he seemed to lose all symptoms of compression or of inflammation
                of the brain or its membranes. The swelling and induration of the parts gradually
                disappeared, leaving in their place a fungus cerebri of considerable size, perhaps
                an inch in height by two and a half or three inches in length, in which the
                pulsation could be distinctly seen and felt. The only unpleasant symptom now
                existing was the occurrence of a paroxysm of giddiness at intervals of ten or twelve
                days, which symptom continued, although at much greater intervals, during the
                remainder of his stay at the hospital. The size and extent of the fungus deterred me
                from using the knife, and I had resort to compression as recommended by the surgeons
                of <name type="place">France</name>, but with such serious results that I was
                startled for the safety of my patient, and therefore threw aside all dressing save
                the simple cerate on soft lint, and proper guard for the delicate tissues. Early in
                December, he was able to sit up and walk about the wards, and was never afterwards
                confined to the bed. From this time the fungus commenced to decrease in size, and
                continued to do so until shortly before his discharge from the service, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-01-26">January 26th, 1863</date>, when it had
                shrunk below the level of the skull, and both openings had been well covered by
                cicatricial tissue. During the progress of the case numerous spiculæ of bone
                were removed as they became detached. The constitutional treatment consisted in
                paying strict attention to the diet, and exhibiting saline cathartics and turpentine
                injections as the symptoms seemed to call for. When the soldier left my hands he
                complained of no inconvenience whatever with the exception of the occasional attack
                of giddiness, and the fact that he could not see a small object when placed in a
                position directly on a level and on a middle line between the eyes. Both which
                defects, I consider, will diminish with time until lost. Shortly before the
                patient's discharge from <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant</name>, an
                excellent picture of the aspect of the injury at that time was made in water color,
                under the direction of <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>,
                    <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who was then in charge of
                the Division of Surgical Records of the Surgeon General's Office, and had secured
                the services of an artist, <name type="person" key="878">Mr. Stauch</name>, whose
                admirable drawing and coloring have furnished some of the best illustrations of this
                book. The figure on the right of the chromo-lithograph opposite is a good copy of
                    <name type="person" key="878">Mr. Stauch</name>'s water-color drawing. I take
                the following memorandum of the case from one of the memorandum books turned over to
                me by <name type="person" key="288">Dr. Brinton</name>: "Gunshot wound of head:
                The picture of this case was taken at the Surgeon General's Office, whither the man
                came as an orderly, or on an errand. He was perfectly well. A small carnified
                cerebral hernia existed at the exit wound, which was healing rapidly. The ball went
                into cavity of the skull and emerged. No symptoms existed at all, when the patient's
                portrait was taken. The wound was then some three or four months old. The history of
                this case, which I took at the time, has been unfortunately mislaid." After this
                we have the history of the case taken up by the pension examining surgeons. The
                patient went to <name type="place">Newcastle, Delaware</name>, and was pensioned at
                four dollars a month, until <date type="pension" when="1869-06">June, 1869</date>,
                when his pension was increased to eight dollars a month. <name type="person" key="1611">Dr. D. W. Maull</name> reports, at this date, that there was a loss
                of substance of the skull two inches wide and three inches long, leaving a large
                depression, covered only by the integuments of the cranium. "Through this can be
                seen at all times the pulsations of the brain. About the cavity the bone is ridged
                by the union of the fractured margins. There is almost constant dull pain, some loss
                of hearing, and the sight of the right eye is impaired." Dr. Maull regarded the
                disability as total. Yet the man worked afterwards in an iron foundry as puddler. On
                    <date type="pension" when="1870-12-20">December 20th, 1870</date>, this patient
                was examined by Doctors <name type="person" key="xx">William Thomson</name> and
                    <name type="person" key="xx">W. W. Keen</name> of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, who have published an interesting account¹ of his
                condition at that time, with a photograph, of which a reduced copy is given in the
                annexed wood-cut, (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 106.) I make the following
                quotations from this paper: "His memory is quite good, but by no means so good
                as before the injury. He is rather easily bothered and confused, and more irritable
                than formerly. The sight of his right eye, he thinks, is poor. <choice>
                    <orig>Whisky</orig>
                    <reg>Whiskey</reg>
                </choice> affects him as usual. Sexual power undiminished. He has no paralysis. The
                wound of entrance * * is marked by a slight depression in the bone, the
                wound of exit by a hollow two and a half by two inches, and one inch deep. No bone
                has closed this opening, but the scalp and hair dip down into the hollow. The
                arterial pulsations are barely perceptible. When recumbent the hollow is gradually
                obliterated and replaced, in about one minute, by a rounded protuberance. To prevent
                pain during this change, he supports the parts with his hand. When he coughs, even
                with moderate force, the depressed scalp instantly hedges up in a cone, which nearly
                reaches the general level of the skull and obliterates the depression, and then as
                suddenly subsides." Drs. Keen and Thomson observe that "the complete
                recovery from paralysis, (as evinced by his subsequent severe labor,) and the almost
                entire restoration of his mental faculties, are remarkable, especially in view of
                the probable deep lesion of the brain, both by the primary injury and the subsequent
                fungus cerebri." They comment also upon "the rapid changes in the state of
                the cranial contents, due to any change of position, to coughing, etc., as evinced
                by the effacement of the depression at the wound of exit." The authors also
                regard the case as of value in throwing light upon the probable anatomy of the optic
                commissure. Their discussion on this point is given in a foot-note.² </p>
            <p>¹ <hi rend="italic">Photographic Review of Medicine and Surgery</hi>. Vol. 1,
                No. 3, p. 26. Philadelphia, February, 1871. J. B. Lippincott &amp; Co. </p>
            <p>² "Wollaston, (Phil. Trans. 1824. p. 222,) reasoning from two attacks of
                transient hemiopsia, occurring in himself, and other cases in friends, appears to
                have been the first to point out the semi-decussation of the optic nerves at the
                chiasm. Longet (Traité de Phys., 2d ed. ii, 476) seems to assent to the
                explanation, though he refers to cases of perfect sight in which it is asserted no
                chiasm existed; and in his Traité d'Anat. et de Phys. du Syst. Nerv., p. 666,
                he gives cases of perfect sight in both eyes, in spite of unilateral cerebral
                atrophy or traumatic lesion. Von Graefe (Archiv, ii, 286) assents cordially to
                Wollaston's view, admitting that he proposes nothing new, but that which is far too
                little known. Hubert Airy, (On a Distinct Form of Transient Hemiopsia, Proc. Roy.
                Soc., Feb. 17th, 1870, in "Nature," i, 444.) after a careful examination of
                preceding writers, also supports it; and the experiments of Laborde and Leven, (Med.
                Gaz., Nov. 5th, 1870; from Gaz. Méd. de Paris,) who found atrophy of the right
                optic nerve following the removal of the superficial right cerebral convolutions,
                and without any apparent irritative processes, would also point in the same
                direction. In our own case, the point to which we desire to call special attention
                is the rigid optical examination of the region between the porus opticus and the
                macula lutea. The semi-decussation of the nerves at the chiasm being admitted, it
                would naturally be supposed that the fibres <hi rend="italic">a</hi> from the left
                tract would supply the left retina from the porus opticus toward <hi rend="italic">a'</hi>; but our examination shows that it supplies <hi rend="italic">less</hi>
                than this, viz.: only that part of the retina from <hi rend="italic">c</hi> to <hi rend="italic">a'</hi>; while in the right eye the fibres <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, instead of supplying the retina from the porus opticus to <hi rend="italic">b'</hi>, supply <hi rend="italic">more</hi> than this, viz.: that
                part of the retina from <hi rend="italic">c'</hi> to <hi rend="italic">b'</hi> . In
                other words the fibres <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> of the
                left optic tract supply, mathematically, the left halves of the two retinæ from
                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi> to <hi rend="italic">a'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c'</hi> to <hi rend="italic">b'</hi> , and the right tract the right halves. As
                to the cerebral seat of the sense of vision, the amount and depth of the injury to
                the brain are too uncertain, perhaps, to warrant us in venturing on any speculations
                us to its locality." </p>
            <figure><graphic url="cww.001401.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 106.—Cicatrix of a gunshot perforation of the
                skull, eight years after the reception of the wound. [From a photograph.]</head></figure>
            <figure><graphic url="cww.001402.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 107.—Diagram indicating the relations of the
                optic commisure and retinæ. [After Drs. Thomson and Keen.]</head></figure>
            <figure><graphic url="cww.001403.001"/><head>PLATE VI, facing p. 207. GUNSHOT FRACTURES OF THE CRANIUM. <hi rend="italic">Two
                    figures</hi>: Left hand, case of McK——, p. 280; right hand, case of
                Hughes, p. 206.</head></figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
