<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e4230">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Peters, George H.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e4230</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">242</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">          
          <term>on continued fevers</term>
          <term>clinical records of continued fevers</term>
          <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
          <term>febrile cases at Seminary Hospital</term>
          <term>typhoid fever</term>  
          <term>aguish paroxysms preceded continued fever</term>
          <term>acute epigastric and right iliac tenderness, tympanites</term>
          <term>rose-colored spots</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00100">
      
        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 100.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Chills; pale, coated
            tongue and offensive breath; jaundice and epigastric pain; bowels quiet; cerebral
            symptoms not marked; record unfinished.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="558">Private George H. Peters</name>, <name type="organization" key="622">Co. F, 4th Mich.
            Vols.</name>; age 21; of weakly constitution, was admitted <date type="admit"
              when="1861-11-01">Nov. 1, 1861</date>, as a case of typhoid fever.  On <date type="injury" when="1861-10-23">October 23</date> he was
          taken with headache and chills which lasted for three days, and with anorexia, weakness,
          diarrh&#339;a, cold feet, tinnitus aurium and fever, for which Epsom salt and quinine
          had been administered.  On admission he was dull and unable to collect his thoughts on
          account of a <choice><orig>fulness</orig><reg>fullness</reg></choice> in the head and ringing in the ears; his pulse was 98 and strong,
          skin warm and soft, left cheek flushed darkly, tongue dry and moist by turns, pale, clean
          at the tip and thickly coated whitish-gray at the base; he had no appetite but much
          thirst, acute epigastric and right iliac tenderness, tympanites, but no diarrh&#339;a;
          respiration was normal, but the breath was very offensive; there was also some pain in
          urinating. Brandy-punch and beef-essence were given with quinine, calomel and opium three
          times daily. A few rose-colored spots appeared next day. On the 4th the skin was dry, warm
          and somewhat jaundiced; the tongue red at the tip and edges, pale and coated white in the
          centre and at the base, the bowels meanwhile remaining tympanitic and tender but unmoved.
          He slept well during the night, and on the 5th his mind was clear and eyes intelligent,
          skin dry, tongue moist, pale and slightly coated in the centre, breath free from all
          offensive odor.  On the 6th a few more rose-colored spots appeared, but the bowels remained
          quiet, and the slight tenderness present was in the epigastric region; the abdomen was
          soft.  He had two stools on the 7th. Turpentine was administered.  On the 8th the skin was
          warm and soft and presented a few dark-red spots which were imperceptible to the touch and
          disappeared on pressure; pulse 56, small and compressible; tongue moist and thickly coated
          in the centre. At this time he did not sleep well and his appetite continued poor. Here
          the record leaves him, concluding with a statement of his transfer to <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name>, on
          <date type="transfer" when="1861-11-18">the 18th</date>. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
