<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e9350">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Link, John</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e9350</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">386</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term> 
                                        <term>admitted delirious</term>
                                        <term>bronchial glands large</term>
                                        <term>&#339;sophagus presented pale yellow ulcers</term>
                                        <term>lungs congested and engorged</term>
                                        <term>liver large, extending entirely across body</term>
                                        <term>stomach immensely distended, occupied greater portion of abdomen in oblique position, minute black spots towards pylorus</term>
                                        <term>jejunum filled with glairy tenacious mass</term>
                                        <term>end of ileum presented ulceration of Peyer's patches, near ileo-c&#230;cal valve ulcers ran together</term>
                                        <term>rug&#230; of large intestine elevated and coated with tenacious mucoid secretion, no ulcers found</term>
                                        <term>kidneys congested, spots of transuded blood noticed</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00187">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 187.&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="715">Sergeant John Link</name>,
                                                <name type="organization" key="699">Co. A, 107th
                                                Ohio</name>, was admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1863-06-15">June 15, 1863</date>, delirious,
                                        and died on <date type="death" when="1863-06-17">the 17th</date>.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi>
                                        examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-06-17">ten hours after death</date>: The brain was normal. The
                                        trachea was purple; its mucous membrane firm; the bronchial
                                        glands at its bifurcation large. The lower part of the
                                        &#339;sophagus was of a pale yellowish color and
                                        presented ulcers of the same hue; its mucous membrane was
                                        not softened. The right lung weighed nineteen ounces and a
                                        half and was congested in its lower and in part of its upper
                                        lobe; the lower lobe of the left lung was somewhat engorged.
                                        The heart was normal and contained a fibrinous clot in its
                                        right side. The liver was large and dark-colored, extending
                                        entirely across the body; the gall-bladder contained three
                                        ounces and six drachms of bile. The stomach was immensely
                                        distended and occupied the greater portion of the abdomen in
                                        an oblique position; its mucous membrane was softened and
                                        presented several minute black spots towards the pylorus;
                                        between its superior curvature and the gall-bladder was a
                                        small quantity of recent lymph. The small intestine was
                                        contracted; its mucous membrane was softened and varied in
                                        color from light pink to deep purple; the jejunum was filled
                                        with a glairy tenacious mass; the last two feet of the ileum
                                        presented well defined ulceration of Peyer's patches, the
                                        ulcers being mostly circular with ragged walls and an
                                        irregular base, which was generally stained of a dull-ochre
                                        color by the intestinal contents; near the
                                        ileo-c&#230;cal valve several of the ulcers ran
                                        together, forming a large ulcerated area, which, with its
                                        black indurated walls and yellowish base, stood out in
                                        strong relief against the purple, livid and congested mucous
                                        membrane. The large intestine was also much contracted, its
                                        rug&#230; elevated and coated with a tenacious mucoid
                                        secretion; no ulcers were found in it. The right kidney was
                                        congested, and several small spots of transuded blood were
                                        noticed on its external surface; the pelvis of the left
                                        kidney was similarly discolored.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. H.
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
