<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10928">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">C&#8212;&#8212;, Daniel</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e10928</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">144-145</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the inner table of the skull</term>
          <term>fractures of the vitreous table of the skull without fracture or depression of the
            outer table</term>
          <term>symptoms of cerebral disorder only within few hours of death</term>
          <term>pus found on surface of left hemisphere beneath depressed fracture</term>
          <term>musket ball inflicted transverse scalp wound near vertex, greater portion over right
            parietal</term>
          <term>intermittent fever</term>
          <term>autopsy performed</term>
          <term>depressed stellate fracture of parietal near sagittal suture</term>
          <term>abscess beneath depressed skull fracture</term>
          <term>contusion of parietal bone</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-30">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0184">
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 10.&#8212;<name type="person">Private Daniel
          C&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organizatiion">Co. D, 76th New York Volunteers</name>,
        was wounded at the <name type="battle" key="127">second battle of Bull Run</name>, <date
          type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30th, 1862</date>, by a musket ball which inflicted
        a long transverse scalp wound near the vertex, the greater portion of the wound being over
        the right parietal. The wounded man was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington"
          >Washington</name>, and thence to <name type="place">Annapolis</name>, where he was
        admitted to the General Hospital on <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-08">September
          8th</date>. He was suffering from intermittent fever, and this diagnosis was placed upon
        his bed card, the wound being regarded as trivial in its nature. Treatment was directed to
        the interruption of the febrile paroxysms, which recurred obstinately in spite of the free
        administration of preparations of quinia. On <date type="injury" when="1862-09-23">September
          23d</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">Assistant Surgeon J. W. Brewer</name> took charge
        of the patient. The remainder of this abstract is compiled from his interesting notes of the
        case. The wound looked well at this date, and gave the patient no uneasiness; it was covered
        by florid healthy granulations, and discharged, in small quantity, laudable pus. The man had
        had no chill for twenty-four hours. Quinine was continued in small doses, and a generous
        diet was ordered. On the following day, <choice>
          <orig>September 25th</orig>
          <reg>September 24th</reg>
        </choice>, the patient complained of acute pain over the lower lobe of the right lung. There
        was no modification of resonance on percussion; and auscultation revealed no alteration in
        the respiratory murmur. Stupes of turpentine were ordered, and an aperient dose. At noon the
        pain in the side was much relieved; but the patient complained of violent pain in the right
        ankle, and in the foot of the same side. The cause of this pain, or of its location, could
        not be ascertained. At night, the pain was not relieved, and the patient was becoming very
        restless and irritable, which led <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Brewer</name> to suspect
        some occult cerebral disorder, and again to examine the wound, and, finally, to request
          <name type="person" key="xx">Assistant Surgeon T. H. Helsby</name>, <name
          type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, to see the patient with him. A careful
        exploration of the wound failed to detect any injury of the bone, a granulating surface
        being everywhere presented. In the absence of any symptoms, except restlessness, that could
        be referred to cerebral disturbance, it was concluded that the wound had no connection with
        the existing pain and general irritability and the patient was ordered to have an anodyne,
        and a stimulating embrocation to the ankle. On the following morning, <date type="death"
          when="1862-09-25">September 25th, 1862</date>, coma suddenly supervened, and death
        promptly ensued. An autopsy was made, <date type="autopsy" when="1862-09-25">two hours after
          death</date>, by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon B. B. Miles</name>.
        The thoracic viscera were found to be in a normal condition, except that there was
        inflammatory engorgement, or possibly, hypostatic congestion only, of the lower lobe of the
        right lung. The abdominal viscera were carefully examined, but no cause of death could be
        found in that cavity. The <choice>
          <orig>calvaria</orig>
          <reg>calvarium</reg>
        </choice> was then removed. The dura mater was adherent to the bone beneath the site of the
        wound. A depressed stellate fracture of the vitreous table of the right parietal was
        discovered near the sagittal suture. A small quantity of pus followed the removal of the
        calvarium. On removing the dura mater, several ounces of pus were found on the surface of
        the left hemisphere. On closer examination, an aperture was discovered in the falx, and it
        became evident that an abscess had formed beneath the depressed fracture, and had burst
        through the falx, inundating the convolutions of the opposite hemisphere. The veins of the
        lower extremity, and of the lung were not examined, and whether the pain in the right foot
        and right chest were signs indicative of embolic complications resulting from the abscess
        was not determined. In concluding his report, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Brewer</name>
        again calls attention to the fact that no symptoms of encephalitis appeared in the case; but
        it is to be remembered that the chills, which were reported as paroxysms of intermittent
        fever, did not come under his observation, and that no record of their attendant symptoms
        has been preserved. The <choice>
          <orig>calvaria</orig>
          <reg>calvarium</reg>
        </choice> was sent to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> by
          <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Brewer</name>. (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 52 and
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 53.) The preparation is described in the Catalogue of the
        Surgical Section, (p. 8.) It is fairly represented in the foregoing wood-cuts as the vault
        of the cranium, showing a contusion of the right parietal bone at the middle of its superior
        border. The outer table is spongy, and a thin plate, one inch in length, is necrosed and
        partially separated. The internal table is fractured and slightly depressed, and shows
        traces of an attempt at repair.</p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001378.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 52.&#8212;Depressed fracture of vitreous table of the
          right parietal from gunshot contusion. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 662, Sect. I, A. M.
          M.</head>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001379.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 53.&#8212;Exterior view of the same specimen, showing
          the exfoliation resulting from the contusion. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 662, Sect. I,
          A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
