<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41929">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Campbell, Ephraim</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41929</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">517-518</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>morbid anatomy</term>
     <term>chronic inflammation of the intestines accompanied by follicular or other ulcers</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
     <term>fever</term>
     <term>dejections mixed with blood</term>
     <term>collapsed right lung</term>
     <term>right pleural cavity contained one gallon of sero-purulent fluid</term>
     <term>large abscess in upper liver communicated with pleural cavity through opening in
      diaphragm</term>
     <term>fifth, sixth and seventh ribs denuded of periosteum and bathed in pus</term>
     <term>omentum devoid of fat</term>
     <term>mesenteric glands enlarged</term>
     <term>mucous membrane of lower ileum coated with pseudomembrane, presented small follicular
      ulcers, Peyer's patches slightly thickened</term>
     <term>cæcum and colon studded with follicular ulcers, edges of many covered with
      pseudomembrane</term>
     <term>follicular ulcers of mucous surface of descending colon, smallest rounded and very
      minute, larger varying from ⅒th to ¼th of an inch in diameter, edges of most
      fringed with curdy yellow pseudomembrane</term>
     <term>appendix vermiformis and caecum showed similar ulcers</term>
     <term>flat new-formation of bony tissue</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p>The chromo plate facing page 520 represents follicular ulcers of the colon fringed with
    pseudomembrane. The following is an account of the case:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 902.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal Ephraim
     Campbell</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 150th Pennsylvania
     Volunteers</name>; age 24; was admitted to the field hospital of the first division, fifth army
    corps, near <name type="place">Petersburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-09-12">September 12, 1864</date>. Diarrhœa: for which he had been treated in his regimental
    hospital. <date type="transfer" when="1864-09-14">September 14th</date>, he was transferred to
    the hospital of the 3d division, fifth corps, and <date type="transfer" when="1864-09-29">September 29th</date>, to the depot hospital of the fifth corps, at <name type="place">City
     Point, Virginia</name>, where the diagnosis recorded was fever. Thence he was transferred to
     <name type="hospital" key="157">Columbian College hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., where he
    was admitted, <date type="admit" when="1864-10-30">October 30th</date>, suffering from all the
    symptoms of chronic diarrhœa. He was extremely emaciated, pulse 110 and small; had five or
    six loose dejections daily, and no appetite. Ordered hot fomentations to be applied to the
    abdomen, with rest in bed, and a diet of boiled milk and beef tea. November 2d, he reports that
    he feels better than on admission, and begins to relish his food a little, but the diarrhœa
    continues unabated. ℞. Chalk mixture three ounces, fluid extract of ginger half an ounce,
    tincture of cinchona one ounce; take a tablespoonful three times a day; continue the hot
    fomentations; extra diet. November 6th: Since the last note the patient has been better, but
    to-day is worse again. His bowels are moved every hour, and the dejections are mixed with blood;
    pulse 110 and thread like; abdomen tympanitic. His strength is less than yesterday; no appetite.
    Continue diet and treatment, with the addition of laudanum enemata. November 7th: The bowels are
    moved less frequently. The patient rested well last night, and has some appetite. Continue
    treatment. November 9th: Pulse 100; bowels again very loose, the dejections contain mucus and
    blood; appetite poor. Continue treatment. November 11th: The symptoms continue with little
    change, except that the patient complains of a dry cough at night; there is, however, no pain in
    the chest, and the respiration appears to be normal. Continue treatment, with the addition of a
    cough mixture containing syrup of senega and paregoric. November 14th: Pulse 96, skin dry and
    harsh, respiration 20 per minute, cough not so dry. The bowels were only moved twice since
    yesterday morning; appetite very poor. Continue treatment. November 15th: Pulse 108, respiration
    32, bowels moved twelve times since yesterday morning; the dejections are bloody, strength
    failing, no appetite. ℞. Brandy four ounces, carbonate of ammonia two scruples; take a
    tablespoonful every three hours; beef tea. November 16th: Pulse 100, respiration 32, bowels very
    loose, strength failing fast. Continue treatment and diet. Died <date type="death" when="1864-11-18">November 18th</date>. <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi>
    <date type="autopsy" when="1864-11-18">nine hours after death</date>: Body very much emaciated.
    The right pleural cavity contained one gallon of sero-purulent fluid. The right lung was
    collapsed, coated with lymph and carnified. The left lung was normal. There was a large abscess
    in the upper portion of the liver which communicated with the pleural cavity through an opening
    in the diaphragm three by four inches in diameter. The fifth, sixth and seventh ribs were
    denuded of periosteum and bathed in pus. The omentum was quite devoid of fat. The mesenteric
    glands were enlarged. The spleen was normal. The mucous membrane of the lower portion of the
    ileum was coated with pseudomembrane and presented a number of small follicular ulcers. Peyer's
    patches were slightly thickened. The cæcum and colon were thickly studded with follicular
    ulcers, the edges of many of which were covered with pseudomembrane.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. H. Wilson</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">U.
     S. A.</name> [Nos. 433-437, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
     Museum</name>, are from this case.]</p>
   <p>The specimens from this case were brought to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>
    immediately after the autopsy, and a drawing in water colors representing a portion of the
    descending colon was made by <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Hermann Faber</name>. The plate
    is a reproduction of this drawing. The mucous surface is seen to be generally reddened, with
    grayish streaks and patches. There are a considerable number of follicular ulcers, the smallest
    of which are rounded and very minute, while the larger ones, varying from ⅒th to ¼th
    of an inch in long diameter, are usually oval; the edges of most of these ulcers are fringed
    with curdy yellow pseudomembrane. The submucous tissue was considerably thickened, as is well
    shown on the left hand of the piece near the bottom where its edge comes into view. This
    specimen has been preserved in <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, No. 437,
    Medical Section. The other specimens from the same case are: No. 436, the appendix vermiformis
    and a part of the caecum, showing similar ulcers; No. 433, the collapsed right lung, thickly
    coated with pseudomembrane; No. 435, a portion of the liver, showing a large abscess cavity on
    its upper surface; and No. 434, the seventh rib, showing the effects of the burrowing of the pus
    from the abscess in its efforts to escape; the pulmonary surface of the bone is denuded of
    periosteum, and presents several flat new-formations of bony tissue. It would appear that in
    this case the large hepatic abscess entirely escaped observation during life, and the remark in
    the history of the case, on the 11th of November, only a week before death, that "the
    respiration appears to be normal," is worthy of note in connection with the considerable
    pleuritic effusion and collapse of the right lung, both of which undoubtedly existed before that
    time.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001508.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XXXI. FOLLICULAR ULCERS OF COLON.—CHRONIC
     DYSENTERY. The edges of many of the ulcers are fringed with pseudo-membrane.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
