<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10962">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Stone, Benjamin Y.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e10962</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">767</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases attributed to non-miasmatic exposures</term>
                                        <term>diseases of the respiratory organs</term>
                                        <term>pneumonia</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term> 
                                        <term>lobar pneumonias</term>
                                        <term>cases of marked typhoid symptoms unconnected with an enteric lesion</term>	
                                        <term>admitted with pneumonia</term>
                                        <term>deafness on both sides</term>   
                                        <term>nervous temperament, considerably depressed, mental anxiety</term>
                                        <term>subject to tertian intermittent fever and diarrh&#339;a</term>     
                                        <term>crepitus in lower lobes of lungs</term>
                                        <term>bronchial tubes dark-purple in color and filled with pus</term> 
                                        <term>upper lobe of lung hepatized gray and crepitant anteriorly, lower lobe brown in color</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-30">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                        
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>                       
                        <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 64.&#8212;<name type="person">Hospital Steward Benjamin Y. Stone</name>, <name type="organization">28th
                                Mich.</name>; age 28; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1865-02-14">Feb. 14, 1865</date>, with pneumonia.  The patient, of a nervous temperament, was considerably depressed and seemed to be laboring under mental anxiety. He said he had been subject to tertian intermittent fever and diarrh&#339;a, for which he had taken
                                        opium and quinine in large quantities. He was not much
                                        emaciated, but his pulse was weak and he had no appetite; a
                                        slight crepitus was detected in the lower lobes of the
                                        lungs; he had headache and some deafness on both sides. He
                                        continued to grow weaker and more depressed in mind, so
                                        that by the 20th he could not leave his bed. The diarrh&#339;a
                                        yielded readily, but the deafness increased; the pulse
                                        became thready and rose to 140; restlessness was followed by
                                        delirium, during which the patient wanted to sit up or kept
                                        picking at the bedclothes. He became drowsy on the 28th,
                                        but continued picking at the bedclothes until the coma
                                        deepened.  He died <date type="death" when="1865-03-03">March 3</date>.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The
                                        cerebral membranes were opaque and serum was effused
                                        beneath them; the brain was quite hard and rather pale; the
                                        choroid plexus pale, almost white near the foramen of Monro;
                                        the spinal cord was pale. The pericardium contained clear
                                        serum. The upper lobe of the right lung was soft, hepatized
                                        gray behind and crepitant only in its anterior edge; its
                                        bronchial tubes were full of pus; the lower lobe was brown
                                        in color and sank in water; its tubes were dark-purple and thickened. A patch of strong adhesion was
                                        found on the external surface of the left lung, the upper
                                        lobe of which was crepitant but softened and presented a
                                        little cicatrix at the posterior part of its apex; the lower
                                        lobe was softened and spotted with blackish or brownish-red
                                        patches in a gray or pinkish-gray crepitant tissue; the
                                        bronchial tubes, dark-purple in color, were filled with
                                        pus. The liver was soft, pale-yellow and of good size; the
                                        spleen soft and small. The ileum was full of air and
                                        slightly injected, but otherwise normal. The kidneys were
                                        fatty and injected with dark blood.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="189">Third Division Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name></hi>  </p>                
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
