<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40875">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Mehn, Jacob</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40875</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">149</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Douglas Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>typhoid fever</term>
       <term>micturition painful, urine normal</term>
       <term>small intestine injected in patches</term>
       <term>c&#230;cum contained small superficial ulcers</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon presented numerous large ulcers, coated with pseudomembrane between them</term>
       <term>large irregular diphtheritic ulcer penetrated muscular coat of colon</term>          
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="162"><hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>OUGLAS <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from February, 1863, to September, 1864, and after September, 1865:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 302.&#8212;<name type="person" key="204">Private Jacob Mehn</name>, <name type="organization" key="228">company I, 108th New York volunteers</name>; age 34; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-13">February 13, 1863</date>.  Typhoid fever.  This man was taken sick at <name type="place">Aquia Creek</name> and brought here in a very low and emaciated condition after being sick three weeks. He was very feeble; pulse 110; tongue clean and red; stools liquid and frequent. He was treated with powders of opium and tannin; diet of scalded milk.  February 27th: Somewhat better; pulse 95; tongue clean and moist; some appetite; stools less frequent. To take powders containing three grains of quinine and one-twelfth of a grain of morphia three times daily.  March 2d: Pulse 85; skin moist tongue clean but rather dry; bowels moved three times during the day; some tenderness in the umbilical and left iliac regions. Continue treatment; two eggs daily.  March 12th: Appearance improved, looked much brighter and seems stronger; has moderate appetite; three stools in twenty-four hours; is still very feeble and greatly emaciated, but there is now no abdominal tenderness; tongue slightly red on the edges and inclined to dryness. Since the 6th has had suppositories of opium and tannin after each stool; milk-punch and beef-tea every four hours.  March 17th: Is worse again; abdomen tympanitic and tender, the tenderness being greatest over the descending colon; there is no tenesmus; tongue and skin dry. Continue treatment.  March 18th: Very weak; pulse 140; tongue and skin dry; considerable thirst; abdomen very tender and tympanitic. He complains of much pain in the epigastric region; had two stools in the last twenty-four hours, they were light-yellow and liquid; there is no tenesmus; micturition painful; the urine normal. The stomach retains stimulants and nourishment very well, but digestion and assimilation are wanting, and emaciation steadily progresses.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-03-19">March 19th</date>.&#8212;<name type="person" key="203">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. L. W. Burritt</name>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> Emaciation extreme. There were recent pleuritic adhesions of the lower lobe of the right lung, which was hepatized; the rest of the right lung and the left lung were normal. The heart was small but normal. The liver presented the nutmeg appearance; it was one-third larger than natural. The spleen was somewhat indurated. The pancreas was firm. The kidneys were natural in size and texture, but the cortical portion was somewhat pale. Stomach much contracted. The lower part of the small intestine was injected in patches. The c&#230;cum contained a number of small superficial ulcers. The mucous membrane of the colon was somewhat thickened, and presented numerous large ulcers, between which the mucous membrane was coated with pseudomembrane. In this case no symptoms observed during life culled attention to the pulmonary lesion.&#8212;<name type="person" key="205">Acting Assistant Surgeon F. M. Holly</name>.  [Nos. 288 and 289, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case. The specimens are successive portions of the colon. In No. 288 the mucous membrane is irregularly coated with pseudomembrane; in the lower portion of the piece is a large irregular diphtheritic ulcer which penetrates to the muscular coat. In No. 289 there are several similar ulcers, but the mucous membrane between them presents very little adherent pseudomembrane.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
