<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41917">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Coleman, T. P.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41917</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">512-513</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
     <term>chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>morbid anatomy</term>
     <term>chronic inflammation of the mucous and submucous coats of the intestines without
      ulceration</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>ball passed through lower chest, fractured eleventh rib and transverse process of
      eleventh dorsal vertebra, probably wounded lung</term>
     <term>ball lodged behind tenth rib</term>
     <term>free hæmorrhage from wound, spat blood, great difficulty breathing</term>
     <term>diarrhœa, dysenteric character</term>
     <term>dysenteric diarrhœa</term>
     <term>pleural sac contained sanguineous effusion</term>
     <term>lower lobe of lung converted into abscess cavity containing lung substance, external
      walls adherent to costal pleura</term>
     <term>liver and kidneys fatty</term>
     <term>in descending colon and rectum solitary follicles enlarged and formed cyst-like vesicles
      containing transparent gelatinous mass</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p>There is, however, a curious lesion occasionally encountered in such cases which deserves
    remark in this place. I allude to the development beneath the mucous membrane of small cysts
    containing a thick mucoid or glue-like fluid. These vary in size from ⅒th to ¼th of
    an inch in diameter, and project from the surface in the form of hemispheres; they are sometimes
    observed in cases of well marked follicular ulceration, but also occur in cases in which no
    ulceration can be detected. The latter condition was noted in the specimen represented by the
    chromo plate facing this page. The patient was a confederate prisoner of war, who died of
    dysenteric diarrhœa of nearly three months duration, which made its appearance while he was
    under treatment for a gunshot wound of the chest. The following is a brief history of the
    case:⃰</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 899.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private T. P.
     Coleman</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company A, 19th Mississippi (confederate)
     volunteers</name>; age 19; was wounded <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">near Petersburg,
     Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-11-05">November 5, 1864</date>, by a ball which
    passed through the lower portion of the left side of his chest, fracturing the eleventh rib and
    the transverse process of the eleventh dorsal vertebra, and probably wounding the lung. He was
    treated at first in a confederate hospital at <name type="place">Richmond, Virginia</name>, and,
     <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-06">May 6, 1865</date>, was transferred to the hospital at
     <name type="place">Point Lookout, Maryland</name>. Thence, <date type="transfer" when="1865-07-24">July 24th</date>, he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., and finally, <date type="transfer" when="1865-08-17">August 17th</date>, to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas
     hospital</name>. The patient stated that on the reception of the injury he had a free
    hæmorrhage from the wound, spat blood and had great difficulty in breathing, but that he
    was doing well under treatment, when, about <date type="injury" when="1865-06-01">the beginning
     of June</date>, while still at <name type="place">Point Lookout</name>, diarrhœa set in
    and persisted in spite of treatment. When he entered <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas
     hospital</name> he was still suffering from diarrhœa, which was of a dysenteric character,
    and he was terribly emaciated. <date type="operation" when="1865-08-18">August 18th</date>, the
    ball, which had lodged behind the tenth rib, about an inch and a half from the wound of
    entrance, was removed by <name type="person" key="201">Asst. Surgeon Wm. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> His dysenteric diarrhœa was treated by
    nitrate of silver, used both internally and by injection. He could hardly be prevailed upon to
    take beef tea or milk, which appeared to make him vomit, but he swallowed whiskey greedily, and
    it was freely administered. He was restless and noisy, but did not complain of dyspnœa, and
    had no cough. He sank rapidly, and died <date type="death" when="1865-08-19">August 19th</date>.
     <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi>
    <date type="autopsy" when="1865-08-19">thirteen hours after death</date>: The right pleural sac
    contained three ounces of sanguineous effusion, and there were old pleuritic adhesions on both
    sides. The lungs were crepitant, with the exception of the lower lobe of the left lung, which
    was converted into an abscess cavity containing detritus of lung substance, and the external
    walls of which were inseparably adherent to the costal pleura. The liver and kidneys were fatty;
    the spleen contained less blood than usual. The small intestine was pale; in the descending
    colon and the rectum the solitary follicles were enlarged, forming cyst-like vesicles the size
    of peas, with minute circular openings at their summits, and each containing a transparent
    gelatinous mass. History by <name type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon Carlos
     Carvallo</name>. [Specimens, viz: No. 660, Medical Section, and No. 1561, Surgical Section,
    (the injured ribs,) presented by <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon Wm. F.
     Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>]</p>
   <p>The diseased intestine was brought to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>
    immediately after the autopsy, and a water-color drawing, representing a portion of descending
    colon, was made by Mr. Hermann Faber; the chromo plate is a reproduction of this drawing. The
    colon was moderately thickened; the general surface of its mucous membrane was pearl-gray, with
    greenish and bluish streaks and patches. There were also a number of reddish patches in which
    congested <choice>
     <sic>bloodvessels</sic>
     <corr>blood vessels</corr>
    </choice> could be distinctly recognized by the naked eye. The cysts varied in size from
    ⅒th of an inch or less to ¼th of an inch in diameter; for the most part they were of
    a bluish color, which in the larger cysts became a dark indigo-blue. At the apices of some of
    them the yellowish contents shone through, or protruded through tiny circular orifices; these
    contents could readily be expelled by pressure, and resembled drops of warm boiled glue. The
    cysts were very unequally scattered over the mucous surface; in some places they were so close
    as to be in contact; in others they were an inch or more apart. No ulceration was detected
    anywhere. The minute anatomy of these cysts will be discussed in a subsequent part of this
    section.</p>
   <p>⃰ The history of this case is also given in the first Surgical Volume, p. 568. The
    account there presented differs from that in the text in stating the diarrhœa to have
    commenced "about the middle of June," and in speaking of the solitary glands of the
    colon as "ulcerated." The latter statement is certainly an error, as shown by the
    specimen, and the former is probably so, as the case-book of the hospital explicitly says
    "about the beginning of June." Both errors occur in the history, sent to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> with the specimens, from which the account in the
    Surgical Volume was taken, while the history as given above was extracted from the case-book of
    the hospital, which is the original record.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001504.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XXVII. COLLOID CYSTS OF COLON.—CHRONIC
     DYSENTERY.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
