<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31545">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">M——, D. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31545</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mbo">Miguel Beltran-Orozco</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">67, 134, 163</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the liver</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>fatal shot wounds of the liver</term> 
       <term>barely survived rail transit, expired in ambulance wagon</term>
       <term>shot through body, ball entered flank and escaped from epigastric region</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of abdomen, simple dressing</term>
       <term>profuse bleeding when moved</term>
       <term>ball entered right hypochondrium at edge of twelfth rib, scraped off outer lamina of rib, penetrated kidney, deflected by vertebral column, passed through duodenum, stomach, and liver, then emerged below end of ensiform cartilage</term>
       <term>blood in peritoneal cavity</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2014-07-03">corrected typo in final figure spec</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb-o" when="2011-02-19">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 452.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal D. H. M——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. H, 6th Pennsylvania Cavalry</name>, in a cavalry engagement near <name type="BATTLE" key="107">Brandy Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-08-01">August 1, 1863</date>, was shot through the body, the ball entering the right flank and escaping from the left of the epigastric region.  There is no account of the symptoms observed at the field hospital station, which was crowded with wounded. The name, military description, and entry, "gunshot wound of the abdomen, simple dressing," constitute the only field record. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-08-02">August 2nd</date>, the corporal was transferred by rail to <name type="place">Washington</name>, a distance of forty miles. He barely survived the transit, and expired, in an ambulance wagon on the way to <name type="place">Douglas Hospital</name>. The dressings and clothing were saturated with blood, and there had evidently been very profuse bleeding after he was moved from the car to the wagon.  At the autopsy, made by <name type="person" key="xxx">Medical Cadet Edward D. Mitchell</name>, it was inferred, from the size of the wounds of entrance and exit, that they were inflicted by a carbine ball. The notes of the autopsy describe a very erratic course of the projectile; but if the position of the entrance and exit wounds is correctly indicated, it must be inferred that the ball entered the right hypochondrium at the edge of the twelfth rib, scraping oft its outer lamina about two and one-half inches from its free extremity, and passed inward and downward, penetrating the right kidney , and was then deflected by the vertebral column, and passed upward through the duodenum, the posterior and anterior walls of the stomach, the left lobe of the liver near the umbilical fissure (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 106), and emerged two inches to the left and below the end of the ensiform cartilage; or its course may have been the reverse of that described. The intestines were inflated. There was a great quantity of blood in the peritoneal cavity. The emulgent vessels had bled with especial freedom.  The perforation of the liver is represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 106).  The wound of the duodenum is figured on page 67, and there will be a drawing of the perforation of the kidney in the subsection on wounds of that organ.</p>    
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001761.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 106.—Segment of the left lobe of the liver, perforated by a carbine ball.     <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1645.     [Reduced to one-fourth.]</head>
   </figure>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001762.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 43.—Shot perforation of the duodenum.     <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1772.</head>
   </figure>   
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001763.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 125.—Section of a kidney with a shot perforation from before backward.     <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1773.</head>
   </figure>   
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
