<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6024">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Brown, Joseph</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6024</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">113-114</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary excisions</term>
     <term>foliaceous masses of callus</term>
     <term>ball passed through thigh, fracturing femur below trochanter minor</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>swelling of thigh, pus burrowed amid muscles</term>
     <term>symptoms of typhoid</term>
     <term>false joint with shortening of limb</term>
     <term>suppuration profuse, pus amid muscles</term>
     <term>general an&#230;sthesia, not specified</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-21">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 261.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Joseph
     Brown</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 3d Michigan</name>, aged 38 years, was
    wounded at the <name type="BATTLE" key="127">second battle of Bull Run</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1862-08-29">August 29, 1862</date>, by a musket ball, which passed through
    the left thigh, fracturing the femur just below the trochanter minor. He laid on the battle
    field three days, and was <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-01">then</date> removed to <name
     type="place">Centreville</name>. On <date type="admit" when="1862-09-11">September 11,
     1862</date>, he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="214">Fairfax Seminary
     Hospital</name>, near <name type="place">Alexandria</name>. The limb was kept in position by
    appropriate apparatus; but suppuration was profuse, and, on two occasions, fragments of bone
    were removed from the wound. Early in <date type="injury" when="1863-03">March, 1863</date>,
    there was great swelling of the thigh, the discharge became scanty and fetid, and pus burrowed
    amid the muscles. On <date type="operation" when="1863-03-21">March 21st</date>, an exploratory
    incision was made from three inches above to five inches below the prominence of the great
    trochanter. The neck and upper extremity of the shaft of the femur were found to be extensively
    diseased, and excision was decided on. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon D. P. Smith</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, performed the operation. Difficulty was
    experienced in separating the muscular attachments from the trochanters, on account of the
    foliaceous masses of callus that had been thrown out. When this dissection was accomplished,
    many necrosed fragments were extracted, and the periosteum and new bone were separated by the
    handle of the scalpel and preserved as far as practicable. The shaft of the femur was then
    divided by powerful cutting bone forceps, about six inches below the tip of the great
    trochanter. A screw was driven into the mass of callus, below the trochanters, to be used as a
    lever in disarticulating the head, but it would not hold, and the bone was seized with large
    forceps and rotated, so as to facilitate the division of the capsular and round ligaments. The
    head, neck, and trochanters, and the masses of callus adhering to the trochanters, were then
    removed. The operation was accomplished with but very trifling h&#230;morrhage, yet great
    prostration followed, and the patient rallied slowly. As the an&#230;sthesia passed off, he had
    much nausea and vomiting. As soon as this subsided, he was given a very full allowance of
    concentrated nourishment, such as strong beef-tea, eggs, milk, etc, with half an ounce of brandy
    every two hours. The wound was partially closed; the limb was supported on pillows until the
    third day, when it was dressed in a Smith's anterior splint. About <date type="operation"
     when="1863-03-23">forty-eight hours after the operation</date>, an erysipelatous blush pervaded
    the limb, and the constitutional symptoms assumed a typhoid character. A female catheter was
    passed through the middle of the wound and another at its lower extremity, through which much
    offensive decomposed serum and grumous blood escaped. The wound was thoroughly washed out
    through the catheters with warm water impregnated with chlorinated soda. On the fifth day there
    was a rigor, and h&#230;morrhage to the extent of six ounces. As the anterior splint did not
    permit convenient access to the limb, it was removed, and the leg and thigh were suspended in a
    canvas hammock, the leg being horizontal and the thigh in an almost vertical position. A piece
    of soft toweling extending from the perineum to the popliteal space, and, connected by cords
    with an upright post at the head of the bed, supported the muscles on the sides and under
    surface of the thigh. The wound freely discharged synovia, bloody serum, and thin pus, until the
    seventh day, when healthy suppuration was fairly established. During April, 1863, the patient's
    progress was satisfactory. He was supplied with very nutritious diet, with porter, and cod-liver
    oil. He took for a time as much as a half a pint of oil daily. During May, the case continued to
    progress favorably. It was necessary to keep a tube in the wound until June 1st. Previously,
    whenever it was removed pus would accumulate and burrow. A mesh of suture wire was finally
    substituted for the tube. This was retained until June 20th, when the patient began to get about
    on crutches. In the <date type="injury" when="1863-07">latter part of July</date> the wounds
    closed. In August, Brown was reported as &#34;well,&#34; and on <date type="servicedischarge"
     when="1863-08-23">August 23, 1863</date>, he was discharged from the hospital and from the
    military service of the United States. On <date type="pension" when="1864-03-21">March 21,
     1864</date>, he wrote from his home in <name type="place">Coopersville, Michigan</name>, that
    his health was good; that he could get about and attend to home business; could saw and split a
    little wood for fuel, though his knee was stiff and his leg painful. On the whole, there had
    been steady improvement. In <date type="pension" when="1865-09">September, 1865</date>, he again
    wrote, and stated that his general health was good; that he had some control over the movements
    of the thigh, being able, when standing on the right foot, to swing the left backward and
    forward, and to adduct the thigh enough to carry the injured limb across the other. He could
    bear some weight on the limb, and use but one crutch, with a stirrup for the foot. There had
    been no fistulous orifices since March 1864, and there was no soreness about the cicatrices. In
     <date type="pension" when="1865-11">November, 1865</date>, in accordance with a request from
    the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name>, <name type="person"
     key="xxx">Mr. Brown</name> had a photograph (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 69) taken to
    represent the amount of deformity in his limb. This picture is numbered 110 in the Photograph
    Series of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>. It is carefully copied
    in the accompanying wood-cut. The excised bone is preserved at <name type="hospital" key="431"
     >the Museum</name>, and is numbered 1192, Section I. It is represented in the adjacent wood-cut
     (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 68). On <date type="pension" when="1868-02-12">February 12,
     1868</date>, he wrote to the compiler of this report: &#34;I take pleasure in informing you
    that my limb is in as good condition as when I last wrote you; but think there is no
    improvement, except that it is not as tender. There have been no abscesses, nor any pain in the
    limb, excepting slight pains about the knee, just before storms. About two years ago, I slipped
    and fell upon the ice, injuring the limb severely about the knee, and was thereby confined to
    the house for about three weeks. In March last I had a severe attack of ague. The limb swelled
    quite badly at this time, and was much inflamed for about ten days. I applied cold water and a
    bandage to reduce the swelling. I had to keep it bandaged about two weeks after the inflammation
    was removed. Since that time the limb has given me no more trouble than usual. Since I was
    discharged I cannot see that there is any lengthening of the limb. I have to use a crutch and
    cane all the time when moving about, and I think I shall always have to do this. The injured
    limb has wasted away somewhat since I last wrote. The circumference of the well limb at the
    upper extremity is 22 inches, and the injured limb measures at the same place 19&#189; inches.
    The knee of the well limb measures around the centre of the knee-pan 15&#189; inches; the
    injured limb measures at the same place 17 inches. The above measurements were made in the
    evening; I think that in the morning the measurements of the injured limb would be less. The
    knee still remains quite stiff, and gives me about all the pain there is anywhere in the limb. I
    have been troubled during cold weather by coldness of the outer side of the leg, and I have to
    warm it by the fire before going to bed nearly every night when I have been out.&#34; On <date
     type="pension" when="1868-11-19">November 19, 1868</date>, another letter was received from Mr.
    Brown, from which the following extract is made: &#34;I take pleasure in informing you that my
    limb is in as good condition as it has been at any time since it was entirely healed, and, if
    anything, in better condition. It does not pain me about the knee as much as it did one year
    ago. It does not have any spell of swelling at the knee as it did for the first two years after
    my discharge, and there is less soreness about the limb than there was even one year ago. I can
    get around without hurting it as much as formerly. I can bear some weight upon it. I have walked
    across a room without the aid of crutch or cane, by stepping very quick with the well limb; but
    it is more like hopping than walking. There have been no abscesses in the limb. I think that it
    is gradually improving, and hope that I may yet see the day that I can go without a crutch. My
    general health is good. I have not been sick a day for a year and a half, and then only a few
    days with ague. My weight now is 167&#189; pounds. Before I entered the army my weight was never
    quite up to those figures, but within a few pounds of it. I have been postmaster at this office
    over a year, and have attended to all the business of the office almost entirely without
    assistance, and it gives me pretty good exercise.&#34; On <date type="pension" when="1875-09-06"
     >September 6, 1875</date>, the date of his last examination for pension, the <name
     type="organization" key="xxx">Grand Rapids Examining Board</name> stated: &#34;There is now a
    false joint with shortening of the limb.&#34; Since then this pensioner has been exempted from
    further surgical examinations. He was paid <date type="pension" when="1877-09-04">September 4,
     1877</date>, remaining in comparatively good health more than fourteen years after the
    operation. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001542.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 68.&#8212;Head, neck, and trochanters of left femur, with
     foliaceous callus. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1192.</head>
   </figure>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001543.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 69.&#8212;Appearance of limb three years after the operation.
     [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
