<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41257">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Morris, Lindsey</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41257</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">182</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a and debility</term>
       <term>peritonitis</term>
       <term>abscesses on front of abdomen</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of whole small intestine inflamed, lower ileum studded with ulcers</term>
       <term>condition of large intestine not recorded</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 416.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Lindsey Morris</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company A, 140th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 20; admitted from the depot hospital of the 2d Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-11-14">November 14, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a and debility.  This man was taken sick <date type="injury" when="1864-10-20">October 20, 1864</date>. At the time of admission he was very much exhausted; extremely emaciated; had no appetite; pulse 110 and weak; urine scanty and light colored; bowels loose. Treatment: Quinine, beef-tea, and brandy.  November 19th: He was attacked with vomiting, ejecting a greenish acrid fluid. Applied a blister to the epigastrium, and directed him to take, every four hours, a powder containing two grains of calomel, half a grain of opium, one and a half of quinine, and four of prepared chalk.  November 24th: The vomiting still continues. Ordered enemata of quinine and beef-tea three times daily.  December 1st: The abdomen is so tender that peritonitis is <choice><orig>diagnosticated</orig><reg>diagnosed</reg></choice>, and warm fomentations applied to the abdomen.  December 4th: The patient lies constantly on his back; pulse 90 and weak.  <date type="operation" when="1864-12-06">December 6th</date>: Eight abscesses were recognized on the front of the abdomen, and being opened discharged freely. The discharge was kept up by warm poultices; at the same time the injections of beef-tea and quinine were continued, as the patient was still unable to keep anything on his stomach.  December 10th: The discharge from the abscesses is lessening. Continued the warm applications over the abdomen.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-12-22">December 22d</date>.  From the time this patient was admitted till his death there was constant nausea and vomiting; during the last few days the injections were not retained.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon E. B. Harris</name>.   <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-12-23">sixteen hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis well marked; body very much emaciated. On the surface of the abdomen there were a number of small punctures which led to little abscess cavities, none of which extended beneath the external oblique muscle or its tendon. The brain weighed forty-seven ounces and a half. The larynx, trachea and lungs were normal. The right lung weighed eighteen ounces, the left nine and a half. The heart was normal, weight nine ounces and a half; each ventricle contained a very small fibrinous clot. The spleen was normal. The liver weighed forty-nine ounces and a half; it was very much congested, and on section a large amount of dark blood exuded; the gall bladder contained four ounces of very dark viscid bile. Both kidneys were apparently normal in texture, but large; the right weighed nine ounces and a half, and the left ten ounces. The lining membrane of the &#339;sophagus was slightly congested, but the stomach appeared to be normal. Throughout the whole length of the small intestine the mucous membrane appeared to be inflamed, and in the lower half of the ileum it was studded with ulcers about a line in diameter. The mesenteric glands appeared to be perfectly normal, varying from the size of a pea to that of a very small almond.  [The condition of the large intestine is not recorded.]&#8212;<name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
