<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2919">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Taggart, M. R.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e2919</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">229</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>clinical records</term>
          <term>continued fevers</term>
          <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
          <term>seminary hospital cases</term>
          <term>rose-spots</term> 
          <term>vibices</term>
          <term>bowel affection not prominent until cessation of perspirations</term> 
          <term> tenderness in right iliac region</term> 
          <term>profuse perspiration</term>
          <term>typhoid cases</term>
          <term>enteric fever</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00049">
      
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 49.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Relapse. Head symptoms
            not marked; rose-spots from the 41st to the 59th day; vibices on 50th; bowel affection
            not prominent until cessation of perspirations; returned to duty in 160
            days.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="509">Private M. R. Taggart</name>, <name
            type="organization" key="619">Co. A, 9th Pa. Vols.</name>; age 34; was admitted <date
              type="admit" when="1861-10-10">Oct. 10, 1861</date>, having been sick since <date type="injury" when="1861-09-01">Sept. 1</date> with
          what had been regarded as enteric fever, for which quinine had been given. On admission
          his eyes were dull, face congested, pulse 110, quick and full, skin hot and dry, tongue
          moist, red at tip and edges, coated white in the centre, appetite poor; he had some cough.
          Dover's powder was given. He slept badly during the night and next day was stupid and
          dull-eyed; a few rose-colored spots were found on the chest and many on the abdomen; the
          pulse was 100 and feeble; his bowels had not been moved. Tincture of iron was ordered to
          be taken three times daily and extract of senna in the evening. He slept well, and on the
          morning of the 12th the pulse was found to have fallen to 90; the eyes were bright and the
          flush had disappeared from the face; the bowels had not been moved, but there was much
          tenderness in the right iliac region. On the 13th the patient was covered with a profuse
          perspiration; pulse 120 and feeble; a slight epistaxis had occurred and one stool had been
          obtained. Tincture of digitalis and sweet spirit of nitre were ordered to be taken four
          times during the day. The perspiration continued on the 14th, and the appetite was found
          to be improved. Five grains of quinine were given every two hours. On the 15th the pulse
          had fallen to 90 and was more regular, the skin was hot but somewhat moist, the tongue
          dry, the appetite poor; the bowels had been moved twice. On the morning of the 16th the
          skin was dry, but there had been a profuse perspiration during the night; the tongue was
          red and clean but dry, and the appetite poor; one stool was passed, and the patient was
          troubled with cough. Profuse perspiration recurred nightly until the 22d. On the 17th the
          tongue became moist and covered with white patches. Next day a few rose-spots appeared on
          the abdomen; two stools were passed, and there was slight umbilical tenderness. On the
          19th the profuse perspiration continued during the day; the pulse rose to 120; tympanites
          and borborygmus were present but no stool was passed. Several rose-spots and vibices
          appeared on the abdomen on the 20th; pulse 86; two stools were passed. The skin was soft
          and natural on the 21st, and next day the tongue was clean and moist and the appetite
          good. During the following week an occasional nocturnal perspiration was noted, but
          otherwise the condition of the patient was good. On the 29th some rose-spots appeared and
          three stools were passed. Four stools were recorded on the following day, and on the 31st
          nine stools, with dry tongue, heat of skin and accelerated pulse. Twelve stools were
          passed on <date type="transfer" when="1861-11-01">November 1</date>, on which day the
          patient was transferred to <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name> [where his case was diagnosed typhoid fever, and
          terminated in a return to duty on <date type="duty" when="1862-03-19">March 19,
            1862</date>]. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
