<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e4126">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Forsyth, S. H.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e4126</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">240-241</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>  
                                        <term>aguish paroxysms preceded continued fever</term>         
                                        <term>cerebral symptoms marked</term>
                                        <term>intestinal and pulmonary symptoms obscured</term> 
                                        <term>chills, nausea and vomiting</term>
                                        <term>rose-colored spots</term>
                                        <term>sordes</term>
                                        <term>anorexia</term> 
                                        <term>epistaxis</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00096">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 96.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Cerebral symptoms strongly marked; intestinal and
                                                pulmonary symptoms obscured; death on 19th
                                                day.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="554">Corporal S. H. Forsyth</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="632">Co. A, 3d Pa.
                                                        Cav.</name>; age 33; was taken sick <date type="injury" when="1861-09-07">Sept. 7, 1861</date>,
                                        with chills, nausea and vomiting, which recurred for
                                        three days. He was admitted on <date type="admit"
                                                when="1861-09-14">the 14th</date>.
                                        Diagnosis&#8212;typhoid fever. He had pain in the head
                                        and bones, increased heat of skin, tinnitus aurium, <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice>
                                        of intellect and occasional epistaxis. A bath was ordered
                                        for him and Dover's powder at night. He rested well, his
                                        bowels remaining quiet although somewhat swollen and tender;
                                        the tongue was brown and dry. Turpentine emulsion was given
                                        every two hours. On the 16th the pulse was 106 and strong,
                                        tongue brown, bowels regular but tympanitic, skin hot and
                                        dry, showing some rose-colored spots; there was anorexia and
                                        occasional epistaxis. He was restless during the night, and
                                        on the 17th became somewhat delirious, dull and drowsy; the
                                        pulse was 106 but weaker; the bowels regular but distended.
                                        A few rose-colored spots appeared on the 18th, and one
                                        dark-colored stool was passed. The tongue was tremulous and
                                        protruded with difficulty on the 19th, and the teeth were
                                        black with sordes. In the evening the tongue was dry, red at
                                        the tip and edges and black in the centre and at the base,
                                        beef-essence and whiskey-punch were prescribed. On the 20th
                                        the eyes were suffused, pupils contracted, pulse 116, skin
                                        hot and dry but soft, teeth and lips covered with sordes,
                                        breathing labored, bowels quiet but tympanitic and gurgling
                                        on pressure. In the evening the pulse had risen to 126; a
                                        slight perspiration bedewed the forehead and arms and a few
                                        rose-colored spots appeared on the chest and abdomen; the
                                        delirium was accompanied by some deafness and muscular
                                        twitchings, but the respiration had become quiet and
                                        natural. Two days were passed without material change, but
                                        on the 23d the respiration became increased to 35; the skin
                                        was moist and hot, hands cold and clammy, pulse 136, small
                                        and tremulous, bowels quiet but largely meteorized, urine
                                        passed involuntarily. Tincture of capsicum was given and a
                                        blister and bandage applied to the abdomen. On the 24th the
                                        pulse reached 144 and was very feeble; the face was covered
                                        with sweat, the hands cold and damp, the feet warm; the
                                        patient was somewhat conscious but very deaf, and he had
                                        some difficulty in swallowing. A tube was passed to relieve
                                        the tympanites. On <date type="death" when="1861-09-25">the 25th</date> he was unconscious, muttering in his
                                        delirium, pulse 148, features pinched, forehead flushed,
                                        nose and lips blanched, eyes sunken and injected, cornea
                                        dull and partly glazed, extremities pulseless, heart's
                                        action feeble, skin of body warm and bedewed with
                                        perspiration, hands shrunken, damp and cold, tongue dry,
                                        brown and badly fissured, lips and teeth covered with
                                        dark-brown sordes; he was very deaf, had violent subsultus,
                                        dysphagia, involuntary urination and excessive tympanites,
                                        but no movement of the bowels; respiration was slow and
                                        labored. He died on this day. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
