<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31499">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">R——, Frank</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31499</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ks">Kelsey Swaney</persName>  
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">23</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>visceral injuries without external wounds</term>
       <term>ruptures of the intestines</term>
       <term>kicked by horse in lower umbilical region</term>
       <term>aged 11 years</term> 
       <term>vomiting blood</term>
       <term>expired twenty-four hours after injury</term>
       <term>small rupture in middle of jejunum</term> 
       <term>abdominal tenderness extended to hepatic region in right hypochondrium</term>
       <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>        
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#ks" when="2011-02-19">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>  
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 119.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Frank R——</name>, aged 11 years, a servant of <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Smoot</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Ordnance Corps</name>, was kicked by a horse in the lower umbilical region, while assisting a child to mount. On receiving the blow he ran to the house and examined the injured part, and then walked a short distance to his mother's quarters, crying. He was put to bed, and was presently attended by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. J. S. Kennedy</name>, who found him, half an hour after the reception of the injury, vomiting blood, complaining of great nausea, and great tenderness over the umbilical region, but of no acute pain. The pulse was accelerated and the heat of surface augmented. There was no abrasion or visible contusion of the surface. An anodyne was prescribed, and absolute rest in the easiest posture.  At the Doctor's second visit in the evening, the stomach was less irritable, but the abdominal tenderness was extreme, and extended to the hepatic region, and was attended with much pain, referred chiefly to the right hypochondrium. During the night, the febrile disturbance augmented; there was excessive restlessness and anxiety, with occasional retching. In the morning, <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Kennedy</name> found the little patient almost moribund; a clammy sweat covered the surface; the pulse was rapid and thready; the patient was conscious and free from pain.  He never rallied from this condition, and expired twenty-four hours after the reception of the injury. The remains were sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where a <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination was made by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. J. F. Hartigan</name>. Careful inspection could not reveal the slightest contusion or ecchymosis externally, nor extravasation in the abdominal muscles. About half a pint of clear serum was contained in the cavity of the abdomen; the peritoneum was agglutinated in various parts, and bands of lymph covered the intestines. About the middle of the jejunum there was found a small rupture of about half an inch, irregular in shape, surrounded with coagula.  The other organs were healthy.  The notes of the cases, and the specimen, No. 6188, represented in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE  I, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. J. F. Hartigan</name>.</p> 
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001757.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  I.     RUPTURE  OF  THE  JEJUNUM  BY  THE  KICK  OF  A  HORSE.     No. 6188.  SURGICAL  SECTION.</head>
   </figure> 
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
