<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18937">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Foulkrod, Samuel</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e18937</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">449-450</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the spine</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the spine</term>
          <term>gunshot injuries of the lumbar vertebr&#230;</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the apophyses of the lumbar spine</term>
          <term>lumbar vertebr&#230; implicated</term>
          <term>thoracic and abdominal viscera implicated</term>
          <term>thoracentesis</term>
          <term>pneumo-hydro-thorax</term>
          <term>erysipelas on face</term>
          <term>wound abscesses in sacral region</term>
          <term>acute pleurisy</term>
          <term>effusion in pleural sac</term>
          <term>phthisis pulmonalis</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Corporal Samuel Foulkrod</name>, <name type="organization">Co. G, 56th Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>, aged 34 years, was
        wounded at the <name type="BATTLE" key="259">the Wilderness, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-06">May 6th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the
        back in the lumbar region, and lodged. He was treated in the field, and, on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-12">May 12th</date>, sent
        to the <name type="hospital" key="189">3d division hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>. It was thought that some of the vertebral processes
        were shattered. Several fragments of bone came away, and the wound healed very slowly. After
        the wound healed, abscesses formed in the sacral region from time to time, which gave vent
        to considerable purulent collections. He was transferred, on <date type="duty" when="1864-10-08">October 8th 1864</date>, to the 102d
        company, 2d battalion, <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve Corps</name>. On <date type="injury" when="1865-02-11">February 11th, 1865</date>, the patient had an
        attack of acute pleurisy. Wet cups were applied to the right chest, and six or eight ounces
        of blood withdrawn. This was followed by fomentations and purgatives, with an anodyne at
        night. February 12th: Abatement of febrile action. Effusion in right pleural sac, extending
        up to the fifth rib anteriorly. Patient placed in an upright position. February 20th,
        accumulation in right pleural sac has increased. Flatness, on percussion, as high as the
        third rib anteriorly; no respiratory act audible below this point. No dyspn&#339;a.
        Decubitus on right side. Appetite fair; pulse 90, and soft. Patient complained of weakness.
          <date type="injury" when="1865-02-28">February 28th</date>, marked increase of fluid in
        chest. On <date type="operation" when="1865-03-02">March 2d</date>, a rapid accumulation was
        noticeable; complete flatness on right side, extending under. Liver depressed three or four
        inches. Apex of heart, two inches to the left of the nipple. Great dyspn&#339;a; pulse, 130.
        Hectic fever, followed by profuse perspiration. The operation of thoracentesis was decided
        upon, and was performed by <name type="person" key="249">Assistant Surgeon Samuel B.
          Ward</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> A straight trochar was
        passed into the pleural sac between the fifth and sixth ribs, in the lateral region of the
        thorax, and fourteen and a half pints of healthy pus withdrawn. The patient experienced no
        faintness during the operation and felt greatly relieved. After the operation, the heart and
        liver returned to their positions. The condition of pneumo-hydro-thorax appeared, giving
        rise to the metallic tinkling and amphoric voice. Stimulants, anodynes, and nutritious diet,
        with absorbents, expectorants, and counter-irritants constituted the main treatment. During
        the month of March, the accumulation returned to a great extent, the dullness extending as
        high as the fourth rib. On <date type="operation" when="1865-04-01">April 1st</date>, the
        incision of operation burst open, giving vent to over a pint of blood, and afterward
        continued discharging. Several abscesses were opened on the right thigh and leg. On April
        15th, erysipelas appeared on the face, terminating favorably in a few days. On<date
          type="transfer" when="1864-04-25"> the 25th</date>, he was transferred to the <name
          type="hospital" key="188">Sickel branch hospital</name>, at which time he was gaining
        strength, and his case was very hopeful. Phthisis pulmonalis supervened, and death resulted
        on <date type="death" when="1865-06-16">June 16th, 1865</date>. The case is reported by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> </p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
