<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e14975">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Private A. D. Seelye</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e14975</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">366</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term> 
     <term>shot contusions of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of shot contusions of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered knee over external condyle of femur, passed out in popliteal space</term>
     <term>unhealthy pus secreted in large amounts</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>internal condyle injured in its posterior aspect</term>     
     <term>abscess in thigh dissected femur half way up limb</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 542.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1123">Private A. D.
      Seelye</name>, <name type="organization" key="465">Co. A, 136th Pennsylvania</name>, was
     wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>, by a musket ball, which entered the right knee
     over the external condyle of the femur and passed out in the popliteal space. He was admitted
     to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-12-23">ten days after the
     injury</date>.  Cold-water dressings and afterwards iodine tincture were applied at first; subsequently
     warm dressings.  The wound did badly; the joint became inflamed, and unhealthy pus was secreted
     in large amounts.  On <date type="operation" when="1863-01-16">January 16, 1863</date>, an incision was made extending six inches from the wound
     of entrance up the thigh. Considerable bleeding followed and several small vessels were tied,
     after which the wound was packed with cotton bandages soaked in persulphate of iron.  Another
     lateral incision, two and a half inches long, was made below the popliteal, opening an abscess.  On <date type="operation" when="1863-01-25">January 25th</date>, an opening was made opposite the large one for the purpose of better drainage.
     Up to this time his appetite had been good, but now it failed, and the patient became delirious
     and had a troublesome diarrh&#339;a. The wound remained open and exposed the blackened surface of
     the femur for the space of three inches.  Death supervened on <date type="death"
      when="1863-02-03">February 3, 1863</date>.  At the <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi>
     examination the internal condyle was found to be injured in its posterior aspect. The
     cartilages of the joint were destroyed and the surfaces of most of the bones roughened and
     honey-combed. An abscess in the thigh had dissected the femur half way up the limb. The history
     of the case was recorded by <name type="person" key="1122">Acting Assistant Surgeon T. H. Dearing</name>. </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
