<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e338">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Shank, Charles</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2010</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e338</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
                    Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                <date>2010</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
                    this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                        Rebellion.</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government
                        Printing Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope><date
                        when="1879">1879</date><biblScope type="page">48</biblScope></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
                    <term>reports and extracts from reports relating to diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
                    <term>treatment with nitrate of silver</term>
                    <term>diarrh&#339;a treated with injections of nitrate of silver at the <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., during the, summer of 1863</term>
                    <term>diarrh&#339;a of seven weeks standing</term>
                    <term>pain in region of sacrum, tenderness along track of colon</term>
                    <term>rheumatic pains</term>
                    <term>cramps in stomach</term>
                    <term>chronic rheumatism</term>                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2012-09-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
            <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Case entered in the book is signed by <name type="person" key="157">Assistant Surgeon A. Hartsuff</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, temporarily acting as surgeon in charge,&#8432; by whom it is understood the majority if not all the cases were treated. To the account of each case as recorded in the case-book the subsequent history of the patient, whenever it has been possible to obtain it, is appended.    &#8432;In the absence of <name type="person" key="147">Assistant Surgeon E. J. Marsh</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 6.&#8212;<name type="person" key="98">Private Charles Shank</name>, <name type="organization" key="108">company H, 4th New York cavalry</name>; age 54; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-04-29">April 29, 1863</date>. Diarrh&#339;a of seven weeks standing, with from five to eight discharges daily. The stools were thin and colorless. Ordered acetate of lead and tonics.  May 1st: The diarrh&#339;a still continues. &#8478;. Nitrate of silver ten grains, tincture of opium twenty-five drops, water one ounce. Use as an enema. This was retained one hour, after which the patient had but one action per day until he was transferred to general hospital in Philadelphia, several days afterward.  [The case-book of <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Satterlee hospital, Philadelphia</name>, shows that this man was admitted to that hospital <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-07">May 7th</date>, still suffering from diarrh&#339;a. He also had difficulty in passing water, pain in the region of sacrum, and tenderness along the track of the colon.  To take every two hours a pill containing two grains of acetate of lead and half a grain of opium. Mustard plaster to abdomen. Milk diet.  May 16th: The patient remains about the same. Discontinue the pills. &#8478;. Tincture of catechu half an ounce, compound tincture of gentian three ounces and a half. Take a tablespoonful three times daily.  May 21st: Bowels constipated. Stop the tincture of catechu and give an ounce of castor oil with twenty-five drops of laudanum. May 25th: The diarrh&#339;a has returned since the oil operated. Renew the tincture of catechu and gentian.  May 27th: Substitute Hope's camphor mixture.  June 24th: The diarrh&#339;a still continues; the evacuations are abundant and watery. The patient complains of intense rheumatic pains, and a certain stiffness is evinced in all his motions. Ordered ten grains of powdered nutmeg every two hours, and a chloroform liniment.  June 27th: The diarrh&#339;a has ceased but the rheumatism still continues. &#8478;. Iodide of potassium one drachm, wine of colchicum root one drachm, compound tincture of gentian two ounces. Take a teaspoonful three times a day.  July 1st: The diarrh&#339;a has returned. The patient complains of cramps in the stomach. Prescribed an aromatic mixture containing ginger and paregoric; subsequently resumed the powdered nutmeg.  <date type="duty" when="1863-07-10">July 10th</date>: The patient appearing to be nearly well, treatment was discontinued, and he was put on duty in the drug store.  <date type="transfer" when="1863-07-13">July 13</date>: The diarrh&#339;a having recurred, he was returned to the ward and treatment was resumed. He was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="216">convalescent hospital</name> <date type="transfer" when="1863-07-30">July 30th</date>. The register of the <name type="hospital" key="216">convalescent hospital</name>, corner of 16th and Filbert streets, reports him admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-08-01">August 1, 1863</date>. Chronic rheumatism.  Transferred to the <name type="organization" key="109">2d battalion, Veteran Reserve Corps</name>, <date type="duty" when="1863-11-15">November 15th</date>.]</p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
