<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41862">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Gray, Charles</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41862</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">263</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>mulatto, afterward an officer's servant</term>
       <term>wound over supraorbital ridge, tetanus</term>
       <term>pneumonia</term>
       <term>diarrhœa during war</term>
       <term>lung completely consolidated, pleural sac contained pint of straw-colored liquid</term>
       <term>well-defined cicatrices over entire surface of large intestine</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-28">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>The history of the following case was forwarded to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, with the specimens, since the close of the war, by the medical officer whose name is attached:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 875.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Charles Gray</name>; mulatto; said to have been a soldier, afterward an officer's servant; admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Washington Asylum</name>, D. C., <date type="admit" when="1868-05-01">May 1, 1868</date>. Shortly after admission he received a slight wound over the right supraorbital ridge, followed by symptoms of tetanus, from which, however, he recovered.  In <date type="injury" when="1868-11">the following November</date>, after going about barefoot and being otherwise exposed, he was attacked with pneumonia, and died <date type="death" when="1868-11-11">November 11th</date>.  He had no symptoms of any abdominal disease while in hospital, but is supposed to have suffered from diarrhœa during the war.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1868-11-11">ten hours after death</date>: Body well developed; rigor mortis well marked; there was a cicatrix on the right side of the forehead. The entire left lung was completely consolidated; the left pleura was coated with a well-defined layer of coagulated lymph; the left pleural sac contained nearly a pint of straw-colored liquid; the right lung was normal. The pericardium contained an ounce of fluid. The heart was normal, with the exception of an opaque spot on the external surface of the right ventricle. A number of well-defined cicatrices were found over the entire surface of the large intestine.—<name type="person" key="134">Assistant Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>   [No. 1003, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, is from this case.  The specimen consists of a portion of the colon, showing several cicatrices.]</p>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
