<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41407">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Koonts, Isaac</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41407</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">191</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>remittent fever</term>
       <term>not emaciated, great omentum very fat</term>
       <term>lower lobe of lung in last stage of pneumonia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>Peyer's patches in lower ileum ulcerated and apparently undergoing healing process</term>
       <term>colon thickened, blackened, and ulcerated, rectum more extensively ulcerated</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-14">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>   
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 456.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx"> Private Isaac Koonts</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company K, 204th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 44; admitted from regimental hospital <date type="admit" when="1864-10-28">October 28, 1864</date>.  Remittent fever.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-11-17">November 17th</date>, of chronic diarrh&#339;a.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="death" when="1864-11-19">forty-one hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis moderate; body not much emaciated; suggillation posteriorly. Head, neck and spinal column not examined. There were no pleuritic adhesions on either side. The right lung and the upper lobe of the left were normal; the lower lobe of the left lung was in the last stage of pneumonia. The pericardium contained two drachms of fluid. The heart was normal. There were but nine attached and three floating ribs, one of the latter being about two inches long. The great omentum was very fat. The intestines were filled with gas. The liver was a little enlarged, and paler than usual. The spleen and pancreas were normal. The mesenteric glands were dark colored, and a little enlarged. The mucous membrane of the stomach, duodenum, and jejunum was normal. Peyer's patches were very dark in the upper part of the ileum, but not thickened or ulcerated; in the lower part they were slightly thickened, ulcerated, and apparently undergoing the healing process. The colon was much thickened, blackened, and ulcerated. The rectum was still more extensively ulcerated. The kidneys were normal; the bladder contained half a pint of urine.&#8212;<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
 