<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7812">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">McLachlan, D. F.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e7812</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName> 
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">355</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>entered as typhoid, but the clinical histories suggestive of malarial complications</term>
                                        <term>condition of Peyer's patches not stated, the intestines variously affected</term>
                                        <term>hemorrhage from bowels, recurrent</term>      
                                        <term>tenderness in iliac and epigastric regions</term>
                                        <term>rose-colored spots (twenty to thirty) on abdomen and chest</term>
                                        <term>mental confusion, ringing in ears</term>
                                        <term>gums covered with sordes</term>
                                        <term>lungs congested and hepatized</term>
                                        <term>kidney small and transformed into thin-walled cyst containing yellow liquid</term>
                                        <term>kidney presented large cavities containing pus</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of colon broken by large ulcers</term>
                                        <term>previous inflammation in small intestine, recently healed sores</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00110">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 110.&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="551">Private D. F.
                                                McLachlan</name>, <name type="organization"
                                                key="623">Co. G. 14th N. Y.</name>, was admitted
                                                <date type="admit" when="1861-09-20">Sept. 20,
                                                1861</date>. He had been taken sick with a chill
                                        followed by severe pain in the head, back and sides, with
                                        loss of appetite and strength. On admission his skin was
                                        warm and perspiring; pulse 92, quick and strong; tongue
                                        glossy and pale, slightly colored brown in the centre and at
                                        the base; bowels moved eight times in the twenty-four hours;
                                        there was tenderness in the iliac and epigastric regions,
                                        with meteorism, borborygmus, epistaxis and rose-colored
                                        spots (from twenty to thirty) on the abdomen and chest. He
                                        was treated with turpentine emulsion, blue pill and opium,
                                        and Dover's powder at night. Next day there was slight
                                        mental confusion with ringing in the ears, and his tongue
                                        was covered with a grayish fur. An eight-grain dose of
                                        quinine was added to the treatment.  During the week which
                                        followed his condition was one of gradual improvement; the
                                        pulse did not rise above 90, the meteorism disappeared, his
                                        appetite began to return and his tongue lost its fur,
                                        becoming moist and pale, but his bowels continued slightly
                                        relaxed notwithstanding the use of opiates and astringents.  After this his progress was uncertain; at times he felt
                                        pretty well. He was treated mainly with wine and quinine in
                                        two-grain doses three times daily, but on October 16 the
                                        throat and larynx became congested and he had some
                                        bronchitic cough. Blisters were applied to the sides of the
                                        neck, the throat was swabbed with a strong solution of
                                        nitrate of silver and five grains each of calomel and jalap
                                        were given. He did not rest well during the night and next
                                        day was pale and weak, hoarse and somewhat deaf; his bowels
                                        were moved three times and there was tenderness with
                                        tympanites and borborygmus. During the day the bowels were
                                        again moved three times. He continued thus for three days.  On the 21st whiskey punch was substituted for wine. On the
                                        23d his expression became anxious, pulse 111, skin hot and
                                        dry, the tongue continuing pale and flabby; he had six thin
                                        evacuations from the bowels; cough was troublesome and the
                                        throat symptoms had become so aggravated that he swallowed
                                        with difficulty and could not speak above a whisper. The
                                        treatment consisted at this time of chlorate of potash,
                                        muriate of iron, beef-tea and whiskey-punch. During the
                                        following night his pulse rose to 140, and next day sordes
                                        appeared on the teeth. Soon after this he became delirious,
                                        imagining that some large animal was in bed with him; that
                                        he was in camp, etc.  On the 27th, having passed a better
                                        night, he was not so delirious, but he looked pale and
                                        anxious; his pulse was weak and small, 94; skin warm and
                                        soft; tongue pale, moist and tremulous; his bowels were
                                        moved involuntarily. At this time there was noted on the
                                        skin dark, almost black, slightly elevated spots somewhat
                                        larger than split-peas, without accompanying inflammation;
                                        those which had arisen more recently were whitish-yellow,
                                        being full of purulent matter. On the 28th he was almost
                                        unconscious; his pulse weak, small and irritable, 120; skin
                                        warm and soft; tongue heavily coated; mouth moist and its
                                        whole surface covered with white sticky mucus; gums covered
                                        with sordes; one side of the face flushed very dark red; his
                                        bowels had been quiet since an injection given on the
                                        previous evening, but there was tenderness on both sides;
                                        submucous and sibilant r&#226;les were heard in both lungs. On
                                        the evening of this day he was quite unconscious, his eyes
                                        and mouth open, pulse 130, respiration 50. During the night
                                        hemorrhage from the bowels took place and recurred on the
                                        afternoon of the next day. His pulse meanwhile becoming
                                        weaker and breathing more rapid.  On <date type="death"
                                                when="1861-10-30">the 30th</date> his extremities became
                                        cold and at 2 P. M. he died.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The brain, pharynx
                                        and &#339;sophagus were not examined. The lungs were
                                        much congested and hepatized. The heart contained fibrinous
                                        clots in both ventricles. The liver and pancreas were
                                        normal: the spleen soft and somewhat enlarged. The right
                                        kidney was small and transformed into a thin-walled cyst
                                        containing a yellowish liquid; the left kidney presented
                                        several large cavities containing pus. "The small intestine
                                        showed that inflammation had been rife there some time ago,
                                        but no ulcers were seen that had been formed lately; there
                                        were places where large and recently healed sores were
                                        evidently indicated." The mucous membrane of the colon was
                                        broken by several large ulcers. The mesentery was quite
                                                healthy.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name
                                                  type="hospital" key="156">Seminary
                                                Hospital</name>, Georgetown, D. C.</hi> </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
