<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9321">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Durst, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9321</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">194-196</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the lower third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>successful cases of shot fractures of the lower third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>disability ceased, injured limb as well nourished as other</term>
     <term>ball entered anterior aspect of thigh at junction of middle and lower thirds, fracturing femur, exit opposite wound of entrance</term> 
     <term>bone united with one and one-fourth inches shortening</term>
     <term>lameness and debility of limb</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-29">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 398.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1030">Private J.
      Durst</name>, <name type="organization" key="176">Co. D, 69th New York</name>, aged 21 years,
     was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="79">Hatcher's Run</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1865-03-25">March 25, 1865</date>. On <date type="admit" when="1865-03-26">the following day</date> he was admitted to the Depot Hospital of the Second Corps, at <name type="place">City Point</name>, and, on
     <date type="transfer" when="1865-03-30">March 30th</date>, he reached <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where he
     entered <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>. <name type="person" key="424">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. K. Smith</name>
     contributed the following history: "A mini&#233; ball entered the anterior aspect of the right thigh
     at the junction of the middle and lower thirds, passing backward and fracturing the femur, and
     made its exit opposite the wound of entrance. The injury produced very little constitutional
     disturbance, and the discharge from the wound did not exceed two drachms in twenty-four hours
     at any time. The limb was treated in Hodgen's splint, without extension, until April 14th, when
     it was placed on a mattress with a sand bag on each side
     to keep it in position, and extension was applied by Buck's method. On June 9th the extension
     was removed and the bone was found to be firmly united, with one and one-fourth inches
     shortening. The patient was now walking on crutches. The anterior wound had healed for about a
     week, but the posterior wound was still discharging very slightly. By June 23d he had good
     movement of the knee and could bend the leg to a right angle with the direction of the thigh.
     The discharge from the wound at this time did not amount to over one drachm in a week. No
     fragments of bone were ever removed, and the limb healed almost as kindly as a simple fracture,
     showing no deformity except the shortening." The patient was subsequently transferred to DeCamp Hospital, <name type="place">David's Island, New York</name>,
     and, on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-19">August 19, 1865</date>, he was discharged and
     pensioned. <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner W. M. Chamberlain</name>, on <date type="pension" when="1866-08-22">August 22, 1866</date>,
     certified to a "well united fracture of the right femur, with only one inch shortening, and
     some lameness and debility of the limb." Substantially the same was reported at subsequent
     examinations until <date type="pension" when="1876-01-19">January 19, 1876</date>, when the <name type="organization" key="xx">New York
      Board</name> certified to the injured thigh being as well nourished as the other, and to the
     disability as having ceased, in accordance with which the pensioner was dropped from the
     Pension Rolls. A photograph of the patient, taken at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army
      Medical Museum</name> in <date type="photo" when="1865-06">June, 1865</date> (<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 46, A. M. M.), is represented in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE LXIII, opp. p. 196.</p>
    
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001809.001" />
    <head>PLATE  LXIII. &#8212; CONSOLIDATED  GUNSHOT  FRACTURES  OF  THE  FEMUR.   Fig 1.  Case of <name type="person" key="1030">Private J. Durst</name>  <name type="organization" key="176">69th New York</name></head>  
   </figure>

   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
