<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3676">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Smith, Jesse</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e3676</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">59-60</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>miscellaneous injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>trephining</term>
                    <term>removal of bone fragments</term>
                    <term>depressed fragments of bone</term>
                    <term>freedman</term>
                    <term>copious pus on removing bone</term>
                    <term>brain protruded through trephined opening in skull</term>
                    <term>cranial fracture from fall</term>
                    <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
                    <term>depressed fracture of parietal bone</term>
                    <term>severe convulsions</term>
                    <term>rolled from stable hay loft, fell twelve feet</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-09">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding,
                edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc2.0026">
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="291">Jesse
                    Smith</name>, Freedman, aged 18 years, employed as a cattle driver, rolled off,
                in his sleep, from the hay in a stable loft, and fell, some twelve feet to the
                floor, striking his head. He was found in the morning, cold and insensible,
                lying on the stable floor, near the horses. Under the use of frictions, hot drinks,
                and other restoratives he revived, and was carried to the <name type="hospital"
                    key="440">Freedmen's Hospital</name>, at <name type="place">Alexandria,
                    Virginia</name>. <name type="person" key="292">Acting Assistant Surgeon Robert
                    N. Atwood</name>, found a wound of the scalp of a crucial form over the right
                parietal eminence, and a depressed fracture of the bone; but, as the general
                condition of the patient was comfortable, sensibility being restored, and the mental
                faculties being apparently normal, <name type="person" key="292">Dr. Atwood</name>
                decided to await further developments. No decidedly bad cerebral symptoms appeared
                for twelve days after the injury, when the patient complained of increased headache,
                and a few hours subsequently had a severe convulsion. On the following day, the patient was much the same as usual,
                except that his headache was increased. <name type="person" key="292">Dr.
                    Atwood</name>, in consultation with <name type="person" key="293">Acting
                    Assistant Surgeon A. W. K. Andrews</name>, decided to operate, and ether having
                been administered, enlarged the original wound and applied the trephine, and removed
                a button of bone to which the greater portion of the depressed fragments were united
                by the inner table. On removing the bone, pus gushed out copiously. At the upper
                posterior part of the perforation the inner table was detached three-fourths of an
                inch more than the outer. This fragment was, with some difficulty, removed by strong
                forceps. An hour afterwards, the patient having recovered from the ether, was highly
                excited, restless, and complained of intolerable pain. He was ordered a grain of
                sulphate of morphia, and in two hours slept comfortably. For ten days subsequently,
                the morphia was continued, being given to the extent of two or three grains daily.
                His diet, at this time, was bread and milk, in small quantities, acidulated with
                vinegar, which he craved earnestly. He also had vinegar and water to drink. In three
                days after the operation the brain commenced to protrude through the opening in the
                skull, and by the tenth day had attained the size and shape of half of a hen's egg.
                    <name type="person" key="292">Dr. Atwood</name> decided to try, by gentle
                compression, to reduce the protrusion, and applied a compress and retentive bandage
                with this view; but immediately violent convulsions occurred; and, although the
                compress was instantly removed, violent convulsive paroxysms recurred during the
                night, not less than fifteen or twenty times. The next day the patient was hovering
                between life and death, but he gradually rallied, and strange to say, after the
                subsidence of the convulsions he had no more pain in his head. His bowels had been
                regular throughout his illness, and he had taken no medicine except the morphia,
                which was discontinued as soon as the pain in the head ceased. Convalescence
                proceeded rapidly; the protrusion subsided; a firm and dense cicatrix covered the
                aperture in the skull; and the patient recovered without any impairment of his
                mental faculties or motor powers. Several months after his recovery he was brought
                to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> to be
                photographed. The picture is numbered 185 in the Surgical Series. The boy was then
                in perfectly good health, and his faculties were unimpaired. The specimen of the
                disk and depressed fragment of the parietal was presented to <name type="hospital"
                    key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="292">Dr. Atwood</name>,
                and is figured in the accompanying wood cut, (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 25.) </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001362.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 25.&#8212;Disk and depressed fragment of bone from
                    right parietal.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4817, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
