<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e14746">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Frazer, H. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e14746</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">362</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>punctured and incised wounds of the knee joint</term> 
     <term>incised wounds of the knee joint</term>
     <term>amputations in the thigh after incised wounds of the knee joint</term> 
     <term>accidentally struck knee while cutting wood</term> 
     <term>cut obliquely across outside of joint</term>
     <term>pus in joint and burrowing above in muscles of thigh</term>
     <term>gangrene</term>
     <term>limb removed six inches below trochanters</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>original wound communicated with knee joint</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 526.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1118">Private H. C.
      Frazer</name>, <name type="organization" key="435">Co. A, 40th New York</name>, while cutting
     wood, on <date type="injury" when="1862-06-20">June 20, 1862</date>, accidentally struck the
     left knee. He entered <name type="hospital" key="64">Ascension Hospital,</name>, Washington,
      <date type="admit" when="1862-07-04">July 4th</date>, whence <name type="person" key="1116">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. W. Bulkley</name> reported that the cut ran obliquely
     across the outside of the joint and had nearly healed when the patient was admitted. About ten
     or eleven days afterwards, however, the leg and joint became greatly swollen and inflamed, the
     skin rapidly assuming a bright red color. This was attended with excessive pain in the joint
     upon motion. Ice, cold irrigations, and tincture of iodine were applied, and salines, small
     doses of tartar emetic, and sweet spirits of nitre were administered. Bandages were applied
     from the foot to the knee joint with good effect. On <date type="operation" when="1862-07-20">July 20th</date>, a small incision was made
     inside the ligamentum patella and gave exit to a large amount of sanious and highly offensive
     pus. About July 27th, the pus was noticed to be accumulating in the joint and burrowing above
     it in the muscles of the thigh. The bandage was still used, and cold, alternated with warm,
     applications were continued. Quinine and tincture of iron was now given, and beef tea and
     brandy punch freely. <date type="operation" when="1862-08-01">About the beginning of August</date> an incision, made in the calf of the leg,
     gave exit to still more offensive pus. After August 5th the patient was slowly sinking. A small
     blackish discoloration was then seen on the inside of the leg, midway between the knee and the
     ankle; the foot, which from the first had remained &#339;dematous, was puffed and pitting on
     pressure. On August 13th the black spot was noticed to be rapidly increasing and was recognized as gangrene, when a lotion of nitric acid was
     applied. On <date type="operation" when="1864-08-14">the following day</date>, the necessity of amputation becoming manifest, two doses of
     one-half grain of morphia each were administered, after which the limb was removed about six
     inches below the trochanters by the antero-posterior flap method. The operation was performed
     by <name type="person" key="1117">Surgeon J. C. Dorr</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="132">U. S. V.</name>, assisted by others, the patient being under the influence of
     chloroform, and losing but a slight amount of blood. Dead and disorganized tissues were found
     in the flaps and dissected out, after which the lips of the wound were closed by silver sutures
     and adhesive plaster. Stimulants were freely given, but the patient sank rapidly, and died at 5
     P. M. on <date type="death" when="1864-08-14">the same day</date>. An examination showed that the soft parts were extensively disorganized
     nearly to the trochanters; also that the original wound had communicated with the knee joint.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
