<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20089">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">T&#8212;&#8212;, William</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e20089</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">567-568</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>excisions</term>
          <term>excisions of portions of the ribs</term>
          <term>excision or removal of portions of the ribs</term>
          <term>ball entered eighth intercostal space</term>
          <term>fractured ninth rib</term>
          <term>necropsy performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private <hi
            rend="italic">William T</hi>&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx"
          >Co. C, 33d North Carolina Regiment</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded at <name
          type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury"
          when="1863-05-03">May 3d, 1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the right side at
        the eighth intercostal space. He lay on the field during the night in a rain storm and on
          <date type="admit" when="1863-05-04">the next day</date> was conveyed to the field
        hospital, where he was treated until <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-08">the 8th</date>,
        when he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>,
        Washington. When admitted, his breathing was very laborious; pulse rapid, quick, and
        non-compressible; expression of the face anxious; sputa frothy and firmly adherent to the
        cup; breathing carried on principally by the left lung. He said the saliva had been tinged
        with blood. Sedatives and expectorants were administered. May 19th: Patient suffers from
        cough, causing intense pain in side. He continued to fail, and died <date type="death"
          when="1863-05-21">May 21st, 1863</date>. At the necropsy the right lung was found to be
        compressed, collapsed, and pushed forward; parenchyma pale red; small bronchial tube
        prominent. The posterior surface was covered with a thick layer of recent yellowish lymph;
        the anterior surface was of a pale greyish blue color and free from lymph. As viewed <hi
          rend="italic">in situ</hi> the lung extended from the first to the sixth rib, projecting
        anteriorly nearly to the median line. The portion not visible was firmly bound to the ribs
        and anterior portion of the diaphragm by adhesions. The lung was separated from the costal
        pleura by a large quantity of purulent matter measuring twenty-four ounces. The
        diaphragmatic and costal surfaces were covered with a thick layer of lymph similar to that
        observed in the lung. The ball had entered the body on the right side, in the eighth
        intercostal space, passed slightly downward and inward, fracturing the ninth rib a little
        anteriorly to its angle, passed through the diaphragm and upper posterior part of the right
        lobe of the liver, re&#235;ntered the pleural cavity, having made a wide ragged track, and
        was found lying on the diaphragm. The track of the ball was lined with lymph. The missile
        would appear to have struck the rib sidewise, and being much flattened (<hi
          rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 269), after partially fracturing the rib to have been
        deflected into the ninth intercostal space. The peculiar fracture of the rib is shown in the
        wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 268). The bone and missile are mounted together in
          <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> specimen, which was contributed, with
        notes of the case, by <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>,
          <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>
      </p>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001484.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 268.&#8212;External and internal views of a section of the
        right ninth rib, with a gunshot willow-fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1141, Sect. I,
        A. M. M.</head></figure>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001485.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 269.&#8212;Musket bull flattened by lateral impact on a rib.
        <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1141, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
