<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11747">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Montague, George</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e11747</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">883-884</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>on certain local diseases</term>
                                        <term>diseases of the kidneys</term>
                                        <term>admitted with acute rheumatism</term>
                                        <term>thigh, knee-joint, leg, ankle and foot swollen</term>
                                        <term>abdomen tympanitic</term>
                                        <term>old adhesions in lung, middle lobe in part hepatized</term>
                                        <term>epithelium of the tubuli granular, contained free oil-drops</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body>                        
                        <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 11.—<name type="person">Corp'l George Montague</name>, <name type="organization">Co. K, 195th Ohio</name>;
                                age 29; was admitted <date type="transfer" when="1865-12-08">Dec. 8, 1865</date>, with acute rheumatism.
                                He had been treated at regimental hospital for <date type="admit" when="1865-11-30">eight days</date>
                                        and had been intoxicated for two weeks previous to the
                                        attack.  On admission the left thigh, knee-joint, leg, ankle
                                        and foot were much swollen and very painful, and the left
                                        elbow and wrist tender and painful; the tongue was dry and
                                        dark-brown, the stomach irritable, the abdomen tympanitic,
                                        the stools frequent, light-colored and watery, the pulse
                                        100 and weak, the skin dry and the mental faculties dull.
                                        Colchicum, morphine and effervescing draughts were
                                        prescribed.  Next day, as the patient had passed no urine
                                        since admission, the catheter was employed, but only a
                                        tablespoonful of ropy liquid was obtained. Small and
                                        repeated doses of calomel, opium and ipecacuanha were
                                        prescribed, and subsequently dry cups to the loins, with
                                        buchu and spirit of nitre, and barley-water as a drink.  No
                                        urine was passed, and the patient died comatose on <date type="death" when="1865-12-11">the 11th</date>.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: Body not emaciated; complexion sallow. The brain was congested, and a small clot was found
                                        in the fissure of Sylvius, near the island of Reil. There
                                        were old adhesions on the posterior aspect and apex of
                                        the right lung; its middle lobe was in part hepatized and
                                        presented old cicatrices on its anterior surface. The heart
                                        was large but otherwise normal. The liver was fawn-colored
                                        and enlarged; the spleen very large and firm. The kidneys
                                        were large, fawn-colored and mottled on the surface with
                                        streaks and spots of congestion; the epithelium of the tubuli was granular and contained free
                                        oil-drops,—[<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 766, Med. Sec., <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>].  The bladder was empty and firmly
                                        contracted. The descending colon was contracted and
                                        contained several small blood-clots, but there was no
                                        ulceration.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. Vols.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="207">Slough Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name></hi> </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
