<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e36053">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Puckett, David</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d2e36053</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">237</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>perforation of intestine</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00084">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 84.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"
                                                >Death, probably from perforation of the intestine,
                                                on the 28th day.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="542">Sergeant David Puckett</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="173">Co. E, 5th U. S.
                                                Cav.</name>; age 27; was admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1861-10-18">Oct, 18, 1861</date>, having been
                                        sick since <date type="injury" when="1861-10-01">the beginning of the month</date> with headache and pain
                                        in the limbs, back and epigastrium. A cathartic, to be
                                        followed by quinine, was prescribed. On the day after
                                        admission the patient was wakeful, his eyes dull and
                                        yellow-tinged, cheeks flushed, pulse 110, full and strong,
                                        skin hot, tongue slightly moist, red at the tip and edges
                                        but heavily coated yellowish-white in the centre; he had
                                        anorexia, thirst, three passages from the bowels during the
                                        twenty-four hours, much umbilical tenderness and tympanites,
                                        a slight cough and difficult micturition. Sinapisms were
                                        applied to the abdomen and emulsion of turpentine given
                                        every three hours, with extract of buchu as required. On the
                                        20th the pulse fell to 90, but the condition of the patient
                                        was otherwise unchanged. A powder containing three grains of
                                        calomel, one grain of opium and one-eighth of a grain of
                                        tartar emetic was given every three hours. Next day the
                                        tongue became dry; seven stools were passed, and the
                                        hypogastric and iliac regions were highly tympanitic and
                                        tender. On the 22d the diarrh&#339;a continued, eight stools having been
                                        passed; cerebral symptoms were manifested, as headache,
                                        hebetude, dizziness and tinnitus; the stomach became
                                        irritable and the tongue dry, red at the tip and edges and
                                        brown in the centre. On the 23d no change was recorded
                                        except the passage of urine without pain for the first time
                                        in several days. Lead, opium and tannin with tincture of
                                        iron were prescribed. On the 24th the patient was dull,
                                        lying with his eyes half closed in a semi-delirious
                                        condition; no stool was passed, but there was much vomiting.
                                        Two grains of calomel and a half grain of opium were ordered
                                        for administration every hour. On the 26th, having slept
                                        well at night, the patient was brighter, his mind less
                                        obtuse, and there was less abdominal tenderness; but the
                                        tongue was heavily coated yellow and the anorexia, thirst
                                        and vomiting persisted. Next day five grains of calomel and
                                        a quarter of a grain of sulphate of morphia were given, but
                                        no marked change was apparent until the 27th, when the
                                        patient was partly unconscious and delirious, lying with his
                                        eyes rolled up and mouth open, his breathing hurried, pulse
                                        125, tongue dry and coated brown and stomach rejecting
                                        everything; there was extreme tenderness of the abdomen and
                                        much meteorism. Stimulants were administered by enemata.
                                        Death took place on the morning of <date type="death"
                                                when="1861-10-28">the 28th</date>. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
