<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5443">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Phelan, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5443</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">107-108</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>compound comminuted fracture of neck and upper extremity of femur</term>
     <term>ball entered in front, passed toward great trochanter</term>
     <term>femur comminuted, great trochanter shattered</term>
     <term>fractured upper femur</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>suppuration moderate</term>
     <term>every bed occupied by patient with suppurating wounds</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 250.&#8212;<name type="person" key="952">Captain John
     Phelan</name>, <name type="organization" key="393">Co. A, 73d New York</name>, aged 22 years,
    received a compound comminuted fracture of the neck and upper extremity of the left femur at the
    battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice>
      <orig>Spottsylvania</orig>
      <reg>Spotsylvania</reg>
     </choice> Court House</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1864-05-14">May 14, 1864</date>. On
     <date type="admit" when="1864-05-16">May 16th</date>, he was admitted to <name type="hospital"
     key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>, Washington. The rapid and incessant influx of wounded
    was such that the attention of the overworked hospital staff was not especially drawn to his
    case for some time after his admission, and the delay in minutely examining the case was
    extended by the uncomplaining fortitude of the sufferer, who expressed his wish that the more
    serious cases should first be attended to, and declared that his own sufferings were
    comparatively slight. When, however, <name type="person" key="953">Acting Assistant Surgeon
     Mulford</name>, the ward surgeon, proceeded, on <date type="operation" when="1864-06-03">June
     3d</date>, to adapt apparatus to what he supposed to be an ordinary gunshot fracture of the
    upper third of the thigh, he was led to apprehend that the injury extended to the coxo-femoral
    articulation, and requested the opinion of the surgeon in charge of the hospital, <name
     type="person" key="339">Assistant Surgeon C. A. McCall</name>, <name type="organization"
     key="190">U. S. A.</name>, as to the diagnosis and treatment. <name type="person" key="339">Dr.
     McCall</name> immediately visited the patient, and found him to be a large, muscular, finely
    formed man, whose previous health had been excellent. When lying quietly in bed, he suffered but
    little. His appetite was good; and his strength, so far, had diminished but little. Altogether,
    his general condition was extraordinarily good, in view of the gravity of the injury he had
    sustained. The ball had entered in front, just over the point at which the profunda is given off
    from the left femoral artery. The aperture of entrance was small and characteristic as an
    entrance wound of a conoidal musket ball. The missile had passed toward the great trochanter and
    shattered it. Further, its course could not be ascertained at the time. Any movement of the limb
    caused extreme pain. Though the femur was much comminuted, <name type="person" key="339">Dr.
     McCall</name> was not positive that the hip joint was implicated, and, with a view to a full
    exploration of the injury, he directed <name type="person" key="953">Dr. Mulford</name> to make
    a longitudinal incision three inches in length over the trochanter, to explore the parts
    thoroughly, and to ascertain by digital examination the condition of the articulation. If it was
    uninjured, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Mulford</name> was instructed to extract detached
    fragments of bone and foreign matters, to close the upper part of the wound, and to avail of the
    lower portion for drainage. In the afternoon the patient was etherized, and the exploratory
    incision was made, and it was found that the fracture extended to the head of the femur. It was
    then decided to excise the head. The patient was again rendered insensible by the inhalation of
    sulphuric ether, and <name type="person" key="339">Dr. McCall</name> extended <name
     type="person" key="953">Dr. Mulford</name>'s incision upward an inch or more, and then made an
    oblique incision across its upper extremity, as represented in the accompanying figure (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 61). The two flaps thus marked out were reflected, and the joint
    was readily exposed, the round ligament divided, and the head of the femur exarticulated. The
    acetabulum was carefully examined and found to be uninjured. Seven large and numerous small
    fragments of the neck and trochanter major were then removed, a task requiring much time and
    patience, many fragments being driven into the gluteal muscles, or deeply retracted by the
    muscles attached to the great trochanter. The fractured upper extremity of the femur was then
    brought out at the wound, by adducting and pushing upward the knee of the injured limb, and all
    diseased tissue was removed. The periosteum was in a healthy condition quite up to the end of
    the bone. The wound was now thoroughly washed out, and approximated by three stitches, and by
    adhesive strips. A grain of sulphate of morphia was administered, and the patient was put to
    bed. The operation lasted three-quarters of an hour. <name type="person" key="339">Dr.
     McCall</name> thinks that the ball was removed during the operation; but is not positive on
    this point. The hospital report, which is quoted at page 69 of <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi>
    No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, states that the patient's pulse was quick and irritable at the time of
    the operation, that he had a furred tongue and diarrh&#339;a, and was reduced by suppuration.
    But <name type="person" key="339">Dr. McCall</name> (letter of February 11, 1868) thinks that
    this report exaggerates the gravity of the constitutional symptoms, and is quite sure that the
    general condition was favorable. The patient rallied well from the operation. For two days the
    wound was dressed with lint. Suppuration then commencing, the limb was placed in Fergusson's
    apparatus for excision of the head of the femur, the counter-extension straps being left off.
    The wound was freely syringed with cold water containing a little permanganate of potassa. A
    nourishing diet was ordered, with tonics and stimulants. For a week or ten days subsequently,
    the case progressed favorably. Suppuration was moderate in amount, and of a healthy character.
    About the middle of June, the weather became intensely hot. The atmosphere of the wards, in
    which nearly every bed was occupied by a patient with suppurating wounds, became intensely
    oppressive. About this time, the patient began to grow worse. The cheerful resolution and
    hopefulness he had hitherto evinced, gave way. Diarrh&#339;a supervened, and he lost strength
    rapidly. The fatal event was thought to have been delayed by the plan which was pursued of daily
    removing the patient in his bed at nine in the morning to a spot beneath the shade trees near
    the hospital, where he had pure air and escaped the distressing scenes of the ward; he remained
    each day until five in the afternoon. He died on <date type="death" when="1864-06-21">June 21,
     1864</date>. The portion of bone excised was forwarded at the time of the operation to the
     <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>. The preparation is No. 2618 of the
    Surgical Series. It is represented in the adjacent wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
    60). </p>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001535.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 60.&#8212;Excised head and fragments of neck of left femur. <hi
     rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2618.</head></figure>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001536.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 61.&#8212;Direction of the incisions in case of excision of
    the head of the femur. [From a drawing by Dr. <hi rend="initialcap">M</hi>c<hi rend="initialcap"
     >C</hi>ALL.]</head></figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
