<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41382">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Rockstadt, Frederick</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41382</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
<date when="1879">1879</date>
<biblScope type="page">189-190</biblScope>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
<bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="#medsurg">
      <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
      <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
      <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
      <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
      <term>great omentum adherent to small intestine</term>
      <term>parietal surface of peritoneum had deposit of lymph, peritoneal cavity contained fluid</term>
      <term>peritoneum covering small intestine inflamed</term>
       <term>knuckles of intestine adherent to each other and to parietal peritoneum</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon inflamed and ulcerated, ulcer near sigmoid flexure perforated</term>
       <term>rectum perfectly disorganized</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-13">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 449.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Frederick Rockstadt</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company G, 204th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 46; admitted from regimental hospital <date type="admit" when="1864-10-28">October 28, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-11-01">November 1st</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-11-02">twenty-four hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis great; body emaciated; slight suggillation posteriorly. Head, neck, and spinal column not examined. The pericardium contained about two drachms of fluid. The heart was normal in size and structure, its valves healthy; the right auricle contained a large firm clot; smaller clots of the same character were found in each of the other cavities; the large arteries and veins contained a small quantity of dark blood. There were extensive old pleuritic adhesions on both sides. The left lung was very much congested, and scarcely crepitated when squeezed; the right lung was in the stage of gray hepatization. The bronchial glands were normal. The great omentum was contracted, thickened, and adherent to the small intestine. The parietal surface of the peritoneum was covered with a deposit of lymph; the peritoneal cavity contained three ounces of fluid. The stomach was filled with a yellow fluid which had a f&#230;cal odor. The peritoneum covering the small intestine was inflamed, and the knuckles of intestine were adherent to each other and to the parietal peritoneum by recent deposits of lymph. The mucous membrane of the small intestine was healthy; the colon inflamed and ulcerated; one of the ulcers near the sigmoid flexure had perforated; the rectum was perfectly disorganized, soft, thickened and dark colored. The rectum was perfectly disorganized, varying in size from a pea to a walnut; the gall-bladder contained about two ounces of bile. The pancreas was normal. The spleen softened. The kidneys and ureters normal; the bladder filled with urine.&#8212;<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
