<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e29413">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Heward, Francis</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e29413</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">893</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>anæsthetics</term>
       <term>deaths from chloroform</term>
       <term>dislocation of humerus forward and inward</term>
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term> 
       <term>pulleys and counter-extending bands</term>
       <term>symptoms of asphyxia</term>
       <term>artificial respiration</term>        
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-27">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1267.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Francis Heward</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 1st New Jersey</name>, was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="214">Fairfax Seminary Hospital</name>, <date type="admit" when="1862-04-05">April 5, 1862</date>, with a dislocation of left humerus forward and inward of a few hours standing. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Henry A. Armstrong</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">2d New York Artillery</name>, reduced the bone without assistance. On <date type="operation" when="1862-05-06">May 6th</date> <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. W. Ducachet</name> discovered that
    the bone was again out of place in the same direction. The patient was chloroformed and reduction attempted with the heel in
    the axilla, but without success. On <date type="death" when="1862-05-09"><date type="operation" when="1862-05-09">the 9th</date></date> pulleys and counter-extending bands were obtained and adjusted. Chloroform was again administered, a drachm being poured upon a piece of lint about two inches square and held about three inches from his face, a towel being thrown over the head of the patient and hand of the operator, and which was removed from time to time to
    admit air. Some time elapsed before the muscles became relaxed, when the chloroform was removed. There was no stertorous
    breathing, choking, or struggling, nor was there occasion to use force to keep him down, as at the previous administration.
    There was, as there always is, congestion of the conjunctiva and vessels of the neck, but not as much, certainly not more, than
    when the chloroform was administered on the 6th.  Reduction was being attempted when symptoms of asphyxia were noticed;
    the pulleys were instantly relaxed, the tongue drawn forward, and artificial respiration resorted to, but everything failed.  No autopsy was made.  The report of the case is signed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H. A. Armstrong</name> and <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Ass't Surgeon H. W. Ducachet</name>.</p>     
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
