<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2391">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Scoffield, James</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e2391</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>                                        
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">223</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>clinical records</term>      
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>dizziness</term> 
                                        <term>deafness</term>
                                        <term>diarrh&#339;a</term> 
                                        <term>hemorrhage from bowels</term> 
                                        <term>inflammatory action in pulmonary and urinary organs</term>
                                        <term>delirium</term>
                                        <term>anorexia</term>
                                        <term>tenderness in right iliac region</term>
                                        <term>scanty and very dark-colored urine</term>
                                        <term>typhoid cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>                                        
                                        <term>epistaxis</term>
                                        <term>profuse hemorrhage from bowels</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-28">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00028">
                        
                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 28.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"
                                                >Dizziness; deafness; diarrh&#339;a; eruption on
                                                the 9th day, not disappearing on pressure; manifest
                                                improvement coincident with epistaxis on 16th day;
                                                hemorrhage from bowels on 19th day, with subsequent
                                                inflammatory action in the pulmonary and urinary
                                                organs, and delirium lasting until the 33d day, when
                                                improvement was again
                                                manifested.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="488">Private James Scoffield</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="177">Co. K, 6th
                                                        Wis.</name>; age 20; became subject about <date type="injury" when="1861-09-25">Sept. 25, 1861</date>, to
                                        faintness and feelings of weakness, chills, fever,
                                        diarrh&#339;a, pain in the head and back and anorexia.
                                        He was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-10-02">October 2</date> as a case of typhoid fever. His face was
                                        flushed darkly; eyes suffused; expression dull and heavy;
                                        pulse 100, strong and full; skin hot, dry, smooth and
                                        without eruption; tongue slightly moist, red at the tip and
                                        thickly coated grayish-white in the centre; bowels relaxed
                                        but not tender; he was somewhat deaf and had a slight cough.
                                        Next day the patient was drowsy and had headache with
                                        dizziness and increasing deafness; the skin hot and
                                        slightly moist, showed a few spots which did not disappear
                                        on pressure; the bowels were moved four times and were
                                        tender. No change took place until the 7th, when tinnitus
                                        aurium and epistaxis were noted, the tongue having become
                                        clean, dry, red and fissured. On the 9th the tongue became
                                        very rough, red and grayish-white in the centre; epistaxis
                                        recurred; four stools were passed, and there was slight
                                        tenderness in the right iliac region; the urine was scanty
                                        and very dark-colored. Next day epistaxis again occurred,
                                        the pulse was 100 and strong, the skin soft although hot and
                                        dry; the expression was less anxious, the eyes clearer, the
                                        hearing improved and the tongue moist and cleaning in the
                                        centre, but the patient complained of headache and pain in
                                        the back and side, a dry hacking cough and much thirst; he
                                        had two thin stools with much tenderness and gurgling
                                        and slight meteorism. On <date type="injury" when="1861-10-13">the 13th</date> a profuse hemorrhage
                                        occurred from the bowels; the patient became very pale and
                                        stupid, pulse 120, skin hot and husky, tongue moist,
                                        fissured and slightly coated; the abdomen was soft and
                                        tender. Next day the pulse was 101, the skin dry and husky,
                                        the tongue dry, dark, cracked and rough, the countenance
                                        pinched and somewhat anxious, the teeth and gums covered
                                        with sordes; the bowels moved three times during the night,
                                        about eight ounces of blood coming away with one of the
                                        passages. No hemorrhage took place on the 15th, but the
                                        patient had subsultus tendinum and some bronchitic cough.
                                        His expression on the 16th was wild; he was very wakeful and
                                        complained much of pain in his heels and legs. On the 17th
                                        he perspired profusely and had frequent epistaxis but no
                                        stool; the bladder was so distended as to require the
                                        employment of the catheter; the tongue was dry, furred and
                                        scaly; pulse 112, feeble; mind dull; countenance anxious;
                                        respiration normal. Two stools were passed on the 18th; the
                                        bowels were tympanitic and acutely tender; the skin was dry
                                        but at times moist and perspiring; the delirium present was
                                        not of a violent character. From this date until the 27th
                                        the patient was dull, drowsy and more or less delirious,
                                        sometimes crying out loudly; the skin was dry and husky but
                                        occasionally moist; the tongue dry, fissured and scaly and
                                        the teeth black with sordes; two or three stools were passed
                                        daily, and there was much right iliac and hypogastric
                                        tenderness, with meteorism and borborygmus; the catheter had
                                        to be used, and the urine withdrawn was strongly alkaline,
                                        containing blood, mucus, pus, epithelium and excess of
                                        phosphates. Some sibilant r&#226;les were heard in the upper
                                        parts of both lungs, and the respiration at one time became
                                        increased to 28 per minute. He was emaciated and very weak;
                                        but on the 27th the mind became clearer. On the 28th the
                                        eyes were bright, the skin warm and sweating, the tongue
                                        moist and cleaning, the bowels quiet, the abdominal
                                        tenderness much diminished, but still acute in the right
                                        iliac and hypogastric regions. On the 29th some appetite was
                                        manifested. The teeth and gums were clean on November 1.
                                        Micturition was free and natural on the 4th, but for some
                                        days after this he had at times much pain in the penis and
                                        bladder. On the 9th bed-sores are mentioned; the skin was
                                        hot and dry; the tongue dry, smooth and fissured; the bowels
                                        were quiet, but tenderness continued in both iliac regions;
                                        the appetite was good. No further record was made except
                                        that on <date type="transfer" when="1861-11-20">the 20th</date> the patient was transferred to
                                        <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name> This case was treated with turpentine
                                        emulsion on October 7th. Dover's powder on the 9th, acetate
                                        of ammonia on the 10th, extract of buchu on the 11th, and
                                        thereafter with quinine, opium and stimulants. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
