<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31258">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Burroughs, M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31258</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="tw">Trevor Wilke</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">913</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint</term> 
       <term>amputations at the elbow joint for shot injury</term>
       <term>secondary disarticulations</term> 
       <term>gunshot wound of hand</term>
       <term>ball entered hand on palmar surface, passed obliquely through, exited on dorsum</term>
       <term>metacarpal bones of little and ring fingers broken and comminuted</term> 
       <term>hospital gangrene</term>
       <term>amputation at lower third of forearm</term>
       <term>application of nitric acid and bromine</term>
       <term>re-amputation performed at elbow joint</term>
       <term>loss of forearm, amputated at elbow joint</term> 
       <term>furnished with artificial forearm</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#tw" when="2011-02-22">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>   
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1841.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private M. Burroughs</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. A, 148th New York</name>, aged 18 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-02">June 2, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="339">Assistant Surgeon C. A. McCall</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, reported his admission to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-06-06">June 6th</date>, with &#34;Gunshot wound of right hand.&#34;  On <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-10">June 10th</date>, the patient entered McDougall Hospital, <name type="place">New York</name>, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon F. H. Hamilton,<choice><orig>jr.</orig><reg>Jr.</reg></choice></name>, recorded the following history: &quot;He was wounded by a rifle ball entering the hand on the palmar surface, passing obliquely through, and making its exit on the dorsum. The metacarpal bones of the little and ring fingers were broken and badly comminuted. The wound looked well until the 15th of June, when it was attacked with hospital gangrene. On the first examination of the condition of the wound sloughing had produced an ulcer two inches in diameter, and the hand and forearm were much inflamed. Pure nitric acid was applied twice, which nearly arrested the disease.  On <date type="operation" when="1864-06-27">June 27th</date>, the patient was seen by <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon H. M. Sprague</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge, and amputation being advised, it was performed by him the same day. The operation was by double flaps at the lower third of the forearm. The constitutional state of the patient at the time of the operation was in good condition and not much reduced. The stump looked well until about the 2d of July, when it was discovered that gangrene was present and the sutures had given away. The stump was laid open and the bones bare, and pure nitric acid applied, which stayed the progress somewhat. July 16th, since the last application of nitric acid&#8212;on July 2d&#8212;two applications have been made of bromine one part to three parts alcohol. The bones are now protruding one inch and the gangrene is nearly arrested. The general state of the patient is not very much prostrated, considering the nature of the wound and its result. He is receiving generous diet, with tonics and stimulants.&#34;  Re-amputation was subsequently performed at the elbow joint, the precise date of which operation has not been ascertained. The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-08-26">August 26, 1864</date>, by reason of &#34;loss of right forearm, amputated at the elbow joint.&#34;  In the following year he was furnished with an artificial forearm by <name type="organization" key="xxx">J. M. Grenell &#38; Co.</name>, of <name type="place">New York</name>, who in their surgical statement described the case as a &#34;flap amputation at the elbow joint.&#34;  In his application for commutation the pensioner stated that he wore the artificial limb only a few times; that it was heavy and made the stump sore, etc.; also that the stump was then&#8212;in 1870&#8212;in a sound condition. <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon Sprague</name>, the operator at the first amputation in this case, is also alleged by the pensioner as having performed the subsequent disarticulation at the elbow joint. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
