<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2149">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Cross, John</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e2149</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">220</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>delirious</term> 
                                        <term>free perspirations</term>
                                        <term>muscular debility</term> 
                                        <term>twitchings</term> 
                                        <term>teeth covered with sordes</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid cases</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-17">additional proofing of transcription and
                                encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-01">additional proofing of transcription and
                                encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00019">

                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 19.—<hi rend="italic">Admitted
                                        delirious and in low condition about the 21st day; free
                                        perspirations occurred two days later, after which
                                        convalescence was gradually established.</hi>—<name type="person" key="478">Private John Cross</name>, <name type="organization" key="147">Co. E, 14th N. Y. State
                                        militia</name>; age 23, and of stout habit; had been sick
                                three weeks when admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-09-14">Sept.
                                        14, 1861</date>, with typhoid fever. He was delirious and
                                affected with great muscular debility and twitchings; pulse 120;
                                skin hot and moist; face hot and dark-red; tongue coated
                                brownish-white and fissured; body emitting a peculiar odor. Next day
                                there was less delirium; but the subsultus continued with great
                                roaring in the ears; the pulse was 104, tongue brown and slightly
                                fissured, teeth covered with sordes, skin hot and dry, face flushed,
                                on one side purplish-red, and abdomen tender on pressure. Turpentine
                                emulsion and stimulants were ordered. In the evening the tongue was
                                dry and coated posteriorly, and the delirium and subsultus
                                persisted. Dover's powder was administered. On the 16th copious
                                perspiration, with subsidence of the delirium and subsultus and
                                increase of appetite was noted; the patient was weak and had great
                                thirst, dryness of tongue and some incontinence of urine. In the
                                evening the skin was warm and perspiring, the mind much clearer, the
                                subsultus absent, the pulse 104, the tongue cleaner and moist and
                                the bowels quiet. The Dover's powder was continued. He rested well,
                                and on the 17th the tongue was white, pulse 100 and skin moist.
                                Aromatic sulphuric acid was given. In the evening the pulse was 100,
                                the tongue white and less fissured and the bowels regular. Next day
                                sudamina appeared with free continued perspirations, great thirst
                                for acid drinks, high-colored urine and regular bowels. After this
                                the daily record varies but little, showing a good appetite, tongue
                                moist, clean or with yellow or brown patches, the skin natural or
                                moist, the bowels quiet except when sometimes moved after the
                                administration of extract of senna, and the sleep sound. Some
                                deafness and tinnitus were noted for a day or two. The patient was
                                transferred to <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1861-10-01">October 1</date>, where he
                                was entered as a case of continued fever, and whence be was returned
                                to duty <date type="duty" when="1861-10-21">October 21</date>. </p>

                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
