<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16936">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">McK——, John</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16936</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">280</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>ball struck skull obliquely, produced slightly depressed fracture</term>
          <term>slightly depressed fracture of parietal bone</term>
          <term>recovery with disability</term>
          <term>convulsions</term>
          <term>bloodletting from temporal artery without apparent benefit</term>
          <term>erysipelas, loss of substance of the integuments and pericranium</term>
          <term>erysipelas denuded large portion of parietal bone</term>
          <term>necrosis of whole thickness of parietal bone</term>
          <term>total disability</term>
          <term>mental faculties impaired</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private John
          McK——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. H, 105th Pennsylvania
          Volunteers</name>, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg, Virginia</name>,
          <date type="injury" when="1864-06-14">June 14th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal musket ball,
        which struck the right side of the skull very obliquely, and produced a slightly depressed
        fracture of the right parietal bone. He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant General Hospital</name>, Washington, on <date type="admit" when="1864-06-24">June 24th</date>, with the report that the progress of the case had been
        so far eminently satisfactory. After admission, he was found to be insensible, and a few
        hours subsequently, convulsions supervened in rapidly recurring paroxysms. Twelve ounces of
        blood were taken from the temporal artery without apparent benefit. A trephine was <date type="operation" when="1864-06-24">then</date> applied to the seat of fracture, and, upon
        the removal of a button of bone, a portion of the inner table was found slightly depressed.
        This was elevated, and the patient soon afterward regained consciousness. On June 28th, the
        wound in the scalp became erysipelatous, and before the inflammation subsided, there was
        extensive loss of substance of the integuments and pericranium, denuding a large portion of
        the parietal bone. Necrosis ensued, and involved the whole thickness of the bone. On <date type="operation" when="1864-09-03">September 3d, 1864</date>, a portion of the parietal,
        three inches by four, had become so much loosened that it was readily removed. Cicatrization
        then went on rapidly, and on <date type="injury" when="1864-12-02">December 2d, 1864</date>,
        the wound had contracted to an ulcer less than an inch in diameter. The patient's mental
        faculties were impaired somewhat, the ward physician thought, but not to a great extent. A
        colored drawing was made representing the appearance of the parts prior to the separation of
        the exfoliation, No. 74, Surgical Series of Drawings, S. G. O., by <name type="person">Hospital Steward P. Baumgras</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>
        It is copied, in chromo-lithography, in the plate opposite page 207. The exfoliation, which
        was contributed, with a minute of the hospital record of the case, by <name type="person" key="339">Assistant Surgeon C. A. McCall</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S.
          A.</name>, is represented in the accompanying wood-cut, taken from page 16 of Circular 6,
        S. G. O., 1865. The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-08-31">August 31st, 1864</date>, and from the hospital <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1865-02-01">February 1st, 1865</date>. He was pensioned;
        the examiner, <name type="person">Dr. Julius Nichols</name>, stating that he was totally
        disabled, and that the case was the most extraordinary that had come under his observation;
        the pulsations of the brain, uncovered by dura mater, and the trunk of the meningeal artery
        being distinctly visible. He went to his home in <name type="place">Montgomery County,
          Pennsylvania</name>. In <date type="pension" when="1871-04">April, 1871</date>, he wrote
        to the compiler of this volume as follows: * * "The space the bone was taken out
        of is three and a half by two inches. In feeling the place lightly, it goes all through my
        head. It is all healed over like a thin shell. I am compelled to lie on my left side when
        sleeping. When exposed to the sun a dull pain through my head is caused. * * I have
        received but seven dollars a month. My pension papers call for eight dollars." </p>
      <figure><graphic url="cww.001425.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 141.—Exfoliation from the right parietal bone. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3452, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>
      <figure><graphic url="cww.001403.001"/><head>PLATE VI, facing p. 207. GUNSHOT FRACTURES OF THE CRANIUM. <hi rend="italic">Two
          figures</hi>: Left hand, case of McK——, p. 280; right hand, case of Hughes, p.
        206.</head></figure>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
