<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6750">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Kelb, Frederick</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6750</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">148</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the hip joint</term>
     <term>coxo-femoral amputations</term>
     <term>secondary amputations</term> 
     <term>entered below fold of natis, passed outward, shattered femur at its middle, lodged in anterior thigh</term>
     <term>ball fractured femur at junction of upper and middle thirds</term> 
     <term>recurring abscesses in thigh, entire femur necrosed</term>
     <term>pelvis of kidney blocked by numerous calculi</term> 
     <term>abscess in kidney</term>
     <term>tuberculosis of both lungs, advanced stage</term>
     <term>chronic osteomyelitis</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 324.&#8212;<name type="person" key="974">Corporal Frederick
      Kelb</name>, <name type="organization" key="240">Co. G, 7th New York</name>, was wounded at
     <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-14">December 14, 1862</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which fractured the
     right femur at the junction of the upper and middle thirds. After remaining for a fortnight in
     the field hospital of the 1st division of the Second Corps he was conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and placed, on <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-25">December 25th</date>, in the <name
      type="hospital" key="159">Patent Office Hospital</name>, where the injured limb was placed in
     a fracture box and the wound was dressed with oakum. The case progressed favorably, and, on
      <date type="transfer" when="1863-04-02">April 2, 1863</date>, the patient was transferred to
      <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square Hospital</name>, and, on <date
       type="transfer" when="1863-05-09">May 9th</date>, was sent to De Camp Hospital, at <name type="place">David's Island, New York</name>. <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon John C. DuBois</name> reported: &#34;The ball entered about one inch below the fold of the right natis, and, passing outward, shattered the femur at its middle, and lodged in
        the anterior part of the thigh. The ball was extracted <date type="operation" when="1862-12-16">two days afterwards</date>. On <date type="operation" when="1863-01-01">January 1, 1863</date>,
     six pieces of bone were removed. The limb was placed on a double inclined plane and cold water
     applied. Six weeks after, the long straight external and short internal splints of pasteboard
     were applied. This was removed in a few weeks and merely the short internal pasteboard splint
     retained. On April 2d and 8th, pieces of bone came away. The splint was then removed, and the
     limb suffered to lie on a hair mattress. <date type="operation" when="1863-05-06">May 6th</date>, several pieces of bone removed. May 12th,
     firm union has taken place, with great deformity. External angular curvature, with about 4&#190;
     inches shortening, as near as can be measured. His whole limb is everted, and he is unable to
     raise it. His general condition is much reduced. As union is firm no treatment can be adopted
     to relieve the deformity. <date type="operation" when="1863-07-10">July 10th</date>, a few more pieces of bone have been removed. The probe
     reveals rough bone, not loose. Internal wound closed; sinus injected with dilute tincture of
     iodine. General health pretty good.&#34; On <date type="transfer" when="1863-07-10">July 10th</date> he was removed to McDougall Hospital, at <name type="place">Fort Schuyler</name>; and on <date type="transfer" when="1864-01-19">January 19, 1864</date>, he was readmitted to De Camp Hospital. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-06-08">June 8, 1864</date>, he was discharged from the service of the United States. There was evidence of disease of the
        femur. On <date type="admit" when="1865-06-07">June 7, 1865</date>, <name type="person" key="974">Kelb</name> was admitted to St. Luke's Hospital, in <name type="place">New York City</name>. There had been a series of recurring abscesses in the
     thigh, and it was believed that nearly the entire femur was necrosed. It was determined to
     amputate at the hip joint, and, on <date type="operation" when="1865-06-07">June 7th</date>, the patient being an&#230;sthetized by sulphuric
     ether and the aorta being compressed by Signoroni's clamp tourniquet, the amputation was
     performed by the attending surgeon, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. R. F. Weir</name>, by the
     method recommended by <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Van Buren</name>, an anterior flap being
     formed by transfixion and a posterior one by section from without inward. The h&#230;morrhage
     was slight and the shock was moderate. The case at first progressed very favorably. Three weeks
     after the operation the healing of the stump was far advanced and the patient was able to leave
     his bed. After this he began to lose ground very gradually. He died on <date type="death"
      when="1865-10-04">October 4, 1865</date>, nearly four months after the operation. At the
     autopsy, the pelvis of the right kidney was found to be blocked up with numerous calculi; there
     was an abscess in the left kidney, and there was tuberculosis of both lungs at an advanced
     stage. The stump was still open and the horizontal portion of the os pubis was necrosed. A
     section of the exarticulated femur presented the characteristic lesions of chronic
     osteomyelitis. </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
