<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19872">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Jordan, John F.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e19872</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">543-544</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>ligations</term>
          <term>traumatic <choice>
              <orig>aneurism</orig>
              <reg>aneurysm</reg>
            </choice></term>
          <term>circumscribed <choice>
              <orig>aneurism</orig>
              <reg>aneurysm</reg>
            </choice> from gunshot injury</term>
          <term>circumscribed traumatic <choice>
              <orig>aneurism</orig>
              <reg>aneurysm</reg>
            </choice> of the axillary artery</term>
          <term>old tuberculosis</term>
          <term>wounds of axillary artery and brachial plexus of nerves</term>
          <term>arm paralyzed, loss of sensibilty and mobility</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>ligation of subclavian artery external to scalenus</term>
          <term>ligations of the subclavian</term>
          <term>autopsy performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>
      <p> The complete report is given in the author's own language:² </p>
      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 20.— "<name type="person" key="xxx">Captain <hi rend="italic">John F. Jordan</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B,
          13th Virginia Cavalry</name>, aged 31 years, and of sound constitution, was admitted to
          <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton United States Army General Hospital</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-06-23">June 23d, 1863</date>. He had been wounded on <date type="injury" when="1863-06-21">June 21st</date>, in action near <name type="battle">Middleburgh, Virginia</name>, by a shot from a carbine. The bullet, which, by the way,
        was conical in shape, penetrated the pectoralis major muscle of the left side, at a point on
        a level with the axillary artery, and about one and a half inches from the margin of the
        armpit, passed directly backward beneath the shoulder, wounding the axillary artery,
        together with the brachial plexus of nerves, and escaped behind. Patient said he lost a
        great deal of blood immediately after the wound was inflicted, so much indeed that he
        fainted, when the hæmorrhage ceased of itself, and did not return. On admission to
        hospital, his left arm exhibited some swelling, œdematous in character, and its inner
        side was ecchymosed nearly down to the elbow-joint. It was also paralyzed, the loss of both
        sensibilty and mobility being complete. There was no radial pulse in that arm, and pulsation
        could not be detected in the brachial or any other artery thereof. From this we inferred
        that the axillary artery had been severed by the bullet. The temperature of the limb was not
        below the normal standard; on the contrary, we thought it to be somewhat warmer than the
        limb of the opposite side. There was nothing remarkable in the appearance of the wound. The
        patient's general condition was good. He did not look as if he had suffered from
        hæmorrhage. His bowels were constipated; ordered a saline purge, together with a spare
        diet, and, with a view to lessen the tendency to secondary hæmorrhage, he was directed
        to remain quiet in bed, to exert himself as little as possible, and to have ice applied
        constantly over the injured artery. He was also directed to take morphine at night if
        necessary to procure rest. Under this treatment the patient progressed without an
        unfavorable symptom; the wound cleaned itself and closed up in a satisfactory manner, and we
        congratulated the patient in that he was likely to get well without suffering the terrible
        secondary hæmorrhage, which frequently attends gunshot wounds of the axillary artery.
        The limb continued to be completely paralyzed as to motion, but sensation had gradually been
        restored to the fingers, hand, and forearm. On the morning of the 12th of July, we noticed
        the appearance of a small, rounded, circumscribed swelling of the size of an egg, at the
        seat of injury to the artery. The scar of the anterior orifice of the gunshot wound was
        exactly on the summit of the convexity of the swelling, as the patient lay in bed. The tumor
        was tense in feel, and pulsated distinctly and synchronously with the heart. There was,
        however, an entire absence of the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> thrill and <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> bruit. By compressing the subclavian artery against the first rib, the tumor
        became soft, much less in size, and ceased to pulsate. On withdrawing compression the tumor
        speedily filled up, became tense, and pulsated again. Patient stated that during the
        preceding night he felt something "give way" in his left armpit, while attempting to change
        the position of this arm by the aid of the right hand. During the day the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> increased rapidly in size, and in the evening was fully twice as large as when
        first noticed in the morning. July 13th, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> continued to increase steadily in size, and in the evening was about half as large
        as the clenched fist. July 14th, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> had grown but little since previous day; it was still rounded, distinctly
        circumscribed, and somewhat oval in shape. By compressing the subclavian, it ceased to
        pulsate, became soft and much shrunken, but the prior condition of things was restored
        speedily on withdrawing compression; as on a previous occasion, there was still no thrill or
        bruit. Diagnosis: <hi rend="italic">Circumscribed traumatic <choice>
            <orig>aneurism</orig>
            <reg>aneurysm</reg>
          </choice> of the axillary artery</hi>. From the entire absence of pulsation in all the
        arteries beyond the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice>, which existed even at the time of admission to hospital, and the complete want of
        thrill and bruit in the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> itself, we believed that the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> had been developed from the proximal end of the severed artery, and that opinion
        was strengthened by the fact that the swelling had not expanded outward and downward into
        the armpit, where there was but little in the anatomical structure of the parts to obstruct
        its growth, any more rapidly than it had done in another direction, where it was covered
        over and bound down by the pectoral muscles. The swelling had expanded so equally in all
        directions, that the scar of the anterior wound still remained exactly over the centre of
        the tumor, as when we first saw it. The <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice> was so distinctly circumscribed that, although its origin was traumatic, it was
        deemed advisable to attempt a cure of it by the Hunterian method. As there was not
        sufficient space to secure the artery below the clavicle without opening the sac, I
        proceeded to tie the left subclavian artery external to the scalenus, on the afternoon of
        that day (<date type="operation" when="1863-07-14">July 14th</date>). The patient being
        under sulphuric ether, that operation was performed without difficulty by the ordinary
        method. On tightening the ligature the tumor ceased to pulsate, shrunk a good deal, and
        became soft. The left arm was directed to be wrapped in cotton wool, and to be kept warm by
        the further aid of bottles of warm water, to be renewed from time to time as occasion might
        require. A full dose of morphia was prescribed. He was enjoined to preserve the recumbent
        posture, and to avoid exertion of every kind. A milk diet was allowed. July 10th, patient
        had a comfortable night; temperature of arm not diminished: discontinued the warm water.
        July 16th, patient doing well in every respect; arm warm; color thereof good; discontinued
        the cotton wool. July 17th, bowels being confined, he took an ounce of sulphate of magnesia.
        July 19th, <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> sac opened spontaneously last night through the anterior sear of the gunshot
        wound, and discharged two or three ounces of very dark-colored blood, mixed with pus.
        Suppuration of the sac had been threatened ever since the day after the operation. He was
        allowed a full diet. July 20th, a moderate discharge of old blood and pus, accompanied with
        a gradual diminution in the size of the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice>, and but a moderate degree of inflammation of the sac continued on this and
        several days following, the patient s general condition being unexceptionable all the while.
        July 27th, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> swelling had entirely disappeared; suppuration of the sac, moderate in quantity,
        still continued, the pus being of a good quality. <date type="operation" when="1863-08-01">August 1st</date>, <hi rend="italic">the ligature separated and was removed to-day,
          without the occurrence of hæmorrhage or any other difficulty</hi>; discharge from sac
        good in quality and steadily diminishing in quantity; discovered some excoriation at the
        inner side of the left elbow, occasioned probably by pressure, the patient having followed
        very closely the injunction to keep as still as possible in the recumbent posture; directed
        a stimulating plaster to be applied, and the pressure to be removed to other situations by
        arranging pillows. August 5th, discharge from sac had subsided to a small quantity of
        healthy pus, and the orifice was manifestly contracting. We hoped that adhesion of the sac
        was taking place. Patient's condition seemed to be favorable in every respect, except that
        he had been losing flesh rapidly for several days without obvious cause. For want of any
        other reason, we attributed it to the extreme heat of the weather, the temperature both day
        and night having been unprecedented ever since July 25th, the mercury at midday ranging from
        90° to 100° in the shade, and seldom falling below 80° at night. August 6th:
        a profuse flow of blood from the sac came on this morning without warning; the loss of blood
        being so rapid as to threaten speedy death. The officer of the day was close at hand, and
        stopped the bleeding by injecting about one ounce of liquor ferri persulphatis into the
        bottom of the sac, through a female catheter, introduced for the purpose. The
        hæmorrhage ceased immediately. We had been emboldened to use the persulphate of iron
        freely in this way, because we had a few weeks before (June 22d) stopped a troublesome
        secondary flow, in alarming quantity, of arterial blood from the cavity of a large abscess,
        associated with gunshot fracture of the right thigh, by injecting about two drachms of
        liquor ferri persulphatis through a catheter, carried into the neighborhood of the supposed
        source of the hæmorrhage, a branch of the profunda artery, and no unpleasant effect of
        any kind followed it. Again, about the same time, we had been troubled to manage a case of
        general oozing of blood from the cut surface of a thigh, amputated secondarily for gunshot
        injury. After trying exposure to the air, ice-water, and even ice, without effect, we
        stopped this bleeding immediately by covering the end of the stump with pledgets of lint
        soaked in liquor ferri persulphatis. Aside from pretty severe pain, which soon subsided, no
        unpleasant consequence of any kind followed. We did not discover any evidence of even the
        feeblest action as an escharotic, and indeed have since thought that the case progressed
        better than other amputations of the same class. In consequence of the secondary
        hæmorrhage and the efforts to repress it, the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> sac became filled up again to the original size. August 10th, another severe
        hæmorrhage occurred from the same orifice; it was readily stopped by again injecting
        persulphate of iron in solution. August 11th: profuse hæmorrhage occurred to-day
        through the opening of the posterior orifice made by the bullet, after it had been healed
        for more than a month. This bleeding was also suppressed immediately by injecting liquor
        ferri persulphatis through a catheter. After this there was no more hæmorrhage. During
        the next few days he seemed to rally from the depression produced by these repeated losses
        of blood. He was ordered to have wine, and anything in the line of supporting treatment that
        he would take. August 18th: the <choice>
          <orig>aneurismal</orig>
          <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
        </choice> sac has again suppurated, and there is a profuse discharge of dark-colored and
        very offensive pus. August 25th: patient failing rapidly; suppuration very profuse and
        extremely offensive in character. <date type="death" when="1863-08-29">August 29th</date>,
        he died worn out with the suppuration and the hæmorrhages, forty-six days after the
        operation, and twenty-eight days after the ligature came away. Autopsy eighteen hours after
        death: Emaciation extreme; rigor mortis moderate; a large elongated cavity, with ragged
        dark-colored walls, occupies the original seat of the <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice>, and extends beyond it outward into the axilla; the axillary artery is found to
        have been severed obliquely by the bullet about one and one-half inches above its
        termination in the brachial; the divided extremities are separated widely apart (to the
        extent of about three inches); the distal end appeal s to have been pushed away from the
        proximal end, either by the original <choice>
          <orig>aneurism</orig>
          <reg>aneurysm</reg>
        </choice>, or the subsequent hæmorrhages and suppuration; the proximal end is oblique
        and closed, while the bruised and lacerated portion of it appears about to be cast off by
        the ulcerative process, as a distinct line of demarcation has been formed; the distal end is
        oblique and unclosed, but the calibre of the artery is contracted down to about a line in
        diameter, and it is blocked up by a coagulum three-eighths of an inch long; the branches of
        the axillary given off above the point of injury, especially the superior thoracic and the
        acromial thoracic, are much enlarged; the axillary vein is greatly diminished in size about
        the track of the bullet, but it is still pervious; the brachial plexus of nerves was also
        wounded by the bullet, all the trunks being cut off except that of the <choice>
          <orig>musculo-spiral</orig>
          <reg>radial</reg>
        </choice> and circumflex nerves. The proximal extremities of the divided trunks were
        somewhat bulbous. At the seat of the operation the wound, which at one time was nearly
        closed, is now open quite down to the artery at the point of ligation, the new granulations
        having been reabsorbed to that extent, but the artery for a distance on each side thereof is
        surrounded by a dense mass of new connective tissue, so thick and dense as to make it a
        little difficult to get at and remove the specimen without injury. On the proximal side of
        the ligature the vessel is blocked up to a distance of about five-eighths of an inch; on the
        other side of the ligature it is blocked up to the extent of about two-eighths of an inch.
        In the cavity of the thorax we find old pleuritic adhesions on both sides, and old
        tuberculous cicatrices at the apex of each lung; but both lungs are now entirely free from
        tuberculous deposits; abdomen not opened." The specimen, represented in the above
        wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 249), and also specimen 3243, showing the brachial
        plexus, were contributed by the operator. </p>

      <p> ²<hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL, <hi rend="italic">On the Wounds of Blood-vessels,
          Traumatic Hæmorrhage, Traumatic Aneurism, and Traumatic Gangrene</hi>. In Surgical
        Memoirs of the War of the Rebellion, Vol. I, p. 101, New York, 1870. </p>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001475.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 249.—Drawing of the arterial preparation from Dr.
        Lidell's case of ligation of he left subclavian. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1684, Sect. I,
        A. M. M.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
