<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11229">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">A&#8212;&#8212;, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e11229</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">161</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term>
                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the skull</term>
                    <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the cranium without depression</term>
                    <term>injury to bone slight, not recognized until after death</term>
                    <term>conoidal ball struck frontal bone between eminences, lacerated muscles
                        denuded bone of periosteum</term>
                    <term>pus found upon dura mater beneath seat of injury, abscess extended into
                        lateral ventricle</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding,
                edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-08">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0189">
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1435">Private William
                    A&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="106">Co. F, 11th
                    Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>, aged 29 years, was wounded at the battle of
                    <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness, Virginia</name>, <date
                    type="injury" when="1864-05-07">May 7th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball which
                struck the frontal bone between the eminences, lacerating the muscles for about two
                inches and denuding the bone of periosteum for about one inch. The wound was
                considered slight. The patient was treated for several days in a field hospital, and
                on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-11">May 11th</date> was sent to the <name
                    type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, at Washington, whence on
                    <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-18">May 18th</date>, he was transferred to
                the <name type="hospital">Satterlee Hospital, Philadelphia</name>. Cold water
                dressings were applied to the wound and the patient was able to be about all the
                time. He was in good condition and appeared to do well until <date type="injury"
                    when="1864-05-21"><choice>
                        <orig>May 31st</orig>
                        <reg>May 21st</reg>
                    </choice></date>, when he became irritable, and complained of severe pain in the
                head. The external wound still looked well. On the following day he became drowsy
                and suffered from nausea. The pain in the head continued unabated and the pulse was
                110, but the mind clear. Small doses of creasote and lime-water were given and he
                was freely purged. On May 24th the nausea subsided and the pulse had risen to 120;
                no pain in the head, and the patient was rational though dull. On <date type="death"
                    when="1864-05-25">the 25th</date> the pulse was weak at 130, but the patient
                seemed perfectly conscious, and his mind was clear, and he declared that he felt
                perfectly easy, yet he died suddenly at five in the afternoon. This is the report of
                    <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. K. Baldwin</name>, yet
                his ward case book states that the patient survived until the 26th, having low
                muttering delirium in the early part of that day. The autopsy was made <date
                    type="autopsy" when="1864-05-27">forty hours after death</date> by <name
                    type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Charles P. Tutt</name>. He
                reported that though the periosteum was removed the external table of the skull was
                scarcely injured, except by a shaving of lead from the ball firmly imbedded beneath
                the outer lamina at the inner upper margin of the wound in the periosteum. On
                removing the calvaria a large amount of pus was found upon the dura mater of the
                anterior lobe of the left hemisphere beneath the seat of injury. On removing the pus
                a <choice>
                    <orig>spiculum</orig>
                    <reg>spicula</reg>
                </choice> of bone from the inner table was found to perforate the dura mater and a
                large abscess extending into the anterior horn of the left lateral ventricle was
                found beneath. A large effusion of serum was found at the base of the brain, and a
                yellow deposit was found on the pons Varolii and <choice>
                    <orig>medula</orig>
                    <reg>medulla</reg>
                </choice> oblongata and in the fissures of the cerebellum. A similar deposition of
                albuminous or puriform matter was also found under the arachnoid near the left
                ventricle. The viscera of the chest and abdomen were in a normal condition. The
                clinical history was furnished by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant
                    Surgeon J. K. Baldwin</name>, who is also accredited with the specimen, of which
                an external and internal view is given in the accompanying wood-cuts, (<hi
                    rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 70, and <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 71.) The
                notes of the autopsy were furnished by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant
                    Surgeon Tutt</name> who made it. In the external table a portion of bone
                measuring one-fourth by one inch, a small fragment of which is depressed one line
                and surrounded by a slight groove, indicated an incipient exfoliation. At the upper
                inner portion of this oval groove a bit of lead is impacted. The inner table beneath
                is fissured for one inch beneath the seat of injury.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001384.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 70.&#8212;Contusion and slight fracture of the
                    frontal bone by a glancing musket ball. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2744, Sect.
                    I, A. M. M.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001385.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 71.&#8212;Interior view of the foregoing
                    specimen.</head>
            </figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
