<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41045">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Shertle, George</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41045</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">165</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>pineal gland absent</term>
       <term>lung collapsed</term>        
       <term>both kidneys had white points the size of millet-seed and yielded puruloid matter</term>
       <term>one kidney had abscess the size of hazel-nut, full of bluish-white pus</term>
       <term>valvul&#230; conniventes of jejunum generally purplish color</term>
       <term>extravasations of blood in ileum, with Peyer's patches well developed, most dark colored, and mammillated appearance</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of c&#230;cum and ascending colon presented ulcers of variable size, generally small and superficial</term>
       <term>ulcers numerous in sigmoid flexure and rectum</term>
       <term>transverse colon had few small ulcers</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 356.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private George Shertle</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 48th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; admitted from the hospital at <name type="place">Windmill Point, Aquia Creek, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-02-08">February 8, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-03-21">March 21st</date>, at 12.30 A. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-03-22">thirty-six hours after death</date>: Height five feet seven inches; no rigor mortis; body extremely emaciated; apparent age 20. The brain weighed forty-three ounces and a half; the veins of the pia mater and of the brain were congested; the gray matter was darker colored than usual; the pineal gland was absent. The right lung weighed eleven ounces and three-quarters, the left seven ounces and a quarter; the posterior portion of the upper and middle lobes of the right lung was congested, the rest of the lung normal. There were old pleuritic adhesions on the left side. The left lung was collapsed, and some portions carnified. The larger bronchi contained a quantity of muco-pus. The heart weighed six ounces and a half; its substance was quite firm; there were white fibrinous clots in both sides; that in the left side extended into the aorta. The liver weighed forty-four ounces and a half; it was quite firm, and full of dark-colored blood; the gall-bladder contained six drachms of light-yellow watery bile. The right kidney weighed five ounces and a half, the left six ounces; in the right kidney, which was generally congested, were a number of white points the size of millet-seed, which upon section yielded a puruloid matter; in the upper part of the left kidney was an abscess the size of a hazel-nut, full of bluish-white pus; this kidney also contained small white purulent deposits similar to those in the right kidney, but not so numerous. The spleen weighed four ounces and a quarter; it was firm, of a reddish purple color, its trabecul&#230; distinct. The suprarenal capsules were dark-yellow and friable; the left capsule was quite large. The pancreas was dark colored, and weighed an ounce and three-quarters. The mucous membrane of the stomach was thin and congested. The duodenum was dilated, its glands large. The valvul&#230; conniventes of the jejunum were generally of a purplish color, while the rest of the mucous membrane was normal; the middle third of the ileum was intensely congested; in places there were extravasations of blood; Peyer's patches were well developed, most of them dark colored, and presenting a mammillated appearance. The mucous membrane of the c&#230;cum and ascending colon presented a number of dark-purplish congested spots and ulcers of variable size, which were generally small and superficial: in the transverse colon, which was irregularly congested, there were but a few small ulcers; in the descending colon there were none; the ulcers were numerous in the sigmoid flexure and rectum, which were intensely congested.&#8212;<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
