<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e12872">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Saxon, J. N.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e12872</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">290-291</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of intermediary amputation in the lower third of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot injury of inner condyle of femur</term>
     <term>secondary arthritis</term>
     <term>suppurative osteomyelitis</term>
     <term>wounded in knee</term>
     <term>bullet entered knee above patella, escaped at inner posterior side, below the joint</term>
     <term>inner condyle of femur fractured by missile passing through it, without opening cavity of joint</term>
     <term>inner condyle of femur extensively comminuted</term>
     <term>synovial membrane reddened</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>h&#230;morrhage, lost more than six pounds of blood</term>
     <term>exsanguinated</term>
     <term>medullary tissue exhibited abscesses, pus under microscope</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>abscess in quadriceps extensor cruris muscle</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-21">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 470.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1093">Private <hi rend="italic">J. N. Saxon</hi></name>,&#185; <name type="organization" key="450">Co. D, 9th
      Louisiana</name>, aged 27 years, was wounded in the right knee, at <name type="BATTLE"
      key="15">Rappahannock Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7,
      1863</date>, and suffered amputation at the <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton
      Hospital</name>, Washington. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name
      type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who performed the operation, described the case
     as follows: "A conical bullet entered the knee about three inches above the patella, on a line
     with its inner margin, passed backward, downward, and a little inward, and escaped at the inner
     posterior side, about six inches below the joint. The inner condyle of the femur was fractured
     by the missile passing through it, but without opening the cavity of the joint. The patient
     stated that his knee was bent at the time of the infliction of the wound. He was admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-11-09">two
      days after the injury</date> and did well, having good spirits, good appetite, and but little pain or
     swelling of the parts until the night of November 16th, when he had a severe chill, accompanied
     with great pain in and about the knee, and the injured parts became hot and swollen. On the
     following morning he exhibited great constitutional disturbances: skin hot; tongue coated
     white; pulse very rapid, gaseous, and weak. The injured knee was much swollen and exquisitely
     tender, and he complained of intense pain in it; the anterior orifice of the wound presented a
     gelatinous appearance, with elevated and everted edges. The patient appeared so feeble that I
     thought he would not then bear the shock of an amputation, and ordered him to take whiskey
     freely with anodynes.  The next day, <date type="operation" when="1863-11-18">November 18th</date>, his general condition appeared unchanged
     with the exception of his pulse, which was stronger and not gaseous, being 120 by the watch. He
     had not slept during the night, and complained of great pain in the knee, which was rather more
     swelled, and the tumefaction was extending up the thigh. The wound presented the same
     gelatinous appearance as the day before, and the skin over the saphenous veins looked purple
     colored, but the veins did not exhibit any induration. The thigh was amputated at the lower
     third, by the flap method, at 1 P. M., about thirty-six hours subsequent to the accession of
     the secondary arthritis. The patient was under sulphuric ether and bore the operation well.
     Examination of the amputated member showed the inner condyle of the femur to be extensively
     comminuted. There was a layer of yellowish gray colored plastic exudation on the articulating
     surfaces of the fragments in the joint, and the cavity of the joint contained about three
     ounces of reddish brown colored liquid, in which shining globules floated resembling oil in appearance. The synovial membrane was reddened, especially the pouches of it in relation with
     the quadriceps extensor cruris. The subcutaneous areolar tissue was infiltrated with a
     yellowish serum. The bullet was ascertained to have passed behind the joint. On the day
     following the operation the patient's tongue was coated and his appetite poor; he had also
     moderate diarrh&#339;a, the evacuations being very offensive. Five grains of blue mass was
     given at night, and free stimulation with whiskey.  On the 20th, the patient was comfortable and
     the stump looked well. The diarrh&#339;a was unchanged, but during the following several days
     it gradually abated and the patient progressed well in every respect.  28th, patient cheerful;
     tongue clean; appetite good; bowels regular; stump but little swollen; granulations healthy;
     suppuration moderate in quantity and laudable in quality.  30th, patient appeared to be doing
     well, but complained a good deal of pain in and about the stump.  December 1st, patient restless
     and complaining of increased pain in the stump, especially about the end of the bone; no
     preternatural swelling, redness or heat in the stump. Prescribed one-fourth of a grain of
     sulphate of morphia and one drachm of Hoffman's anodyne every four hours.  2d, patient more
     restless, appearing much agitated and very nervous, having slept but little, and complaining of
     agonizing pain about end of bone and end of femoral artery. There were exacerbations in the
     pain and sometimes the whole stump ached, but there was no febrile excitement and nothing
     untoward in the appearance or feel of the stump; neither was it swelled, red, or hot.  <date type="death" when="1863-12-03">3d</date>,
     patient had a bad night, and complained much of sickening pain in end of stump and in bowels.
     About 7 A. M. the ligature separated and a most profuse h&#230;morrhage occurred, the blood
     pouring out in a stream as large as the calibre of the artery. It was finally stopped by
     digital compression, but, in the meantime, he had lost more than six pounds of blood, which
     brought him very low. He was stimulated as freely as possible with whiskey and carbonate of
     ammonia, but did not rally, and died about 3 P. M.  Autopsy twenty-three hours after death:
     Surface of body very pale and waxy (exsanguinated); rigor mortis strong; superficial lymphatic
     ganglia lying along the vena saphena magna of amputated thigh all enlarged and exhibiting a
     faint reddish hue on section; deep ganglia not affected; stump not &#339;dematous and no part
     sloughy; stump healed throughout except in the track of the ligatures and at the end of the
     bone. The femoral ligature had come away and the end of the vessel was patulous, uncontracted,
     and unobstructed. The coats of the artery were infiltrated with blood (recent) at its end and
     for about half an inch above it. A branch of considerable size was given off from the artery
     about three-fourths of an inch above its end, which had apparently interfered with the
     formation of a suitable clot for the permanent plugging up of the vessel; there had been but
     little effort towards occlusion. No other abnormity existed in the artery. The end of the
     femoral vein was well sealed up, the vein itself diminished in size up to the nearest valve, a
     distance of about an inch, and its walls thickened in same locality so as to equal those of the
     femoral artery; lining membrane not stained with blood; no emboli and no thrombi found
     anywhere, and no vein presenting any abnormity, the vena profunda not being overlooked. A
     remarkable osteophyte was found in relation with the femoral artery and vein at their
     respective ends in the stump. It was developed from (connected with) the linea aspera, a little
     above the end of the femur, and thence passed horizontally inward, separating or forking into distinct plates, toward the ends of which the one laid in front of and was
     closely adherent to that side of the artery at and near its end; the other laid behind and was
     adherent to the vein at and near its end. This osteophyte was about seven-eighths of an inch
     wide where broadest, and about one-fourth of an inch thick. It was of recent formation. The
     lower part of the femur in the stump was moderately enlarged by deposit (laminated) of new bone
     beneath the periosteum (hyper-nutrition); this membrane was detached for about one-fourth of an
     inch above the line of the saw all the way round the bone, which presented a dull white color in that locality. The medullary membrane was noticed to bulge out
     a good deal at the end of the bone and to present a dark red or reddish brown color. It was
     also strong and tough (flesh like). On sawing through the lower part of the femur lengthwise
     and cleaning off the bone dust the medullary membrane was seen to be more vascular than
     natural; the medullary tissue exhibited about a dozen small milk-colored abscesses on the
     surface of the section, showing pus under the microscope, and varying in size from that of a
     split pea to a mustard seed. The osseous tissue outside of the medullary canal was more compact
     and heavier than natural in the same locality. The periosteum was thickened to the extent of
     from one to three lines and more vascular than natural, the thickening being greatest where it
     had been detached from the bone. There was also a small abscess, flattened in shape, and
     holding about an ounce of cream-like pus, in the quadriceps extensor cruris muscle, and the red
     muscular tissue in immediate relation with it was changed to a dark brown color, which,
     however, did not extend to any depth. The spleen was enlarged, and the other organs all
     exsanguinated but presenting no other abnormity." The bones of the knee of the amputated limb
      (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 1819), the femoral vein and artery (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi>
     1892), with portion of the osteophyte attached, and a longitudinal half section of the lower
     end of the stump of the femur (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1860, shown in <hi
      rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 4 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XLIII</hi>, opposite p. 290) four
    and one-fourth inches long, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="70">the operator</name>.</p>
   <p>&#185; <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL (<hi rend="initialcap">J. A.</hi>), in <hi rend="italic">Surgical Memoirs</hi>,   &#42;   &#42;   <hi rend="italic">by the United States Sanitary Commission</hi>, New York, 1870, Vol. I, p. 358, gives a detailed account
    of this case.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001815.001" />
    <head>PLATE  XLIII. __ RESULT  OF  OSTEOMYELITIS.    Figs. 4, 5.  Lidell's Case of J. N. Saxton,  Specimen. 1860.</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
