<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e6542">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Lowe, J. W.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e6542</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">344-345</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">                                        
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>condition of Peyer's patches not stated, ileum or small intestine ulcerated and large intestine affected</term>
                                        <term>ileum perforated</term>
                                        <term>peritoneal cavity contained pus</term>
                                        <term>inflammation of all abdominal viscera</term>
                                        <term>neck swollen and stiff from blow of rebel musket</term>
                                        <term>pain in testicle, no swelling but great tenderness</term>
                                        <term>typhoid ulceration and perforation</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00050">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 50.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieut. J. W. Lowe</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B, 9th N. Y.
                                                Cav.</name>, was admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-09-21">Sept. 21, 1863</date>, with his
                                        neck somewhat swollen and stiff, the result of a blow from a
                                        rebel musket at <name type="BATTLE" key="107">Brandy Station, Va.</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-08-01">Aug. 1, 1863</date>; his general
                                        health was good.  On <date type="furlough" when="1863-08-30">the 30th</date> he went home on leave of
                                        absence. He returned November 14 much improved, stating that
                                        during his absence he had an attack of diarrhœa which
                                        lasted only a few days; the attack was preceded by vomiting,
                                        and was attributed by him to some error of diet. He felt
                                        well and expressed himself as able to join his regiment. But
                                        at midnight of <date type="injury" when="1863-11-18">the 18th</date> the officer of the day was called to
                                        see him as he had been seized with a violent pain in the
                                        testicle, without swelling but with great tenderness. An
                                        anodyne lotion relieved him and he fell asleep, but awoke
                                        about daylight vomiting a pale-green liquid and with great
                                        tenderness over the stomach. The abdomen soon became
                                        tympanitic, the pulse sank, the vomiting became constant and
                                        the countenance livid and anxious. A blister was applied and
                                        laudanum given by injection. At noon the vomiting became
                                        less frequent and he was able to swallow small quantities of
                                        brandy and water with morphia; the pulse, however, was
                                        scarcely perceptible and the face and hands were covered
                                        with cold sweat.  He died at <date type="death" when="1863-11-19">3.30 P. M.</date> after vomiting
                                        as much of a pea-green liquid as half filled a common tin
                                        basin.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The
                                        thoracic viscera were healthy. The peritoneal cavity
                                        contained two ounces of pus. The whole intestinal canal was
                                        in a state of acute inflammation; the ileum was perforated
                                        in several places, some of the openings being large enough
                                        to admit the end of the little finger. The inflammatory condition extended to all the abdominal
                                        viscera. "How this state of things existed without symptoms
                                        for a longer period than fifteen hours I am at a loss to
                                        explain or even conjecture. The man was not emaciated; on
                                        the contrary he had gained in flesh during his visit home. I
                                        am informed by his brother, who came for his remains, that
                                        he had complained at times of a pain in the bowels, but of
                                        so slight a character as not to attract much attention and
                                        which was usually relieved by a draught of warm ginger-tea."  [<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 77, Med. Sect.,
                                        <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, showing typhoid ulceration and
                                        perforation, is from this case.]—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="xxx">Surg. H. W.
                                                  Ducachet</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U.S.V.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary Hospital</name>, Georgetown,
                                                D.C.</hi> </p>                       
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
