<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31539">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">I&#8212;&#8212;, Henry L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31539</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb-o">Miguel Beltran-Orozco</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">133</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the liver</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>fatal shot wounds of the liver</term> 
       <term>wounded and captured</term>
       <term>ball entered epigastrium, shattered elbow joint</term>
       <term>an&#230;mic from loss of blood</term>
       <term>ball crossed superior surface of liver, injuring both right and left lobes</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb-o" when="2011-02-16">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>  
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 440.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant <hi rend="italic">Henry L. I</hi>&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">7th South Carolina Battery</name>, aged 38 years, was wounded and captured at the <name type="place">Six Mile House</name>, near <name type="place">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-08-21"> August 21, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon L. W. Read</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, at the 3d division hospital of the Fifth Corps, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon W. L. Faxon</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">32d Massachusetts</name>, at <name type="place">City Point</name>, describe the injury as inflicted by a conical musket ball entering the epigastrium and shattering the right elbow joint. The wounded officer was conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and placed in <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name> on <date type="admit" when="1864-08-24">August 24th</date>, under the care of <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. B. Wright</name>, who reported the patient as "<choice><sic>&#230;nemic</sic><corr>an&#230;mic</corr></choice> from loss of blood, the countenance anxious, the pulse tolerably strong at 95."  There appears to have been no nausea, since the patient took beef-tea and stimulants without inconvenience. There was no jaundice.  On the 25th and 26th, the pulse became smaller and more frequent, and the patient complained of loss of sight. Concentrated nourishment and stimulants were retained, but the patient failed rapidly, and died in the afternoon of <date type="death" when="1864-08-26">August 26, 1864</date>, five days after the reception of the injury.  <name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name> made an autopsy on <date type="autopsy" when="1864-08-27">the following day</date>, and preserved the specimen represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 104), with the following memorandum: "Body well nourished; rigor, well marked; height, 5 feet 11&#189; inches; &#339;sophagus normal. Lining membranes of larynx and trachea were of a pinkish hue. Posterior portion of lower lobe of each lung was very much congested; otherwise the lungs appeared normal; right weighed 20 ounces; left, 15&#189; ounces.  Pericardium normal. The right side of the heart contained a large black clot; left cavities empty; organ healthy; weight, 9&#189; ounces.  Spleen considerably enlarged and pulpy; weight, 14 ounces.  Liver, the ball crossed its superior surface, injuring both the right and left lobe; organ weighed 76&#189; ounces.  Both kidneys were healthy; right weighed 6 ounces; left, 6&#189; ounces." </p>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001760.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 104.&#8212;Section of convex portions of the left and right lobes of the liver grooved by a musket ball passing from left to right.     <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3123.     [Reduced to one-fourth.]</head>
   </figure>  
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
