<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9166">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Moran, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9166</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">191</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recovery after shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered anterior side of thigh at top of middle third, fractured bone, emerged on inner side of thigh at bottom of middle third</term>
     <term>bone united with considerable shortening</term> 
     <term>shot fracture of femur, three and a half inches shortening, anchylosis of knee, impaired power of limb</term>
     <term>injured femur affected with necrosis</term>     
     <term>debility superinduced by necrosis of injured femur, attended by continued exfoliation and suppuration</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-04">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change> 
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 391.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. Moran</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 25th Ohio</name>, aged 22 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>, and admitted to hospital at <name type="place">Alexandria</name> <date type="admit" when="1862-09-03">four days afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported: &#34;A ball entered on the anterior side of the left thigh, at the
    top of the middle third, passed though the limb, fracturing the bone, and emerged on the
    inner side of the thigh, at the bottom of the middle third. The patient was treated by rest
    and position, and the bone united with considerable shortening. He was discharged from
    hospital <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1863-01-30">January 30, 1863</date>.&#34; The man subsequently joined the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve Corps</name>, and
    was ultimately discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-03-28">March 28, 1865</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner S. S.
     Thorn</name>, of <name type="place">Toledo, Ohio</name>, <date type="pension" when="1865-10-03">October 3, 1865</date>, certified to the &#34;shot fracture of the femur, followed by three and a half inches shortening, anchylosis of knee, and impaired power of limb;&#34; also to &#34;the wound being still open and exfoliating bone.&#34; <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner S. M. Smith</name>,
    of <name type="place">Columbus</name>, <date type="pension" when="1866-10">one year later</date> reported the injured femur as affected with necrosis, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner T. A. Reamy</name>, of <name type="place">Cincinnati</name>, in <date type="pension" when="1873-09">September, 1873</date>, describes the &#34;muscles firmly adherent to the bone at the point of the
    injury, an open sinus communicating with the bone anteriorly, and great angular deformity at the union of the fractured bone.&#34;
    The attending physician of the pensioner certified that he died <date type="death" when="1874-11-11">November 11, 1874</date>, of debility superinduced by necrosis of the
    injured femur, which was attended by continued exfoliation and suppuration.</p>
    
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
