<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31369">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Green, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31369</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mh">Minda Haas</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">987</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and operations in the forearm</term> 
       <term>shot wounds of the forearm</term>
       <term>amputations in the continuity of the forearm for shot injury</term> 
       <term>secondary amputations in the forearm for shot injury</term>
       <term>recoveries after secondary amputations in the forearm</term>
       <term>wounded in forearm</term> 
       <term>ball entered arm anteriorly on radial aspect above radio-carpal articulation, escaped posteriorly at ulnar aspect, fracturing radius and ulna</term>
       <term>comminuted oblique fracture of radius an inch from articulation of carpus</term>
       <term>transverse fracture of the ulna</term>
       <term>radius driven into interosseous space, injured posterior interosseous artery, h&#230;morrhage proceeded</term>
       <term>necrosis of fractured parts</term> 
       <term>forearm amputated at middle third for secondary h&#230;morrhage</term>       
       <term>secondary h&#230;morrhage presumed from radial artery</term>    
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mh" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>  
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1929.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. Green</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. C, 35th Massachusetts</name>, aged 23 years, was wounded in the right forearm, at <name type="BATTLE" key="33">Antietam</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-09-17">September 17, 1862</date>, and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="82">Capitol Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-09-23">six days afterward</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon E. DeW. Breneman</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 715), and reported the following history: "The ball entered the arm anteriorly one inch above the radio-carpal articulation, on radial aspect, fracturing that bone, and escaped posteriorly at the ulnar aspect, fracturing that bone also. The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Satterlee Hospital</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1862-10-12">October 12th</date>, his arm in pasteboard splints. It was greatly tumefied and he was in intense pain. Placed the limb upon a straight splint, well padded, and had cold water constantly applied.  On the evening of <date type="injury" when="1862-10-19">October 19th</date>, secondary h&#230;morrhage supervened, presumed to be from the radial artery; the forearm was amputated by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon N. P. Hickman</name>, by the circular method, at the middle third, by the advice of <name type="person" key="294">Assistant Surgeon J. S. Billings</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>  I made an examination of the amputated portion and found a comminuted oblique fracture of the radius, commencing an inch from the articulation of the carpus; also a transverse fracture of the ulna, with the formation of a capsular ligament, thus producing a false joint; and a detached portion of the radius driven into the interosseous space and injuring the posterior interosseous artery, from which the h&#230;morrhage proceeded. Considerable callus was thrown out between the injured portions of each bone posteriorly, and at this part of the radius nature also made an attempt to form a capsular ligament. The radio-carpal articulation was uninjured."  This patient was transferred to the care of <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon A. H. Smith</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who reports, <date type="injury" when="1862-10-23">October 23rd</date>, that "he had removed pieces of bone occasionally, and that the wound was nearly healed."  The patient was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-01-17">January 17, 1863</date>, pensioned, and was paid <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>.  The specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 715) shows the lower halves of the bones of the forearm, with necrosis of the fractured parts and slight osseous deposits above the lines of necrosis.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001744.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 715.&#8212;Necrosed bones of forearm after secondary amputation.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 880.</head>
   </figure> 
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
