<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7106">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Bangson, Charles</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e7106</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">347</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial fever</term>
                                        <term>entered as typho-malarial with or without a record of symptoms to substantiate the diagnosis</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's glands enlarged, ulcerated lower down near ileo-c&#230;cal valve, but not deeper than mucous membrane</term>
                                        <term>solitary glands enlarged, dark-purple color in lower ileum, ulcerated nearest termination of ileum</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of c&#230;cum and ascending colon dark-bluish color</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                        
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00068">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 68.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="641">Private Charles Bangson</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="124">Co. I, 14th
                                                Conn.</name>; age 27; was admitted <date
                                                type="admit" when="1863-10-19">Oct. 19, 1863</date>,
                                        with typho-malarial fever.  He had been sick <date type="injury" when="1863-10-07">for twelve days</date>
                                        and on admission was in a semi-comatose condition; tongue
                                        dry, glazed and red at the tip and edges; pulse 120, full,
                                        bounding and incompressible.  On the 27th the pulse was 108
                                        and scarcely perceptible at the wrist; the patient had some
                                        cough with thick, tenacious yellowish <choice><orig>sputa</orig><reg>sputum</reg></choice>. The
                                        ileo-c&#230;cal region was tender, but no eruption was
                                        observed.  Death occurred on <date type="death"
                                                when="1863-10-29">the 29th</date>.  At first tincture of
                                        aconite was given, for which, on the 25th, quinine,
                                        carbonate of ammonia and whiskey were substituted.  <hi
                                                rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-10-29">">four
                                        hours after death</date>: The trachea was palish but mottled at its
                                        bifurcation; several ecchymotic spots were observed on its
                                        posterior surface. The &#339;sophagus was pale and its
                                        mucous membrane firm. The right lung was perfectly healthy;
                                        the left lung weighed thirty-one ounces and a half, its
                                        upper lobe being congested generally and solidified in its
                                        central parts and its lower lobe mottled with dark-brown
                                        spots about the size of a pea. The heart contained fibrinous
                                        clots in its right chambers. The liver was congested and
                                        weighed seventy-two ounces; the spleen firm, fourteen ounces
                                        and a half; the pancreas normal; the kidneys congested. The
                                        small intestine near the ileo-c&#230;cal valve was of a
                                        darker color than elsewhere; its mucous membrane was healthy
                                        to within ten feet of the valve, at which point it became
                                        unusually vascular and softened, Peyer's patches and the
                                        solitary glands being of a deep pink color; lower down
                                        Peyer's glands became enlarged, whitish and hard, with
                                        abrupt edges; still lower down they were ulcerated, which
                                        condition frequently existed in the centre of a patch while
                                        its margins remained enlarged and hard; the glands near the
                                        valve were ulcerated in their whole superfices, some of them
                                        looking not unlike Hunterian chancres; the ulceration did
                                        not extend deeper than the mucous membrane; the solitary
                                        glands were enlarged and of a dark-purple color in the lower
                                        part of the ileum, and some near its termination were
                                        ulcerated. The mucous membrane of the c&#230;cum and
                                        ascending colon was of a dark-bluish color; lower down it
                                        was pale and in some places pink; the solitary glands were
                                        conspicuous but not elevated, appearing as whitish spots
                                        with pigmented centres.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="245">Ass't Surg. Harrison Allen</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name
                                                type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>,
                                        Washington, D. C. </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
