<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31416">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">P.&#8212;&#8212;, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31416</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="cp">Chang Pang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">540</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
       <term>decapitations of the humerus for shot injury</term>
       <term>intermediary decapitations of the humerus for shot injury</term>
       <term>unsuccessful cases of intermediary decapitation of the humerus</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of shoulder</term> 
       <term>ball entered over coracoid process of scapula, emerged after splintering head of humerus</term>
       <term>patient absolutely refused operation</term>
       <term>excision of head of humerus</term> 
       <term>py&#230;mia</term>
       <term>head of humerus excised at surgical neck after fracture at greater tuberosity by conoidal bullet</term>       
       <term>inner part of anatomical neck of humerus carried away</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#cp" when="2011-02-20">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1511.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant J. P.&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 4th Michigan</name>, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="71">Malvern Hill</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-07-01">July 1, 1862</date>.  He was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="168">Cliffburne Hospital</name>.  <name type="person" key="294">Assistant Surgeon J. S. Billings</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, reported: &#34;Gunshot wound of the left shoulder. The ball entered over the coracoid process of the scapula, passed in a horizontal line outward and a little backward, and emerged, after splintering the head of the humerus. At the date of his admission, there was very little swelling of the part, slight discharge, and no constitutional symptoms. The patient could move the arm without difficulty or pain, and absolutely refused to have any operation performed.  <date type="injury" when="1862-07-11">After ten days</date> had elapsed, suppuration having greatly increased, the arm became brawny and &#339;dematous, and hectic supervened. A probe was introduced; and the patient, having been informed that he would certainly die if the operation of excision of the head of the humerus were not resorted to, consented to have it done. On the afternoon of <date type="operation" when="1862-07-11">the same day</date>, a semi-circular incision was made from the posterior edge of the wound to within an inch of the interior. The integument having been laid back, the furrow made by the ball and spicula detached in its passage were seen. Forcing the head of the bone out of the cavity, <name type="person" key="294">Dr. Billings</name> removed it with the saw, just below the tuberosities. There was slight h&#230;morrhage from the deep-seated vessels, which were retracted beneath the capsule in such a way as to prevent their being twisted. The wound was left unclosed, stuffed with lint, and dressed with cold water. No recurrence of the bleeding took place during the night, but upon the removal of the charpie in the morning, there was a slight h&#230;morrhage, easily stopped by the persulphate of iron. The brawny feel had disappeared, together with the pain and &#339;dema.  From this period, until three days before his death, <date type="death" when="1862-07-21">July 21st</date>, the patient remained without any change of consequence taking place.  Under the influence of the treatment adopted, he retained his strength to all appearance, and the power of his faculties.  Suddenly, however, the edges of the wound broke down, its odor became very offensive, and subsultus and hectic supervened. Successive rigors, increasing in violence, set in, with short intermissions, and the patient rapidly succumbed.  The autopsy disclosed no derangement of the viscera; no disease of the heart and lungs. The periosteum was not stripped off the bone of the wounded limb, but the brachial and cephalic veins opposite to the seat of the injury were thickened very much, and the axillary up to within an inch of the clavicle. One sinus, not of a metastatic character, was revealed, extending from the axilla along the upper third of the humerus. The patient died in the first stage of py&#230;mia.&#34;  The specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 410) was one of the earlier contributions to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> (<hi rend="italic">Cat. Army Med. Mus.</hi>, 1863, p. 9), and is represented in the adjacent wood-cut. It has been described (<hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1866, p. 93) as: &#34;The head of the left humerus, excised at the surgical neck after fracture by a conoidal bullet at the greater tuberosity, which, with the inner part of the anatomical neck, is carried away.&#34;</p> 
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001748.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 410.&#8212;Head of left humerus, excised a week after shot fracture.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 14.</head>
   </figure>  
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
