<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e21795">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Lazier, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e21795</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">584</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>bullet entered close to anterior edge of internal malleolus, internal malleolus slightly comminuted</term> 
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>pus accumulated in calf of the leg</term>
     <term>pleurisy</term> 
     <term>metastatic abscesses in lungs caused by py&#230;mia</term> 
     <term></term>
     <term></term>
     <term></term> 
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>femoral artery ligated</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 832.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1364">Private W. Lazier</name>, <name type="organization" key="513">Co. M, 5th Artillery</name>, aged 25 years,
     was wounded in the right ankle joint, at <name type="BATTLE" key="107">Brandy Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-08-01">August 1, 1863</date>, by a bullet, which entered close
     to the anterior edge of the internal malleolus, slightly comminuting it. On <date type="admit" when="1863-08-02">the following day</date>
     he was conveyed to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name> at Washington. The
     missile was supposed to have lodged, there being no external wound of exit and the patient not
     being aware of it having been removed. On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-03">the next day</date> <name type="person" key="200">Assistant
      Surgeon W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of
     the hospital, etherized the patient and explored for the missile, but it could not be found.
     The comminution was so slight that it was deemed possible to save the foot with the aid of free
     incisions should they become necessary. A prescription consisting of two drachms of fluid
     extract of rhubarb, one scruple of quinine, and three ounces of whiskey was ordered, on August
     5th, to be given in teaspoonful doses every four hours. Dead bone having been felt with the
     probe, and the inflammation becoming so extensive and severe as to render operative
     interference necessary, two large incisions were made at the sides of the internal malleolus on
     <date type="operation" when="1863-08-08">August 8th</date>, by <name type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. Carvallo</name>, and
     several loose fragments of bone were extracted. On this day the patient also had a chill of ten minutes
     duration, and one-half drachm of quinine dissolved in four ounces of whiskey was prescribed to
     be taken in tablespoonful doses. On August 11th the inflammation became erysipelatous,
     involving the leg below the knee, and there was another chill. The quinine and whiskey mixture
     was then repeated and tincture of iodine was used to the limb, after which a wash consisting of
     one-half ounce of muriate of ammonia, ten grains of acetate of morphia, two ounces of sulphuric
     ether, and one pint of water, was applied over it. On August 13th there was still pain,
     swelling, and redness, and another chill of fifteen minutes duration took place. Fluctuation
     was well marked, and incisions were made to give free exit to pus. In addition to the quinine,
     tablespoonful doses of a mixture of two drachms of muriated tincture of iron, two ounces each
     of spirit of Mindererus and water, and half an ounce of simple syrup, were administered three
     times a day. On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-15">August 15th</date>, incisions were again required over both malleoli and another on
     the on the calf of the leg to allow accumulated pus  to discharge. The patient's condition was now too much depressed to allow an amputation. Two days later pleurisy developed, which was treated by
     counter-irritation of turpentine and alcohol fomentations to the breast, and mustard poultices.
     On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-18">August 18th</date> the limb had grown very red, swollen, and painful as high as the knee, and,
     fluctuation being felt, another incision was made by <name type="person" key="208">Dr.
      Carvallo</name>, after which the leg was placed in a bran-box, and the wash, with one-half
     drachm of fluid extract of hyosciamus superadded, was re-applied. H&#230;morrhage from one of
     the incisions in the calf of the leg, and supposed to proceed from one of the muscular branches, came on one-half hour afterwards, when
     cold water, alum, and compression was applied, and Hoffman's anodyne mixed with brandy and water was given every half
     hour. H&#230;morrhages recurred in the afternoon and evening, being decidedly arterial, and
     were checked by persulphate of iron applied with charpie. Though active interference was
     demanded, the undoubted disease of the lungs caused by metastatic abscesses from py&#230;mia,
     together with the very rapid and difficult respiration and the collapse of the patient from the
     loss of six or eight ounces of blood, made amputation impossible. The only other resort being
     ligation of the femoral, ether was carefully administered and that operation was performed at 9 P. M., at the point of election, by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant
      Surgeon Thomson</name>, the leg being so distended with clotted blood as to make any effort to
     secure the divided vessels abortive. The clots of blood were removed from the leg by
     compression, and after the operation the case was treated with the largest doses of stimulants,
     including aromatic spirits of ammonia and fluid extract of senega. Though he reacted from the
     low state he was in before the operation, the patient gradually sank during the night and died
     at 8 A. M. on <date type="death" when="1863-08-19">August 19, 1863</date>.  At the autopsy both
     lungs were found to be filled with metastatic abscesses; there was also effusion of serum in
     both thoracic cavities. No injured artery could be detected, nor could the missile be found.
     The detailed notes of the case were furnished by the operators. <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name> also contributed the bones of the injured ankle (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1682), showing the articular surfaces to be eroded by suppuration and the internal malleolus to be slightly fractured. </p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
