<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e22237">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Davis, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e22237</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">590</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint</term>
     <term>excisions at the ankle joint for shot injury</term> 
     <term>intermediary excisions at the ankle joint</term> 
     <term>fatal intermediary excisions at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot wound of foot and hip</term>
     <term>gunshot wound of tarsus</term> 
     <term> ball struck below external malleolus, passed through tarsus horizontally, escaping below and behind internal malleolus</term> 
     <term>resection of anterior extremity and part of external <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice></term>
     <term>py&#230;mia</term>
     <term>ankle joint contained pus, bones partially denuded of cartilage, muscles of leg infiltrated with pus</term> 
     <term>lungs contained several abscesses and lobular pneumonia</term>
     <term>thrombi in femoral vein</term> 
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term> 
     <term>pneumonic symptoms, blood mingled with sputa</term>
     <term><choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice> fractured entirely through, its cancellous structure gangrenous</term>
     <term>osteomyelitis, shown by gangrene of cancellous tissue</term>     
     <term>breath bovine</term> 
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 851.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1373">Private J.
      Davis</name>, <name type="organization" key="101">Co. L, 1st Michigan Cavalry</name>, aged 18
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="83">Salem Church</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-28">May 28,1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon W. H.
      Rulison</name>, <name type="organization" key="474">9th New York Cavalry</name>, reported his
     admission to the field hospital of the 1st division, Cavalry Corps, "with shot wound of left foot and hip."  <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J.
      A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who operated in the
     case, made the following report:  "The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-06-04">June 4th</date>,
     with a gunshot wound of the left tarsus, inflicted by a mini&#233; ball, which struck the foot a
     little below the external malleolus and passed through the tarsus horizontally inward and
     somewhat backward, escaping a little below and behind the internal malleolus. It occasioned
     compound comminuted fracture of the <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice>, <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>, and posterior edge of the external malleolus. At the
     time of the operation, <date type="operation" when="1864-06-10">June 10th</date>, the ankle and foot were much swollen, inflamed, and very
     painful; the leg was also swollen. The edges of the orifices of both entrance and exit were
     pouting and exhibited no tendency to close; discharge thin and scanty. Since the patient came
     to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name> the wound had been treated with ice
     dressings, but was manifestly growing worse. He now had a good deal of constitutional
     disturbance; pulse quick and ranging from 110 to 120; skin dry and too warm; countenance
     pinched and anxious; tongue coated, and appetite poor. He was also restless, got but little
     sleep, and his general condition was daily getting worse. Wishing to avoid secondary amputation
     of the leg if possible on account of the great fatality which had lately attended it, resection
     was performed of the anterior extremity and part of the external side of the <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice>. Some
     fragments of the <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice> were also extracted, and a splinter from the posterior edge of the
     external malleolus. The incisions were made on the external side of the foot, from the orifice
     of entrance, first, to the base of the metatarsal bone of the little toe; second, to the base
     of the external malleolus; third, to the point of the heel; and fourth, to the dorsum of the
     foot, two and a half inches. Sulphuric ether constituted the an&#230;sthetic. There was no
     shock. Ice-water dressings were continued. On June 11th the patient was cheerful and free from
     pain and the swelling and irritative fever had abated.  He died of py&#230;mia on <date
      type="death" when="1864-06-20">June 20, 1864</date>.  Autopsy: The ankle joint contained pus;
     the bones were partially denuded of their cartilage; muscles of leg infiltrated with pus. The
     left pleural cavity contained a large quantity of dark-colored effusion, and the left lung was
     compressed against the vertebral column; the inferior lobe contained an abscess about the size
     of an egg, which was filled with dark-colored and offensive pus. The right lung contained several superficial abscesses and some patches of
     lobular pneumonia. Thrombi existed in the femoral vein."  In his publication&#185; of the operation <name type="person" key="70">the operator</name> furnished the
     following supplementary details of the patient's progress, as well as of the autopsy, in
     addition to his comments on the case:  After the operation "the limb was placed upon a wire
     splint (Smith's) bent to a right angle, which was well padded and applied to the posterior part
     of the leg and sole of the foot, where it was properly secured by roller bandages for the
     purpose of keeping the ankle joint in a fixed position. The wound was plugged with lint and a
     full opiate was given. The constitutional treatment consisted in the administration of
     nutrients, tonics, and stimulants. On June 12th the patient had a severe py&#230;mic chill and
     sweat, and quinine in full doses was added to the treatment. On the next day he was much worse;
     wound discharging a thin dark-colored pus; chills and sweats increasing in frequency and
     severity; complexion assumed a bronzed hue; breath bovine; body exhaling a sweet mawkish smell;
     anorexia; debility; diarrh&#339;a set in. Pneumonic symptoms also appeared, and a large
     proportion of blood was mingled with the sputa. He sank rapidly. At the autopsy the <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice>
     was found to be fractured entirely through and its cancellous structure was gangrenous. The <choice><orig>astragalo-scaphoid</orig><reg>tarso-scaphoid</reg></choice> articulation contained pus and the articulating surface of its bones was
     entirely denuded of its cartilage. The connective tissue on the front of the leg was
     infiltrated with pus from the ankle joint upward to the extent of three inches, and the tibia
     and fibula were denuded of periosteum to the extent of two inches. The liver and spleen were
     both enlarged and softened, but the kidneys presented a normal appearance. There were clots in
     both ventricles of the heart.  Comments: In this case also osteomyelitis supervened, which was
     conclusively shown by the gangrenous condition of the cancellous tissue belonging to the <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice>, or, rather, the gangrenous condition of the
     medullary tissue which filled the cancelli of that bone. Besides, it is probable that if the
     interior of the tibia and fibula had been examined the marrow would have been found inflamed at
     and above the place where those bones were seen to be denuded of periosteum at the <hi
      rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination. It is also probable that the medullary tissue of
     the denuded portion of the tibia contained collections of purulent matter which were produced
     by the suppurative character of the inflammatory process involving that tissue. Furthermore, it
     is probable that the inflammatory process had extended to the medullary tissue of the tibia
     prior to the performance of the resection of the tarsus, and if its presence there had then been recognized, it would have
     contra-indicated that operation and called for amputation far up the limb. The thrombosis of
     the femoral vein was of recent occurrence. The coagulated blood which filled that vein
     presented a fresh appearance and had not yet undergone the puriform transformation, nor even
     become at all softened. It was therefore obvious that the thrombosis had not occasioned the
     visceral abscesses nor the inflammation of the lungs, since the morbid process in those organs
     was considerably older than the thrombus of the femoral vein. The thrombosis was a more recent
     event than the py&#230;mia. This circumstance is important, because it shows that the
     py&#230;mic process in this case could not have had its origin in the thrombosis, and that if
     any relationship or necessary connection existed between them, the py&#230;mic process induced
     the formation of the thrombi. The symptoms of irritative fever (or, speaking properly, the
     surgical fever of an irritative type), which where so strikingly relieved by the operation, had
     been produced entirely by local causes, namely, the inflammation of the various structures
     bordering upon and connected with the gunshot wound, such as the connective, the fibrous, the osseous, and the medullary tissues. The symptoms of the purulent
     infection did not make their appearance till two days after the operation. They presented a marked contrast to those of the
     surgical fever which preceded the operation. They denoted the occurrence of a poisoned
     condition of the blood and the whole system, under which the patient sank rapidly, and died on
     the eighth day after its advent."</p>
   <p>&#185; <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL (<hi rend="initialcap">JOHN A.</hi>), in <hi rend="italic">U. S. Sanitary Commission Memoirs</hi>, Surgical Volume I, pp. 524-6, and <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ULBERTSON (<hi rend="initialcap">H.</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Excision of the Larger Joints of the Extremities</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the American Med. Association</hi>, Philadelphia, 1876, Supplement to Vol. XXVII, p. 314.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
