<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31891">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">L&#8212;&#8212;, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31891</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">216</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the pelvis</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the pelvic bones</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the ilium</term> 
       <term>ball entered groin outside of femoral artery and below Poupart's ligament, extended backward</term>
       <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>py&#230;mia</term>
       <term>ball struck os innominatum, compound impacted fracture of bone above acetabulum</term>
       <term>ball passed into pelvic cavity and found lying under bladder</term>
       <term>abscess in right lobe of liver</term>
       <term>ball contused internal surface of ilium below and behind anterior inferior spinous process</term>
       <term>yellow discoloration of skin general over whole body and whites of eyes</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-09-06">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 630.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant William L&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. D, 10th New York Cavalry</name>, aged 25 years, was admitted to hospital at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-10-15">October 15, 1863</date>, having received a gunshot wound at <name type="BATTLE" key="26">Bristoe's Station</name> on <date type="injury" when="1863-10-14">the previous day</date>. The ball entered the left groin one-half inch to the outside of the femoral artery and half an inch below Poupart's ligament, extending backward; the probe could be passed toward the pelvic cavity for a distance of five inches, but the ball could not be found. At the time of admission there were no symptoms of injury of the abdominal viscera; his general health was good, and there was no derangement of the functions. On October 16th, he was attacked with a violent diarrh&#339;a and had passages of a light-green color; the pain in the groin was slightly relieved and the diarrh&#339;a was partly controlled on the next day, and, on the 19th, he had a slight chill, and there was a yellow discoloration of the skin around the wound; pulse 100, and feeble; patient weak; diarrh&#339;a more severe.  The yellow discoloration of the skin increased, and, by the 21st, was decided and general over the whole body and whites of the eyes.  On <date type="death" when="1863-10-22">the 22d</date>, the bowels were regular as to the number of passages, but of a loose character and light-green color; pulse 100, and feeble; he had a severe chill, and died five minutes afterward, death being caused by py&#230;mia. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination showed that the ball had struck the os innominatum and caused a compound impacted fracture of a portion of the bone, two inches square, above the acetabulum. The ball had passed into the pelvic cavity, and was found lying directly under the bladder. The whole course of the intestinal canal as well as the stomach was found highly congested. An abscess was found in the right lobe of the liver containing two and a half ounces of pus, and the whole organ was softened. All the abdominal viscera were congested. The specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 144) consists of the iliac portion of the left acetabulum and adjacent bone, with a conoidal ball (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 145), which has contused the internal surface of the ilium just below and behind the anterior inferior spinous process, and was contributed, together with the history, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. Hunt Stillwell</name>.</p>   
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001788.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 144.&#8212;Shot fracture of the inner lamina of the left ilium.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1743.</head>
   </figure>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001789.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 145.&#8212;Ball taken from the pelvic cavity.</head>
   </figure>  
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
