<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31454">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Carroll, S. S.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31454</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="cd-mg">Corey Day and Martine Gouw</persName>  
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">848</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>excisions at the elbow joint for shot injury</term>
       <term>primary excisions at the elbow</term>
       <term>recoveries after primary excisions at the elbow</term> 
       <term>only upper extremity of radius resected</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of arm, resection of radius</term>
       <term>wound of elbow</term> 
       <term>ball traversed elbow</term>
       <term>head of radius comminuted, anterior surface of ulna broken, including coronoid process</term>
       <term>resection of head of radius performed on the field</term>
       <term>complete anchylosis of elbow joint</term>
       <term>erysipelas</term>
       <term>use of wrist joint and of hand and fingers unimpaired</term>          
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#cd-mg" when="2011-02-20">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1781.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Colonel S. S. Carroll</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">8th Ohio</name>, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice><orig>Spottsylvania</orig><reg>Spotsylvania</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-12">May 12, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. L. Brenton</name>, of <name type="organization" key="xxx">the regiment</name>, recorded the injury as follows: "Gunshot wound of left arm; resection of radius." The patient entered the field hospital of the 2d division, Second Corps, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. F. Dyer</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">19th Massachusetts</name>, recorded: "Wound of left elbow; cold-water dressings."  In a report to the <name type="person" key="xxx">Medical Director</name> of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Army of the Potomac</name>, dated November 4, 1864, <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon A. N. Dougherty</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Medical Director Second Corps</name>, makes mention of this case as follows: "<name type="person" key="xxx">Colonel Carroll</name> was wounded by a minié ball, which traversed the left elbow. He was brought to the hospital near <name type="place">Alsop's Mills</name>, where I saw him. Before any examination of the injury (which was of course made under chloroform) he insisted that an effort should be made to save the arm, and I assented. The head of the radius was comminuted and the anterior surface of the ulna, including, as I thought, the coronoid process, was broken. I enlarged the wound with the scalpel; with the chain saw I removed the head of the radius, and with the forceps I picked out whatever loose spiculæ of bone presented themselves; then having the wounds patulous, I put up the arm in a hollow obtuse angle splint. After a very exhausting operation, and irritative fever lasting all summer, and accompanied by bed-sores and great emaciation, he is, as I learn by recent advices, recovering slowly but satisfactorily.  The wounds are still uncicatrized, and there is complete anchylosis of the joint.  He was confined to bed almost three months since he left; since that time he has gained greatly in strength and weight."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Colonel Carroll</name> was promoted Brigadier General, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, on <date type="promotion" when="1864-06-14">Jun 14, 1864</date>, and mustered out <date type="servicedischarge" when="1866-06-15">June 15, 1866</date>.  Subsequently he was appointed Lieutenant Colonel of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">21st Infantry</name>, and on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1869-06-09">June 9, 1869</date>, he was retired from active service with the rank of Major General.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon B. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, was requested to report the result in this case, and had the kindness to furnish the following memorandum: "I have read the narrative of the case of <name type="person" key="xxx"><choice><orig>Major-General</orig><reg>Major General</reg></choice> S. S. Carroll</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. Army</name>, retired, and can only add that he was under my care, at his mother's house in <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, two or three months after the operation of resection of the head of the radius was performed on the field by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Dougherty</name>. Erysipelas supervened and extended up the arm and over the shoulder, and for two years after he suffered pain and occasionally abscesses, and particles of necrosed bone were discharged. I meet him frequently in <name type="place" key="#Washington">the city</name> and at his house in <name type="place">Montgomery county, Maryland</name>. The elbow joint is completely anchylosed. He has use of the wrist joint and of the hand and fingers unimpaired. He can hold the fork firmly in carving at table, and says the arm is invaluable."</p>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
