<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11145">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Kemper, John</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e11145</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">777-778</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases attributed to non-miasmatic exposures</term>
                                        <term>diseases of the respiratory organs</term>
                                        <term>pneumonia</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term> 
                                        <term>lobar pneumonias</term>
                                        <term>cases of coexisting tubercle</term>
                                        <term><choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> over apex of right lung and lower part of left lung</term>
                                        <term>left lung compressed and heart rolled to right side by effused pleural liquid</term>
                                        <term>right lung compressed anteriorly and adherent to parietal pleura</term>
                                        <term>apex of right lung contained walled abscess, remainder darkened by black deposits</term>
                                        <term>right middle and lower lobes crepitant and dark-red posteriorly</term>
                                        <term>left lung speckled with scattered tubercular deposits</term>
                                        <term>heart enlarged</term>
                                        <term>liver large, smooth on surface, granular, dotted clay-yellow</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>                        
                        <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 143.&#8212;<name type="person">John Kemper</name>, substitute, age 44;
                                admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-07-20">July 20, 1864</date>.  He caught cold about <date type="injury" when="1864-07-13">a week before
                                        admission</date>, while en route to his regiment. His countenance
                                was pale and he suffered from cough, dyspn&#339;a and acute
                                diarrh&#339;a. There was <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> over the apex of the right and
                                        lower part of the left lung. The heart-sounds were muffled
                                        and indistinct, but a clear metallic sound was heard over
                                        the apex during the first beat. The diarrh&#339;a was checked,
                                        but the cough and dyspn&#339;a became so distressing that the
                                        patient had to sit up constantly.  From August 15 till death,
                                        on <date type="death" when="1864-08-30">the 30th</date>, the heart-sounds could not be heard or the
                                pulsation felt.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The upper anterior
                                        edge of the left lung adhered to the right costal
                                        cartilages, the outer inferior edge to the left costal wall,
                                        the inner inferior edge to the diaphragm; a long membranous
                                        band stretched outward, forward and slightly upward from the
                                        anterior surface of the upper lobe to the parietal pleura
                                        about the third rib; the lung was compressed by two pints
                                        of liquid, but a space of half-gallon capacity remained
                                        anterior to the effused liquid. The heart was rolled over to
                                        the right side so that the outer side of the left ventricle
                                        presented forward under the anterior edge of the left lung,
                                        and the anterior surface of the right ventricle was pushed
                                        under the adherent inner edge of the right middle lobe. The
                                        right lung was compressed anteriorly and adherent by its
                                        entire outer surface to the parietal pleura; its apex
                                        contained a cartilaginous-walled abscess the size of a
                                        small orange, and its remaining parts were darkened by
                                        close, black, mottling deposits; the middle lobe and lower
                                        lobe posteriorly were crepitant and dark-red. The substance
                                        of the left lung was speckled with scattered tubercular
                                        deposits of the size of raisins and also with dark deposits
                                        as on the right side; the anterior edge of the lower lobe
                                        contained two abscesses of the size, respectively, of a
                                        walnut and of a raisin. The heart was enlarged, pale and
                                        softened; a large black coagulum, tipped with fibrin, filled its right
                                        side. The liver was large, smooth on its surface, granular,
                                        dotted clay-yellow; the spleen of normal size,
                                        light-colored, bloodless, softened; kidneys small; intestines healthy. &#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="189">Third Division Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name></hi> </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
