<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18259">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Semmons, William</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e18259</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date
                                                  when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">372-373</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the face</term> 
                                                                  <term>plastic operations</term>       
                                                                  <term>cheiloplastic operations</term>
                                                                  <term>complex operations for vicious cicatrices</term>
                                                                  <term>complex operations for losses of tissue in soft parts of the face</term>
                                                                  <term>reparative autoplastic operation</term>
                                                                  <term>gunshot wounds of the face</term> 
                                                                  <term>gunshot fractures of the facial bones</term>                                                                  
                                                                  <term>fracture of upper maxilla</term> 
                                                                  <term>fracture of lower maxilla</term> 
                                                                  <term> face extensively disfigured</term>
                                                                  <term>mastication impracticable</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-11-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text>
                                <body>
                                                
                                                <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private William Semmons</name>, <name type="organization">Co. F, 14th New
                                                                York Heavy Artillery</name>, aged 20 years, was wounded
                                                                at <name type="BATTLE" key="254">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-25">March 25th, 1865</date>, by a fragment of
                                                  shell, which entered the right cheek, fractured
                                                  the zygomatic process of the malar bone,
                                                  comminuted the ramus and body of the inferior
                                                  maxilla, lacerated and opened the ducts of the
                                                  parotid and maxillary glands, and removed all the
                                                  integuments of the cheek, leaving the right angle
                                                  of the mouth hanging loose. He was taken to the
                                                  field hospital of the Ninth Corps, where about two
                                                  inches of the alveoli of the <name type="operation">superior maxilla was
                                                                  excised</name> and the wound stitched. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-01">April 1st</date>, he
                                                                was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>,
                                                  Washington. Owing to his inability to swallow,
                                                  liquid food and stimulants were introduced by the
                                                  stomach pump. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-09-21">September 21st</date>, he was
                                                                transferred to De Camp Hospital, <name type="place">New York Harbor</name>,
                                                                and discharged from service on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-10-21">October 21st, 1865</date>.
                                                                On <date type="admit" when="1865-10-26">October 26th</date>, he was admitted to the <name type="hospital">New York
                                                                                Hospital</name>. The wounded parts had been completely
                                                  cicatrized for more than two months. The face was
                                                  extensively disfigured. The chin, owing to the
                                                  absence of the lower jaw, had retracted and lost
                                                  its prominence. On the right side of the face a
                                                  cicatrix extended from the middle of the zygoma to
                                                  the angle of the mouth, at which latter point it
                                                  was deeply depressed and closely adherent to the
                                                  alveolar margin of the upper jaw, from which the
                                                  teeth had been carried away. This adhesion had
                                                  drawn up the upper lip and lengthened it
                                                  considerably toward the right side. The lower lip
                                                  having been detached by a laceration vertically at
                                                  the right angle of the mouth, and also
                                                  horizontally by another laceration crossing the
                                                  upper part of the chin, nearly an inch below its
                                                  vermilion border, had dropped below its proper
                                                  level and become adherent, leaving a separation
                                                  between the two lips at the right angle of the
                                                  mouth of a finger's breadth, which exposed the end
                                                  of the tongue to view, and permitted a constant
                                                  escape of saliva. Irregular cicatrical lines
                                                  crossed each other below the left angle of the
                                                  mouth, one of which passed across the left cheek
                                                  nearly to its middle. All that remained of the
                                                  lower jaw was the upper half of the ramus on the
                                                  right side, and the entire ramus, with the angle
                                                  supporting two molar teeth, on the left side. From
                                                  the point where the right angle of the mouth
                                                  adhered to the upper jaw, a free, callous, thick
                                                  border of skin stretched across the cavity of the
                                                  mouth and terminated at the left angle of the jaw,
                                                  to which it firmly adhered. This was, evidently,
                                                  the lacerated edge from which the lower lip had
                                                  been torn by the original injury and had remained
                                                  separated. It performed the important office of a
                                                  substitute for the lower jaw, affording support to
                                                  the tongue, the attachments of which were felt
                                                  connecting with its posterior surface. The last
                                                  upper molar tooth on the right side remained <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi>. All the upper teeth between it and the left
                                                  canine were gone, those beyond the canine on the left side
                                                  remaining. Upon introducing the finger into the
                                                  mouth, it was found that the body of the tongue
                                                  was bound on the right side to the adjacent parts
                                                  by adhesion, and its movement of protrusion
                                                  thereby limited. Mastication being impracticable,
                                                  the patient was restricted to the use of soft
                                                  solids and liquids. Deglutition was unimpaired.
                                                  His articulation was very defective, owing to the
                                                  confinement of the tongue by the adhesions. In
                                                  consequence of this defect, the patient was averse
                                                  to using his voice, and preferred making himself
                                                  understood by signs and the use of a pencil and
                                                  paper. His health was good, his complexion florid,
                                                  and his general appearance robust. On <date type="operation" when="1865-11-07">November
                                                                  7th</date>, <name type="person">Dr. Gurdon Buck</name> performed the following
                                                  reparative autoplastic operation: The lower lip
                                                  was detached by a horizontal incision extending
                                                  along the cicatricial line crossing the chin, to a
                                                  point below the left angle of the mouth. The
                                                  entire thickness of the lip, with its lining
                                                  mucous membrane, was divided. Its vermilion
                                                  border, which had shrunken into a fan-like shape
                                                  by cicatrization, could now be straightened out
                                                  and applied to the upper lip throughout its entire
                                                  length. To form a new angle for the mouth, a point
                                                  was chosen at the margin of the upper lip,
                                                  equidistant from the median line with the left
                                                  angle, and at this point the border was pared away
                                                  obliquely. A corresponding point was chosen on the
                                                  lower lip and pared in the same manner. The two
                                                  fresh cut surfaces were brought into accurate
                                                  apposition and secured by sutures. The adherent
                                                  right extremity of the upper lip was dissected up
                                                  from the alveolar border of the jaw, and from this
                                                  point an incision was carried outward and upward,
                                                  along the upper margin of the cicatrix crossing
                                                  the cheek as high as the zygoma. The skin and
                                                  subjacent tissue were detached freely toward the
                                                  orbit and temple. Another incision was then
                                                  commenced below the left angle of the mouth, at a
                                                  point where the incision detaching the under lip
                                                  terminated, and carried to the right, across the
                                                  chin, at a finger's breadth below the free callous
                                                  border above described as constituting a
                                                  substitute for the lost jaw. This incision was
                                                  continued on obliquely upward and outward, over
                                                  the cheek below, and close to the cicatrix as far
                                                  as the zygoma. A third incision, beginning at the
                                                  starting point of the preceding one, below the
                                                  left angle of the mouth, was carried
                                                  perpendicularly downward a distance of two inches
                                                  upon the neck. In its course a cyst, of the size
                                                  of a dollar, was encountered, filled with a
                                                  brownish, transparent, viscid fluid, such as is
                                                  met with in ranula, and was dissected out entire.
                                                  The angle included between these two incisions, as
                                                  well as the integument below, crossing the right
                                                  cheek, were extensively detached from the parts
                                                  beneath. An upper and lower flap, including the
                                                  entire right cheek and nearly the whole chin, were
                                                  thus formed. They were separated by the cicatrix
                                                  crossing the cheek, which had been left <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi>.
                                                  After paring off the surfaces of the cicatrix,
                                                  the edges of the flaps were brought together so as
                                                  to cover it up, and secured by sutures. At the
                                                  right angle of the mouth, reconstructed in the
                                                  manner already described, the flaps above and
                                                  below were matched to the lips and also secured by
                                                  sutures. Sutures were introduced in close
                                                  proximity throughout the entire extent of the
                                                  flaps, so as to maintain their edges in accurate
                                                  adjustment. Four of the sutures were twisted and
                                                  were inserted, one at the right angle of the
                                                  mouth, two upon the right cheek at points where
                                                  they would afford the best support to the flaps,
                                                  and one at the angle of the flaps, below the under
                                                  lip. The newly constructed mouth was of medium
                                                  dimensions, the lips maintaining themselves in
                                                  contact and retaining the salivary secretion. The
                                                  adjustment of the different parts to each other
                                                  was effected without any strain upon the sutures
                                                  at any one point. No adhesive plaster was used.
                                                  Liquid nourishment was directed to be given
                                                  through a tube, and water dressings to be applied
                                                  to the face. The case progressed favorably, and by
                                                                  <date type="operation" when="1865-11-10">November 10th</date>, adhesions had taken place
                                                  throughout almost the entire extent of the flaps,
                                                  and all the pin sutures, with most of the thread
                                                  sutures, were removed. A free discharge of pus was
                                                  taking place at the lower extremity of the
                                                  incision under the chin, where the cyst was
                                                  removed. Strips of adhesive plaster were applied
                                                  at points where their support seemed needed. A
                                                  superficial slough of the size of a copper cent
                                                  had formed over the zygoma, which could not,
                                                  however, mar the result of the operation. The
                                                  suppuration below the chin gradually diminished,
                                                  and ceased entirely in a few days, every part of
                                                  the wound healing completely. On <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1865-12-12">December 12th,
                                                  1865</date>, the patient left the hospital to return to
                                                  his home. The ability to maintain the lips in
                                                  contact, and thus retain the saliva, constituted
                                                  an immense amelioration of his condition. His
                                                  improved appearance, and some improvement of
                                                  articulation, were also results highly gratifying
                                                  to the patient. </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
