<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19368">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">L——, Edward</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e19368</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">486</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
          <term>penetrating gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the scapula</term>
          <term>ball struck clavicle, passed through chest, and emerged posterior scapula</term>
          <term>pneumonia</term>
          <term>clavicle, scapula, and ribs shattered by same projectile</term>
          <term>autopsy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-20">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private Edward
          L——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. A, 87th New York Volunteers</name>,
        was wounded at <name type="battle">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-27">August 27th, 1862</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which struck the left clavicle about
        three inches from its sternal extremity, passed through the chest, and emerged near the
        posterior border of the left scapula. <date type="admit" when="1862-09-01">Five days
          subsequently</date> he was admitted into the <name type="hospital">Cranch Hospital</name>
        at Washington, in a feeble condition. There was constipation and troublesome cough
        accompanied by hæmoptysis. The bowels were relieved by sulphate of magnesia, and the
        cough was alleviated by ipecac and opium. An engorged condition of the injured lung, with
        sanguineous expectoration and dyspnœa, continued for some twelve days, when the patient
        began to grow better. His general health improved, and, to all appearance, resolution was
        taking place in the lung. Improvement continued till <date type="injury" when="1862-10-12">October 12th</date>, when the patient took cold through indiscretion, and had a chill.
        After appropriate treatment he had partially recovered by October 27th, when he again
        exposed himself unnecessarily, took a fresh cold, and had another chill, lasting an hour and
        a half, followed by fever and pneumonia of the right lung. Wet cups were now applied, and a
        dose often grains of calomel was administered. On October 30th, the cups were repeated, and
        another expectorant mixture was prescribed. There was no reaction, however, dyspnœa
        continuing unabated, and terminating in death on <date type="death" when="1862-11-03">November 3d, 1862</date>. The autopsy showed the left clavicle fractured at the junction
        of the middle with the outer third, the distal portion being driven in. There was a
        formation of callus, but no union of bone. The third, fourth, and fifth ribs, of the left
        side, were fractured near their spinal articulations, and the dorsum of the left scapula was
        perforated. The apex of the left lung was grooved by the passage of the ball and appeared
        entirely solidified. The track of the wound through the lung was entirely cicatrized, and
        seemed cartilaginous to the touch. There were also pleuritic adhesions in the right side,
        and the right pleural cavity contained from two to three pints of fluid. The specimen,
        represented in the adjoining wood-cut, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 225, was contributed
        to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, with the history, by
          <name type="person" key="1353">Surgeon A. Wynkoop</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
      </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001463.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 225.—Left scapula, clavicle and ribs fractured by a
          conoidal musket ball. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 245, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
