<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20323">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">P&#8212;&#8212;, Allman M.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e20323</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">588</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>excisions</term>
          <term>balls and foreign bodies lodged</term>
          <term>remarkable lodgement of foreign bodies on post-mortem</term>
          <term>missile lying against junction of two pulmonary veins</term>
          <term>missile lying against fibrous cord remaining of ductus arteriosus</term>
          <term>fragmentary projectile puzzling in specimen</term>
          <term>penetrating wound of chest</term>
          <term>traumatic pleuro-pneumonia</term>
          <term>fractured first rib and clavicle</term>
          <term>injured apex of lung</term>
          <term>necropsy performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 17.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private <hi
            rend="italic">Allman M. P</hi>&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx"
          >Co. C, 34th Virginia Regiment</name>, aged 35 years, was wounded at <name type="battle"
          key="xxx">Hatcher's Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-10-27">October 27th,
          1864</date>, and made a prisoner. He was taken to the field hospital of the 1st division
        of the Second Corps, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon William Vosburg</name>,
          <name type="organization" key="xxx">111th New York Volunteers</name>, noted the case (one
        of penetrating wound of the chest) and applied the necessary dressings, and administered
        restoratives, and, when the patient had rallied from the shock of the injury, sent him in an
        ambulance to the rear, whence he was conveyed on a hospital steamer to <name type="place"
          key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where he was admitted to <name type="hospital"
          key="157">Columbian Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-30"
          >October 30th, 1864</date>, with a &#34;gunshot penetrating wound of the chest, received
        at <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg, Virginia</name>, on <date type="injury"
          when="1864-10-27">the 27th</date>. A mini&#233; ball entered the triangle of the neck,
        passed downward into the chest, fractured the first rib and partially the clavicle, and
        slightly injured the apex of the left lung.&#34; <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting
          Assistant Surgeon C. F. Lloyd</name>, in charge of the ward, treated the case mainly on
        the expectant plan, with careful nursing, and palliative remedies to meet symptoms. The ball
        was out of reach, and <name type="person" key="126">Surgeon T. R. Crosby</name>, <name
          type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the hospital, decided that an
        attempt to extract it was unwarrantable, as was clearly proved in the sequel. The patient
        suffered greatly from oppressed breathing and the usual complications of traumatic
        pleuro-pneumonia, especially from frequent painful cough. Concentrated sustaining
        nourishment was given, but the patient steadily grew worse, and death resulted on <date
          type="death" when="1864-11-11">November 11th, 1864</date>, from intermediary
        h&#230;morrhage. The necropsy showed rigor mortis great. Old pleuritic and diaphragmatic
        adhesions existed on the left side of the chest. There were about four ounces of clotted
        blood on the walls of the chest near the wound. The upper lobe of the left lung was
        atrophied and almost gangrenous in appearance. The adjoining wood cut (<hi rend="initialcap"
          >F</hi>IG. 287) shows a wet preparation of the upper half of the left lung, with a
        conoidal ball embedded in its substance, partially blocking up the left pulmonary vein. It
        was contributed, with a memorandum of the case, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting
          Assistant Surgeon J. Fischer</name>. After the specimen had been hardened in alcohol, upon
        tracing the track of the wound from its entrance in the pleura at the posterior part of the
        upper lobe of the left lung, near the apex, downward and forward to the root of the lung,
        the larger of the two missiles figured in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 288)
        was found lying against the common trunk formed by the junction, in this case, of the two
        left pulmonary veins. There was a small jagged opening in the vein, whether produced
        mechanically after death, or by ulceration, could not be determined. The track of the wound
        was filled with coagula. <choice>
          <orig>Near by</orig>
          <reg>Nearby</reg>
        </choice> the larger missile, lying against the fibrous cord constituted by the remains of
        the <hi rend="italic">ductus arteriosus</hi> was found a smaller misshapen fragmentary
        projectile, apparently a portion of a carbine ball. It was difficult to account for its
        presence, which had not been remarked in the examination of the specimen in its recent
        state. It had apparently entered through the same track as the larger missile, a track that
        was large and much lacerated. It is hardly possible that it could have been introduced <hi
          rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> to freight the preparation, which submerged in alcohol by
        its own density. It was not a fragment of the larger ball, which, though battered and
        flattened by impact on the first rib, was entire and weighed 540 grains. Its presence in the
        already perplexing specimen was very puzzling. </p>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001493.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 287.&#8212;Ball lodged against pulmonary vein. <hi
          rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3388, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001494.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 288.&#8212;Ball and fragment of ball removed from <hi
          rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3388.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
