<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e10685">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wearing, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e10685</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">224-225</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>recoveries after primary amputation in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>amputation at junction of middle and lower third of thigh, femur protruded about
      one-fourth of an inch</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>supplied with artificial leg</term>
     <term>wound of knee joint</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ak" when="2014-10-08">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 437.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1070">Private J.
     Wearing</name>, <name type="organization" key="427">Co. L, 2d Pennsylvania Heavy
     Artillery</name>, aged 20 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg</name>,
     <date type="injury" when="1864-06-17">June 17, 1864</date>, and admitted to the field hospital
    of the 1st division, Ninth Corps, where <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon M. K. Hogan</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded: "Wound of left knee joint;
    amputation at junction of middle and lower third of thigh." <date type="transfer"
     when="1864-06-24">One week after the reception of the injury</date> the man was transferred to
     <name type="hospital" key="152">Finley Hospital</name>, Washington, and in <date
     type="transfer" when="1864-10">October following</date> he entered Broad and Cherry Streets
    Hospital, Philadelphia, whence <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon T. C.
     Brainerd</name> made the following report: "At the date of admission the femur protruded about
    one-fourth of an inch, and the stump was healed to within one inch of the bone. The patient
    being an&#230;mic, iron and quinine were administered. Simple dressings were applied to the
    stump. By November 15th his general health had improved and the line of separation was forming
    around the protruding portion of the bone. On December 1st, the ulcer upon the stump presented a
    sloughing tendency, but again cleaned up. On <date type="operation" when="1865-01-06">January 6,
     1865</date>, about four inches of the extremity of the femur was <choice>
     <orig>exsected</orig>
     <reg>excised</reg>
    </choice> by cutting down upon it from the outer anterior surface of the stump and sawing
    through the bone with a chain saw. The bone removed was necrosed and surrounded by a large
    amount of reparative material. A small artery spouted from the medullary canal of the bone, the
    h&#230;morrhage from which was promptly controlled by pressing a piece of soft wax into the
    canal. Three ligatures were applied and ether was used. The operation was performed by <name
     type="person" key="1071">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Bellows</name>. The patient reacted
    promptly. Simple dressings were continued to the stump. Two days later an attack of erysipelas
    supervened, extending as for up as the groin, but yielding to treatment, and by January 15th it
    had entirely disappeared and the general condition had much improved. One month later
    cicatrization was almost complete, and the patient was walking about with the aid of crutches."
    In April he was transferred to South Street Hospital, and subsequently to <name type="place"
     >Chester</name>, where he was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge"
     when="1865-07-26">July 26, 1865</date>, and pensioned. Some weeks afterwards the man was
    supplied with an artificial leg, manufactured by <name type="person" key="xx">K.
    Clements</name>. In his application for commutation, dated <date type="pension" when="1870"
     >1870</date>, he represented the stump as being in a sound and healthy condition. The pensioner
    was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. The sequestrum (<hi
     rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4196) removed from the stump was contributed to <name type="hospital"
     key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="1071">the operator</name>, and is
    represented in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 3 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi
     rend="initialcap">LXX</hi>, opposite p. 242.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001812.001"/>
    <head>
     PLATE LXX. __ INVOLUCRA OF THE FEMUR Fig 3.__Case of <name type="person" key="xx">Pt. J.
     Wearing </name>, <name type="organization" key="569">2 Pennsylvania Art.</name>. Spec. 4196,
    Surg. Sect., A. M. M. 
    </head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
