<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e16869">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wright, E. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e16869</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">408</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the knee joint</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations at the knee joint</term>
     <term>successful cases of secondary amputations at the knee joint</term> 
     <term>shot wound carried off foot</term> 
     <term>primary amputation of leg at junction of middle and lower third, performed on field</term>
     <term>abscess in region of liver, discharged by track between ribs over right lobe of liver</term>
     <term>succession of abscesses during healing of stump</term>     
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>fitted with artificial leg</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>   
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 652.—<name type="person" key="1220">Corporal E. C.
      Wright</name>, <name type="organization" key="485">Co. H, 21st New Jersey</name>, aged 19
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="xx">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>, by a solid shot, which carried off his right foot.
     Amputation of the leg by posterior flap, at the junction of the middle and lower third, was
     performed on the field by <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon D. McNeill</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">21st New
      Jersey</name>, and <date type="admit" when="1863-05">several days afterwards</date> the patient was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where he entered <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square Hospital</name>. He was discharged from service
     <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-06-13">June 13, 1863</date>, and pensioned. Subsequently the stump became diseased, inducing <name type="person" key="1220">the pensioner</name>, in <date type="injury" when="1864-01">January
      following</date>, to seek relief by treatment at St. Luke's Hospital, <name type="place">New York City</name>. The tibia became necrosed and cloaca formed, leading to
     sinuses in the substance of the bone, so that an injection would find its way through the
     canals. On <date type="operation" when="1864-06-23">June 23, 1864</date>, amputation through the knee joint by antero-posterior flaps was
     performed by <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Gurdon Buck</name>, the cartilages and patella
     being allowed to remain. Sulphuric ether was used as the anæsthetic. At the time of the
     operation the patient was in feeble condition, owing not only to the amount of pus discharged
     from the stump, but also to the presence of an abscess in the region of the liver, which had
     formed some months after the first amputation. This abscess discharged itself by a track
     passing between the ribs over the right lobe of the liver. There had been no admixture of bile,
     however, in the discharge, nor did jaundice exist at any time. A succession of abscesses formed
     during the healing of the stump. The first appeared at the upper boundary of the synovial sac
     and was freely laid open by <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Buck</name>. Six days after the
     operation a tendency to slough appeared, and permanganate of potash was applied to the affected
     parts. <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Buck</name>'s method of extension by weight and pulley,
     with bands of adhesive plaster, was also used to prevent the retraction of the edges of the
     flaps and maintain them in apposition. This afforded great relief to the patient, steadying the
     limb and taking all the strain off the flaps. On <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1864-09-01">September 1, 1864</date>, the patient was discharged from hospital, the stump being solid and
     well rounded. The abscess in the side had ceased to discharge. In the following month the
     pensioner was fitted with an artificial leg by <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. E. D.
      Hudson</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">New York City</name>. Pension Examining
     Surgeons who have inspected the stump have described it as a "very good" one, and the pensioner
     has reported its condition as "sound and healthy." He was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-03-04">March 4, 1880</date>.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
