<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18555">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Seymour, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e18555</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
                    Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph
                        K. Barnes, United States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                        D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">422-423</biblScope></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the neck</term> 
                    <term>gunshot wounds of the neck</term>
                    <term>operations on the neck</term>
                    <term>hæmorrhage and ligations</term>
                    <term>ligation of internal jugular vein</term>
                    <term>arm weak</term>
                    <term>one side of tongue paralyzed</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-11-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
            <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>            
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body>
            
            <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private William Seymour</name>, <name type="organization">Co. G, 57th New York Volunteers</name>, aged 19 years,
                was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="259">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered
                    just below the lobulus of the left ear, and passing obliquely downward and
                    forward, emerged one inch above the sterno-clavicular articulation of the right
                    side, external to the sterno-mastoid muscle; the missile then struck the
                    subclavian region at the external end of the middle third of the clavicle, and
                    glanced off along the arm without touching it. He fell unconscious on the
                    reception of the injury; fifteen minutes after which, he walked to the rear
                    assisted by a comrade. He had considerable hæmorrhage, which ceased
                    spontaneously. He was admitted to the hospital of the 3d division, First Corps.
                    Cold water dressings were applied to the wounds, and beef tea administered,
                    which partly escaped through the wound of exit, giving evidence of injury of the
                    pharynx. He was transferred to hospital via <name type="place">Fredericksburg</name> and <name type="place">Belle Plain</name>; the
                    mode of conveyance being an army wagon, the jolting of which caused a slight
                    hæmorrhage, which he expectorated <hi rend="italic">per orem</hi>; he also stated having expectorated
                a piece of meat one inch in length. He was, on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-11">May 11th</date>, admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington. Cold water dressings were applied to the wounds, and the
                    patient was fed through gumelastic bougies, and injections <hi rend="italic">per anum</hi> of beef tea
                    for four days, at the end of which he was able to swallow milk with ease. He
                    gradually improved until <date type="injury" when="1864-05-19">May 19th</date>, when he had a secondary hæmorrhage from the
                    mouth, amounting to seven ounces of blood. On May 20th, he bled one ounce; 26th,
                    four ounces; and on the 27th, a venous hæmorrhage occurred, which was arrested
                    by compression. On the 29th, hæmorrhage recurred, amounting to two ounces of
                    blood; and again on <date type="operation" when="1864-05-30">the 30th</date>, to the amount of four ounces; after which it was
                thought advisable to ligate the carotid artery. <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, made an incision for the artery, which was searched for a
                    long while, but found to be obliterated. From that time no hæmorrhage occurred,
                    and the patient rapidly recovered. On June 10th, the wound of entrance was
                    entirely closed, and that of exit granulating finely. He had lost the power of
                    the right arm, and for a long time had complete aphonia. The wound had an
                    excrescence not unlike cauliflower, which was daily decreasing in size. He was
                    transferred to <name type="hospital">Turner's Lane Hospital, Philadelphia</name>, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-09-11">September 11th</date>. On his
                    admission, the wounds had closed; sensation and motion feeble throughout the
                    right arm; neck had only one-fourth range of movement; the sense of touch was
                    lost from the chin to the external angle of the right eye, and lessened on upper
                    neck; analgesia was more or less complete in these parts; loss of gustation of
                    the right side of the tongue, pain and sense of temperature limited by median
                    line. Very far back there seemed to be considerable sensation, motion seemed
                    good on the right side, and the left side was paralyzed as to motion entirely.
                    Deglutition was imperfect; the voice nearly perfect; appetite and digestion
                    good. On October 10th, the face had recovered sensation; taste not perfect; tact and pain still absent. On the 20th,
                    there was some feeling in the tongue, but no motion on the left side. He was
                    returned to duty on <date type="duty" when="1864-12-09">December 9th, 1864</date>. On <date type="pension" when="1866-05-02">May 2d, 1866</date>, <name type="person">Examining Surgeon E. Winslow</name> reports that Seymour's wounds had healed externally; but the trachea was
                    constantly discharging pus, brought up by coughing, and was hoarse, and his
                    right arm weak. </p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
