<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16959">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Wiest, Philip A.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16959</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">283</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>recovery with disability</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>disability total and temporary</term>
          <term>ball <choice>
              <orig>imbedded</orig>
              <reg>embedded</reg>
            </choice> in integument and muscles of head</term>
          <term>fracture and depression of skull above occipital protuberance</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="xx">Private Philip A.
          W——</name>, <name type="person">Co. A, 50th Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>,
        aged 21 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="254">Petersburg, Virginia</name>,
          <date type="injury" when="1864-07-30">July 30th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which <choice>
          <orig>imbedded</orig>
          <reg>embedded</reg>
        </choice> itself in the integument and muscles of the left side of the head, fracturing and
        depressing a portion of the skull a little above and to the left of the occipital
        protuberance. The missile was removed by the hand. He was somewhat stunned by the blow, but
        arose and <date type="admit" when="1864-07-30">walked to</date> the hospital of the 3d
        division, Ninth Corps, when he became unconscious and remained so for eighteen hours. On the
        following day he returned to his regiment, not knowing that his injury was severe, but he
        was returned to the hospital, where he remained for one week. He suffered severe headache
        and was unable to see or hear well. On <date type="transfer" when="1864-08-11">August
          11th</date>, he was admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="200">Soldier's
          Rest</name>, branch of <name type="hospital" key="186">1st division hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria, Virginia</name>. He seemed to improve for two days, then grew
        worse, complaining of pain in the frontal region of the head, especially over the left
        orbital ridge. On <date type="operation" when="1864-08-16">the 16th</date>, he became
        unconscious for about two hours. It being deemed advisable to remove the depressed portion
        of bone, ether was administered, and <name type="person">Assistant Surgeon Theodore
          Artaud</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, made a crucial
        incision, half an inch in length, directly over the injury, and dissected up the
        occipito-frontalis muscle, revealing an indentation, half an inch in length, making a very
        regular cup-shaped depression, three-fourths of an inch in diameter, with a slight fissure
        around its edge and an irregular one across its centre. The trephine was applied so as to
        partially cover one side of the depression, and a portion of the skull was removed. The
        depressed bone was then removed by the elevator, exposing the dura mater, which was found to
        be healthy. A circular tent was applied over the exposed portion of brain, the wound dressed
        with cold water dressings, and morphia given to quiet the patient. The following day he was
        able to sit up, and by <date type="injury" when="1864-08-20">the 20th</date> could walk
        about. On <date type="injury" when="1864-08-26">the 26th</date>, he was seized with violent
        signs of compression, but was soon relieved by sinapisms to the neck, abdomen, and
        extremities. Croton oil was given, and afterward the wound, which had nearly healed, was
        enlarged and kept open with tents for three days, with but slight inconvenience to the
        patient. He had slight headache on the morning of September 1st, but his general condition
        was good and improving. He ate and slept well, and by <date type="injury" when="1864-09-22">the 22d</date>, the wound had entirely closed. He occasionally complained of slight
        headache, and was, to all appearances, cured. He was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="207">Slough Barracks</name>, branch of <name type="hospital" key="189">3d division
          hospital</name>, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-05">October 5th</date>, remaining
        until <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-10">May 10th, 1865</date>, when he was sent to the
          <name type="hospital" key="218">Augur Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, and thence, on <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-20">the
        20th</date>, transferred to the <name type="hospital">McClellan Hospital,
          Philadelphia</name>. He was discharged from the service on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-06">July 6th, 1865</date>. A communication from the Commissioner of
        Pensions, dated <date type="pension" when="1868-07">July, 1868</date>, states that <name type="person" key="xx">Wiest</name> is a pensioner at $8 per month, his disability being
        rated total and temporary. The specimen was contributed, with an history, by the operator,
          <name type="person">Assistant Surgeon Theodore Artaud</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
      </p>
      <figure><graphic url="cww.001426.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 142.—Disk and fragments removed after a fracture by a
        spent ball. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 5042, Sect. I, A. M. M. [Nat. size.]</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
