<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8833">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Friederick, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8833</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">189-190</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recovery after shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>compound fracture of femur</term>
     <term>ball entered inner thigh at middle third, fractured femur, and lodged</term>
     <term>gangrene</term>
     <term>leg withered and badly deformed</term>
     <term>seven inches shortening of thigh</term>
     <term>marked deformity, outward curvature of thigh</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 386.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1026">Private J.
     Friederick</name>, <name type="organization" key="418">Co. F, 127th New York</name>, aged 19
    years, was wounded in the right thigh at <name type="BATTLE" key="42">Honey Hill</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1864-11-30">November 30, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xx"
     >Assistant Surgeon J. F. Huber</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
    reported his admission to hospital at <name type="place">Hilton Head</name>, on <date
     type="admit" when="1864-12-01">the day following the injury</date>, with "compound fracture of
    femur, treated with splints," and his transfer to <name type="place" key="#Washington"
     >Washington</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-07">May 7, 1865</date>, but gave no
    account of the progress of the case. The following notes were furnished by <name type="person"
     key="424">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. K. Smith</name>, from <name type="hospital" key="171"
     >Armory Square Hospital</name>, and by <name type="person" key="xx">Assistant Surgeon W.
     Webster</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of DeCamp
    Hospital, <name type="place">David's Island, New York</name>. The wound was caused by a round
    ball, which entered the inner side of the thigh at its middle third, passing obliquely outward
    and forward, fracturing the femur and lodging. An attempt to stand on the limb after receiving
    the injury caused the thigh to bend to an obtuse angle at the seat of the fracture. The wounded
    man was placed on a shelter tent and conveyed to a steamboat, about eight miles distant, no
    examination of the wound having been made and no local support having been applied to the broken
    bone. During <date type="operation" when="1864-12-01">the night following the injury</date> the
    ball was removed through an incision on the external aspect of the thigh. Cold-water
    applications were used, and a partial support was given by an arrangement of blankets around the
    parts. On arriving at the <name type="hospital" key="xx">Hilton Head Hospital</name> a surgical
    examination was made under chloroform, but with no operative result, the limb being exceedingly
    tumefied. Smith's anterior suspensory apparatus was then applied, and the topical applications
    of cold water were continued. This treatment was kept up until January 7th, when side splints,
    extending below the foot, were substituted, and the limb was maintained in a straight position.
    This apparatus was continued for nearly two months, and during this stage of the treatment the
    swelling greatly subsided, and about a half dozen pieces of bone were removed by the attending
    surgeon at various intervals. The largest of these is represented to have been about three
    inches long, one-half inch wide, and one-eighth inch thick. An abscess also opened,
    spontaneously, about two inches below Poupart's ligament. In the latter part of March the side
    splints gave way to a fracture-box, the cold-water dressings being still persevered in. On May
    1st all local supports by means of splints were cast aside, bandages and pillows being
    sufficient from that period in consequence of the advanced stage of bony consolidation. On <date
     type="transfer" when="1865-05-10">May 10th</date>, when the patient was admitted to <name
     type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, the fractured femur had firmly united,
    with seven inches shortening, a marked deformity by an outward curvature of the thigh, and very
    limited motion of the knee joint. There was still a slight discharge, and the extremity of the
    upper fragment lapping by the lower fragment presented itself on the outer aspect of the limb,
    close to the external condyle, at which point the skin was ulcerated through, exposing the end
    of the bone. By June 1st the patient's recovery was so far advanced as to enable him to walk
    about the ward with the aid of crutches. About the last of June, however, he was compelled to
    resume his bed in consequence of the appearance of an abscess on the outer side of the thigh,
    which was opened and gave exit to about eight ounces of sanious and offensive pus. Up to this
    time the purulent discharges from the wound had been moderate in quantity and healthy in
    character. On July 5th, however, the several openings were attacked by gangrene, which rapidly
    extended up the thigh and destroyed the skin and superficial and deep fascia nearly the whole
    length of its external surface. This disease was, at length, arrested by the application of
    bromine, and by August 15th the wound had become filled with granulations, and cicatrization was
    progressive. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-08-17">August 17th</date> the patient was
    transferred to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, where a subsequent
    exploration of the limb resulted in the removal of six small sequestra from the external wound.
    Simple dressings were now used, and no further operative interference was required in the case
    until after the arrival of the patient at DeCamp Hospital, where he was transferred on <date
     type="transfer" when="1865-10-23">October 23d</date>. At <date type="injury" when="1865-10-23"
     >this date</date> he was strong enough to walk from the steamboat landing to his ward on
    crutches, and his general health was excellent. There were three apertures, two on the external
    and one on the posterior surface of the thigh, from which pus of a healthy appearance found exit
    in small quantities. An examination of the wound by means of a probe revealed secondary
    splinters, but not sufficiently approachable to warrant an attempt at their removal. The amount
    of new osseous deposit was considerable, but unfortunately the sequestra were found so
    intimately embedded in it as to cause their removal to be attended with great difficulty and
    even impossibility, and involving the sacrifice of so much new growth as to endanger the limb.
    On <date type="operation" when="1866-02-25">February 25, 1866</date>, however, the further
    removal of necrotic pieces was induced by constitutional symptoms, which manifested themselves
    and indicated local irritation. Portions of the involucrum were removed by the trephine and
    chisel, where necessary for the purpose, and small masses of dead bone were extracted from each
    of the orifices. One of the pieces, deeply situated, measured about two inches in length. As a
    seeming consequence of the operation the unfavorable constitutional symptoms entirely
    disappeared, and the condition of the patient and his wounds became highly satisfactory." In
     <date type="injury" when="1866-06">June following</date> he was supplied with an apparatus for
    the injured limb by <name type="person" key="xx">E. D. Hudson</name>, of <name type="place"
     key="xx">New York City</name>, and <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1866-10">four months
     later</date> he left for his home, having been discharged from service <date
     type="servicedischarge" when="1865-11-25">November 25, 1865</date>, but re-admitted to the
    hospital <date type="admit" when="1866-11">one month afterwards</date>. The <name
     type="organization" key="xx">Examining Board</name> of <name type="place">Augusta,
    Maine</name>, certified, in <date type="pension" when="1873-05">May, 1873</date>, and in <date
     type="pension" when="1876-12">December, 1876</date>: "The leg is withered and badly deformed,
    and there are discharging ulcers all the time. He can perform no manual labor of any kind, and
    is confined to his bed a large part of the time. The leg, from knee to foot, is nothing but skin
    and bone." The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>.
    The wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 151) represents a photograph of the patient, taken
     <date type="photo" when="1865-08-15"/>August 15, 1865. (<hi rend="italic">Photo's of Surgical
     Cases</hi>, Vol. 9, p. 16, and <hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 90.) Card
    photographs, taken at a subsequent date at the DeCamp Hospital, were contributed by <name
     type="person" key="xx">Assistant Surgeon Webster</name>. (<hi rend="italic">Card Photo's</hi>,
    Vol. 2, p. 22, A. M. M.)</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001567.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 151.&#8212;Shot fracture of middle third of right femur. [From
     a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
