<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e23876">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wheelwright, C. S.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e23876</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">620</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
     <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered external dorsal aspect of foot anterior to fourth tarso-metatarsal articulation, emerged posterior to metatarso-phalangeal articulation of big toe, having </term> 
     <term>ball fractured fourth metatarsal bone obliquely, passed beneath other metatarsals</term>
     <term>seton conducted through both wounds to keep them open and promote suppuration</term>     
     <term>flexor tendons of middle toes and some ligaments of pedal arch were injured</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>   
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 900.—<hi rend="italic">Shot fractures of metatarsal
      bones.</hi>—<name type="person" key="1397">Private C. S. Wheelwright</name>, <name type="organization" key="152">Co. M, 1st New Jersey Cavalry</name>, aged 26 years, was wounded
     on picket duty near <name type="place">Warrenton</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-01-31">January 31, 1864</date>,
     and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-02-01">the
     following day</date>.  <name type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. Carvallo</name>,
     reported:  "The ball entered the external dorsal aspect of the right foot anterior to the fourth
     tarso-metatarsal articulation, and emerged posteriorly to the metatarso-phalangeal articulation
     of the big toe, having fractured the fourth metatarsal bone obliquely and passed beneath the
     others. Water dressings had been applied before admission and were continued. The foot became
     red, swollen, and painful, and the patient had considerable fever, anorexia, and pain. Epsom
     salts, weak diaphoretics, and the dressings soothed the symptoms considerably. On <date type="operation" when="1864-02-08">February 8th</date>
     the distal fragment of the fourth metatarsal bone was found to be movable, but still attached
     by its phalangeal articulation, and an effort to remove it proved impossible without injuring
     that joint. It was therefore decided to leave its removal to nature, and a seton was conducted
     through both wounds in order to keep them open and promote suppuration. Subsequently an
     exacerbation of the symptoms manifested itself, after which the foot showed an erysipelatous
     tendency by swelling, redness, heat, and puffiness. A solution of nitrate of silver with
     acacia, constantly applied for forty-eight hours, finally subdued the inflammation, when a
     profuse discharge of healthy pus followed and gave great relief to the patient. Thenceforward
     the stimulants were substituted by tonics, and water dressings took the place of all former
     local applications. In a very short time all the swelling and redness had left the foot, and
     the wound showed such a healthy appearance and discharged such small quantities of pus that I entertained hopes the fractured bone would heal without being removed. I then applied Sentin's
     starch bandage, which the patient still had on when he went home on furlough on <date type="furlough" when="1864-03-15">March 15th</date>. I afterwards heard that he was attacked
     with erysipelas and had entered Central Park Hospital, <name type="palce">New York City</name>."  The patient was discharged at the latter hospital <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-05-20">May 20, 1864</date>, and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xx">Examining Surgeon J. T. Burdick</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Brooklyn, N. Y.</name>, certified that "the flexor tendons of the
     middle toes and some of the ligaments of the pedal arch were injured."  The pensioner was paid
     <date type="pension" when="1880-09-04">September 4, 1880</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
