<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41155">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Harbaugh, Joseph</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41155</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">175-176</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a and semi-gangrenous feet</term>
       <term>anterior upper lobe and all of middle lobe of right lung emphysematous, posterior upper lobe filled with bronchial secretion</term>
       <term>right lower lobe engorged and crepitated under pressure</term>
       <term>large intestine presented usual appearances of chronic diarrh&#339;a, ulcers superficial and not confluent, extended some distance into small intestine</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of small intestine congested, solitary glands conspicuous and dark-purplish color, Peyer's patches darker color but not elevated or ulcerated</term>       
       <term>condition of feet not recorded</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 388.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Joseph Harbaugh</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 6th Maryland volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-11-23">November 23, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a and semi-gangrenous feet.  [This man appears on the register of the regimental hospital of the 6th Maryland volunteers, then at <name type="place">Brandy Station, Virginia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-11-14">November 14th</date>&#8212;typhoid fever&#8212;sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1863-11-23">November 23d</date>.]  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-12-08">December 8th</date>, at 6 P. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-12-09">twenty-one hours after death</date>: Height five feet eight inches; rigor mortis marked; body emaciated. The brain was healthy, and weighed fifty ounces; the ventricles contained a drachm of fluid. The mucous membrane of the trachea was injected. The right lung weighed twenty-four ounces; the anterior part of its upper and the whole of the middle lobe were somewhat emphysematous; the posterior portion of the upper lobe was filled with an excessive amount of bronchial secretion, and inferiorly was in the stage of red hepatization; the lower lobe was engorged and of a dark-purple color, but crepitated under pressure; the left lung was healthy, but congested hypostatically; it weighed thirteen ounces. The pericardium contained ten ounces of fluid. The heart weighed ten ounces; its valves were healthy; the right cavities contained a large mixed clot. The liver was healthy, and weighed sixty-four ounces; the gall-bladder contained two and a half ounces of bile. The spleen was moderately firm, of a dark-purple color; it weighed eight ounces. The pancreas weighed three ounces. The kidneys were an&#230;mic, their cortical substance unusually pale; the pyramids were also pale, but darker than the cortical substance; the right kidney weighed five ounces, the left six ounces. The large intestine presented the usual appearances of chronic diarrh&#339;a; the ulcers were superficial, not confluent, and tinged with a delicate pink color; this condition extended some distance into the small intestine, the mucous membrane of which was congested, while the solitary glands were conspicuous and of a dark-purplish color; Peyer's patches were of a still darker color, but not elevated or ulcerated.  [The condition of the feet is not recorded.]&#8212;<name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>&#8432;</p>
   <p>&#8432; September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief &#34;<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>,&#34; to which the reader is referred.&#8212;(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
