<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6835">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">O'Neil, Michael</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6835</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">150-151</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the hip joint</term>
     <term>coxo-femoral amputations</term>
     <term>secondary amputations</term>
     <term>ball entered upper anterior thigh, passed backward and slightly upward</term>
     <term>comminuted upper extremity of femur, fissures extended down shaft and through trochanters
      halfway up neck</term>
     <term>wound suppurating freely</term>
     <term>pus bathing acetabulum and femoral artery</term>
     <term>abscess between iliacus externus muscle and iliac fascia</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-27">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 327.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Michael
     O'Neil</name>,&#178; <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 58th Massachusetts</name>, aged
    19 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="263">Cold Harbor</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1864-06-03">June 3, 1864</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which entered
    the upper anterior part of the right thigh, and passed backward and slightly upward through the
    limb, comminuting the upper extremity of the femur. The fissures extended about three inches
    down the shaft, and through the trochanters halfway up the neck. The wounded man was sent in an
    ambulance to the <name type="place">White House</name>, on the <name type="place">York
     River</name>, and thence by a hospital steamer to <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, where
    he was received at the <name type="hospital" key="512">Third Division Hospital</name> on <date
     type="transfer" when="1864-06-07">June 7th</date>. On admission his limb was much swollen, yet
    there was but little pain, and this was not increased by moving the limb. His general condition
    was satisfactory, though he reported that he was subject to attacks of intermittent fever. His
    limb was arranged in a straight position, supported by cushions and pillows; evaporating lotions
    were applied to the wound, and a nutritious diet was ordered. On <date type="operation"
     when="1864-06-10">June 10th</date>, several fragments of bone were extracted. On June 12th the
    patient had a chill, and was ordered to take four grains of sulphate of quinia every four hours.
    The injured limb was now suspended by means of Smith's anterior splint. On June 24th there was
    another chill. The wound was now suppurating freely, and the limb was very sensitive when
    handled. On June <sic>31st</sic> there was a slight chill. From this date to August 1st there
    was little change in the symptoms. It was now decided that there was little hope of
    consolidation of the fracture. The suppuration was profuse, and it was believed that the patient
    would inevitably succumb ultimately to the constitutional irritation and the drain upon the
    system. It was determined, therefore, that amputation should be performed, and the character of
    the fracture admitted only of amputation at the hip joint. On <date type="operation"
     when="1864-08-10">August 10th</date>, the patient was an&#230;sthetised by sulphuric ether, and
    amputation at the hip joint was performed by the lateral flap method by <name type="person"
     key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
    There was but little h&#230;morrhage, and the operation was borne well. The patient had an
    anodyne, and was freely stimulated. For forty-eight hours after the operation there was some
    febrile excitement, with complete anorexia. The fever then subsided and the appetite returned.
    The wound looked well, and the amount of suppuration was trifling. The case progressed very
    favorably until <date type="operation" when="1864-08-20">August 20th</date>, when secondary
    h&#230;morrhage supervened from ulceration of the femoral near the ligature. About six ounces of
    blood were lost. A ligature was promptly placed upon the external iliac just above Poupart's
    ligament. After the operation the patient was very weak and faint, and stimulants were freely
    administered. On August 22d there was an excess of febrile excitement, but this abated on the
    following day and the appetite again became moderately good. On August 28th there was nausea and
    vomiting, which persisted for forty-eight hours. The wound at this time had assumed a very
    unhealthy appearance, and the patient had become much emaciated. On the night of September 1st
    there was delirium. The case terminated fatally on the morning of <date type="death"
     when="1864-09-03">September 3d</date>, twenty-three days after the operation. At the autopsy
    the viscera was found to be healthy, except that there was an old cicatrix with cretaceous
    deposit at the apex of the left lung. The lips of the wound were united in nearly their entire
    extent. There was a large accumulation of pus within the flap, bathing the acetabulum and the
    gaping mouth of the femoral artery. The wound left by the incision above Poupart's ligament,
    through which the external iliac was tied, communicated with an abscess between the iliacus
    externus muscle and the iliac fascia, filled with pus. The ligature on the external iliac was
    found to be placed about half an inch below the origin of the epigastric; the circumflex iliac
    was given off a little below the epigastric. There was a firm conical plug in the external
    iliac, ending at the origin of the epigastric. Through this plug ran a canal communicating with
    the mouth of the circumflexa ilii; this canal was closed by a clot colored by included red
    corpuscles and of more recent formation than the plugging clot. Ulceration of the external iliac
    just above the ligature had commenced. The femoral vein was collapsed and contracted; the
    external iliac vein was distended by a dirty fluid, which, when placed under the microscope, was
    found to abound in pus globules. Higher up, the contents of the vein consisted of a granular
    detritus. The branches of the external iliac vein was blocked up by dense coagula. The
    deep-seated abdominal lymphatic glands were enlarged and deeply injected. An examination of the
    fractured femur showed that it was shattered, with much loss of substance, just below the
    trochanters. The fissures ran up with the capsule, and the fractured extremities of the bone
    were carious and had lost tissue by absorption. </p>

   <p> &#178; The abstract of this case was compiled from a report by the operator, Surgeon <hi
     rend="initialcap">E</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>ENTLEY, <hi rend="initialcap">U</hi>. <hi
     rend="initialcap">S</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">V</hi>. See <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No.
    7, S. G. O., 1867, p. 39. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001550.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 105.&#8212;Gunshot fracture of the upper extremity of the right
     femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3098.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
