<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5632">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Boyle, Peter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5632</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">108-109</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>entered hip and passed antero-posteriorly through soft parts and surgical neck of the
      femur</term>
     <term>fractured trochanter major</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 254.—<name type="person" key="955">Private Peter
     Boyle</name>, <name type="organization" key="395">Co. D, 59th Massachusetts</name>, aged 60
    years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-07-30">July 30, 1864</date>. A conoidal musket ball entered the left hip and passed
    antero-posteriorly through the soft parts and surgical neck of the femur, and fractured the
    trochanter major. His entry at the base hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name> and
    transfer to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> are recorded on <date type="admit" when="1864-08-01">August 1st</date>. He was conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> on an hospital steamer, and on <date type="transfer" when="1864-08-03">August 3d</date> was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas
     Hospital</name>. His constitutional condition, on admission, was poor. The wound, however, had
    an healthy aspect, and a thorough exploration showed that the injury to the soft tissues
    involved no important part, and that the fracture at the junction of the neck and trochanter
    major was not accompanied by much longitudinal splintering in either direction. <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, decided that an excision of the injured bone was expedient, and that
    the operation should be done as soon as the patient had rallied from the fatigue and
    irritability induced by his long journey. On <date type="operation" when="1864-08-05">August
     5th</date>, ether having been administered, <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon
     Thomson</name> proceeded to excise the head, neck, and trochanters of the left femur, through a
    straight incision of sufficient length made over the trochanter major. The rotator muscles and
    the tendons of the psoas and iliacus being divided, the round ligament was readily cut and the
    head exarticulated. The section of the shaft was made by a chain saw at the level of the
    trochanter minor. The operation was rapidly accomplished, and there was no hæmorrhage of
    moment. The wound was dressed with an antiseptic solution of one drop of creasote to each ounce
    of water on charpie, and the limb was supported by a sand bag on either side. The patient
    reacted well after the operation; but at night there was profuse sweating and some nausea. On
    the following morning he ate a good breakfast. He still had a cool, sweating skin, and his pulse
    was at 128. He gradually sank, and died from exhaustion on <date type="death" when="1864-08-07">August 7, 1864</date>. The pathological preparation, presented by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name> to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>,
    is figured by the accompanying wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 63).</p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001537.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 63.—Shot perforation of neck of left femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3593.</head>
   </figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
