<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31649">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Barnard, Henry B.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31649</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">96</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>ball entered anterior aspect of upper third thigh, came out at gluteal region</term>
       <term>wounded sigmoid flexure of colon</term>
       <term>fæcal matter and urine escaped from wounds</term>
       <term>ulcer of inner thigh with fistulous track possibly connecting with urethra or rectum</term>       
       <term>wounded thigh measures in circumference one-half less than opposite</term>
       <term>pain in back and lameness after protracted labor</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-24">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 290.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Captain Henry B. Barnard</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. L, 2d New York Mounted Rifles</name>, aged 27 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-07-30">July 30, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the anterior aspect of the upper third of the left thigh and came out at the right gluteal region; in its passage, it wounded the sigmoid flexure of the colon.  He was taken to the field hospital, and, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-08-03">August 3d</date>, was transferred to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and admitted into <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, under the charge of <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>  Fæcal matter and urine escaped from the wounds. Tonics and good diet were ordered. The patient did well, and, on <date type="furlough" when="1864-09-08">September 8th</date>, was furloughed, at which time the wound was still open.  About <date type="duty" when="1864-11">two months afterward</date>, he returned to the hospital on his way to his regiment, and was "perfectly well."  He is reported by the <name type="person" key="xxx">Adjutant General of the State of New York</name> as having been discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-01-20">January 20, 1865</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner H. F. Montgomery</name> reports, <date type="pension" when="1965-03-22">March 22, 1865</date>: "There is now, on the inside of the left thigh, one inch from the groin, an ulcer with a hard inflamed base and a fistulous track upward and downward, possibly connecting with the urethra or rectum."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiners B. L. Hovey</name> and <name type="person" key="xxx">H. F. Montgomery</name>, of <name type="place">Rochester</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1871-11-24">November 24, 1871</date>, that "the left thigh measures, in circumference, one-half less than the right at a corresponding point. He complains of pain in the back, and lameness after protracted labor."  He was last paid <date type="pension" when="1872-12-04">December 4, 1872</date>.</p>     
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
