<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30956">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Bradford, W. B.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e30956</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="bl">Ben Lesiak</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">955</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and operations of the forearm</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the forearm</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the forearm</term>
       <term>excisions in the continuity of the bones of the forearm for shot injury</term> 
       <term>intermediary excisions in the bones of the forearm</term> 
       <term>recoveries after intermediary excisions</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of arm</term>
       <term>ball entered middle of right forearm on radial side, passed transversely through, produced compound comminuted fracture of middle third of radius</term> 
       <term>partial shaft of radius removed</term>
       <term>movable false joint, hand and limb nearly useless for labor</term>
       <term>effort produces severe pain in limb</term>
       <term>arm deprived of rotary power</term>
       <term>necrosis excised end of radius</term> 
       <term>wrist joint partially anchylosed, pronation and supination of arm injured, arm reduced in power</term>       
       <term>general anesthesia</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#bl" when="2011-02-24">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1913.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. B. Bradford</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 20th Maine</name>, aged 20 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>, and admitted to the field hospital of the 1st division, Fifth Corps, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon W. R. DeWitt, <choice><orig>jr.</orig><reg>Jr.</reg></choice></name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, noted:  &#34;Gunshot wound of arm.&#34;  <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon O. A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver Hospital</name>l, Washington, furnished the specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 698) and the following history:  &#34;The missile, a conoidal ball (probably), entered the middle of the right forearm on the radial side, passing transversely through, and produced a compound comminuted fracture of the middle third of the radius. The general condition of the patient at date of admission&#8212;May 11th&#8212;appeared good. Simple dressings were applied, and a pint of ale was ordered during every twenty-four hours.  <date type="operation" when="1864-05-20">May 20th</date>, patient anaesthetized and about three inches of radius removed, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. C. Clark</name>, making a straight incision, and removing sequestra and the serrated ends of the bone with the chain saw. The incision was then filled with charpie and cold-water dressings applied.  25th, wound filling rapidly with healthy granulations. Appetite good. Treatment continued.  June 1st, patient about the same; the wound secretes a large quantity of laudable pus; simple cerate dressings used.  12th, pus burrowing about forearm to slight extent; free incisions were made.  <date type="furlough" when="1864-07-18">July 18th</date>, has continued to improve. Wound now nearly healed. Patient was furloughed today.  <date type="furlough" when="1864-09-16">September 16th</date>, patient returned from furlough.&#34;  The specimen consists of eleven fragments, comprising the excised portion, from the middle of the radius. The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-03-02">March 2, 1865</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. Nichols</name>, of <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, <date type="pension" when="1865-03-07">March 7, 1865</date>, certified:  &quot; &#42;   &#42;   &#42;   No union has yet taken place; movable false joint exists, rendering hand and limb nearly useless for labor.&#34;  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner C. N. Germaine</name>, of <name type="place">Rockland, Me.</name>, <date type="pension" when="1867-09-05">September 5, 1867</date>, certified:  &quot; &#42;   &#42;   &#42;   The usual action required by an effort to use any implement, etc., produces severe pain in the affected limb. Besides this, the arm is almost entirely deprived of its rotary power. His arm is useful so far as regards any duty which does not require dexterity or strength. The arm is now in a worse condition than formerly, in consequence, I presume, of necrosis of one of the excised ends of the radius <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi>, which more effectually destroys the power and comfort of the limb,&#34; etc. In <date type="pension" when="1873-09">September, 1873</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">the same examiner</name> reported:  &#34;The wrist joint is partially anchylosed, pronation and supination of his arm injured, and his arm much reduced in power. Manual labor of an hour or less completely exhausts his arm.&#34;  The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>.</p>
   
<figure>
 <graphic url="cww.001701.001" />
 <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 698.&#8212;Eleven fragments of right radius removed by excision.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2297.</head>
</figure> 
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
