<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10433">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Davis, John</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e10433</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">580</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases allied to or associated with</term>
                                        <term>the paroxysmal and continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>cerebro-spinal fever</term>
                                        <term>clinical and post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>quotidian intermittent fever</term>   
                                        <term>dark-purple spots with well-defined margins</term>
                                        <term>infiltration of dark-colored blood in all layers of skin and subcutaneous connective</term>
                                        <term>restlessness and convulsive movements resembling hysteria</term>
                                        <term>delirium, then coma</term>
                                        <term>arachnoid opaque, limpid serum beneath</term>
                                        <term>theca vertebralis well filled with serum, cerebro-spinal fluid contained flocculi in lumbar region</term>
                                        <term>lungs engorged, middle lobe of lung contained apoplectic extravasation</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 92.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="833">Private John Davis</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="731">Co. E, 8th Vt.</name>;
                                        age 28; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-07-26">July 26, 1864</date>, with quotidian intermittent
                                        of moderate severity.  This was immediately checked by
                                        quinine, and the patient seemed in a fair way to recovery
                                        when, on the morning of the 31st, he remained in bed
                                        feeling weak and without appetite. The tongue was clean;
                                        about midnight he had been seized with great restlessness
                                        which lasted twenty minutes, but he had not slept until
                                        towards morning. He did well during the day until 5.30 P.
                                        M., when he was again attacked with restlessness and
                                        convulsive movements resembling those presented by certain
                                        cases of hysteria. He became delirious, tossing himself
                                        about in bed and uttering shrill screams; his pupils were
                                        dilated; respiration 14; pulse 100 and full. Ice was applied
                                        to the head and spine and mustard to the epigastrium; a
                                        turpentine enema was given. No medicine was prescribed by
                                        the mouth as the ability to swallow appeared to be lost.  Coma gradually supervened, and the patient died <date type="death"
                                                when="1864-08-01">at midnight</date>,
                                        twenty-four hours after the onset of the attack and six and
                                        a half hours after the full development of its character.
                                        Toward the last he was bathed in perspiration.   <hi
                                                rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: Body
                                        well developed; surface of back of neck and shoulders
                                        showing twenty-five or thirty dark-purple spots from the
                                        size of a mustard-seed to that of a pea, circular, somewhat
                                        elevated, with well-defined margins, and consisting of an
                                        infiltration of dark-colored blood in all the layers of the
                                        skin and to some extent in the subcutaneous connective.
                                        During the removal of the skull-cap about six ounces of
                                        serum colored with blood flowed away; the Pacchionian bodies
                                        were unusually numerous, large and adherent for a subject of
                                        28 years; the arachnoid was opaque, especially over the
                                        vertex, and some limpid serum lay beneath it; the ventricles
                                        contained a moderate quantity of serum; the choroid plexus
                                        in the fourth ventricle was thickened and looked like a
                                        lamina of pale flabby granulations, but the vessels in the
                                        other ventricles presented no <choice><orig>abnormity</orig><reg>abnormality</reg></choice>; the substance of
                                        the cerebrum, cerebellum, pons and medulla oblongata was
                                        moderately congested throughout. The theca vertebralis was
                                        well filled with serum, notwithstanding the large quantity
                                        which had escaped during the examination of the brain, and
                                        the cerebro-spinal fluid contained flocculi in the lumbar
                                        region; the arachnoid was opaque and the vessels beneath it
                                        intensely congested; the substance of the cord seemed
                                        healthy. The lungs were engorged and the middle lobe of the
                                        right lung contained an apoplectic extravasation as large as
                                        a walnut. The heart-clots were small. The blood was much
                                        more fluid than natural. The liver and intestines were
                                        healthy; the kidneys congested; the urine highly
                                                albuminous.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name
                                                  type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>,
                                                        Washington, D. C.</hi>&#8432;</p>
                        <p>&#8432; <hi rend="initialcap">J</hi>OHN <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL, <hi rend="initialcap">U. S. V.</hi>, published this case in an article on <hi rend="italic">Epidemic Cerebro-spinal Meningitis</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">American Jour. Med. Sciences</hi>, June, 1865.</p>                         
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
