<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7330">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Kennedy, Thomas</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e7330</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">111</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term>
                    <term>contusion of the skull without fracture</term>
                    <term>encephalitis</term>
                    <term>conoidal pistol ball contused parietal bone near descending branch of
                        lambdoidal suture</term>
                    <term>ague, chill daily</term>
                    <term>injury found near middle of posterior edge of parietal bone</term>
                    <term>missile found against skull, inches from point of injury</term>
                    <term>meninges thickened and blackened and firmly adherent to <choice>
                            <orig>calvaria</orig>
                            <reg>calvarium</reg>
                        </choice></term>
                    <term>brain substance softened</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-16">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-06-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding,
                edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-17">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0093">
            <p><name type="person" key="371"><hi rend="initialcap">K</hi>ENNEDY, <hi
                        rend="initialcap">T</hi>HOMAS</name>, Private, <name type="organization"
                    key="150">Co. M, 1st Massachusetts Heavy Artillery</name>, aged 30, was wounded,
                at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg, Virginia</name>, <date
                    type="injury" when="1864-06-16">June 16th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal pistol
                ball, which contused the right parietal bone, near the right descending branch of
                the lambdoidal suture. He was conveyed to Washington, and admitted, on <date
                    type="admit" when="1864-06-21">the 21st</date>, into the <name type="hospital"
                    key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>. Simple dressings were applied, as the injury
                was considered slight. He was furloughed on <date type="furlough" when="1864-07-16"
                    >July 16th</date>, but returned on <date type="admit" when="1864-07-29">the 29th
                    of the same month</date>. He stated that during his absence from the hospital he
                had suffered from ague, and, for the last ten days, had experienced a chill daily. A
                careful examination of the wound was now made, and a roughness of the external table
                of the skull was detected. He was much prostrated, but complained of no pain or
                uneasiness about the head. His pulse was frequent and feeble, tongue dry and red,
                and the abdomen tympanitic and painful. Three grains of calomel, with one-fourth of
                a grain of opium, were ordered every three hours, until the third dose had been
                taken; meantime, tonics and stimulants were given, and afterwards continued in
                liberal doses. Sinapisms were applied to the epigastric region and extremities. No
                perceptible improvement in his condition, however, was obtained. He died on the
                afternoon of <date type="death" when="1864-07-31">the 31st</date>, remaining fully
                sensible and able to answer questions intelligently until within two or three hours
                of his death. At the autopsy, the seat of injury was found to be near the middle of
                the posterior edge of the right parietal bone. The missile had glanced downward and
                forward, and was found lying against the skull, two inches from the point of injury.
                The pericranium was separated a distance of three and three-quarter inches along the
                track of the missile, and beneath it the bone was spongy and porous. The line of
                separation from healthy bone was well-marked. Upon the removal of the skull-cap, a
                slight sponginess of the internal table, beneath the point of impact, was observed.
                (See <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 35.) The meninges, for some distance around the
                seat of injury, were very much thickened and blackened, and firmly adherent to the <choice>
                    <orig>calvaria</orig>
                    <reg>calvarium</reg>
                </choice>. The brain substance was softened, and the vessels very much congested.
                The heart, liver, and spleen were flabby. The case is reported by <name
                    type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeons Dean</name> and <name
                    type="person" key="370">Atwater.</name>
            </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001365.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="intitialcap">F</hi>IG. 35.&#8212;Showing the extent of necrosis in a <choice>
                    <orig>calvaria</orig>
                    <reg>calvarium</reg>
                </choice> sixteen days after a gunshot contusion. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2920,
                    Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
            </figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
