<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6545">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Lemon, George W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6545</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">145</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the hip joint</term>
     <term>coxo-femoral amputations</term>
     <term>secondary amputations</term>
     <term>femur fractured at junction of middle and upper thirds</term>
     <term>upper fragment of femur protruded from wound</term>
     <term>abscesses in thigh, profuse suppuration</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 320.&#8212;<name type="person" key="972">Private George W.
     Lemon</name>, <name type="organization" key="399">Co. C, 6th Maryland</name>, aged 30 years,
    had his left femur fractured, at the junction of the middle and upper thirds, by a conoidal
    musket ball, at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="259">the Wilderness</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>. He was left in a shelter tent on the field
    and fell into the hands of the enemy. On May 13th he was recaptured, and was sent to <name
     type="place">Fredericksburg</name>, and thence to <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, where
    he was received at the <name type="hospital" key="512">Third Division Hospital</name> on <date
     type="admit" when="1864-06-14">June 14th</date>. When admitted he had diarrh&#339;a and was
    greatly emaciated. There was a bed-sore, four inches in diameter, over the sacrum, and smaller
    sores over the prominences on the spine and scapul&#230;. The lower end of the upper fragment of
    the femur protruded from the wound, from which there was a profuse offensive ash-colored
    discharge. To check the diarrh&#339;a, to administer suitable nourishment, and to take pressure
    from the bed-sores by supporting the body on air cushions, were the first matters attended to.
    Then moderate extension was applied to the injured limb, and a tolerably good position was
    maintained by means of pillows and cushions. In three weeks the bed-sores were healed, and there
    was a slight improvement in the general constitutional condition. Extension of the limb causing
    pain, it was discontinued. For the next ten or twelve months the patient clung to life by the
    slenderest thread. Detached fragments of bone frequently gave rise to inflammatory swelling,
    abscesses in the thigh, and profuse suppuration. Yet the appetite and digestion continued to be
    good, and the great drain upon the system was supported unusually well. In May, 1865, it was
    found that the fracture was quite firmly consolidated. The patient now occasionally sat up in a
    chair, but every attempt of the sort was followed by acute inflammation of the thigh, with
    increased suppuration. It was now decided that the patient must ultimately sink under the
    profuse suppuration, and that an operation should be performed as soon as it was opportune, and
    that every effort should be made to put the patient in a condition to support this shock. On
     <date type="operation" when="1865-10-12">October 12, 1865</date>, <name type="person" key="134"
     >Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, proceeded
    to amputate at the hip joint. Chloroform was administered; the external iliac artery was
    compressed at the pubis; anterior and posterior semilunar flaps were formed by transfixion, and
    the femur was disarticulated. The h&#230;morrhage was inconsiderable, and the patient reacted
    soon and satisfactorily. From the day of the operation he steadily improved, with scarcely an
    untoward symptom. On <date type="operation" when="1865-11-15">November 15th</date>, <name
     type="person" key="134">Dr. Bentley</name> reported that the ligatures had all come away, and
    that the wound was granulating kindly. In December the stump was healed, and the patient began
    to get about on crutches. The fracture of the exarticulated femur was found to be imperfectly
    but quite firmly united, with great antero-posterior angular deformity and shortening. The bone
    was sent to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, where it is
    preserved as <hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 4386. A posterior view of it is given by the
    annexed left hand wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 98). On <date type="transfer"
     when="1866-01-31">January 31, 1866</date>, a photograph of the man was taken, from which the
    right hand wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 99) is copied. Lemon was then transferred
    to the <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, at Washington. He was then
    quite well, and able to go where he chose on crutches. The cicatrix was firm and healthy. On
     <date type="servicedischarge" when="1866-02-03">February 3, 1866</date>, he was discharged from
    the hospital, and from the service of the United States, at his own request. He went to his home
    at <name type="place">Bird Hill, Carroll county, Maryland</name>, and resumed his trade of
    shoemaking. He was granted a pension of fifteen dollars a month. On <date type="pension"
     when="1867-04-23">April 23, 1867</date>, a letter was received from him in which he stated that
    his health was excellent; that he weighed ninety-nine and a half pounds, an increase of twelve
    and a half pounds from the date at which he left the hospital; and that he had been able to walk
    to the village of <name type="place">Westminster</name>, a distance of seven miles, without
    fatigue. In a letter dated <name type="place">Westminster, Maryland</name>, <date type="pension"
     when="1870-07-31">July 31, 1870</date>, he states &#34;that the artificial limb is not now or
    ever has been of the least service to me. &#42; &#42; I have tried to wear it; but it only
    serves to irritate the stump, and makes it so raw and sore that I cannot bear it to touch
    anything for days afterwards.&#34; The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1878-06-04"
     >June 4, 1878</date>.&#185; </p>

   <p> &#185; This secondary amputation at the hip is noted on page 52 of <hi rend="italic"
     >Circular</hi> No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, in a foot-note. In the <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the
     Surgical Section of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name></hi>, of
    1866, p. 248, there is a brief memorandum of the facts of the case, with a wood-cut of the
    fractured femur, contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by the
    operator, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon <hi rend="initialcap">E</hi>DWIN <hi
      rend="initialcap">B</hi>ENTLEY</name>, <name type="organization" key="132"><hi
      rend="initialcap">U</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">V</hi>.</name> A
    detailed account of the case, compiled from the reports of the <name type="hospital" key="512"
     >Third Division Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, and <name
     type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, is printed in <hi rend="italic"
     >Circular</hi> No. 7, S. G. O., 1867, p. 42. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001547.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 98.&#8212;Consolidated gunshot fracture of the left femur. <hi
      rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4386.</head>
   </figure>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001548.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 99.&#8212;Appearance of cicatrix after secondary coxo-femoral
     amputation. [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
