<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e14835">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Perkins, G. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e14835</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">365-366</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term> 
     <term>shot contusions of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of shot contusions of the knee joint treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered knee at lower outer edge of patella, came out over head of fibula</term>
     <term>head of tibia grazed, joint opened</term>
     <term>large quantity of bloody pus and synovia escaped from joint</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>died from immediate effects of h&#230;morrhage</term>
     <term>source of bleeding anterior tibial artery near bifurcation</term>
     <term>lung found much congested</term>     
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 540.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1120">Private G. W.
      Perkins</name>, <name type="organization" key="80">Co. G, 1st Massachusetts Cavalry</name>,
     aged 22, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="109">Beverly Ford</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1863-06-09">June 9, 1863</date>, by a pistol ball, which entered the left knee at the
     lower outer edge of the patella, passed downward, and came out over the head of the fibula.
     <date type="admit" when="1863-06-12">Three days after the reception of the injury</date> he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, where he was etherized and an incision made to examine
     the wound, when the head of the tibia was found to be grazed and the joint opened, allowing
     synovia to escape on motion of the limb. Ice-water dressings were applied for a <date type="operation" when="1863-06-14">couple of days</date>.  It was then resolved by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W. Thomson</name>,
      <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of the hospital, to lay the
     knee joint freely open by means of liberal incisions on either side of the patella and through
     the original track of the wound. By this means it was hoped to give free exit to pus, which was
     already filling the joint, and to save the limb with anchylosis, the operation being adopted as
     the only alternative to amputating the thigh. A large quantity of bloody pus and synovia
     escaped when the lateral incisions were made; two or three cutaneous vessels were tied, and by
     means of a syphon the limb was kept constantly under the effect of ice water. The patient,
     though having some fever and retention of urine, had very little pain in the knee and felt
     comfortable. Morphia and sweet spirits of nitre were prescribed. On <date type="operation" when="1863-06-17">June 17th</date>, there was some
     fluctuation along the base of the internal condyle, for which a free horizontal incision was
     made, and flaxseed poultices were applied. All the incisions about the knee continued to
     discharge freely.  About <date type="operation" when="1863-06-24">one week later</date> an erysipelatous swelling was noticed, a deep-seated
     abscess having apparently formed and fluctuation being detected below the head of the tibia. A large quantity
     of pus was then liberated by a careful dissection, and the painful tension of the leg was
     thereby relieved.  On June 26th, the patient had a severe chill for the first time, and his
     stimulants were at once increased and quinine and capsicum added to the prescription of
     morphia. On the following day the fever had disappeared, but pneumonic symptoms were detected, and a mustard
     plaster was applied over the left chest. Suppuration still continued freely from all the openings.  On the morning of <date type="death" when="1863-07-01">July 1st</date>, a large amount of arterial blood was found to have escaped through the
     incision along the gastrocnemius muscle, and compression was at once made in the groin and the
     wound was cleaned out carefully, the source of the bleeding being apparently the anterior or
     posterior tibial artery near the bifurcation, and too deeply seated to be reached without
     careful dissection. Meanwhile the patient, already moribund, was stimulated, but without avail.
     He died within a half hour, from the immediate effects of the h&#230;morrhage. At the autopsy a
     diffused abscess was found following the course of the vessels in the popliteal space into
     Hunter's canal but not otherwise involving the thigh; all the connecting tissue in the ham was
     in a sloughing condition. When the artery was dissected out the perforation was found in the
     anterior tibial, about three-fourths of an inch from its origin, the vessel being much
     thickened, soft, and tough, though not materially diseased. The left lung was found firmly
     adherent and much congested. The bones comprising the injured knee joint were contributed by <name type="person" key="200">Dr.
      Thomson</name> (<hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1866, p. 323, <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1339), and the history
     of the case was furnished by <name type="person" key="457">Assistant Surgeon C. C. Lee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
