<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31359">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Hareh, C. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31359</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mh">Minda Haas</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">962</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and operations in the forearm</term> 
       <term>shot wounds of the forearm</term>
       <term>excisions in the continuity of the bones of the forearm for shot injury</term> 
       <term>secondary excisions in the bones of the forearm</term>
       <term>recoveries after secondary excision of bones of the forearm</term>
       <term>wounded in forearm</term> 
       <term>ball entered arm below olecranon process of ulna, extracted same distance above wrist joint, caused compound fracture of ulna</term>
       <term><choice><orig>exsection</orig><reg>excision</reg></choice> of nearly two-thirds of ulna</term>
       <term>ulna not broken in entire thickness, splinter remaining intact</term>       
       <term>no voluntary motion of thumb or fingers</term>
       <term>arm helpless as if amputated</term>  
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mh" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>   
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1923.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private C. W. Hareh</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. A, 105th New York</name>, age 29 years, was wounded in the left forearm at <name type="BATTLE" key="33">Antietam</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-09-17">September 17, 1862</date>, and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="65">Cranch Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-09-24">about one week afterward</date>.  <name type="person" key="1353">Surgeon A. Wynkoop</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, noted the injury. Entering <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name> <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-05">December 5th</date>, <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-11">several days afterward</date> the wounded man was transferred to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon L. K. Baldwin</name> reported: &#34;The missile was a mini&#233; ball, which entered the left arm about two inches below the olecranon process of the ulna, and was extracted about the same distance above the wrist joint, causing a compound fracture of the bone. The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Satterlee Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-13"><date type="operation" when="1862-12-13">December 13th</date></date>. The wound at the time of his admission presented rather an unhealthy appearance, the discharge being of a thin sanious nature, giving evidence of the existence of a considerable amount of dead bone. The patient complained of a pricking sensation in and around the seat of the injury, as though there were some pieces of loose bone in the wound. After carefully examining the injury with the probe, a number of loose pieces were discovered in the region of the wound of exit, all of which were within reach and were removed by means of a pair of forceps. By this means it was hoped to get rid of the cause of the irritation and to promote the healing; but all was to no effect, the amount of injury being so extensive, and portions of dead bone so numerous, that the irritation was still kept up, rendering an operation necessary to a cure. The patient suffered so much inconvenience from the pricking sensation already alluded to that he was quite anxious to have an operation performed for the removal of the cause of the irritation. He being of a stout and robust constitution, an operation was soon decided on. He was accordingly, in order to better fit him for an operation, placed upon quinine and iron, together with a good nutritious diet, which treatment was continued until <date type="operation" when="1863-01-10">January 10th</date>, when he was considered in a fit condition to be operated on. The mode of procedure decided upon was the excision of as much of the ulna as was found to be in any way diseased. The patient having been put under the influence of an anesthetic (pure chloroform has been used on this occasion), an incision was made from a short distance below the olecranon process to within about an inch of the wrist joint. The bone was found to be so much shattered by the passage of the ball as to require <choice><orig>exsection</orig><reg>excision</reg></choice> of nearly two-thirds of its whole extent, which was accordingly done. A number of pieces of bone were found lying loose in the course traversed by the ball; others were firmly united to the main shaft of the bone by granulations which had been thrown out by nature in her effort at reproduction. After the bone was removed the wound was kept open by the introduction of a piece of lint into the bottom of it, which was kept wet with cold water until the third day, when active suppuration had taken place. The wound was subsequently dressed with flaxseed poultices, and the patient's strength sustained by the administration of tonics and good nutritious diet. Active suppuration was kept up, and the wound soon began to heal kindly from the bottom. The granulations were at no time exuberant, and at the present time, January 30th, the wound is almost healed. The patient's health has not suffered any from the effects of the operation. He is beginning to have considerable motion in the arm and hand, and there is every reason to suppose that the normal use of the arm and hand will be almost wholly regained.&#34;  The specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 708) consists of four and a half inches of the excised portion of the ulna, and shows that the bone was not broken in its entire thickness, a splinter one-fourth of an inch remaining intact. A fragment of about the same diameter and a little more than an inch in length has been fixed by new bone parallel with it. Other small fragments have been consolidated above and below it. The specimen was contributed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. Leidy</name>. The patient, on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-07-29">July 29, 1864</date>, was discharged and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. H. Helmer</name>, of <name type="place">Lockport</name>, <date type="pension" when="1868-01-08">January 8, 1868</date>, certified: &#34;The ulna was removed nearly the whole length. The thumb is flexed upon the palm, and all the fingers are flexed upon the thumb. He has no voluntary motion of the thumb or fingers.&#34;  The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Lockport Examining Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1875-08-04">August 4, 1875</date>: &#34;He is totally unable to perform manual labor. The arm is as helpless as if amputated at the shoulder joint.&#34;  This pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>.</p>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001741.001" />
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 708.&#8212;Excised part of ulna showing a consolidated partial shot fracture.     <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1865.</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
