<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e20758">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Mullen, F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e20758</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">539</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the upper third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>recovery after secondary amputations in the upper third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>ball passed through and fractured tibia in lower third</term>
     <term>fell and re-fractured limb</term>
     <term>leg amputated at junction of upper and middle thirds</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 787.—<name type="person" key="1313">Private F.
     Mullen</name>, <name type="organization" key="464">Co. E, 43d New York</name>, aged 21 years,
    was wounded in the left leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="xx">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>, and subsequently underwent secondary
    amputation. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who performed the operation,¹ forwarded the following
    descriptive history: "The wound was caused by a minié ball, which passed through and
    fractured the tibia in the lower third. The man was brought to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-05-06">three days
     afterwards</date>. His general condition was good, and it was judged expedient to attempt to
    save the limb without operation. It was accordingly placed in Hodgen's splint and cold-water
    dressings were applied; stimulants administered. After several days the parts suppurated freely,
    and by June 1st the wounds were discharging a good and healthy pus, consolidation taking place,
    and appetite and pulse being normal. The parts continued to heal nicely up to <date type="injury" when="1863-07-28">July 28th</date>, when the patient fell and re-fractured the
    limb while attempting to walk across the Ward. On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-02">August 2d</date>, several pieces of bone were removed. August 15th, parts œdematous;
    discharge thin and fetid. On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-19">August 19th</date>,
    several openings for the exit of pus were made, when a small necrosed splinter came away; pulse
    weak; general health suffering. The leg remained in about the same condition until September
    1st, when compression by bandage was applied. About October 1st there was both general and local
    improvement, the discharge being of a thick and healthier character. The splints were now
    removed and stimulants continued. One month later necrosis of the shaft of the tibia had become
    extensive, the dead bone being completely encased in an involucrum; condition fair; discharges
    from several openings. But little change took place up to December 1st, and none for the better
    for one month afterwards. The involucrum was now large and the skin covering the front of it
    thin and about to ulcerate extensively; the foot being considerably twisted inward by abnormal
    muscular action (partial talipes varus) and the deformity steadily increasing; ankle joint also
    becoming stiff. There being now no hopes of preserving a useful limb it was deemed advisable to
    remove it by amputation. The operation was performed on <date type="operation" when="1864-01-09">January 9th</date>, at the junction of the upper and middle thirds, by the flap method (double
    flaps, the anterior one being short). The sawn end of the tibia was beveled off as recommended
    by Sanson, that is, by placing the saw obliquely—not on the ridge, but on the internal
    surface of the bone. The fibula was divided somewhat higher up than the tibia, as practised by
    Roux. Throughout the operation the patient was kept insensible by sulphuric ether. He did not
    exhibit any perceptible shock. The flaps were carefully coaptated and secured at several points
    by interrupted sutures and strips of isinglass plaster. Several turns of a roller were placed
    around the leg to serve as a supporting bandage; but no other dressing was applied. A full
    anodyne was administered after the operation and another at 12 P. M. On the following day the
    patient was sitting up in bed reading a newspaper, the stump being in fine condition, free from
    heat and redness, and almost devoid of pain and swelling. On January 13th the sutures were
    removed and the stump was dressed for the first time and found to be uniting by primary
    adhesion. There was no constitutional disturbance whatever. On January 24th the last ligature,
    that of the posterior tibial artery, came away. The patient had not at any time nor in any way
    suffered in consequence of the amputation, and the stump had united by first intention. In
    short, he recovered precisely in the same way as the most fortunate cases of amputation of the
    leg on account of disease get well." The amputated bones of the leg (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 2022) were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by
     <name type="person" key="70">the operator</name> and are represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 313), showing the fractured tibia, with an abundant involucrum
    formed to nearly the point of section, and a large detached but imprisoned sequestrum being
    exhibited through the cloacæ. A few points of osseous deposit are also seen on the fibula,
    which is uninjured. The patient entirely recovered, and was ultimately discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-09-05">September 5, 1864</date>, and pensioned. In his
    application for commutation, dated <date type="pension" when="1870">1870</date>, he described
    the condition of the stump as being "in good order." He died <date type="death" when="1871-03-05">March 5, 1871</date>. The cause of his death has not been ascertained. </p>
   <p>¹ <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>lDELL (<hi rend="initialcap">J. A.</hi>), <hi rend="italic">On the Major Amputations for Injuries in both Civil and Military Practice</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Am. Jour. Med. Sciences</hi>, 1864, Vol. XLVII, p. 376.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001643.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 313.—The lower thirds of the bones of the left leg,
     with involucrum of the tibia. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2022.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
