<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e25006">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ettinger, L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e25006</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">658, 659</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>miscellaneous injuries</term>       
       <term>operations for miscellaneous injuries</term>      
       <term>excisions for miscellaneous injuries</term>
       <term>accidentally injured by blow of axe</term>
       <term>foot injured below external malleolus, penetrating ankle joint</term>
       <term>fetid pus escaped wound, dead bone felt at bottom</term>
       <term>sinuses ran down each side of tendo-achillis</term>
       <term>partial excision of ankle joint</term>
       <term>external malleolus, whole of <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>, and portion of scaphoid were carious and removed</term>
       <term>h&#230;morrhage slight</term>
       <term>anchylosis of ankle joint</term>
       <term>pensioner</term>
       <term>disability</term>
       <term>inmate of hospital for insane</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-05">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 992.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Partial excision at the ankle joint.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private L. Ettinger</name>,&#185; <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 58th New York</name>, aged 52 years, was accidentally injured, near <name type="place">Hunter's Chapel</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-12-06">December 6, 1861</date>, by the blow of an axe, which struck his right foot just below the external malleolus, penetrating the ankle joint.  <name type="person" key="294">Assistant Surgeon J. S. Billings</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who operated in the case, made the following report:  &#34;The man was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="155">Union Hotel Hospital</name>, Georgetown, <date type="admit" when="1862-01-01">January 1, 1862</date>, being very feeble and emaciated and complaining of great pain in the foot. A large gaping wound existed at the site of the injury, from which sanious fetid pus was escaping and at the bottom of which dead bone could be felt. Sinuses also ran down each side of the tendo-achillis, and the whole integument about the ankle joint was livid and undermined. On <date type="operation" when="1862-01-06">January 6th</date> partial excision of the ankle joint was performed by a curved incision three inches long, made just below the external malleolus and including the original wound. The external malleolus, the whole of the <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>, and a small portion of the scaphoid were found to be carious and were removed by means of the bone gouge and Liston's forceps. The h&#230;morrhage was slight. Simple dressings were applied, and ale and good diet were furnished. By March 1st the wound had entirely healed, the skin had resumed its natural appearance, and the patient could walk with a cane. He was then sent to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, where he was discharged from service.  I saw him eight months afterwards, walking with a cane and with but a very slightly perceptible limp. The age and debilitated condition of this patient rendered the expediency of excision very doubtful; but the result proved entirely satisfactory.&#34;  The records of South Street Hospital, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, show that the patient was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1862-09-17">September 17, 1862</date>, by reason of &#34;anchylosis of the right ankle joint&#34; resulting from the wound. The man subsequently became a pensioner.  The nature of his injury and disability has since then been corroborated by successive certificates of various examining surgeons. The pensioner has been for some years an inmate of the hospital for the insane at <name type="place">Randall's Island, New York Harbor</name>.</p>
   <p>From <hi rend="initialcap">T</hi>ABLE  <hi rend="initialcap">CVI</hi>.  <hi rend="italic">Summary of Twenty Cases of Excisions of the Bones of the Extremities.</hi>:  . . . February, 1881, has been for the past eight years an inmate of Hospital for the Insane at Randall's Island.</p>
   <p>&#185; <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ULBERTSON (<hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">Excision of the Larger Joints of the Extremities</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Transactions American Medical Association</hi>, 1876. Supplement to Vol. XXVII, p. 344.  Prize Essay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
