<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16330">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">W——, James F.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  </edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e16330</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor>
                                                  <name>Center for Digital Research in the
                                                  Humanities</name>
                                                  <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                                  </distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl>
                                                  <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                                                  <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                                                  <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                                  <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                                  <date when="1870">1870</date>
                                                  <biblScope type="page">249</biblScope>
                                                  </bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>                                                                  
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term> 
                                                    <term>removal of fragments after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                                                    <term>fatal cases of gunshot fractures of the skull treated by the removal or elevation fragments</term>
                                                    <term>treated by operation, not by formal trephining</term>
                                                    <term>extent of injury ascertained with precision, organic alterations accurately observed</term>
                                                    <term>musket ball fractured both tables of occipital bone above and to left of protuberance</term>
                                                    <term>abscess extended from wound into left lateral ventricle</term>
                                                    <term>congested and discolored state of meninges</term>              
                                                    <term>portion of brain protruded from opening to left of centre of occipital bone</term>
                                                    <term>autopsy performed</term>                                                   
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>                                                
                                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private James F. W——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. H, 3d Maine
                                                                Volunteers</name>, aged 24 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="">Raccoon
                                                                                Ford, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-27">November 27th, 1863</date>, by a musket
                                                  ball, which fractured both tables of the occipital
                                                  bone, just above and to the left of the
                                                  protuberance.  He was admitted to the 1st division,
                                                                  Third Corps, field hospital on <date type="admit" when="1863-11-27">the same day</date>, and
                                                                transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="189">3d division hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria, Virginia</name>, on <date type="transfer" when="1863-12-04">December 4th</date>.  On the
                                                  following day he was still conscious, but very
                                                  restless; his head was very painful, pulse 120,
                                                  strong and full, tongue coated and dry, skin hot
                                                  and bowels constipated. During the night he was
                                                  delirious, and vomited often, and on the <date type="operation" when="1863-12-06">next
                                                                  morning</date> he became comatose. A piece of bone, one
                                                  inch long and three-fourths of an inch wide, was
                                                  removed from the wound, but failed to relieve the
                                                  patient, and he died at twenty minutes after three
                                                  o'clock P. M. of <date type="death" when="1863-12-06">the same day</date>.  The autopsy
                                                  revealed a congested and discolored state of the
                                                  meninges, and an abscess extending from the wound
                                                  into the left lateral ventricle. Several small
                                                  spiculæ were lying loose in the wound. An opening
                                                  was found near the middle and a little to the left
                                                  of the centre of the occipital bone, through which
                                                  a portion of the brain was protruding.  The
                                                  pathological specimen is No. 1904, Sect. I, A. M.
                                                  M., the posterior portion of the cranium showing a
                                                  nearly circular fracture of both tables. The
                                                  internal surface of the opening, which measures
                                                  one inch in diameter, is slightly the larger.  The
                                                  specimen and history were contributed by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. Cass</name>.</p>                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
