<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40934">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Nichols, George</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40934</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">154</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Douglas Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a for a year</term>
       <term>tormina and tenesmus</term>
       <term>external piles</term>
       <term>stools bloody</term>
       <term>acute pleurisy</term>
       <term>lung collapsed but connected to thoracic parietes and diaphragm by pleuritic adhesions</term>
       <term>apex of upper lobe of lung contained tubercular deposits</term>
       <term>colon ulcerated</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="162"><hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>OUGLAS <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon William F. Norris</name> in charge from October, 1864, to September, 1865:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 322.&#8212;<name type="person" key="233">Sergeant-major George Nichols</name>, <name type="organization" key="243">5th United States cavalry</name>; admitted from <name type="place">Winchester, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1865-01-18">January 18, 1865</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  This patient had suffered from diarrh&#339;a for a year. At times the symptoms were very severe, at other times he had but three or four stools in the twenty-four hours. At present the stools are bloody, and accompanied by tormina and tenesmus. He is greatly debilitated, and had upward of thirty-six scanty stools in the last twenty-four hours. An aperient of castor oil was prescribed, to be followed by quarter of a grain of nitrate of silver and one grain of sulphate of quinia every four hours; also an injection of twenty drops of laudanum in thin starch-water three times a day. Stimulants were also prescribed.  January 21st: The stools have diminished to eight or nine daily. The patient complains of a cough, which he says he has had for some time; the sputa are thin and yellow. An expectorant mixture was prescribed.  January 22d: He complained of external piles; applied an ointment containing tannic acid.  January 24th: Complained of weakness in the back; applied a pitch plaster.  January 26th: Ordered tincture of the chloride of iron three times daily.  February 5th: Has eight or nine passages in the twenty-four hours; is still much debilitated.  &#8478;. Persulphate of iron fifty grains, peppermint water one ounce. Take thirty drops four times a day.  February 10th: There is slight fever and headache, for which a diaphoretic was prescribed.  February 12th: Symptoms of acute pleurisy set in.  Died, <date type="death" when="1865-02-14">February 14th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1865-02-15">twelve hours after death</date>: Body emaciated; rigor mortis well developed. The left lung was collapsed, but connected to the thoracic parietes, and especially to the diaphragm, by pleuritic adhesions; the left pleural sac contained upward of thirty-two ounces of thin yellow serum in which clots of coagulated lymph floated; the superior lobe of the left lung was healthy, its inferior lobe somewhat hepatized; there were slight recent pleuritic adhesions on the right side. The apex of the upper lobe of the right lung contained tubercular deposits; the rest of the lung was healthy. The colon was ulcerated. The other organs were not examined.&#8212;<name type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon Carlos Carvallo</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
