<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41184">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Smale, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41184</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">177</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>typhoid fever</term>
       <term>large intestine congested and thickened, no ulceration</term>
       <term>small intestine congested</term>
       <term>pleuritic adhesions on both sides, both pleura pulmonalis and costalis coated with thick layer of fibrinous exudation</term>
       <term>deposit of tubercles in base of left upper lobe</term>
       <term>both pleural cavities contained serum</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 397.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private William Smale</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 67th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 22; admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-02-03">February 3, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears on the register of the regimental hospital of the 67th Pennsylvania volunteers, then near <name type="place">Brandy Station, Virginia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-12-14">December 14, 1863</date>&#8212;typhoid fever&#8212;sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1864-02-03">February 3, 1864</date>.]  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-02-27">February 27, 1864</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-02-28">fifteen hours and a half after death</date>: Height five feet ten inches and a half; body very much emaciated. The brain was soft, but apparently healthy; it weighed forty-four ounces and a half. The larynx and trachea were healthy; there were firm pleuritic adhesions on both sides, and both pleura pulmonalis and costalis were coated with a thick layer of fibrinous exudation; the right pleural cavity contained ten ounces of serum, the left eight ounces. The left lung weighed twenty-four ounces; there was a small deposit of tubercles in the base of its upper lobe; the whole lung was considerably congested, and the anterior part of its lower lobe was carnified; it sank in water; the right lung weighed nineteen ounces and a half; it was moderately congested, but otherwise healthy. The heart was healthy; weight eight ounces and a half. The pericardium contained half an ounce of fluid. The liver was bronzed; there were a few patches of fibrinous exudation on the upper surface of its right lobe: it weighed sixty-nine ounces. The external surface of the spleen was covered with patches of fibrinous exudation; internally the organ was mahogany colored; it weighed eleven ounces and a half. The pancreas was healthy; weight five ounces. The left kidney weighed eight ounces and a half; its cortical substance was pale and fatty; the right kidney was similar to the left, and weighed seven ounces and a half. The small intestine was very much congested. The large intestine was also very much congested and greatly thickened, but there was no ulceration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
