<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8301">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Worthen, E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8301</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">183</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball entered thigh in front, passed directly through, emerged posteriorly at lower border
      of glutei muscles</term>
     <term>comminuted fracture of femur</term>
     <term>injured limb shortened and considerably deformed</term>
     <term>discharge of burrowing pus</term>
     <term>typhoid fever</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 372.&#8212; Corporal E. Worthen, Co. B, 2d Vermont, aged 25
    years, was wounded in the right thigh, at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>,
     <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5th, 1864</date>, and admitted to hospital in <name
     type="place">Alexandria</name>
    <date type="admit" when="1864-05-26">three weeks afterwards</date>. <name type="person"
     key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
    described the wound as a "shot fracture of the upper third of the femur," but the progress of
    the case was not recorded. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-03-17">March 17, 1865</date>, the
    patient was transferred to Sloan Hospital, <name type="place">Montpelier</name>, whence <name
     type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H. Janes</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
     V.</name>, contributed the following history: "The wound was caused by a mini&#233; ball, which
    entered the thigh in front, passed directly through and emerged posteriorly, at the lower border
    of the glutei muscles, comminuting the femur for about three inches. From the field the wounded
    man was taken to the hospital of the 2d division, Sixth Corps, at Fredericksburg, and thence by
    boat to <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, where the limb was first adjusted, and kept in
    position by sand bags without extension. He stated that no other apparatus was ever used.
    Subsequently he had typhoid fever and erysipelas. The first fragment of bone was removed in
     <date type="operation" when="1864-07">July, 1864</date>, and since that time about fifty pieces
    have come away. When admitted to Sloan Hospital the wound was still slightly discharging, but
    the patient was able to go about on crutches. About three months afterwards the bone had become
    so firmly united that he could walk a short distance without crutch or cane. When discharged
    from service, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-06-23">June 23, 1865</date>, the patient
    was in good general health, and able to walk a considerable distance on smooth ground without
    crutch or cane, the injured limb being shortened two and a half inches and considerably
    deformed. There was also necrosed bone remaining, and the wound still slightly discharging."
     <name type="person" key="xxx">Examining Surgeon C. L. Allen</name>, of <name type="place"
     >Rutland, Vt.</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1866-09-24">September 24,
     1866</date>: "The right limb is now three inches shorter than the left. An opening (the wound
    of entrance) still exists in front of the trochanter, into which a probe passes about four
    inches; another opening posteriorly (the wound of exit) allows the probe to pass in about three
    inches. A third opening exists near the middle of the inside of the thigh, having been made by
    the Surgeon for the discharge of the burrowing pus." The same examiner subsequently certified
    that he was called on to visit the pensioner on <date type="pension" when="1870-10-23">October
     23, 1870</date>, and found him "suffering from py&#230;mia, resulting from the wound breaking
    out anew, from the effects of which he died <date type="death" when="1870-10-25">October 25,
     1870</date>." A card photograph of the patient, taken at the Sloan Hospital, was contributed by
     <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Janes</name> (<hi rend="italic">Card Photos</hi>., A. M.
    M., Vol. II, p. 22), an enlarged copy of which, taken at the <name type="hospital" key="431"
     >Army Medical Museum</name> (<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 129), is shown in
    wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 139).</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001560.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 139.&#8212;Result of a shot wound of upper third of femur.
     [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
