<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41132">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Shannon, Thomas</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41132</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">174</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>skin dull yellowish-slate color and furfuraceous</term>
       <term>feet and toes persistently cold, toes bluish</term>
       <term>quantity of subarachnoid fluid larger than usual</term>
       <term>both lungs collapsed, right lung had softened tubercles at apex</term>
       <term>liver apparently fatty</term>
       <term>kidneys an&#230;mic</term>
       <term>mucous membrane far above ileoc&#230;cal valve assumed granular appearance, became more marked farther down and assumed more character of exudation of lymph</term>
       <term>toward ileoc&#230;cal valve deposit yellowish, pultaceous, and resembled false membrane in diphtheria</term>
       <term>colon ulcerated throughout</term>
       <term>above ileoc&#230;cal valve ulcer perforated ileum and communicated with perforating ulcer in c&#230;cum</term>
       <term>between two ulcers small cavity contained pus, which was adherent and appeared to prevent extravasation of intestinal contents into abdominal cavity</term>
       <term></term>
       <term></term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 382.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Thomas Shannon</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company F, 42d New York volunteers</name>; age 25; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-09-12">September 12, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears on the register of the regimental hospital of the 24th New York volunteers, admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-08-24">August 24th</date>&#8212;diarrh&#339;a&#8212;sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1863-09-10">September 10th</date>.]  The patient stated that he had been sick <date type="injury" when="1863-05">four months</date>; was extremely emaciated; his hair was dry and long; his eyes were dim, but ulceration of the cornea had not yet taken place; the skin was of a dull yellowish-slate color, and slightly furfuraceous; the abdomen was much depressed; the feet and toes were persistently cold, the toes bluish.  About the 13th of October he began to sink rapidly, but with singular vitality he reacted from a condition bordering upon death, and for several weeks improved so greatly that hopes of his recovery were entertained. He subsequently became languid and exhausted, the diarrh&#339;a became again more violent, and he died <date type="death" when="1863-11-19">November 19th</date>, at 7.30 A. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-11-19">six hours after death</date>: Height five feet nine inches; rigor mortis well marked; body much emaciated. The brain was healthy, and weighed fifty-seven ounces; the ventricles contained a drachm of serum; the quantity of subarachnoid fluid was larger than usual. The mucous membrane of the trachea was pale. The right lung was collapsed, and weighed eight ounces and a half; it contained an abundance of pigment and some softened tubercles at its apex; the left lung was also collapsed, and weighed nine ounces. The pericardium contained six drachms of serum. The heart was healthy, and weighed eight ounces; its right cavities contained a soft black clot, and a similar one was found in the left ventricle. The liver was of a pale-yellowish color, apparently fatty; it weighed fifty-five ounces and a half; the gall-bladder contained eight drachms of dark tar-like bile. The spleen was firm, of a reddish mahogany-color, and weighed eight ounces and a half. The kidneys were pale and an&#230;mic; the right kidney weighed three ounces and a half, the left four and a half. The pancreas was hard and tallow-like; it weighed two ounces. Seven feet above the ileoc&#230;cal valve the mucous membrane of the small intestine assumed a granular appearance, which became more marked farther down, assuming more and more the characters of an exudation of lymph. The exudation was arranged on the surface of the valvul&#230; conniventes, or in lines parallel to them, for they were quite indistinct, and in some places entirely obliterated; toward the ileoc&#230;cal valve the deposit was yellowish, pultaceous, and resembled the false membrane in diphtheria; just above the ileoc&#230;cal valve, midway between the mesenteric attachment and Peyer's patches, there was an ulcer which had perforated the ileum and communicated with a perforating ulcer in the c&#230;cum; between the two ulcers was a small cavity containing pus, which was bounded by the intestinal walls, the iliac muscle, and a portion of the great omentum, which had become adherent, and appeared to have prevented the extravasation of the intestinal contents into the abdominal cavity. The colon was ulcerated throughout.&#8212;<name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>&#8432;  [Nos. 116 to 118, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  Nos. 116 and 117 are successive portions of the thickened ileum; the mucous membrane is coated with pseudomembrane, and presents a number of ulcers.  In No. 117 the opening of the abscess above described into the ileum is seen. The corresponding portion of the c&#230;cum was, unfortunately, not preserved.  No. 118 is a portion of the colon of the same patient, which is greatly thickened, and coated with pseudomembrane.]</p>
   <p>&#8432; September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief &#34;<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>,&#34; to which the reader is referred.&#8212;(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
