<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19861">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Kahea, K. P.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e19861</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">542-543</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term> 
                                                    <term>operations on the chest</term>
                                                    <term>ligations</term>
                                                    <term>traumatic <choice><orig>aneurism</orig><reg>aneurysm</reg></choice></term>
                                                    <term>circumscribed <choice><orig>aneurism</orig><reg>aneurysm</reg></choice> from gunshot injury</term>
                                                    <term>erysipelas</term>
                                                    <term>severed axillary artery</term>
                                                    <term>pleuritis</term>
                                                    <term>ligations of the subclavian</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                  <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                  <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                  <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 19.— "<name type="person" key="xxx">Private <hi rend="italic">K. P. Kahea</hi></name>,
                                                  <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B, Jeff Davis Legion</name>, aged 29 years, very
                                                  large and muscular, while acting as scout near the
                                                  <name type="battle">Peaks of Otter</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1864-06-14">June 14th, 1864</date>, was shot with
                                                  a minié ball through the left axilla; hæmorrhage
                                                  represented as very profuse, notwithstanding which
                                                  he rode eight miles, closely pursued for three
                                                  miles. He spent several days in a private house,
                                                  and was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="174">Campbell's Hospital</name> on <date type="admit" when="">June
                                                  19th</date>. The ball had passed through the tendons of
                                                  the pectoralis major and latissimus dorsi,
                                                  severing the axillary artery, apparently in its
                                                  lower third; the hæmorrhage had ceased
                                                  spontaneously on the first day and had not
                                                  recurred; pulse imperceptible; very great
                                                  swelling and hardness in the axilla, extending to
                                                  the elbow, with great discoloration from
                                                  ecchymosis; severe pain from shoulder to hand,
                                                  with a sense of numbness, but not complete loss of
                                                  sensation; the capillary circulation but little
                                                  impaired, and temperature normal; when he sat up
                                                  the veins of the forearm became much distended;
                                                  wounds healthy and healing; pulse in the right
                                                  arm feeble and frequent above 100; appetite
                                                  feeble; he slept but little, and then from the
                                                  influence of opium. He continued in the same
                                                  state, with little variation, for three weeks;
                                                  some times we thought that we could feel a faint
                                                  pulsation in the radial artery, but it was so
                                                  slight as to be doubtful. Early in July, while the
                                                  general swelling of the arm diminished, the tumor
                                                  in the axilla was obviously enlarging and
                                                  extending under the pectoral muscle, when, by the
                                                  8th, it became very prominent and as large as the
                                                  fist. On the night of <date type="injury" when="1864-07-10">the 10th</date>, a free arterial
                                                  hæmorrhage took place from the posterior wound;
                                                  after the loss of about a pint of blood, it was
                                                  arrested by pressure, for an hour, upon the
                                                  subclavian above the clavicle, and did not return;
                                                  his pulse very feeble, and above 120; he was very
                                                  much alarmed about his condition, indeed he had
                                                  been unusually low-spirited from the first. On the
                                                  11th, for the first time, a distinct pulsation was
                                                  felt in the tumor, both in the axilla and over the
                                                  pectoral muscle; there was no perceptible thrill
                                                  or bruit; from this time the tumor steadily
                                                  increased in size, and the pulsation daily became
                                                  stronger; there was also increase of the pain and
                                                  numbness in the limb; constant fever and
                                                  sleeplessness, and loss of appetite. It was
                                                  decided, in consultation, to tie the subclavian
                                                  above the clavicle, as affording him the best
                                                  chance of recovery, although his general condition
                                                  was not favorable for an operation. Accordingly on
                                                  <date type="operation" when="1864-07-23">the 23d July</date>, assisted by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Blackford</name> and
                                                  the rest of the surgical staff of this post, I
                                                  ligated the artery where it passes over the first
                                                  rib. The operation was rendered somewhat difficult
                                                  by the unusual number of superficial arteries that
                                                  required to be tied, and by the elevation of the
                                                  clavicle from the tumor in the axilla. The
                                                  pulsation in the tumor immediately ceased, and did
                                                  not return; the swelling became less tense, but
                                                  the pain continued, and the fever increased; the
                                                  capillary circulation in the limb continued good,
                                                  and its temperature appeared to be little, if at
                                                  all, diminished (we had no thermometer to test it
                                                  accurately), for a few days he seemed doing pretty
                                                  well, but on <date type="injury" when="1864-07-26">the 26th</date>, the incision presented an
                                                  unhealthy appearance, with a slight erysipelatous
                                                  blush and some swelling below the clavicle. By the
                                                  28th, the shoulder and breast became enormously
                                                  swollen, so as completely to conceal the
                                                  <choice><orig>aneurismal</orig><reg>aneurysmal</reg></choice> tumor. On the next day there was
                                                  extensive erysipelas on the outside and back of
                                                  shoulder, which spread rapidly over the breast and
                                                  down the arm to the elbow; the incision
                                                  suppurating and unhealthy. On the same day, he was
                                                  seized with a severe pleuritic pain on the left
                                                  side, and great difficulty of breathing, but
                                                  without cough; the respiratory motion was
                                                  confined so exclusively to the right side, that
                                                  the left seemed paralyzed, and was obviously
                                                  several inches smaller than the right side,
                                                  although auscultation showed the presence of
                                                  effusion in the left thorax; bowels torpid and
                                                  tympanitic; pulse 150, and very feeble. July 30th:
                                                  No improvement in his condition, although the pain
                                                  in the side had nearly ceased. July 31st:
                                                  Prostration extreme; respiration more difficult;
                                                  died soon <date type="death" when="1864-08-01">after midnight</date>.  Autopsy: Axillary
                                                  artery and vein both severed by the ball in their
                                                  lower third; the axilla filled with a large clot
                                                  extending to within three inches of the elbow and
                                                  considerably beneath the pectoralis major. The
                                                  coagulum was moderately firm, and contained in a
                                                  thin adventitious sac of cellular tissue, but
                                                  without any fibrinous deposit. The median nerve
                                                  had escaped division, but was very much
                                                  discolored, as were also the other nerves in the
                                                  axilla. The artery, where ligated, had united, but
                                                  not very firmly; no clot had formed within it,
                                                  owing, probably, to the fact that the posterior
                                                  scapular artery, instead of being a branch from
                                                  the transversalis colli, arose directly from the
                                                  subclavian, between the scaleni, and about
                                                  two-thirds of an inch above the point of ligation;
                                                  this would, probably, have led to secondary
                                                  hæmorrhage after the separation of the ligature.
                                                  There was a large serous effusion in the left side
                                                  of the thorax, with a deposit of a thick layer of
                                                  fibrin over a large surface of the lung; phrenic
                                                  nerve healthy. There was also slight deposit in
                                                  the pericardium, and some effusion. The only
                                                  treatment that was admissible after the operation
                                                  was morphine, stimulants, and tinct. mur. ferri.
                                                  It would, probably, have been better to have tied
                                                  the subclavian soon after his admission, when his
                                                  general health was less impaired. But would the
                                                  rules of surgery have justified the ligation of a
                                                  large artery when there was no hæmorrhage and no
                                                  pulsation in the tumor? The axillary swelling and
                                                  absence of pulse at the wrist afforded strong
                                                  presumptive evidence that the artery was divided,
                                                  but we could not be sure that the absence of pulse
                                                  was not owing to the pressure of the tumor, which
                                                  might have arisen from the division of a branch of
                                                  the axillary, and if so we might reasonably hope
                                                  that in time it would be absorbed and the
                                                  circulation restored. It was not until the tumor
                                                  began to increase in size, with distinct
                                                  pulsation, that we felt satisfied that an
                                                  operation was indispensable, and our choice then
                                                  lay between disarticulation and ligature of the
                                                  subclavian—the ligature of the axillary in the
                                                  midst of such swelling and altered
                                                  relation of parts was out of the question. We
                                                  decided upon the ligation of the artery as being
                                                  sanctioned by the highest authority; the more
                                                  especially as his constitutional condition almost
                                                  forbade the hope of successful amputation. I would
                                                  suggest that, in a similar case, where the
                                                  posterior scapular arose directly from the
                                                  subclavian, it would be proper to tie it, as well
                                                  as the main artery; in this case it could have
                                                  been done without difficulty, as it could be
                                                  plainly seen and felt where it crossed the
                                                  cervical plexus. The other branches of the
                                                  transversus colli and the supra-scapular would
                                                  probably be sufficient to supply the anastomosing
                                                  circulation. The immediate cause of death in this
                                                  case was pleuritis, which has been observed to be
                                                  far the most frequent cause of death after
                                                  ligation of the subclavian. The erysipelas, to
                                                  which there has latterly been some tendency in
                                                  this neighborhood, no doubt also contributed to
                                                  the fatal termination."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Wm. Selden</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">P. A. C. S.</name>, reported the case.¹ </p>
                                  
                                  <p> ¹ <hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ELDEN, <hi rend="initialcap">W</hi>., <hi rend="italic">Confederate States Medical and Surgical Journal</hi>, Vol. I, No. 9, p. 134, September, <choice><sic>1804</sic><corr>1864</corr></choice>. </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
