<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e13655">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Riley, Peter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e13655</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">307</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the upper third of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>fatal cases of secondary amputations in the upper third of the thigh</term>
     <term>amputation performed twenty-two months after injury, wound reopened, femur protruded
      through fistulous passage</term>
     <term>gunshot fracture of thigh, upper third</term>
     <term>gunshot fracture of femur</term>
     <term>ball entered anterior surface of thigh below anterior superior spinous process of ilium,
      produced compound comminuted fracture of upper third of femur, lodged in muscular substance of
      thigh posteriorly</term>
     <term>ball entered inner aspect of thigh, fractured femur opposite great trochanter</term>
     <term>limb distorted and marked with fistulous passages, from one lower portion of femur
      protrudes</term>
     <term>py&#230;mia</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 480.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1100">Private P.
     Riley</name>, <name type="organization" key="235">Co. A, 10th New York</name>, aged 24 years,
    was wounded at <name type="person" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date type="injury"
     when="1864-06-03">June 3, 1864</date>, and admitted to the field hospital of the 2d division,
    Second Corps. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon J. F. Dyer</name>, <name type="organization"
     key="386">19th Massachusetts</name>, recorded: "Gunshot fracture of left thigh, upper third."
     <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. C. McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190"
     >U. S. A.</name>, contributed a photograph, which is shown in the wood-cut (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 199), and reported as follows: "Admitted to <name type="hospital"
     key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-06-11">June
     11th</date>, with a gunshot fracture of the left femur, the ball entering the anterior surface
    of the thigh four inches below the anterior superior spinous process of ilium, passing directly
    backward, producing a compound comminuted fracture of the upper third of the femur, and lodging
    in the muscular substance of the thigh posteriorly. Extension and counter-extension were used,
    but removed on account of the inflammation of the parts and the severe pain produced. Three
    weeks after admission free incisions were made for the discharge of pus. The patient slowly
    recovered, with four and a half inches shortening of the limb." He was mustered out of service
     <date type="discharge" when="1865-08-01">August 1, 1865</date>, and pensioned. A cast of the
    injured limb in this case was also contributed by <name type="person" key="243">Dr.
    McKee</name>, and constitutes specimen 4051 of the Surgical Section of <name type="hospital"
     key="431">the Museum</name>. (See <hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1866, p. 535.) <name
     type="person" key="200">Examiner W. H. Thomson</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">New York
     City</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1866-01-22">January 22, 1866</date>: "A ball
    entered the inner aspect of the left thigh and fractured the femur opposite the great
    trochanter. The limb is now much distorted and marked with fistulous passages, from one of
    which, at the anterior upper third of the limb, the end of the lower portion of the femur
    protrudes. He should not have been discharged from hospital in that condition." <name
     type="person" key="xx">Dr. M. M. Marsh</name>, Surgeon at the Lincoln Hospital, <name
     type="place">New York City</name>, certified: "That in the month of <date type="operation"
     when="1866-04">April, 1866</date>, <name type="person" key="1100">Peter Riley</name> came into
    the hospital for an operation on a shattered femur in its upper third, the lower fragment of
    bone protruding. Amputation was performed, and the patient died of py&#230;mia <date
     type="death" when="1866-05-07">May 7, 1866</date>, and in consequence of the injury received in
    the service as the remote cause." (See <hi rend="italic">Photo. Series</hi>, A. M. M., No.
    117.)</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001599.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 199.&#8212;Appearance of limb a year after injury. [From a
     photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
