<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e19163">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Taylor, G. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e19163</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">480</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>fatal primary amputations in the middle third of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>ball entered inner edge of middle of tibia, comminuted bone above and below, made two
      openings of exit on anterior and outer aspect of leg above external malleolus</term>
     <term>limb amputated at middle third, considerable blood lost, all vessels requiring
      ligation</term>
     <term>morbific influence of malaria</term>
     <term>fibula not broken by ball, fractured by supporting weight of patient after tibia
      fractured</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-07">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 738.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Brigadier General G.
     W. Taylor</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, was wounded in the left
    leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-27"
     >August 27, 1862</date>. The character of the injury and its result was reported by <name
     type="person" key="288">Assistant Surgeon <choice>
      <sic>J. B. Brinton</sic>
      <corr>J. H. Brinton</corr>
     </choice></name>, <name type="organization" key="132"><choice>
      <sic>U. S. A.</sic>
      <corr>U. S. V.</corr>
     </choice></name>, as follows: &#34;A ball entered at the inner edge of the tibia, about six
    inches above the internal malleolus, passed directly through and comminuted the bone very badly
    for about six inches above and below, making two openings of exit on the anterior and outer
    aspect of the leg about five inches above the external malleolus. The patient was admitted into
    the <name type="hospital" key="185">Mansion House Hospital</name>, <name type="place"
     >Alexandria</name>, <date type="operation" when="1862-08-27">thirteen hours after the reception
     of the injury</date>, where <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, amputated the limb by the double flap method at
    the middle third. The operation was performed <date type="operation" when="1862-08-28"
     >twenty-six hours after the reception of the injury</date>, the patient losing considerable
    blood and all the vessels requiring ligation. He had been with the army through the Peninsular
    campaign and his blood appeared to be very much vitiated by morbific influence of malaria. After
    the amputation it was discovered, what was previously suspected, that the fibula was not broken
    by the force of the ball, but by the weight of the patient coining upon it suddenly when the
    support from the tibia was destroyed by its fracture. The patient's arterial system did not
    fully react; his pulse, which was feeble, tremulous, and very irregular at times, evidently
    denoted a depraved condition of the system. He refused to take stimulants except sparingly. This
    condition continued until <date type="death" when="1862-09-01">September 1, 1862</date>, when he
    died at 4 o'clock A. M. He was under the influence of chloroform during the operation.&#34; The
    amputated parts of the tibia and fibula (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 313, <hi rend="italic"
     >Surg. Sect.</hi>, A. M. M.), represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
    289), were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name
     type="person" key="288">the operator</name>.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001635.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 289.&#8212;Left tibia fractured by a musket ball; fibula
     fractured by the subject's weight suddenly coming upon it.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>.
     313.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
