<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e8889">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Donohue, Frank</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e8889</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">383</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>   
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>complete deafness</term>    
                                        <term>both lungs had blackish-brown fluid, which also filled the bronchi</term>
                                        <term>aorta somewhat contracted and deeply congested</term>
                                        <term>cicatrix-like puckering with surrounding congestion in aorta beyond semilunar valves</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of upper small intestine presented ulcers in Peyer's patches</term>
                                        <term>lower small intestine had ragged excoriating ulcers, did not involve Peyer's patches</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of large intestine had ulcers on ileo-cæcal valve and in cæcum</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00165">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 165.—<name type="person" key="699">Sergeant Frank
                                                Donohue</name>, <name type="organization" key="693">Co. A, 17th Pa. Cav.</name>, was admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-19">Feb. 19, 1863</date>,
                                        having been sick <date type="injury" when="1862-12">for two months</date> with typhoid fever. He was
                                        completely deaf.  On March 1 he had sore throat, severe
                                        headache and constipation.  On the 15th his stomach became
                                        irritable and there was soreness in the bowels with
                                        diarrhœa. Later the stools became dark-looking but
                                        less frequent.  He died on <date type="death" when="1863-03-25">the 25th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-03-27">forty-eight hours after death</date>: Body well developed and not emaciated. The
                                        right lung weighed sixteen ounces and a half and the left
                                        twenty-one ounces and a quarter; posteriorly the lower lobe
                                        of the right lung was full of blackish-brown fluid, which
                                        also filled the bronchi; similar appearances were found in
                                        spots in the left lung. The heart weighed nine ounces and
                                        contained no clots; the aorta was somewhat contracted,
                                        deeply congested, and three inches beyond the semilunar
                                        valves was a cicatrix-like puckering with intense
                                        surrounding congestion. The liver was pale and weighed
                                        fifty-eight ounces and a half; the spleen soft, reddened,
                                        weighed twelve ounces and a half; the pancreas natural,
                                        three ounces and three-quarters; the stomach healthy. The
                                        mucous membrane of the upper part of the small intestine was
                                        yellowish and presented several roundish ulcers with
                                        well-defined edges in Peyer's patches and one patch, a half
                                        inch in diameter, enlarged and indurated; lower down the
                                        ulcers were more ragged and apparently did not involve
                                        Peyer's patches; in the last fifteen inches of the ileum the
                                        mucous membrane was of a reddish-slate color, the solitary
                                        glands brownish, and there were ragged excoriating ulcers in
                                        many of which was a thick yellowish exudation. The mucous
                                        membrane of the large intestine was of a dull slate color,
                                        presenting one ulcer on the ileo-cæcal valve, one
                                        at the commencement of the cæcum and a third four
                                        inches beyond. The kidneys were flabby and much
                                                congested.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. Harrison
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
