<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3485">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">H——, Charles</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e3485</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">57-58</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>miscellaneous injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>trephining</term>
                    <term>found lying in street in comatose condition</term>
                    <term/>
                    <term/>
                    <term>detached pieces removed by elevator</term>
                    <term>parietal bone fractured and depressed</term>
                    <term>incised and puncture wounds</term>
                    <term>abscess in right hemisphere and neighboring brain substance</term>
                    <term>punctured wound of lower parietal area</term>
                    <term>autopsy performed</term>
                    <term>abscess in hemisphere of brain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-09">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-06-10">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding,
                edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc2.0023">
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="248"> Private Charles
                    H——</name>, <name type="organization" key="174">Co. G, 61st Ohio
                    Volunteers</name>, aged 37 years, was found lying in the street, at <name type="place">Alexandria, Virginia</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1863-09-27">September 27th, 1863</date>, in a comatose condition, with a
                wound on the right side of his head. He was conveyed to the <name type="hospital" key="198">New Hallowell branch of the 3d Division General Hospital</name>, by
                the provost guard. On admission his breathing was stertorous, laborious, slow; his
                pulse was at 48, full and regular. There was a punctured wound over the lower
                portion of the right parietal, and an examination by the probe showed that the bone
                was fractured and depressed. A <date type="operation" when="1863-09-27">crucial
                    incision</date> was made through the scalp, and the cranium being freely
                exposed, it was found that the fracture was much more extensive than had been
                supposed. A disk of bone was removed by the trephine, and several detached pieces
                were removed by the elevator, so that, altogether, a portion four inches in length
                by two inches in width of the skull-cap was taken away. The flaps of the integument
                were then brought together and were united by sutures. Cold water dressings were
                applied. The immediate effects of the operation were very remarkable. In less than
                three minutes after the removal of the depressed fragments, the patient opened his
                eyes, and appeared to awake to consciousness, and in less than a minute more he
                spoke, articulating distinctly. For the first week after the operation his diet was
                restricted to barley water. On October 4th, seven days after the operation, he was
                reported to have had no bad symptom and he complained of nothing but hunger. The
                sutures had been removed, and the greater portion of the incision had united by
                first intention. He was now allowed the "extra diet" of the hospital, consisting of
                oyster broth, rice pudding, and the like. On October 20th, the patient was up and
                about the ward. No untoward symptoms had intervened meanwhile, and the treatment had
                been unchanged. At this date the patient was put on "half diet," and the nearly
                cicatrized wound was dressed with simple cerate. He continued to do well until <choice>
                    <orig>November</orig>
                    <reg>October</reg>
                </choice> 26th when he was visited by his brother, who brought him some bad news
                from home which disturbed him very much, and he immediately went to bed and became
                stupid and sullen, taking no notice of anything. Is it not possible that his brother
                brought him some stimulant as well? On October 27th the patient had become comatose,
                with every sign of compression of the brain, and on <date type="death" when="1863-10-26">October 28th, 1863</date>, he died. At the autopsy, <date type="autopsy" when="1863-10-27">twenty hours after death</date>, there was
                found to be an abscess in the right hemisphere and the neighboring brain substance
                was softened. The thoracic and abdominal viscera were healthy. The edges of the
                aperture were found to be rounded off and in process of repair. The notes from which
                the abstract is compiled were made by <name type="person" key="249">Acting Assistant
                    Surgeon S. B. Ward</name>, and the specimen was forwarded to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
                    V.</name> It is represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 22)
                on the preceding page. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001359.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 22.—Section of cranium with great loss
                    of substance from the removal of depressed fragments.—<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2673. Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
            </figure>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
