<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e1019">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Soistman, L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e1019</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">22</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>shot flesh wounds</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower limbs unattended by primary injury of the large nerves or blood-vessels</term>
     <term>lodgement of missiles in soft parts</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>shell entered thigh at middle of upper third, under deep fascia, under femoral artery</term>
     <term>piece of shell lodged in thigh sixty-six days</term> 
     <term>leg weak from disorganization of great muscles of thigh</term>
     <term>loss of muscular tissue, partial loss of power in limb</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p>  <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 35.&#8212;<name type="person" key="882">Lieutenant L.
      Soistman</name>, <name type="organization" key="209">Co. H, 98th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 23
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="258">Salem Heights</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>. <date type="admit" when="1863-05-06">Three days afterwards</date> he entered the <name
      type="hospital" key="174">Campbell Hospital</name>, Washington, where he obtained a leave of
     absence on <date type="furlough" when="1863-05-19">May 19th</date>. On <date type="admit" when="1863-07-08">July 8th</date>, he was admitted
     to the Officers' Hospital, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, where <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon W. Cammac</name> recorded the following
     history: &#34;A piece of shell entered the right thigh at the most depending inner part of the
     middle of the upper third, went under the deep fascia, and upward under the femoral artery and
     buried itself. The missile appears not to have been noticed at first, as the wound was sewed
     up. After going to his home in Philadelphia he was attended by a private physician, but the
     missile remained still undiscovered. On July 8th, <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant
      Surgeon W. Hunt</name> was called in, who was struck by the peculiar feel, and on introducing
     a probe immediately found the foreign body, and ordered the patient to the hospital to have it
     removed. On <date type="operation" when="1863-07-09">July 9th</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Hunt</name> enlarged the wound, and,
     after considerable trouble from the proximity of the large vessels, removed, with the
     assistance of the forceps, a piece of shell weighing nine ounces, which had lodged in the thigh
     sixty-six days. Its presence had given rise to no great disorganization, but he complained, he
     says, of a weight in the part during the whole time. After recovery from the effects of the
     ether, a half grain of sulphate of morphia was given. Cerate dressings and light pressure were
     applied, and the wound drawn together with adhesive straps. The patient's general health was
     excellent. He did remarkably well and felt greatly relieved by the operation. On July 13th,
     cataplasms were ordered, the wound looking well and suppurating moderately, and the patient
     having better appetite than any time since wounded. On September 5th he was attacked with
     intermittent fever, which was checked after several days by quinine. By October 1st the wound
     had nearly healed, but the leg was still weak from extensive disorganization of the great
     muscles of the thigh. On <date type="duty" when="1863-11-09">November 9, 1863</date>, he was
     returned to duty.&#34; This officer was again wounded, at the battle of the <name type="BATTLE"
      key="259">Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>, in the
     right side, for which injury he was treated in hospitals at <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> and <date type="place">Annapolis</date>. On
     <date type="duty" when="1864-08-02">August 2, 1864</date>, he was again returned to duty, and on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-10-13"
      >October 13, 1864</date>, he was mustered out of service. The <name type="organization"
       key="xx">Philadelphia Examining Board</name> certified, <date type="pension" when="1870-10-19">October 19, 1870</date>:   &#42;  &#42;  &#34;A deep flesh wound,
     which, in healing, caused a cicatrix about five inches long and four inches wide, with loss of
     portion of muscular tissue, causing partial loss of power in the limb upon making much
     exertion,&#34; etc. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1876-03-04">March 4, 1876</date>.  </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
