<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40978">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Northrup, Alpheus D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40978</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">157-158</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>both lungs full of blood, tubercles in right upper lobe</term>
       <term>atelectasis and consolidated lobules in left lower lobe</term>
       <term>congestion resembling ecchymosis in lower jejunum</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of ileum thin and easily scraped off</term>
       <term>numerous irregular, nearly circular ulcers of mucous membrane of lower large intestine</term>
       <term>rectum dark-colored, presented numerous black spots in which were ulcers</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-30">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 336.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Alpheus D. Northrup</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company G, 37th Massachusetts volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-01-02">January 2, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-01-28">January 28th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-01-28">ten hours after death</date>: Height five feet ten inches; body greatly emaciated; the blood was fluid. The brain weighed forty-three ounces; it was of a light color and firm consistence; there were firm pleuritic adhesions on both sides. Both lungs were quite full of blood; the right lung weighed seventeen ounces and a half; there was a slight deposit of tubercles in its upper lobe; the surrounding lung-tissue was tough and partially solidified; the inferior lobe was intensely congested and partly hepatized; portions sank in water. The left lung weighed thirteen ounces and a half the posterior part of its lower lobe was in a state of atelectasis, and several of the lobules were consolidated. The heart weighed five ounces and a half; its substance was very flabby and of a deep-red color; the left auricle contained a small fibrinous clot; the other cavities were empty; the pericardium contained half an ounce of clear serum. The liver weighed thirty-five ounces and a half; it was full of blood, rather soft, and faintly mottled; the gall-bladder was small and filled with dark viscid bile. The spleen weighed three ounces and three-quarters; it was decidedly tough. The pancreas weighed two ounces. The right kidney was pale, and weighed three ounces and a quarter; the left kidney weighed four ounces and a quarter; the base of its pyramids was congested. The mucous membrane of the stomach was thin. There were several patches of congestion, almost resembling ecchymosis, in the lower portion of the jejunum; its mucous membrane was thin; in the upper part of the ileum the mucous membrane was thin and easily scraped off. On the mucous membrane of the upper part of the large intestine there were patches of a whitish exudation, which, farther down, covered the whole surface; still lower down there were numerous irregular, nearly circular, ulcers, surrounded by zones of white granular matter; the rectum was dark-colored, and presented numerous black spots in which were other ulcers; the adjacent surface was frosted with granules of white fibrinous matter.&#8212;<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
