<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e6395">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Tomlinson, Silas</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e6395</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>                                        
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">343</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>condition of Peyer's patches not stated, ileum or small intestine ulcerated</term>  
                                        <term>deafness</term>                                        
                                        <term>small intestine perforated</term>
                                        <term>Liquid fæces escaped into pelvic cavity</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00045">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 45.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Silas Tomlinson</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 24th
                                                Mich.</name>, was admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-11-30">Nov. 30, 1864</date>. The patient
                                        had been sick for some time in hospital at City Point, Va.;
                                        he suffered much and received but little attention during
                                        his journey to Alexandria. On admission: Pulse weak,
                                        thread-like and from 90 to 100 per minute; skin hot and dry;
                                        tongue very dry, red and slightly coated; thirst urgent;
                                        appetite small; epistaxis; deafness; expression stupid;
                                        delirium; abdomen generally tender, tympanitic and showing a
                                        few sudamina and many petechial spots. December 1: No
                                        change. 2d: Pulse somewhat stronger, fuller and less
                                        frequent; tongue less dry; expression of countenance
                                        brighter and hearing improved; diarrhœa less
                                        active, but tenderness and tympanites of the abdomen
                                        unchanged. 3d: Pulse 80 and decidedly stronger;
                                        diarrhœa checked; tongue throwing off its fur;
                                        appetite improved; patient intelligent. 4th: The favorable
                                        symptoms continued; tenderness of the abdomen lessened. <date type="death" when="1864-12-05">5th</date>:
                                        At 2 A. M. a change for the worse took place; the pulse
                                        became weak and ran up to 100; the patient had slight
                                        chills; his tongue became dry and red and sordes gathered on
                                        his teeth, gums and lips, while the whole surface was bathed
                                        in a cold clammy sweat; petechial spots assumed the
                                        appearance of purplish blotches, and the abdomen became
                                        exceedingly tender, swollen and tympanitic. Ten hours after
                                        this change took place the patient had several involuntary
                                        stools of a dark-greenish color, after which he fell into a
                                        semi-stupor from which he could with difficulty be aroused,
                                        and when aroused gave imperfect answers to questions
                                        proposed; his face was sunken and there was much twitching
                                        of the muscles of the upper extremities. He died on this
                                        day. <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination
                                        twenty-three hours after death: A few purple-colored points,
                                        said to be of ante-mortem formation, were noticed on the
                                        chest and abdomen; there was also purple hypostasis of the
                                        posterior part of the body. There was a quantity of fluid
                                        under the arachnoid at the vertex of the brain, but the
                                        substance of the brain was normal. The heart was dilated on
                                        its right side and almost completely filled by a large
                                        semi-transparent clot. The left lung was crepitant, although
                                        somewhat dark colored posteriorly. The right lung was
                                        closely adherent by firm tissue and apparently compressed or
                                        drawn over to the right side; the posterior part of its
                                        upper lobe was of a dark brown-red color, softened and with
                                        minute points, apparently bronchi, filled with a yellow
                                        froth; the remainder of the lung was normal. The liver was
                                        large and of a uniformly pale clay color; the spleen large
                                        and softened; the cortical part of the left kidney of a
                                        yellow, semi-fatty appearance. About twelve inches from the
                                        colon the small intestine was perforated by a black-margined
                                        aperture the size of a small shot; recent lymph glued the
                                        perforated coil of the ileum to the bladder and sigmoid
                                        flexure. Liquid fæces of a yellow color had to a
                                        small extent escaped into the pelvic cavity.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="xxx">Act.
                                                  Ass't Surg. W. C. Minor</name>, <name type="hospital" key="xxx">General Hospital,
                                                          Alexandria, Va.</name></hi>
                                </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
