<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9622">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">O'Conner, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9622</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">196, 198</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the lower third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>successful cases of shot fractures of the lower third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>necrosis of bone</term>
     <term>sciatic nerve injured</term> 
     <term>veins in varicose condition</term>
     <term>ball entered external thigh three inches above patella, fractured shaft of femur through upper end of lower third, exit posteriorly</term>        
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-29">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 403.—<name type="person" key="1056">Private J.
      O'Conner</name>, <name type="organization" key="357">Co. F, 16th Michigan</name>, aged 16
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-02">June 2, 1864</date>. He reached the Fifth Corps Hospital at <name type="place">White House</name> <date type="admit" when="1864-06-05">three days after the injury</date>, and was thence conveyed to
     <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where he entered the <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>
     <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-10">June 10th</date>. <name type="person" key="424">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. K. Smith</name> made the following report of the case: "A minié ball
     entered the external aspect of the left thigh three inches above the patella, and, passing
     obliquely inward and upward, fractured the shaft of the femur through the upper end of the
     lower third, making its exit posteriorly. The patient was treated by <name type="person" key="271">Acting Assistant Surgeon T. O. Bannister</name>. Hodgen's splint was used, and no extension
     was applied other than the tying of the foot to the foot-board with a bandage. During the
     treatment eight small fragments of bone were removed. On <date type="duty" when="1864-12-27">December 27th</date> the patient, though his
     wound had not entirely healed, was transferred to the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve Corps</name> and placed on guard duty; but being unable to perform it, he was
     readmitted to the hospital for treatment several weeks afterwards. He came under my care on
     June 22, 1865, at which time he was in good health, but slightly lame and able to walk without
     a cane. There was still a slight discharge of sero-purulent fluid from the wound. The limb was
     shortened one and one-fourth inches, and, at the seat of the fracture, it was a little larger
     than normal but not otherwise deformed. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-18">July 18,
      1865</date>, the patient was mustered out of service, with his wound still open." <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner W. G. Wilkinson</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Farwell, Michigan</name>, <date type="pension" when="1876-05-16">May 16, 1876</date>, certified to the wound, and stated: "The fracture has
     been followed by necrosis of bone, several pieces having been removed during the year 1875. The
     sciatic nerve was injured, and the veins are in a varicose condition. The wound has continued
     open." The pensioner was paid June 4, 1879. His photograph, taken at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> in June, 1865 (<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>,
     No. 49, A. M. M.), is copied in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE LXIV, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 2, opp. p. 198.</p>
    
   <figure> 
    <graphic url="cww.001810.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  LXIV. — CONSOLIDATED  GUNSHOT  FRACTURES  OF  THE  FEMUR.   Fig 2.  Case of <name type="person" key="1056">Private J. O'Connor</name>  <name type="organization" key="357">16th Michigan</name></head> 
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
