<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3276">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Dickerson, John</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e3276</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">231</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>clinical records</term>
          <term>continued fevers</term>
          <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
          <term>typhoid fever</term>
          <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
          <term>mental dullness</term> 
          <term>rose-spots</term>
          <term>bowel affection slightly marked</term> 
          <term> umbilical tenderness</term> 
          <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00063">
      
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 63.—<hi rend="italic">Mental <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice>;
            rose-spots on the 9th day, disappearing on the 16th; bowel affection slightly
            marked.</hi>—<name type="person" key="521">Private John Dickerson</name>,
            <name type="organization" key="622">Co. A, 4th Mich.</name>; age 21; was taken about
          <date type="injury" when="1861-09-09"/>Sept. 9, 1861, with pain in the bones, back and head, fever which was said to be worst at
          noon, and diarrhœa. He was admitted on the <date type="admit" when="1861-09-16">16th</date>. Diagnosis—typhoid fever. In the evening the fever was slight;
          pulse 71; skin warm and dry; face flushed; tongue red at the edges, coated yellowish at
          the base and in the middle, moist and with prominent papillæ; a bitter taste was
          felt in the mouth; one stool was passed during the day, and there was some umbilical
          tenderness. Two grains each of calomel and jalap were given. Next day the pulse was 70 and
          small; the skin dry; the tongue dry, heavily coated and brownish; the cheeks flushed; the
          patient was weak and dull; his bowels had been moved once; a few characteristic rose-spots
          were seen. Quinine was ordered. During the next week there was little change in the
          patient's condition; his eyes were injected and half closed and he was dull and drowsy,
          answering questions in a low tone; the face was flushed and the skin hot, dry, husky and
          profusely spotted with the rose-colored eruption; the tongue, heavily coated and brown,
          became moist on the 19th; the bowels quiet and neither tender nor tympanitic; there was
          some headache with dizziness at this time. On the 22d the patient was dull; his pulse 80
          and feeble; face flushed; skin hot, moist and spotted; tongue red at tip and gray in
          centre; he vomited once during the day and had one stool. Next day the pulse was 82 and
          weak, the eyes suffused, the skin warm and moist, the tongue gray in the centre and red at
          the tip, the bowels quiet and not tender. On the 24th the pulse was 78, the skin warm and
          soft, the tongue moist and slightly coated gray, the appetite good. Wine was occasionally
          given. He was returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1861-10-24">October 24</date>. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
