<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6259">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Carroll, Lewis</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6259</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">139</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the hip joint</term>
     <term>coxo-femoral amputations</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations</term>
     <term>ball entered thigh in front, striking femur at junction of upper thirds</term>
     <term>longitudinal splintering of femur, extending below lesser trochanter downward, several
      oblique fissures</term>
     <term>pus in external iliac vein and lungs</term>
     <term>gangrenous abscess in spleen</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>h&#230;morrhage from small artery of thigh</term>
     <term>soft tissues of thigh infiltrated with pus</term>
     <term>amputation preceded by primary partial excision of shaft of femur</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-22">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 298.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant Lewis
     Carroll</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. H, 1st Delaware</name>, aged 23 years,
    was wounded on <date type="injury" when="1864-10-22">October 22, 1864</date>, near the <name
     type="place">Weldon Railroad</name>.&#179; A conoidal musket ball entered the right thigh in
    front, and, striking the femur at the junction of the upper thirds, produced a remarkable
    longitudinal splintering of the bone, extending from an inch below the lesser trochanter
    downward for ten inches, together with several oblique fissures. The wounded man was conveyed in
    an ambulance to one of the field hospitals of the Fifth Corps, where the ball was extracted and
    the sharp extremity of the upper fragment of the femur was sawn off. The fractured limb was then
    dressed, and the patient sent to <name type="place">City Point</name>, and thence on a hospital
    steamer to <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, where he was admitted to the <name
     type="hospital" key="512">Third Division Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer"
     when="1864-11-02">November 2d</date>. The thigh was swollen to three times the size of its
    fellow. An incision six inches long on the outer side presented inflamed everted edges, between
    which fasciculi of muscles protruded. There was much febrile irritation, but the patient's
    strength was maintained to a remarkable degree. On <date type="operation" when="1864-11-11"
     >November 11th</date>, there was quite free h&#230;morrhage from a small artery, and the
    patient was etherized and the vessel secured, and afterward a thorough exploration of the wound
    was made. The very extensive longitudinal splintering was recognized; the bone was found denuded
    in several places; the soft tissues of the thigh were infiltrated with pus of a very offensive
    character. In view of this condition of things, it was determined to remove the limb at the hip
    joint. The patient was placed under the influence of chloroform, and the operation was performed
    by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization"
     key="132">U. S. V.</name> An external flap was made by cutting from without inward; then the
    head of the femur was disarticulated, and an internal flap was cut from within outward. The loss
    of blood was slight and the patient reacted promptly. The progress of the case for two or three
    days after the operation was very favorable. Then a chill occurred, followed by a cold clammy
    sweat. The wound looked badly and the discharge was unhealthy; the stump was kept covered with
    yeast poultices. Beef essence, stimulants, and anodynes were administered. Six days after the
    operation there was yellowness of the surface and of the conjunctival membranes; then delirium
    and coma, and death on <date type="death" when="1864-11-19">November 19th</date>, eight days
    from the date of the operation. At the autopsy, pus was found in the external iliac vein,
    metastatic foci in the lungs, and a gangrenous abscess in the enlarged spleen. The preparation
    of the femur was sent to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, and is
    figured in the adjacent wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 94). </p>

   <p> &#179; See <hi rend="italic">Circ</hi>. No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 50, <hi rend="initialcap"
     >C</hi>ASE 18, and <hi rend="italic">Circ</hi>. 7, S. G. O., 1867, <hi rend="initialcap"
    >C</hi>ASE XXXVI, pp. 38 and 62, and <hi rend="italic">Cat. of Surg. Sect.</hi>, of 1866, p.
    247. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001545.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 94.&#8212;Right fem. fissured by a musket ball. <hi
      rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1020.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
