<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41233">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Chipman, J. F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41233</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">180</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of back of left hand</term>
       <term>purpura and exhaustion</term>
       <term>ulcer on side of larynx penetrated through mucous membrane to hyoid bone, bone roughened as if carious</term>
       <term>lower lobes of both lungs much congested, large amount of rust-colored frothy fluid exuded on section</term>
       <term>skin of abdomen studded with spots, resembled gunpowder deposited beneath integument</term>
       <term>straw-colored fluid in abdominal cavity, deposit of lymph on peritoneum</term>
       <term>liver an&#230;mic, acini not well marked</term>
       <term>old ulcers in ileum, many penetrated to muscular coat</term>
       <term>large intestine studded with ulcers resembling those in ileum</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 409.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. F. Chipman</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 36th Wisconsin volunteers</name>; age 36; admitted from the <name type="organization" key="377">army of the Potomac</name> <date type="admit" when="1864-08-30">August 30, 1864</date>.  Gunshot wound of the back of the left hand.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-10-17">October 17th</date>, of purpura and exhaustion.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-10-18">next day</date>: Height five feet eight inches; no rigor mortis; body very much emaciated. The brain appeared to be normal, and weighed forty-seven ounces and a half. On the left side of the larynx was an ulcer which penetrated through the mucous membrane to the hyoid bone, which was roughened as if carious. The lower lobes of both lungs were very much congested, and on section a large amount of frothy fluid of a rust-color exuded, but no part of the lobes would sink in water; the remaining lobes were normal; the right lung weighed sixteen ounces and a half, the left fifteen and a half. The heart and its valves were normal; it weighed eight ounces and a half; its right cavities were filled with a large dark clot; the left auricle contained a medium-sized black clot, the left ventricle a small vermiform one. The skin of the abdomen was studded with spots about a line in diameter, which resembled those seen when gunpowder has been deposited beneath the integument; there was quite a large amount of straw-colored fluid in the abdominal cavity, and a deposit of lymph on the peritoneum. The liver weighed thirty-eight ounces; it was of a dull slate-color externally, and on section appeared to be an&#230;mic; its acini were not well marked; the gall-bladder contained twelve drachms of bile. The spleen weighed seven ounces. The right kidney was normal and weighed three ounces and a half, the left four ounces; the cortical substance of the left kidney was dark colored. The stomach appeared to be normal. The mucous membrane of the small intestine was very much congested, and in the ileum there were quite a number of old ulcers, many of which penetrated to the muscular coat. The large intestine was studded with ulcers resembling those seen in the ileum.&#8212;<name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
