<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41918">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Kelcher, Thomas</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41918</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">513, 520</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>morbid anatomy</term>
     <term>chronic inflammation of the mucous and submucous coats of the intestines without
      ulceration</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>gunshot fracture of thigh</term>
     <term>ball entered external surface of thigh at junction of middle and lower thirds, passed
      transversely inward, comminuted femur, and exited internal surface opposite wound of
      entrance</term>
     <term>comminuted fracture of femur</term>
     <term>abscess at lower border of popliteal space, caused by pressure of splint on posterior
      surface of thigh</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>appearance of gangrene</term>
     <term>pleurisy</term>
     <term>apex of each lung studded with tubercles</term>
     <term>numerous ulcers of mucous membrane of large intestine</term>
     <term>cysts of descending colon contained lymph, some appeared undergoing ulceration, others
      already perforated and filled with pus</term>
     <term>ruptured cysts resembled follicular ulcers</term>
     <term>observed with microscope delicate nucleated cells resembling white corpuscles of
      blood</term>
     <term>acute catarrhal dysentery, passed into chronic flux</term>
     <term>colon presented cysts containing jelly-like substance</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and
    added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>A very similar specimen to that just described is represented in the plate facing page 514,
    which is reproduced from a photograph of No. 602, Medical Section, and represents the specimen
    after it had been preserved in alcohol for some time. The following history of the case was
    furnished by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon George K. Smith</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 900.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Thomas
     Kelcher</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 28th Massachusetts
     volunteers</name>; age 29; Irish; enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1864-08-01">August 1,
     1864</date>. <date type="injury" when="1865-03-25">March 25, 1865</date>, he received a gunshot
    fracture of the left thigh in action <name type="BATTLE" key="58">near Petersburg,
     Virginia</name>. He was admitted to the depot field hospital of the Second Army Corps, <name
     type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, and on <date type="transfer" when="1865-03-31">the
     31st</date> was sent on board the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">steamer State of Maine</name>
    for transfer to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>. He was admitted to <name
     type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., <date type="admit"
     when="1865-04-01">April 1st</date>. On examination it was found that the ball had entered the
    external surface of the left thigh at the junction of its middle and lower thirds, and passing
    transversely inwards comminuted the femur, and made its exit on the internal surface opposite
    the wound of entrance. <date type="operation" when="1865-04-02">April 2d</date>, he was
    etherized, the wound of entrance enlarged, and five fragments of bone removed. When admitted to
     <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square</name> this man had an abscess at the lower
    border of the left popliteal space, caused by the pressure of the end of a splint which had been
    applied to the posterior surface of the thigh. This caused so much pain and soreness that he
    could not at first bear extension, but at the end of the month of April this trouble was so much
    better that he was able to bear extension well. May 10th, he was attacked with the stools
    containing mucus but no blood, and this continued until his death, with the exception of two or
    three short intervals. June 15th, he was doing remarkably well; appetite good, tongue clean and
    bowels regular; but, July 1st, he had a return of the dysentery, which was not subsequently
    benefited by treatment. July 25th, the injured limb was attacked by erysipelas, and for a little
    distance around the wound, not exceeding half an inch at any point, it presented the appearance
    of gangrene. This was treated by the application of solution of bromine. The limb was
    considerably swollen, and the patient felt great pain near the ankle joint. July 29th, a large
    patch of the epidermis over the left ankle was raised, and the space beneath filled with
    dark-colored serum. The true skin presented the bluish color seen in the first stage of
    gangrene. This appearance continued to extend up the limb until his death, on <date type="death"
     when="1865-07-30">the following day</date>. The night before his death he had a severe pain in
    his left side, indicative of pleurisy. <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi>
    <date type="autopsy" when="1865-07-30">8 hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis well marked. The
    apex of each lung was studded with tubercles. The posterior surface of the lower part of the
    left lung was covered with lymph, and the pleura at this point was highly inflamed. The heart
    was normal; the stomach and small intestine were also normal. The mucous membrane of the large
    intestine throughout its whole extent presented numerous ulcers about a quarter of an inch in
    diameter, and in the descending portion there were a large number of cysts containing lymph,
    some of which appeared to be undergoing ulceration, while others, already perforated, were
    filled with pus. The femoral and iliac veins of the injured side were completely filled with a
    firm fibrinous clot extending from the knee to the vena cava ascendens. The fractured femur was
    firmly united, with three-quarters of an inch shortening. [Specimens Nos. 602 and 603, Medical
    Section, are portions of the colon in this case, and No. 1105, Surgical Section, is the
    fractured femur.]</p>
   <p>The large intestine from this case was brought to <name type="hospital" key="431">the
     Museum</name> immediately after the post mortem examination. When received its mucous surface
    was of a pale cream color, with livid bluish discoloration around the cysts. These contained a
    semi-transparent yellowish matter resembling calves'-foot jelly, in which, with the microscope,
    a few delicate nucleated cells resembling the white corpuscles of the blood were observed to be
    imbedded. This substance was undoubtedly what is described as pus in the history of the case
    given below. Many of the cysts had ruptured and their contents escaped, leaving cavities
    resembling follicular ulcers. I found no other ulcers in any part of the specimen. The specimen,
    No. 602, Med. Section, represented in the photo-plate, is a portion of the transverse colon,
    exhibiting some fifty of the cysts described; the action of the alcohol has caused them to
    collapse, but their position and dimensions can still be recognized; several have so ruptured as
    to be converted into the cavities just described. No. 603, Medical Section, is a portion of the
    descending colon from the same case; it contains a small number of similar cysts, and also
    presents a number of small, irregular, oval cicatrices, such as result from the healing of
    follicular ulcers. A few of these cicatrices can also be recognized in the photo-plate by the
    help of a lens.</p>
   <p>In both the cases just described the death of the patient was undoubtedly hastened by the
    gunshot wound.</p>
   <p>The plate facing page 528 gives an excellent idea of the appearances presented by these
    characteristic cicatrices. It is reproduced from a photograph of a portion of No. 603, Medical
    Section. The specimen represented is from the case of Thomas Kelcher,. related on page 513. In
    that case the patient, while under treatment for a gunshot fracture of the thigh, suffered an
    attack of acute catarrhal dysentery which passed into a chronic flux. His colon presented a
    number of cysts, containing a jelly-like substance; these were fully described in the place
    referred to, and are represented in the plate facing page 514, which is reproduced from a
    photograph of No. 602, Medical Section. But between these cysts and the ulcer-like cavities
    formed here and there by their rupture there were a considerable number of stellate cicatrices.
    Several of these cicatrices can be recognized in the plate just mentioned as representing No.
    602, Medical Section. The photograph of a portion of No. 603, reproduced in the plate now
    described, was taken one-half larger than nature in order that the surface details might be
    better seen. In the portion reproduced there are several small, deep, oval cavities which
    represent the ruptured cysts just referred to. The surface of the intestine exhibits, besides,
    rather more than a dozen stellate cicatrices, some four or five of which form a conspicuous
    group near the centre of the plate. Each cicatrix consists of a central smooth area, oval or
    almost linear in shape, and varying in the specimen from one-twentieth to one-fifth of an inch
    in long diameter. From this central smooth portion radiate numerous delicate sinuous ridges,
    which sometimes branch and sometimes anastomose. In the plate, almost as well as in the
    specimen, the orifices of the glands of Lieberk&#252;hn can readily be recognized with a lens in
    the interspaces of the network formed by these radiating ridges.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001505.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XXVIII. TRANSVERSE COLON WITH CYSTS. No. 602. MEDICAL
     SECTION.</head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001506.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XXXV. COLON, WITH CICATRICES OF FOLLICULAR ULCERS. No.
     603. MEDICAL SECTION. [ENLARGED ONE-HALF.]</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
