<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31592">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Dugan, H. P.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31592</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">83-84</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>ball entered below crest of ilium, removed through counter-opening</term>
       <term>fracture of ilium, comminuted</term>
       <term>fæcal matter escaped with pus through wound</term>
       <term>external opening communicates with colon, wind and fæces exit</term>
       <term>barred from employment</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-10">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>   
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 252.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private H. P. Dugan</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 121st Pennsylvania</name>, aged 26 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="2">Gettysburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-07-03">July 3, 1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered one inch below the crest of the right ilium. He was taken to the field hospital, where the missile was removed through a counter-opening two inches posterior to the point of entrance; simple dressings were applied to the wound.  On July 22nd, he was transferred to the <choice><sic>Chesnut</sic><corr>Chestnut</corr></choice> Street Hospital, <name type="place">Harrisburg</name>. Here the fracture of the right ilium was noted by the ward surgeon, who also states that "since the day he was wounded some fæcal matter has escaped with the discharge of pus through the wound. Water dressings and nourishing diet.  August 12th, general health improving; fæcal discharge much less.  August 20th, general health good. Small pieces of necrosed bone have been removed through the opening; there is still a very slight discharge of fæcal matter."  On <date type="transfer" when="1863-09-16">September 16th</date>, he was transferred to South Street Hospital, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, and placed in Ward I, under the charge of <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Know</name>, who states that "since his admission the wound has been dressed simply. The external opening communicates with the colon, and wind and fæces make their exit through the fistulous opening. On September 20th, he complained of great pain in the lower right side of the pelvis, which was relieved by enemata and the application of warm cloths externally. This trouble occurred again on the 23d, but disappeared under the same treatment."  On <date type="transfer" when="1864-07-07">July 7, 1864</date>, he was transferred to <name type="place">Beverly, New Jersey</name>, at which time the fistulous opening still remained. At <name type="place">Beverly</name> he was reported as "convalescent," and was returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1865-02-21">February 21, 1865</date>; but, on <date type="admit" when="1865-02-27">the 27th</date>, was admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="501">2d division hospital</name> at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, was transferred on <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-21">May 21st</date> to McClellan Hospital, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, and was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-08">July 8, 1865</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner John Neill</name> reports, <date type="pension" when="1868-07-16">July 16, 1868</date>, that "the entrance wound is depressed and discharging, with evidence of necrosed bone. The ilium was comminuted, and numerous small pieces of bone have escaped. There is probably more to be discharged. The man is ruddy and in perfect health, and can pursue his trade except when a fresh suppuration takes place. He has entire use of all of his limbs."  The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Pension Examining Board</name> at <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> reports, <date type="pension" when="1870-03-23">March 23, 1870</date>, that the inconvenience and disgusting nature of the disability has not improved, and debars him from obtaining employment, and recommends him for an increase of pension, which was granted.  He was last paid on <date type="pension" when="1872-12-04">December 4, 1872</date>.</p>          
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
