<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20024">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Q——, John</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e20024</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">561-562</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>necrosis of clavicle following simple fracture</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>excisions</term>
          <term>excisions of the clavicle</term>
          <term>partial excisions of clavicle</term>
          <term>excision of bone for necrosis</term>
          <term>excision of middle third of clavicle</term>
          <term>fracture of clavicle</term>
          <term>horse shot during charge, falling upon him</term>
          <term>general emphysema</term>
          <term>wound of apex of pleura from fragments of broken bone</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 11.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private John
          Q——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 9th New York
          Cavalry</name>, sustained a comminuted fracture of the right clavicle, by his horse being
        shot during a charge into <name type="battle">Winchester, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-06-08">June 8th, 1862</date>, and falling upon him. He was
        conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="152">Finley Hospital</name>, where he was found to be suffering from
        general emphysema, the result, probably, of a wound of the apex of the pleura from some of
        the fragments of the broken bone. He was treated for this difficulty for a considerable time
        and finally entirely recovered. Several spiculæ of bone were removed through an
        incision from under the skin in the situation of the sternal extremity of the clavicle. On
          <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-21">October 21st, 1863</date>, he was admitted to St.
        Joseph's Hospital, Central Park, <name type="place">New York</name>. The wound over the
        sternal aspect was still open and presented the pouting and indolent appearance indicative
        of dead bone at its bottom. A probe being passed into this opening disclosed bare bone,
        which was still firm in its attachments and which was decided to be a portion of the head of
        the clavicle. His condition was good and it was thought best to wait until the sequestrum
        should detach itself before any attempt at removal should be made. <date type="operation" when="1864-01-14">January 14th, 1864</date>, an abscess formed over the outer third of the
        clavicle which was opened and showed the existence of dead bone at that point also. Simple
        applications were made to both wounds. February 10th: The sternal extremity of the clavicle
        commenced to protrude itself through the inner opening and was found to be connected with
        and evidently to form a solid piece with that portion of sequestrum felt through the outer
        opening. It was thought that the whole of that portion of the bone between these two points
        was dead. There was a considerable amount of thickening around it caused by the deposit of
        involucrum. The wound discharged slightly. June 1st: The bone was now freely movable in its
        bed and its sternal end pointed out of the wound for a distance of three-fourths of an inch.
        Aside from a pain in the right side of the chest and in the right shoulder, with an
        inconvenience in the motion of the parts, the patient suffered very little and enjoyed a
        good appetite. On <date type="operation" when="1864-06-21">June 21st, 1864</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. K. Merritt</name> removed the
        sequestrum by slightly enlarging the internal opening. The parts from which this portion of
        bone was removed soon became firmly braced by a new bridge of osseous tissue, formed by the
        involucrum, and really constituted a new clavicle. The motions of the arm, though somewhat
        restrained, were nevertheless good, all the support to the shoulder necessary for the
        subsequent good use of the limb being left good. The case progressed well until July 16th,
        when the wounds covered themselves with an ashy slough and hospital gangrene fairly declared
        itself. On the 10th, a thick, angry-looking slough covered both wounds; the edges of the
        openings were tumid and inflamed. The surfaces of the ulcers were touched with bromine, but
        the sloughs were so thick that the remedy failed to have the desired effect. On the 14th,
        the sloughs were removed and bromine applied directly to the part. By the 16th, the gangrene
        had extended itself into the track which communicated between the two wounds. The patient
        complained of a great deal of pain and soreness. Bromine was introduced into the track of
        the wound, but owing to the presence of the slough and the difficulty of removing it, the
        remedy could not be brought in direct contact with the surfaces underneath. The parts were
        repeatedly touched with bromine and bathed with a wash made of the same. Under this
        treatment they assumed a healthy aspect and the patient commenced to do well. By September
        19th, the parts had entirely healed; there was a marked enlargement from deposit of new bone
        at the seat of exfoliation. The soldier was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-10-01">October 1st, 1864</date>; the arm was useful and
        nearly all the normal movements could be made with it. The sequestrum is represented in the
        adjoining wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 258). It is partially tubular and is
        about three inches in length. The sternal articular surface is destroyed as well as all the
        cancellous structure in the longitudinal diameter of the bone. It is evident, too, that the
        acromial end of the clavicle did not become necrosed, and the deficiencies of the compact
        tissue of the head portion of the bone may be accounted for by the removal of the several
        small fragments at the hospital at Washington. The excavation on the anterior face of the
        bone was probably caused by the removal of two or three detached fragments at that time. If
        there were any small fragments toward the sternal end, as doubtless there were, they must
        have been firmly attached to the periosteum and become incorporated with the involucrum, and
        helped to form the firm bridge of bone which exists over the subclavian vessels. The
        specimen was contributed, with a history of the case, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. F. Shrady</name>. </p>

      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001479.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 258.—Tubular sequestrum from necrosis of right
          clavicle. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4332, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
