<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e12313">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ellis, H. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e12313</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">224, 288</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>successful cases of intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>ball fractured patella extensively, involved joint</term> 
     <term>synovitis</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term> 
     <term>thigh amputated at lower third</term>
     <term>h&#230;morrhage</term>
     <term>patella broken into fragments, fissure extended through inner cartilaginous face of bone</term> 
     <term>ligation of femoral artery performed below profunda</term>
     <term>fitted with artificial limb</term>     
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>prostrated from loss of blood, almost died from effects of ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-29">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 465.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1088">Corporal H. H.
      Ellis</name>, <name type="organization" key="445">Co. I, 16th New York</name>, aged 23 years,
     was wounded in the left knee, at <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>. <date type="admit" when="1863-05-08">Five days after the injury</date> he was admitted
     into <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, whence the following
     history was received: "On examining the wound it was found that a conical ball had fractured
     the patella so extensively as to involve the joint. On <date type="operation" when="1863-05-13">May 13th</date>, there were symptoms of
     synovitis, and the thigh was amputated at the lower third, by the circular method, by <name type="person" key="616">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. E. Smith</name>. Portions of clothing were
     removed from the amputated knee, and an examination showed that the patella had been broken
     into numerous fragments, that a fissure extended through the inner cartilaginous face of the
     bone, and that synovitis had been developed. The patient was broken down with diarrh&#339;a.
     The stump was dressed with alcohol, and stimulants, quinine, and nutrients were given as
     largely as possible. The general condition of the patient was so unfavorable that no effort at
     repair was perceptible in the stump for many days. On May 20th, a h&#230;morrhage of several
     ounces occurred and was controlled by pressure. During the following night the bleeding
     recurred so freely as to render a ligation of the femoral artery necessary, which was performed below the profunda on <date type="operation" when="1863-05-21">May 21st</date>.
     The patient was so prostrated from the loss of blood that he almost died from the effects of
     the ether. The most careful administration of whiskey, ammonia, valerian, and morphia alone
     sustained his life during the next forty-eight hours. There was no recurrence of
     h&#230;morrhage after the ligation, nor did this ligature of the main artery produce the
     slightest perceptible effect upon the appearance of the stump. The usual changes were resorted
     to in the various astringents given for the diarrh&#339;a, nitrate of silver, opium, tannin,
     and sulphuric acid, all proving at first beneficial and then losing their effect. Lemon juice was
     given, as the patient's stomach would bear it with evident benefit as an antiscorbutic. For
     weeks the patient hung between life and death. His whole thigh was much swollen and very tender
     on pressure; the incisions were healthy in appearance, the discharge moderate, and the granulations very tedious. Under a careful treatment he gradually grew stronger, his diarrh&#339;a
     ceased, and the stump, though yet greatly swollen, became closed excepting at the inner
     extremity, where the end of the femur protruded, the flaps from the first having been
     insufficient. On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-09">August 9th</date>, <name type="person" key="616">Dr. Smith</name> was ordered to
     remove the exfoliating end of the bone, which was loose, and, to his surprise, proved to be a
     very extensive sequestrum ten inches in length. Considerable h&#230;morrhage supervened, but
     after the operation convalescence was very rapid, and the stump, no shorter than before, soon
     closed entirely, being firm and in every way satisfactory. A formation of new bone could be
     plainly felt in it. The patient regained his flesh and strength, and left the hospital <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1863-10-23">October
     26, 1863</date>, his term of service having expired <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-05-22">May
      22d</date>." The history, with the sequestrum, represented in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
     1 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXIX</hi>, opposite p. 224, and the bones of the amputated
     knee, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name
      type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas
      Hospital</name>. A ligamentous preparation of the latter specimen constitutes No. 1852 of the
     Surgical Section. The patient was subsequently an inmate of the Post Hospital at <name type="place">Albany</name>, and afterwards entered Central
     Park Hospital, <name type="place">New York City</name>, to be fitted with an artificial limb by <name
      type="person" key="xx">Dr. E. D. Hudson</name>. He left for his home <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1864-06-06">June 6, 1864</date>. His pension
     was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. (See wood-cut 64, p. 63, <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> 6, S. G. O.,
     Washington, Nov. 1, 1865.)</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001811.001" />
   <head> PLATE  LXIX. __ TUBULAR  SEQUESTRA  FROM  AMPUTATIONS  OF  THE  FEMUR.     1.  Spec. 1853.</head>
   </figure>
   
    

   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
