<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40876">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Livingston, J. S.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40876</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">149-150</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Douglas Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>lost forty pounds in weight</term>
       <term>intestines congested in patches, patches dark mahogany color, no ulceration detected</term>
       <term>Peyer's patches and mesenteric glands healthy</term>             
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="162"><hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>OUGLAS <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from February, 1863, to September, 1864, and after September, 1865:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 303.—<name type="person" key="206">Private J. S. Livingston</name>, <name type="organization" key="229">company K, 7th Wisconsin volunteers</name>; age 32; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-03-23">March 23, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  Had contracted diarrhœa in <date type="injury" when="1862-09">September, 1862</date>, but continued on duty until <date type="injury" when="1862-12-24">Christmas</date>, when he was sent to the regimental hospital for debility, having lost forty pounds in weight.  [The register of the regimental hospital shows that he was admitted <date type="admit" when="1862-12-24">December 24th</date>, and transferred to division hospital <date type="transfer" when="1863-03-07">March 7th</date>.]  He was then transferred to field hospital, where he remained until <date type="transfer" when="1863-03-22">March 22, 1863</date>.  [He appears on the register of the hospital of the 1st Division, 1st Army Corps, as admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-03-07">March 7th</date>—chronic diarrhœa—sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1863-03-22">March 22d</date>.]  The diarrhœa had continued unchanged, averaging about three stools daily, except when temporarily aggravated by hard work or exposure. There had been very little pain or abdominal tenderness; the stools were small and light-colored; appetite good. His diet had consisted chiefly of hard bread and fresh or salt beef. When admitted to this hospital his pulse was nearly normal; tongue moist, and in the center covered with a yellowish-white fur; the skin dry; he had about three liquid light-colored stools daily; no abdominal tenderness; moderate appetite; micturition was frequent but not painful. He was very much emaciated.  ℞. Nitrate of silver one grain, powdered opium and blue mass each half a grain, ipecacuanha quarter of a grain, every four hours. Water acidulated with nitric acid for drink; whiskey and beef-essence.  March 27th: Substituted three grains of subnitrate of bismuth with quarter of a grain of sulphate of morphia every four hours.  Diet: Milk, rice, mutton broth, eggs. April 7th: Seems somewhat better, but still haw two or three stools daily; appetite moderate; tongue clean; is able to sit up a little. Discontinue medicine, and give an enema of one drop of creasote in an ounce of mucilage three times daily.  April 15th: Two grains of quinine and ten drops of aromatic sulphuric acid three times daily.  April 18th: Had five stools during the day, attended with tormina and tenesmus. Continue the quinine; give also bismuth and whiskey.  April 20th: Still has five or six stools a day; bilious vomiting has set in, accompanied by loss of appetite. Stop the quinine.  April 22d: The vomiting has ceased, but the diarrhœa continues about the same. He has become considerably emaciated; tongue red and dry.  ℞. Opium one-third of a grain, acetate of lead two grains, every four hours.  April 27th: Continues about the same.  ℞. Elixir of opium twenty drops, subnitrate of bismuth four grains, every four hours.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-05-08">May 8th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> Old pleuritic adhesions about the lower lobe of the right lung; the posterior part of the upper lobe of the lung was hepatized; left lung normal. The liver was slightly enlarged and of a mahogany color. The intestines were somewhat congested in patches throughout their entire length, the congested patches being of a dark mahogany color, but no ulceration could be detected. Peyer's patches and the mesenteric glands were healthy.—<name type="person" key="205">Acting Assistant Surgeon Francis M. Holly</name>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
