<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41310">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Kellogg, Marvin</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41310</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">185</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Carver Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>jaundice</term>
       <term>sordes on teeth</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of stomach presented severe inflammation about cardiac orifice</term>
       <term>agminated glands in lower ileum congested, congestion increasing and dark spots appearing near ileocæcal valve</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon roughened with pseudomembrane; in the lower portion of the descending colon there were a number of small ulcers</term>
       <term>small ulcers in lower descending colon</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of both ileum and descending colon coated with pseudomembrane</term>
       <term>small follicular ulcers in colon</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-28">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>The notes were forwarded, with the specimens, to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> from <name type="hospital" key="167"><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ARVER <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon Oliver A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 428.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Marvin Kellogg</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company G, 2d New York heavy artillery</name>; age 33; admitted from the depot hospital of the 2d Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-08-21">August 21, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  The patient was greatly emaciated and had a jaundiced look. He had a severe diarrhœa, amounting to fifteen or twenty dejections during the twenty-four hours; his pulse was weak and easily compressed; his tongue was moist and thinly coated with gray fur.  He continued in about this condition till August 25th, when the fæcal discharges became very frequent and involuntary.  Treatment: Opiates and astringents, pills of opium and nux vomica, opiate enemata, &amp;c.; brandy as a stimulant.  Diet: Milk, chicken, beef-tea, beef-essence, &amp;c.  He died <date type="death" when="1864-08-28">August 28th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> Rigor mortis great; body greatly emaciated; there was a large collection of sordes on the teeth. The lungs were normal. The right side of the heart contained a fibrinous clot, the left side was filled with dark blood; the valves were healthy; the pericardium contained about two ounces of fluid. The liver was slightly enlarged and congested; the gall-bladder was filled with viscid bile. The spleen was dark colored, small and firm. The mucous membrane of the stomach was congested and red, presenting signs of severe inflammation about the cardiac orifice; the pyloric end of the organ was greatly contracted, the mucous membrane being thrown into large folds. The agminated glands in the lower portion of the ileum were congested, the congestion increasing, and dark spots appearing on the mucous membrane near the ileocæcal valve. The mucous membrane of the colon was congested, thickened and roughened with pseudomembrane; in the lower portion of the descending colon there were a number of small ulcers.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon O. P. Sweet</name>.   [Nos. 401 and 402, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  No. 401 is a portion of the ileum, No. 402 of the descending colon. The mucous membrane of both is coated with pseudomembrane; in the colon there are a number of small follicular ulcers.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
