<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8539">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ziliox, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8539</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">185-186</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>fatal cases of shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>suppuration, burrowing of pus</term>
     <term>ball entered outer middle portion thigh, fractured femur, lodged in surrounding
      muscles</term>
     <term>effusion in knee joint</term>
     <term>joint swollen, erysipelatous hue</term>
     <term>pyarthrosis</term>
     <term/>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding for fig. 145</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 377.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1022">Private William
     Ziliox</name>, <name type="organization" key="416">Co. F, 29th New York</name>, aged 31 years,
    was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury"
     when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>. He was standing erect and in the act of firing. The
    missile, a conoidal ball, entered the outer and middle portion of the left thigh, passed upward,
    fractured the femur, and lodged in the surrounding muscles. He was left on the battlefield and
    fell into the hands of the enemy, and received no treatment until his return within our lines,
     <date type="admit" when="1863-05-15">May 15, 1863</date>. He was then admitted into the field
    hospital of the Eleventh Corps, at <name type="place">Brook's Station</name>, where his leg was
    dressed in splints. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-14">June 14th</date>, he was admitted
    into the <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington. <name
     type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190"
     >U. S. A.</name>, reports: "When admitted his affected limb looked as though no extension had
    been employed. The ball had not been extracted, there was no union, and there was four and a
    half inches shortening. <name type="person" key="1023">Acting Assistant Surgeon D.
    Weisel</name>, under whose care the patient was placed, removed the splints and applied the
    anterior splint. This treatment was continued until June 20th, when, suppuration becoming so
    great, fear was entertained of pus burrowing toward the hip joint, and it was discontinued, and
    sand bag supports and extension, produced by a bag of stones suspended by a rope run through a
    pulley and attached to the base of the foot, substituted. The case progressed favorably. August
    1st, small abscesses appeared near the knee, not, however, troublesome. There was little
    burrowing of pus. <date type="operation" when="1863-08-07">August 7th</date>, <name
     type="person" key="1023">Dr. Weisel</name> opened a small abscess on the posterior portion of
    the thigh immediately behind the seat of fracture. <date type="operation" when="1863-08-26"
     >August 26th</date>, several spicul&#230; of bone were extracted through this opening, together
    with the bullet, which was flattened and contorted to a very irregular form. Early in September,
    the pus was observed extending down the inner side of the thigh and opening two inches above the
    internal condyle of the femur. By pressure pus could, at any time, be made to pass out of this
    opening, it, no doubt, communicating with the injury above. The constitutional symptoms were
    still favorable. October 1st, effusion in the knee joint of the corresponding side was first
    noticed; the skin over the joint had an erysipelatous hue, and the joint was swollen. It was at
    first thought that the opening on the inside of the thigh communicated with the joint, and that
    pyarthrosis was caused thereby; but it was afterwards thought to be a case of suppurative
    arthritis and in no direct way connected with the pus-producing surface about the seat of
    fracture. From the first appearance of this complication the patient sank rapidly, the tongue
    became dry and brown, the stomach rejected all aliment; hiccough was a constant and distressing
    symptom. Severe pain was experienced in the limb. These signs of constitutional exhaustion
    continued without relief until the day of his death, <date type="death" when="1863-10-06"
     >October 6, 1863</date>." The secondary inflammation of the knee joint is shown in <hi
     rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XXV</hi>, opposite p. 184. The fractured
    femur, showing fractures in the upper third, large deposits of callus, but without union, is <hi
     rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 176l of the Surgical Section, A. M. M. (<hi rend="initialcap"
    >F</hi>IG. 145.)</p>
   <p>PLATE XXV. SECONDARY INFLAMMATION OF THE KNEE JOINT. Case of Pt. William Ziliox, F, 29th New
    York</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001564.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 145.&#8212;Shot fracture of upper third of left femur. <hi
      rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1761.</head>
   </figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
