<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e35006">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wick, Isadore</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e35006</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">839</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>hospital gangrene</term>
     <term>circular ampuation</term>
     <term>right thigh ampuation on field</term>
     <term>comminuted fracture of tibia by mini&#233; ball</term>
     <term>tedious granulation</term>
     <term>free discharge</term>
     <term>typhoid symptoms</term>
     <term>limb removed after death</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-02-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
    and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>In <date type="injury" when="1863-02">February, 1863</date>, a number of cases of hospital
    gangrene occurred at the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D.
    C., and were observed by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who, in a special report to the Surgeon
    General, gives the following interesting account of the pathology and treatment of the cases. In
    several instances later information has been added to the cases cited by <name type="person"
     key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>: <!--<ref xml:id="n01" target="#n48" n="1" /> --></p>

   <p>"On the 26th of December, 1862, about two hundred wounded from the battle of <name
     type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name> were received into the <name type="hospital"
     key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>.</p>

   <p>&quot;CASE V.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Isadore Wick</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="xxx">Co. D, 1st New York Artillery</name>, aged 32 years, had his
    right thigh amputated on the field, for comminuted fracture of the tibia, received <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13</date>,
    1862, at <name type="battle" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, caused by a mini&#233; ball. He was admitted <date type="admit" when="1862-12-26">December 26th</date>. I regret that I
    can give no account of his progress, but I learn that the flaps had been insufficient, and that
    the stump had been closing by tedious granulation. There had been a free discharge, and his
    general condition was, therefore, unfitted to withstand the depressing influence of hospital
    gangrene. His bed was on the same side of the ward, and in close proximity to the first case
    reported. The operation had been a circular one; the granulation had entirely covered the end of
    the bone, and there was, when seen on the 18th of February, only a narrow strip, not yet
    cicatrized between the margins of skin. This was now covered with a gray slough and had the
    characteristic fetid odor. It was dressed simply with the creasote solution, my faith in the
    acid treatment having been shaken by the reports of medical officers who had visited the cases
    at Annapolis. February 23d : The case was now considered an unequivocal one of hospital
    gangrene, and was removed to the ward selected for such cases. The cicatricial tissue had all
    yielded to the sloughing, and the subcutaneous connective tissue had been destroyed for two
    inches beneath the skin at the outer angle of the original incisions. No change was made in the
    local treatment, as the creasote was a perfect deodorant, and as good results were hoped for
    from its local use, as had been reported from Annapolis. The destruction was limited to the
    connective tissue until March 9th, when there was a margin of sphacelus half an inch wide in the
    true skin. The constitutional symptoms had been growing more grave. His mental despondency was
    most marked, his face pale and anxious, his pupils dilated, his pulse 100 per minute and feeble,
    and his skin very moist; a free diarrh&#339;a had also commenced. The tonics and stimulants,
    having produced anorexia and nausea, were replaced by a mixture of tincture of opium and
    hydrochloric acid in such proportions that he took gtt. xvi of tr. opii and git. iv of acid,
    hydrochlor. every fourth hour. Beef essence and milk punch were given as freely as his stomach
    would tolerate them, llth : As his general condition became less favorable the local action was
    changed from molecular death to sphacelus. The whole face of the stump has now a margin of black
    mortification of the skin, outside of which was the usual areola of purple congestion the
    complete stasis of to-day becoming the sphacelus of to-morrow. The end of the femur, protected
    by rosy granulations, now protrudes from the black mass of sphacelus. the integument having
    become loosened by the destruction of the subcutaneous connective tissue and retracted. The
    presence of this mass of putrefaction seems to add to the nervous prostration, if indeed the
    absorption of such peccant material is not its sole cause. Pure nitric acid had been applied
    several times, but it had been found impossible to convey it into the depths of the ulcer. <date type="death" when="1863-03-21">21st</date>
    : No change except for the worse had occurred. Stimulating poultices of cinchona, ginger, and
    flaxseed had been used locally, but with no benefit. Antiseptics, such as the solutions of
    chloride of soda, creasote, and per manganate of potash, were necessary to purity the ward and
    render it endurable for his attendants. Nutrients and stimulants had been pushed to the last
    extent, and opium had been largely given for its supposed specific effect in the disease as well
    as to allay suffering. The symptoms had been typhoid for several days; emaciation had gone on
    rapidly ; there had been subsultus tendinum and muttering delirium with extreme prostration
    until this date, when death occurred. The limb was removed after death and the specimen sent to
    the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>. [<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 1000, <hi rend="italic">Surg. Sect</hi> ] The sphacelus had involved all
    the tissues for five inches above the divided bone, and there seems to have been a faint effort
    to form a line of demarcation.</p>

   <p>&quot;This was, at first, a very mild case, with no very decided constitutional depression
    until the system seemed to be poisoned by the absorption of the products of the gangrene, when
    the ulceration became more rapid, and was finally, as the strength succumbed, converted into
    uncontrollable and rapidly extending sphacelus, accounting satisfactorily for the unfortunate
    result. The treatment locally had been, first, weak solution of creasote, made soluble by one
    drachm of alcohol, four drops to one ounce of water; and second, strong nitric acid, never fully
    applied, however, to the depths of the diseased tissues. The constitutional treatment was
    stimulating, sustaining, and tonic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
