<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16697">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">M——, A——</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16697</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">265</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>trephining practiced, fatal termination</term>
          <term>conoidal musket ball entered at juncture of coronal and squamous sutures and
            lodged</term>
          <term>symptoms of compression of brain</term>
          <term>eyeballs, especially right, prominent and pupils fixed and contracted</term>
          <term>blood and brain substance oozed from wound</term>
          <term>cerebro-meningitis, advanced to stage of suppuration</term>
          <term>pus collected over anterior surface of brain and between pia mater and
            arachnoid</term>
          <term>ball lacerated anterior portion of middle lobe of brain, terminal branches of
            internal carotid, and anterior branch of temporal artery</term>
          <term>fragment of ball found in middle lobe of cerebrum, remaining portion imbedded in
            sphenoid bone</term>
          <term>large clot on floor of middle fossa of cranium</term>
          <term>post-mortem examination</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private A——
          M——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. D, 155th Pennsylvania
          Volunteers</name>, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th,
          1862</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which entered at the juncture of coronal and
        squamous sutures, and lodged. He was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="159">Patent
          Office Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., on <date type="admit" when="1862-12-17">the
          17th</date>, complaining but very little of his wound, and was able to walk about until
        the 19th, when the pain became so severe that he was compelled to take to his bed. He became
        restless, showing all the symptoms of febrile excitement. A lotion of lead water and
        laudanum was ordered to be applied to the wound, and an anodyne administered. Up to this
        time he had not been delirious and was able to give rational answers to all questions. On
        the morning of <date type="operation" when="1862-12-20">the 20th</date>, he was comatose and
        all the symptoms of compression of the brain were well marked; his eyeballs, especially the
        right, were prominent and the pupils fixed and contracted. On removing the dressing, blood
        and brain substance oozed from the wound. The wound of the scalp was then enlarged and the
        skull trephined; spiculæ of bone were removed, causing considerable hæmorrhage,
        but no relief to the patient. He died <date type="death" when="1862-12-20">a few hours after
          the operation</date>. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination revealed
        cerebro-meningitis, advanced to the stage of suppuration, pus having collected over the
        anterior surface of the brain, and between the pia mater and arachnoid. The ball had
        lacerated the anterior portion of the middle lobe of the brain, the terminal branches of the
        internal carotid, and the anterior branch of the temporal artery. There was a large clot on
        the floor of the middle fossa of the cranium. A fragment of the ball was found in the centre
        of the middle lobe of the cerebrum, and the remaining portion was imbedded in the sphenoid
        bone. The pathological specimen is figured in the wood-cut. The opening in the cranial wall
        measures one inch from above downward and is three-fourths of an inch wide; from this point
        one fissure passes downward across the glenoid cavity and a second forward into the external
        wall of the right orbit, which is comminuted. The ball is encrusted with calcareous matter.
          <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. H. Jamar</name> contributed the
        specimen and history.</p>
      <figure><graphic url="cww.001419.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 132.—Segment of cranium and portion of lower maxilla,
        and round musket ball. The skull was trephined. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 685, Sect. I,
        A. M. M.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
