<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5360">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Marston, Charles E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5360</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">105-106</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>laid on battle-field several days</term>
     <term>large bullet wound anterior to and in line with trochanter major</term>
     <term>comminution of head and neck of femur</term>
     <term>neck of femur crushed into fragments</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-16">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 247.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Charles E.
     Marston</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 1st Massachusetts</name>, aged 19
    years, a pale and delicate boy, was wounded at the <name type="BATTLE" key="127">second battle
     of Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>. He was
    admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="170">College Hospital, Georgetown</name>, D. C., on
     <date type="admit" when="1862-09-06">September 6th</date>, having laid on the battle-field
    several days, and then moved in an ambulance wagon thirty miles over very rough roads. An
    examination revealed a large bullet wound an inch anterior to and on a line with the right
    trochanter major, with great comminution of the head and neck of the femur. The limb was
    shortened, and the foot was everted. The circumference of the limb exceeded that of its fellow
    by half. The pulse was 112, and of moderate volume. The tongue was rather dry. The patient
    suffered little pain. The general condition was not promising, and yet not very bad. Excision of
    the fractured bone was decided upon, and, on the <date type="operation" when="1862-09-27">27th
     of September</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon B. A. Clements</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, assisted by <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon Charles H. Alden</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S.
    A.</name>, and the surgical staff of the hospital, proceeded to perform the operation.
    Chloroform was administered, and a slightly curved incision five inches in length was made on
    the outside of the thigh, the shot hole in the middle of the incision, and the trochanters and
    neck were thus exposed. The neck was crushed into about forty fragments, which were extracted.
    The head was also much broken, and the round ligament was absorbed or destroyed, so that
    exarticulation was easy. The roughened portion of the neck, at its attachment with the
    trochanter, was sawn off with a small chain saw. The missile, a conoidal musket ball, was found
    on the inner side of the thigh at the bottom of a large cavity, and was removed with difficulty.
    After thoroughly syringing the wound and removing the powdered bone, the wound was closed by
    silver sutures, except at the bullet hole, and sand bags were placed to keep the limb in
    position. Slight extension was made by a weight to the foot. The patient expressed himself as
    relieved by the operation, and he slept well that night. On the following day his pulse had
    risen to 128, and the discharge from the wound was very copious, thin, and brown. On September
    29th, his pulse was still quick and feeble, and his tongue dry, and, though he took nourishment
    well, and was free from distress, he gradually sank. He died on <date type="death" when="1862-09-30">September 30, 1862</date>, at half past 8 o'clock A. M., three days after the
    operation. At the autopsy, on <date type="autopsy" when="1862-10-01">October 1st</date>, made by
     <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. K. Smith</name>, the wound made by
    the operation was found to be filled with very offensive pus. The upper end of the shaft of the
    femur was found to be diseased on its posterior surface near the trochanter minor, and the
    periosteum was loosened from the bone for some distance above and below this point. The fracture
    of the ischium, which was noticed at the operation, extended obliquely upward and backward from
    the lower border of the acetabulum, terminating in the sciatic notch, about an inch and a
    quarter above the spine of the ischium. The lower half of the acetabulum had been broken into
    several fragments, which were held in position by the cotyloid ligament. The excised portions of
    the femur were forwarded to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, and
    are numbered 328 in the Surgical Section. They are represented in the adjoining wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 58). </p>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001533.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 58.—Shot comminution of head and neck of right femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 328.</head></figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
