<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41910">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Snow, Daniel</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41910</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">448</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>remarks on the pathology and treatment of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>acute dysentery</term>
     <term>post mortem appearances in acute dysentery</term>
     <term>diphtheritic inflammation</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
     <term>confined as deserter</term>
     <term>chronic dysentery</term>
     <term>jaundice and bilious vomiting</term>
     <term>large intestine presented large irregular ulcers from c&#230;cum to anus</term>
     <term>colon ulcers involved muscular coat</term>
     <term>perforation in caput coli</term>
     <term>periton&#230;um covering intestine adherent to right lobe of liver</term>
     <term>liver contained yellow metastatic foci, most in right lobe and in course of branches of
      portal vein</term>
     <term>liver foci contained disorganized liver tissue, granular matter, and fat globules, but no
      pus</term>
     <term>acute diphtheritic dysentery</term>
     <term>diphtheritic sloughs completely separated before death</term>
     <term>metastatic foci in liver like those in py&#230;mia</term>
     <term>metastatic foci consecutive upon colon ulcers</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>

   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and
    added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>The chromo-plate facing page 452 exhibits one variety of diphtheritic ulcers. The following is
    an account of the case:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 896.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Daniel
     Snow</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company F, 2d New York heavy artillery</name>;
    enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1864-01-06">January 6, 1864</date>, and is reported present
    with his company until after the first of May. On the muster-roll for May and June he is
    reported missing, and on that for July and August: "Absent; confined as a deserter by the
    provost-marshal." While in confinement he was attacked with dysentery, and became so sick that
    he was admitted to the field hospital of the 2d Army Corps at <name type="place">City Point,
     Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-09-06">September 6, 1864</date>, where the
    diagnosis recorded was chronic dysentery. He appeared to be so ill that <date type="transfer"
     when="1864-09-07">next day</date> he was put on board the <name type="hospital" key="xxx"
     >steamer Connecticut</name> for transfer to general hospital. He was admitted to <name
     type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., <date type="admit"
     when="1864-09-09">September 9th</date>, and the following particulars were communicated by
     <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon Wm. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization"
     key="190">U. S. A.</name>: The patient was much emaciated, and, in addition to the usual
    symptoms of the advanced stage of dysentery, had jaundice and frequent bilious vomiting. The
    abdomen was flat and tender, the skin cool, the pulse feeble. He had stupor, low delirium and
    involuntary stools. Died, <date type="death" when="1864-09-17">September 17th</date>. <hi
     rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> Body somewhat emaciated and intensely jaundiced. Organs of the
    thorax healthy. [The state of the small intestine is not recorded.] The large intestine was
    greatly thickened, contracted in calibre, and presented, from the c&#230;cum to the anus,
    numerous large, irregular, ragged ulcers, most of which involved the muscular coat. The ulcers
    had sharp, abrupt, ragged edges. In the caput coli there was a perforation the size of a dime.
    Externally the periton&#230;um covering the intestine was roughened and adherent to the right
    lobe of the liver for an extent of two inches. There was but little f&#230;cal matter in the
    large intestine, which contained a number of black and gray fibrin-like clots. The liver
    contained numerous yellow metastatic foci from a quarter to half an inch in diameter; these were
    mostly in the right lobe and in the course of the branches of the portal vein; many of them
    contained a small drop of yellow fluid in the centre, and consisted, as seen under the
    microscope, of disorganized liver tissue, granular matter and fat globules, but no pus. The
    other abdominal viscera were healthy. [Nos. 448 and 449, Medical Section, <name type="hospital"
     key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.]</p>
   <p>A portion of the descending colon and the liver from this case were brought to <name
     type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>on the day of the autopsy, and water-color drawings
    of the appearances presented made by <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Hermann Faber</name>;
    these are reunited in the chromo-plate. The very large ulcer shown near the middle of the piece,
    and parts of some of the others, laid bare the muscular coat, which was smooth and shining,
    while the bottoms of some of the ulcers only penetrated more or less deeply into the submucous
    connective tissue. The prevailing tint of the mucous membrane between the ulcers was yellowish,
    but it was streaked with bluish, gray and greenish tints, and in places brownish, reddish-brown
    or even bright red. Greenish or bluish neutral tints prevailed on the surface of the ulcers;
    their edges were rounded or bevelled, in but few places overhanging. The liver was dark brown
    externally, except where the metastatic foci described in the report of the autopsy were
    visible. Its cut section presented the nutmeg appearance in a marked manner and numbers of the
    metastatic foci. The description, given in the report, of the microscopical characters of these
    foci and of their relations to the portal vein was verified at <name type="hospital" key="431"
     >the Museum</name>. This case, then, is to be regarded as one of acute diphtheritic dysentery
    in which the sloughs had completely separated before death. The exact duration of the dysentery
    cannot be determined, but it probably set in some time after the deserter was captured by the
    provost-marshal, so that it is improbable that it commenced earlier than July, and it may not
    have done so until sometime in August. The metastatic foci in the liver were quite like those
    which occur in py&#230;mia, and I am disposed to regard them as consecutive upon the colon
    ulcers.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001502.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE XIX. EXTENSIVE ULCERATION OF COLON.&#8212;CHRONIC
     DYSENTERY. METASTATIC FOCI OF LIVER.</head>
   </figure>
   <p/>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
