<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e8527">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Barrett, William T.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e8527</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">380</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">                                       
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the ileum or small intestine only affected</term> 
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated through to peritoneum</term>
                                        <term>bronchitis</term>       
                                        <term>pleuritic adhesions on both sides</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated in centre, some ulcerated into peritoneum</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>lower lobe of lung  congested and friable</term>
                                        <term>mass of solidified tissue in posterior lower lobe of lung</term>
                                        <term>bronchial glands mottled black and white</term>
                                        <term>spleen presented inferiorly cyst containing fluid</term>
                                        <term>kidney full of blood</term>
                                        <term>intense congestion in  small intestine</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change> 
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                        
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00148">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 148.—<name type="person" key="687">Private William T.
                                                Barrett</name>, <name type="organization" key="165">Co. K, 39th Mass.</name>, was admitted <date type="admit" when="1862-12-24">Dec. 24, 1862</date>,
                                        with typhoid fever.  Bronchitis set in about a week before
                                        his death, which occurred <date type="death" when="1863-01-29">Jan. 29, 1863</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-01-30">twelve
                                        hours after death</date>: The brain was pale, firm and weighed
                                        forty-three ounces. There were pleuritic adhesions on both
                                        sides. The lungs were marked by black pigment in the course
                                        of the ribs. The left lung weighed nineteen ounces and a
                                        half; its lower lobe was much congested and friable and its
                                        bronchial tubes congested, especially in their finer
                                        ramifications. The right lung weighed twenty-five ounces and
                                        three-quarters; there was a mass of solidified tissue in the
                                        posterior part of its lower lobe, the centre of which was
                                        occupied by fluid and opened into an inflamed bronchial tube
                                        of the third magnitude; several condensed pulmonary lobules
                                        were found also in the upper part of the lung; the bronchial
                                        glands were mottled black and white and were quite firm. The
                                        heart was flabby and contained clots. The liver,
                                        seventy-four ounces, was firm and of a light brown color,
                                        its acini comparatively distinct; the spleen, eleven ounces
                                        and a half, was soft and presented inferiorly a cyst
                                        containing half a drachm of fluid; the left kidney, five
                                        ounces, was slightly flabby and full of blood; the right
                                        kidney, four ounces and a half, was normal. The mucous
                                        membrane of the stomach was softened and free from folds.
                                        There were patches of intense congestion in the small
                                        intestine; some of Peyer's patches were ulcerated in the
                                        centre, some were neither ulcerated nor thickened and others
                                        near the valve contained black pigment and were ulcerated
                                        through to the peritoneum. The large intestine was quite
                                        thin.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
