<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31589">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Morell, Louis</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31589</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">80-81</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>first wound by small ball lodged in globe of eye</term>
       <term>second wound by ball to right of umbilicus, passed directly through body, emerged near sacro-iliac synchondrosis</term>
       <term>third wound in thigh, ball passed through quadriceps extensor above patella</term>
       <term>remained on battlefield three days</term>
       <term>ingestion of liquids escaped by posterior wound</term>
       <term>penetrating shot wound of abdomen, loss of eye, knee contracted</term>
       <term>suffered great torture in long ride</term>
       <term>removed considerable fragment of wing of ilium perforated by ball</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-10">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 243.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant Louis Morell</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. D, 119th New York</name>, aged 19 years, on the afternoon of <date type="injury" when="1863-07-01">July 1, 1863</date>, in <name type="BATTLE" key="2">the assault</name> on the lines of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Eleventh Corps</name>, received two wounds, and, falling, and remaining on the field between two fires, a third wound.  The first wound was from a small ball, which lodged in the globe of the left eye; the second was inflicted an instant afterward by a musket-ball, which entered four inches to the right of the umbilicus, passed directly through the body, and emerged near the right sacro-iliac synchondrosis, having grooved the crest of the innominatum. The sergeant was then in the act of reloading, the right arm elevated to use the ramrod. He recollected seeing his cartridge-box torn by the missile, and the next instant fell unconscious. He dimly recalls a temporary return of consciousness, on being struck soon afterward in the left thigh, by a musket-ball, which passed through the quadriceps extensor, a little above the patella.  He remained on the field until the morning of July 4th, without suffering from hunger or thirst. He had an indistinct impression that some one had given him water and had washed the wounds on his head and thigh; the wound in the flank appeared to have escaped notice. On July 4th, he was placed in an ambulance wagon and carried to a neighboring farm house, suffering great torture in the long ride. Arrived at the farm house, his wounds were dressed by a Confederate surgeon on duty there, and he drank a little gruel, portions of which escaped by the posterior wound almost as fast as it was swallowed. The sergeant is positive that, on this and subsequent occasions, an interval of not more than half an hour elapsed between the ingestion of liquids and their escape by the posterior wound. The appearance of the clothing indicated that there had been copious hæmorrhage. Beyond this, the sergeant says, his recollections are very confused and indefinite. Probably he was under the influence of opiates.  On <date type="transfer" when="1863-07-08">July 8th</date> he was taken to the Eleventh Corps field hospital, suffering again acutely in moving. No record appears here. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-08-06">August 6th</date> the patient was again moved to the Camp Letterman Hospital, and was under the immediate charge of <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon James A. Newcombe</name>, in the division in charge of <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. B. Stonelake</name>. The case is here registered as "a penetrating shot wound of the abdomen, loss of left eye, knee contracted."  There had been a fæcal discharge from the posterior wound, but it ceased about July 12th. Getting drenched with rain one night at the field hospital, the wound near the left knee became very painful, and the limb was semi-flexed and could not be again extended. At Camp Letterman, the discharges from the abdominal wounds were purulent. On <date type="operation" when="1863-10-30">October 30th</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Stonelake</name> enlarged the posterior wound and removed a considerable fragment of wing of the ilium, perforated by the ball. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-31">October 31st</date>, the wounded man was sent, under care of <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Newcombe</name>, to <name type="place">New York</name>, and entered Ladies Home Hospital. At that time he had no fever and suffered very little pain; his bowels were uniformly regular and his health quite good. The anterior wound had healed, but the posterior wound was still open. After the journey to <name type="place">New York</name> there were slight discharges of fæcal matter, at long intervals, by the posterior wound.  In February, 1864, the patient began to leave his bed, and then the stercoral discharge from the fistulous became more copious.  In May, Morell moved about on crutches. The flesh wound in the thigh had nearly healed; but a succession of abscesses had formed, and there was much contraction about the joint.  In <date type="operation" when="1864-12">December, 1864</date>, the hamstring tendons were divided by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon A. B. Mott</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, and the limb was extended and placed in a useful position. While the patient was continued to his bed, after his operation, the stercoral fistula closed.  <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-30">May 30, 1865</date>, the patient on the closure of Ladies' Home Hospital, was sent to MacDougal Hospital, at <name type="place">Fort Schuyler</name>. The fæcal fistula reopened in June, but soon dosed again.  On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-18">August 18th</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Morell</name> was discharged from service and pensioned.¹  <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon Samuel H. Orton</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, signed the certificate of disability, referring to the shot wounds through the abdomen and left thigh, and the loss of the left eye.  <date type="pension" when="1866-07-28">July 28, 1866</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner A. L. Lowell</name> reports that the exit wound was still open and discharging, and that exfoliations from the ilium still continued.  The fistula again closed, and, on <date type="enlist" when="1867-05-11">May 11, 1867</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Morell</name> re-entered the service as a hospital steward, and was assigned to clerical duty in the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Division of Surgical Records</name>, of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name>, where he is still employed.  A photograph, showing the cicatrices of entrance and exit, was made at <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> in <date type="photo" when="1873-03">March, 1873</date>, and is accurately copied in the left hand or sitting figure in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">V</hi>.</p>
   <p>¹ Notes of this case have been printed in the <hi rend="italic">American Medical Times</hi>, 1864, Vol. VIII, pp. 13, 301, and by Dr. <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>AMILTON (<hi rend="italic">Treatise on Mil. Surg.</hi>, p. 350). </p>  
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001774.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  V.   CICATRICES  AFTER  SHOT  PERFORATIONS  OF  THE  ABDOMEN.     Fig. 1.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Hospital Steward L. Morell</name>.</head>
   </figure>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
