<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41016">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Manning, Peter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e41016</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">162</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>consumption</term>
       <term>diarrhœa</term>
       <term>severe cough, copious purulent expectoration, pain in both lungs</term>
       <term>bronchial glands enlarged and black</term>
       <term>pericardium contained purulent serum</term>
       <term>solitary follicles of ileum slightly enlarged, two of Peyer's patches thickened, remaining Peyer's patches healthy</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 348.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Peter Manning</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company B, 49th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-19">February 19, 1863</date>.  Consumption.  [This man appears on the register of the hospital of the 2d Division, 6th Corps, <name type="place">Windmill Point, Aquia Creek, Virginia</name>, admitted January 20th—diarrhœa; no disposition recorded.]  This patient was extremely emaciated and prostrate when admitted. He had a severe cough, with copious purulent expectoration; he was also suffering from diarrhœa, and had six or eight evacuations daily. His cheeks were flushed; pulse from 100 to 120; he complained of pain in both lungs, but especially in the left. Nourishing diet, wine, and anodynes were administered.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-02-26">February 26th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-02-26">five hours and a half after death</date>: Height five feet one or two inches; body much emaciated; rigor mortis marked; apparent age 30. The brain weighed forty-two ounces; it was light colored and quite firm; the veins of the pia mater were full of blood. The right lung weighed twelve ounces and a half, the left thirty-three ounces. The bronchial glands were large, soft, and black. The heart weighed seven ounces and a half; it was firm and dark-red; there was very little adipose tissue externally; there was a large, firm, black clot in the right auricle, and mixed clots in both ventricles; the clots weighed four ounces. The pericardium contained five ounces of purulent serum in which flakes of lymph floated. The liver presented the nutmeg appearance; it weighed fifty-nine ounces and a half; the gall-bladder was empty. The spleen weighed four ounces, was of a very dark-purple color and unusually firm. The pancreas was flesh-colored, firm, and weighed three ounces and a half. The suprarenal capsules were remarkably large, firm, and dark-brown internally. The right kidney weighed four ounces, the left four and a quarter; both kidneys were dark-red and firm. The fundus of the stomach was congested. There was an area of congestion in the middle of the jejunum, and patches of congestion in the ileum; the solitary follicles of the ileum were slightly enlarged, and two of Peyer's patches, one in the lower part of the jejunum, the other in the ileum, were thickened; the remaining Peyer's patches were healthy; in the vicinity of the thickened patches the intestine was contracted. There were a number of congested spots in the ascending and transverse colon. (The intestines were not examined until <date type="autopsy" when="1863-02-27">thirty-eight hours after death</date>.)—<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
