<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e11375">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Briot, C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e11375</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">243-244</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the lower third of the femur</term>
     <term>recoveries after primary amputations in the lower third of the femur</term>
     <term>ball entered external aspect of knee, passed through joint, and lodged</term>
     <term>missile extracted from internal aspect of leg on the field</term>
     <term>limb amputated at lower third of thigh</term>
     <term>bone protruded from stump over an inch</term>
     <term>sequestrum removed</term>
     <term>tetanic pains, relieved by opium</term>
     <term>unable to wear artificial limb, consequence of tenderness of stump</term>
     <term>died of phthisis pulmonalis 14 years later</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-16">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 450.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private C.
     Briot</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 39th New York</name>, aged 26 years,
    was wounded in the left knee, at <name type="BATTLE" key="26">Bristoe Station</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1863-10-14">October 14, 1863</date>. He was conveyed to <name type="place"
     >Alexandria</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-10-15">the following day</date>, and
    admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="186">First Division Hospital</name>, whence <name
     type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. W. Koechling</name> transmitted the
    pathological specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 185), with the following history:
    &#34;The wound was caused by a mini&#233; ball entering the external aspect of the knee, passing
    through the joint, and lodging. The missile was extracted from the internal aspect of the leg,
    on the field, by <name type="person" key="xxx">the regimental surgeon</name>, and the limb was
    amputated at the lower third of the thigh, by the circular method, on <date type="operation"
     when="1863-10-16">October 16th</date>, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant
     Surgeon N. Barnes</name>. The patient came under my care on October 26th, at which time the
    bone protruded from the stump over an inch. For this gentle attraction of the integuments was
    made by adhesive strips and kept up for a week, when, the patient suffering too much pain, it
    was continued no longer, and a roller was applied from above downward and kept on until the bone
    was nearly covered. The patient improved every day, there being but very little discharge, but
    occasionally very severe pain in the stump. On <date type="operation" when="1864-02-08">February
     8, 1864</date>, the accompanying sequestrum was removed. On <date type="injury"
     when="1864-02-20">February 20th</date>, the patient was seized with tetanic pains, which,
    though relieved by the free administration of opium, recurred every other day for a month. After
    that period the patient did well, and was able to take exercise on crutches, the stump having
    healed. On <date type="furlough" when="1864-05-09">May 9th</date>, the patient left the hospital
    on furlough.&#34; He subsequently passed through different hospitals, and lastly entered De
    Camp, <name type="place">David's Island, New York Harbor</name>. On <date
     type="servicedischarge" when="1865-09-19">September 19, 1865</date>, the man was discharged
    from service and pensioned. The upper portion of the bones of the leg of the amputated limb were
    forwarded to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="xxx"
     >the operator</name>, and are represented in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGURE 184, and a cast
    of the stump was contributed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. F.
     Shrady</name>. (<hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1866, p. 548, <hi rend="italic"
     >Spec</hi>. 1787.) The <name type="organization" key="xxx">New York City Examining Board</name>
    certified, <date type="pension" when="1874-03-11">March 11, 1874</date>: &#34;The pensioner is
    unable to wear an artificial limb in consequence of excessive tenderness of the stump, rendering
    him unable to stand the pressure upon it. He has tried one several times, but it was so painful
    that he could not wear it more than a few hours.&#34; This pensioner died November 12, 1877, of
    phthisis pulmonalis. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001587.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 184.&#8212;Upper parts of bones of left leg; tuberosity of
     tibia split off obliquely. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2344.</head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001588.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 185.&#8212;Sequestrum from stump of left femur. <hi
      rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3027.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
