<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19431">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">L&#8212;&#8212;, G. P.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e19431</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">492</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
          <term>penetrating gunshot wounds of the chest</term>
          <term>complicated gunshot wounds of the lung</term>
          <term>air entered and escaped freely from wound</term>
          <term>entry of ball on the back, passed inward and upward</term>
          <term>fractured transverse process, chipped eighth rib, fractured fifth rib</term>
          <term>lung perforated by bullet through lower lobe</term>
          <term>lung compressed and collapsed</term>
          <term>autopsy performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-20">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private G. P.
          L&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization">Co. F, 4th New York Artillery</name>,
        aged 28 years, was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>,
        Washington, <date type="admit" when="1865-04-05">April 5th, 1865</date>, with a penetrating
        gunshot wound of the chest, received at <name type="BATTLE" key="283">South Side Railroad,
          Virginia</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1865-04-02">April 2d</date>. He stated that
        he spat blood upon the reception of injury. Pleurisy of the right side was well marked, with
        slight emphysema of the cellular tissue near the posterior wound, from which issued a thin
        sero-purulent fluid. The pulse and respiration were rapid; air entered and escaped freely
        from the posterior wound; the patient rapidly grew worse in spite of a generous diet and
        supporting treatment, and died on <date type="death" when="1865-04-09">April 9th,
          1865</date>. Fifteen hours subsequently the entry of the ball was noticed on the back, a
        little to the right of the spinous process of the ninth dorsal vertebra, whence it had
        passed inward and upward, fracturing the transverse process, chipping the eighth rib,
        fracturing the fifth, and escaping from the axilla of the same side. The right pleural
        cavity contained thirty-four ounces of a dark, offensive, sero-purulent fluid. The parietal
        and visceral pleur&#230; were covered with a greenish, soft, cacoplastic lymph, and the
        right lung, perforated by the bullet through the lower lobe, was compressed and collapsed.
        There was a slight serous effusion in the left pleural cavity: the remaining thoracic and
        abdominal viscera appeared healthy. Two specimens accompanying this history were contributed
        to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> by <name type="person"
          key="201">Assistant Surgeon W. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S.
          A.</name> The first, No. 2411 of the Surgical Section, consists of the seventh, eighth,
        and ninth dorsal vertebr&#230;, with the fifth, seventh, and eighth ribs of the right side.
        The right transverse process of the eighth vertebra and the dorsal extremity of the
        corresponding rib are chipped by a bullet. The fifth rib is obliquely broken, and comminuted
        on its internal surface, with a transverse fracture externally. The second, a preparation of
        the lung, is shown in the adjoining cut. (See <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 234.) </p>

      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001470.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 234.&#8212;Preparation of the right lung, showing
          perforation by a bullet. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2707, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
