<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7496">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Plummer, Daniel</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e7496</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">351-352</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>entered as typhoid, but the clinical histories suggestive of malarial complications</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the ileum or small intestine only affected</term>
                                        <term>erysipelas</term>       
                                        <term>deafness, tinnitus aurium</term>
                                        <term>gangrenous spots on blistered surface</term>
                                        <term>lips and teeth covered with sordes</term>
                                        <term>kidneys inflamed and suppurating</term>
                                        <term>peritoneum inflamed</term>
                                        <term>mesentery and its glands inflamed, some glands ulcerated</term>
                                        <term>in ileum glands of Peyer showed cicatrizing ulcerations</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                 
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00093">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 93.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="562">Private Daniel Plummer</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="636">Co. H, 33d Pa.</name>;
                                        age 23; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-10-02">Oct. 2, 1861</date>, with headache,
                                        diarrh&#339;a, loss of appetite and strength. He had
                                        been sick <date type="injury" when="1861-09-27">five days</date>, having had a chill and fever on each
                                        day.  A bath was given, with quinine at night. Next day his
                                        face was flushed, eyes injected, skin hot, dry and rough,
                                        tongue coated whitish-gray, pulse 101, full; he had pain in
                                        the head and back, slight deafness, tinnitus aurium,
                                        insomnia, confusion of thought and muttering; his bowels were tender and had been
                                        moved four times. Treatment&#8212;Dover's powder and
                                        quinine.  During the five following days his tongue became
                                        dry and brown, pulse less frequent, 84, countenance more
                                        anxious and prostration much increased; his bowels were
                                        moved about twice daily.  On the 8th the treatment was
                                        changed to turpentine, Dover's powder and whiskey-punch. A
                                        gallon of strongly acid urine, sp. gr. 1009, was passed on
                                        the 9th, but later in the disease the urine became alkaline.  A blister was applied to the abdomen on the 14th.  On the
                                        16th he craved apples, and next day had some appetite; the
                                        bowels were quiet, having been moved but once daily for
                                        several days back.  On the 18th gangrenous spots appeared on
                                        the blistered surface, which was dressed with chlorinated
                                        soda solution.  Three days later an erysipelatous redness
                                        extended downward to the thigh and the patient was in
                                        extremely low condition, lying on his back with his mouth
                                        and eyes open, unable to protrude his tongue, his lips and
                                        teeth covered with sordes and his body generally, except the
                                        face and neck, with vibices. The gangrenous blistered
                                        surface was treated with a solution of one drachm of nitrate
                                        of silver in one ounce of water, but without benefit.  His
                                        throat became sore on the 23d, and he died on the morning of
                                        <date type="death" when="1861-10-24">the 24th</date>.  <hi
                                                rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: The
                                        lungs were congested; the heart, liver, spleen and pancreas
                                        healthy; the kidneys inflamed and suppurating. The
                                        peritoneum was inflamed; the mucous membrane of the stomach
                                        unusually corrugated; the mesentery and its glands
                                        inflamed&#8212;of the latter some were ulcerated; the
                                        glands of Peyer in the ileum showed cicatrizing
                                                ulcerations.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name
                                                  type="hospital" key="156">Seminary
                                                Hospital</name>, Georgetown, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
