<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e24320">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Miller, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e24320</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">629</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
     <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>amputations in the foot</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the foot</term>
     <term>wounded in foot</term>
     <term>amputation at tarsus</term>
     <term>Chopart's amputation performed on field</term>
     <term>gangrene</term>
     <term>enormous leg abscess</term>
     <term>severe pain, incision into periosteum giving exit to confined pus</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>supplied with artificial foot</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>

   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 924.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1407">Private J.
     Miller</name>, <name type="organization" key="437">Co. E, 6th Pennsylvania Reserves</name>,
    aged 20 years, was wounded in the right foot, fracturing the bone, at <name type="BATTLE"
     key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>.
    He was admitted to the field hospital of the 3d division, First Corps. <name type="person"
     key="xx">Surgeon C. Bower</name>, <name type="organization" key="437">6th Pennsylvania
     Reserves</name>, reported that he performed "amputation at the tarsus" <date type="operation"
     when="1862-12-13">on the day of the injury</date>. <name type="person" key="1406">Acting
     Assistant Surgeon H. Hirschfield</name> reported the progress of the case as follows: "The
    patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name> at Washington
     <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-23">ten days after being wounded</date>. Chopart's
    amputation had been performed on the field. On December 27th, when the case was first seen by
    me, there was much suppuration and the wound seemed to be drawn open, by the tendo-achillis. I
    applied a splint to correct the tension and at first used cold water and afterwards warm
    dressings; tonics and stimulants were administered. By January 20, 1863, the wound had nearly
    healed and dry lint and bandages were used. A small abscess had appeared at the ankle and had
    been opened. About February 15th this opening became gangrenous and the leg in this locality
    swelled up to an enormous size the abscess, which originally was only two inches long, growing
    into a large sore of circular shape three and a half inches in diameter. All the tissues and
    even the periosteum were destroyed. Healthy granulations, however, were finally brought out, and
    the part was healing but could not close up on account of necrosis in part of the tibia. While
    the healing process of the neighboring parts was progressing favorably, erysipelas set in and
    spread from the foot to nearly up to the knee, being attended by excessive sloughing of the
    original abscess. This soon passed off, however, and after a few days the wound again became
    healthy in appearance, decreased in extent, and the leg resumed its natural size rapidly. Things
    now went on favorably again <date type="operation" when="1863">for a time</date>, when severe
    pain indicated another collection of matter above the line of the affected tibia and towards the
    middle of the leg, which was relieved by an incision two inches in length into the periosteum,
    giving free exit to the confined pus. This last opening healed up readily, and by <date
     type="operation" when="1863-06-01">June 1st</date> nature had completed the exfoliation of the
    cortical substance of the tibia, which I removed four inches in length. The wound now healed up
    very rapidly, but several days afterwards gangrene re-appeared and continued up to June 10th.
    Poultices were continued in the mean time and the treatment was adapted to the exigencies of the
    case. During the progress of the case the patient's general condition, which was very good now,
    had varied according to the several complications, being sometimes very low and prostrated from
    hectic and diarrh&#339;a, but always reacting rapidly. On June 14th healthy granulations once
    more showed themselves, and by July 8th the wound had closed up to the size of a two-shilling
    piece. Ten days later it was healed entirely, the patient's general condition being excellent."
    He was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-09-04">September 4,
     1863</date>, and pensioned, and <date type="pension" when="1864-09">one year afterwards</date>
    he was supplied with an artificial foot by the <name type="organization" key="xx">Palmer Arm and
     Leg Co.</name> of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>. The pensioner was paid <date
     type="pension" when="1880-06-04">June 4, 1880</date>.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001656.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 361.&#8212;<hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>HOPART'S amputation
     of the foot. [After <hi rend="initialcap">E</hi>SMARCH.]</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
