<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20111">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">C&#8212;&#8212;, Thomas P. C.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e20111</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">568</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term>
          <term>operations on the chest</term>
          <term>excisions</term>
          <term>excisions of portions of the ribs</term>
          <term>excision or removal of portions of the ribs</term>
          <term>fracture of eleventh rib</term>
          <term>fracture of transverse process of eleventh dorsal vertebra</term>
          <term>ball entered posterior thorax</term>
          <term>lower lobe of lung collapsed</term>
          <term>h&#230;morrhage from posterior thorax wound, spat blood, difficulty breathing</term>
          <term>succumbed from dysentery</term>
          <term>autopsy performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private <hi
            rend="italic">Thomas P. C. C</hi>&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization"
          key="xxx">Co. A, 9th Mississippi Regiment</name>, aged 19 years, was wounded near <name
          type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-11-05"
          >November 5th, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the posterior portion of the
        left thorax, passed between the tenth and eleventh ribs, fracturing the latter, as well as
        the transverse process of the eleventh dorsal vertebra. He was treated in a Confederate
        hospital at <name type="place">Richmond</name>, and, on <date type="transfer"
          when="1865-05-06">May 6th, 1865</date>, was admitted into the hospital at <name
          type="place">Point Lookout, Maryland</name>. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-07-24"
          >July 24th</date>, he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square
          Hospital</name>, Washington, and, on <date type="transfer" when="1865-08-17">August
          17th</date>, to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>. The patient
        stated that on the reception of the injury he had a free h&#230;morrhage from the wound,
        spat blood, and had great difficulty of breathing, but that he was doing well until about
        the middle of June, when he was attacked with diarrh&#339;a. On his admission to <name
          type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name> he was terribly emaciated&#8212;almost a
        living skeleton. On <date type="operation" when="1865-08-18">the 18th</date>, the ball,
        which had lodged behind the tenth rib about one and a half inches from the wound of
        entrance, was removed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon William F.
          Morris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> In spite of the free
        administration of beef tea and stimulants, with astringents and injections of nitrate of
        silver for his dysentery, the patient sank rapidly, and died <date type="death"
          when="1865-08-20">August 20th, 1865</date>. An autopsy was made thirteen hours after
        death. There were strong pleuritic adhesions between both lungs and the walls of the thorax.
        The lungs were healthy except the lower lobe of the left lung, which was collapsed and
        firmly adherent to the walls of the chest near the seat of injury, in such a manner as to
        form a cavity of considerable dimensions between the wall of the chest and the lung
        substance. The liver and kidneys were fatty, the spleen healthy, the intestines shrunken and
        pallid, but everywhere healthy except the descending colon and rectum, where the solitary
        glands were much enlarged and had ulcerated. They presented the appearance of small cysts,
        the size of a pea, with minute circular openings at the summit, and contained a transparent
        gelatinous mass. The pathological specimen is represented in the accompanying wood-cut (<hi
          rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 271). The wound of entrance in the fractured rib is well
        rounded, and the two are firmly agglutinated by osseous deposit. The preparation was
        contributed, with a history of the case, by the operator, <name type="person" key="xxx"
          >Assistant Surgeon W. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S.
          A.</name>
      </p>

      <figure><graphic url="cww.001486.001"/><head>
        <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 271.&#8212;Posterior halves of tenth and eleventh left ribs,
        showing a consolidated fracture by a conoidal ball, which is attached. <hi rend="italic"
          >Spec</hi>. 1561, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
