<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2589">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Felter, George</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e2589</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">225</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>seminary hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>delirium</term> 
                                        <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
                                        <term>rose-spots</term> 
                                        <term>vibices and bed-sores</term> 
                                        <term>pneumonic complications</term>
                                        <term>acute iliac tenderness</term>
                                        <term>tympanites</term>
                                        <term>constipation</term>
                                        <term>enlargement of the thyroid gland</term>
                                        <term>dullness</term>
                                        <term>typhoid cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>pneumonic complications</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00036">
                        
                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 36.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Delirium; diarrh&#339;a; rose-spots, vibices
                                                and bed-sores; pneumonic complications delay
                                                convalescence until after the 40th
                                                day.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="496">Private George Felter</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="619">Co. H, 9th Pa.
                                                        Vols.</name>; age 22; was taken sick about <date type="injury" when="1861-09-01">Sept. 1,
                                                                1861</date>, and admitted on <date type="admit"
                                                                        when="1861-09-19">the 19th</date> with typhoid fever.
                                        The notes of the case on the 20th are: pulse 96; skin hot
                                        and dry; high fever; tongue coated white in centre, red at
                                        tip and edges, slightly moist; acute iliac tenderness;
                                        tympanites; constipation; enlargement of the thyroid gland.
                                        Ordered: enema of soapsuds; emulsion of turpentine; Dover's
                                        powder at night. On the 21st: pulse 120, full and soft; skin
                                        hot and moist; tongue dark-red at the margins, dry and brown
                                        in the centre; characteristic rose-spots; no sudamina; less
                                        tympanites; tenderness of abdomen on pressure; borborygmus;
                                        subsultus; delirium; drowsiness; decubitus dorsal;
                                        respiration 30. Gave wine whey four times daily with
                                        beef-essence. On the 22nd morning: delirium; subsultus;
                                        pulse 118, full and soft; few rose-spots; skin hot and dry;
                                        tongue very red and moist; respirations hurried; submucous
                                        and sibilant r&#226;les in upper part of both lungs; decubitus
                                        dorsal; acute general abdominal tenderness; tympanites less;
                                        borborygmus; one stool. Ordered: one-fourth of a grain of
                                        morphia; cold applications to head. Evening: pulse 120; face
                                        flushed; skin hot and dry; tongue dry; rose-spots; high
                                        fever; delirium; deafness. No change took place until the
                                        24th, when there was some diarrh&#339;a. On the 25th the
                                        tongue became slightly moist and cleaner, the delirium gave
                                        place to <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice>, vibices appeared on the chest, the urine
                                        and feces were passed involuntarily and a large bed-sore
                                        formed over the sacrum. The tongue became again dry on the
                                        26th, and the lungs were found consolidated in their lower
                                        portions. On the 27th the pulse was 113 and strong, the face
                                        flushed, the skin hot and dry, the respirations 10, with
                                        submucous and sibilant r&#226;les in the upper part of the right
                                        lung and a short dry cough. A blister was applied to the
                                        upper part of the chest. The bowels were quiet on the 28th.
                                        The tongue became moist on the 29th, red at the tip and gray
                                        in the centre; the skin was warm, dry, and soft; the bowels
                                        were quiet, but there was tenderness on both sides, with
                                        tympanites and borborygmus; the sacral sore was healing and
                                        the patient rational. The chest was again blistered; tonics
                                        and stimulants were administered. The stools became
                                        involuntary on the 30th, with acute right iliac tenderness
                                        and some anxiety of expression; pulse 106; surface
                                        circulation sluggish; respirations 10; some cough and much
                                        dyspn&#339;a. The patient became restless on October 1.
                                        Vibices appeared on the abdomen on the 2d; some
                                        diarrh&#339;a occurred, the stools being involuntary;
                                        delirium occasionally returned at night. On the 4th there
                                        was some improvement in the chest symptoms. On the 7th the
                                        face was slightly flushed; the pulse 111, steady; the skin
                                        hot and dry, moist in some places, the tongue moist, red at
                                        tip, coated in centre; the bed-sores showing points of
                                        granulation; the stools involuntary at long intervals, with
                                        borborygmus and some tympanites but no tenderness;
                                        micturition involuntary. On the 8th, 9th and 10th the pulse
                                        fell respectively to 108, 106 and 100, one or two stools
                                        occurring daily with some tenderness&#8212;the skin
                                        continuing hot and dry, but the tongue becoming cleaner and
                                        its edges moist. On the 10th the eyes were bright and the
                                        countenance cheerful. The pulse fell to 90 on the 11th; the
                                        condition of the tongue improved and the appetite returned.
                                        On the 17th the tongue was clean and moist but redder than
                                        natural; the bowels were regular; the appetite good; a
                                        slight cough yet remained. The record, which is continued in
                                        detail up to the 27th, shows the occurrence of an occasional
                                        thin stool but the tongue preserved its clean and red
                                        condition, the appetite was good and the sleep sound at
                                        night; no further reference is made to the healing of the
                                        bed-sores. This patient was transferred to hospital at
                                        <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1861-12-20">December 20</date>. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
