<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41053">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Chambers, Stephen</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41053</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">166</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>diarrhœa and ascites</term>
       <term>globular cysts in choroid plexus, racemose appearance</term>
       <term>lobular emphysema of apex of right lung</term>
       <term>pericardium contained serum</term>
       <term>aorta presented spots of atheroma just above semilunar valves</term>
       <term>abdominal viscera agglutinated together and to abdominal parietes by adhesions</term>
       <term>jejunum stone-gray color, Peyer's patches pale and inconspicuous, summits of villi presented blackened points</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of large intestine dark-gray color, rectum dark dirty red</term>
       <term>ragged dark-green ulcer in cæcum</term>
       <term>large intestine had greenish exudation of lymph externally</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 358.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Stephen Chambers</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company F, 145th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-20">February 20, 1863</date>.  Diarrhœa and ascites.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-03-30">March 30th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-03-30">two hours after death</date>: Height five feet five inches and a half; body rigid and considerably emaciated. The brain was firm and weighed forty-seven ounces and three-quarters; there were several globular cysts in the choroid plexus, giving it a racemose appearance. The lungs were anæmic and bluish; there was slight lobular emphysema of the apex of the right lung, and in its posterior part a carnified spot which measured two inches by an inch, was of deep-purple color on section, and sank in water; a similar carnified spot was observed in the lower lobe, which was adherent posteriorly. The pulmonary pleura between the lobes was roughened by a number of minute whitish points of exudation. The upper lobe of the left lung was normal, but bound to the lower lobe by tough adhesions; its edge was also adherent to the pericardium; the right lung weighed fifteen ounces and three-quarters, the left fifteen and a quarter. The pericardium contained twenty-seven drachms of serum. The heart was flabby, its surface œdematous; there was no adipose tissue about it, and it contained no clots; the valves were healthy. The aorta presented several small whitish spots of atheroma just above the semilunar valves. The arteries of the body were filled with black blood. The abdominal viscera were agglutinated together and to the abdominal parietes by firm recent adhesions. The omentum was obliterated. The liver was congested, presented the nutmeg appearance, and weighed fifty-five ounces and a quarter. The spleen was rather firm, of a uniform dark-lake color on section, and weighed seven ounces and a quarter. The suprarenal capsules were rather dark colored. The right kidney was pale, of a light-ash color, its pelvis highly injected; it weighed five ounces; the left kidney was similar to the right, and weighed five ounces and three-quarters. The pancreas was normal, and weighed two ounces and a quarter. The mucous membrane of the œsophagus and stomach was pale; the duodenum yellowish; the jejunum of a stone-gray color; Peyer's patches were pale and inconspicuous; the solitary glands not observable: the summits of the villi, especially on the valvulæ, presented blackened points. The mucous membrane of the large intestine was of a dark-gray color; that of the rectum of a dark dirty red; the entire large intestine, externally, was irregularly contort with a greenish exudation of lymph. In the cæcum there was a ragged dark-green ulcer.—<name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>⃰</p>
   <p>⃰ September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief "<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>," to which the reader is referred.—(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
