<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30563">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Geary, John W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e30563</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="nk">Nathan Kumm</persName>  
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">830</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow treated on the expectant plan</term>
       <term>struck in foot, afterward more severe wound in elbow</term>
       <term>ball shattered olecranon and outer condyle, flattened itself against the latter</term>
       <term>battered projectile and bone splinters extracted</term>       
       <term>tolerable motion of elbow</term> 
       <term>again wounded at Chancellorsville</term>
       <term>subsequently elected Governor of Pennsylvania</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#nk" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1741.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Brigadier-General John W. Geary</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, was wounded at the engagement at <name type="battle" key="68">Cedar Mountain</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-09">August 9, 1862</date>. He was struck in the evening in the left foot, and afterward received a more severe wound in the left elbow, "but
    remained on the field until nine o'clock, when he was compelled to retire from exhaustion produced by pain and loss of blood."  (<hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>ATES, in <hi rend="italic">Hist. of Penna. Vols.</hi>, 1869, Vol. I, p. 427.)  His wounds were dressed at the field hospital of the 2d division, Second Corps, established by<name type="person" key="xxx"> Surgeon A. Ball</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">5th Ohio</name>, and he was sent to <name type="place">Culpeper</name> and thence to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>.  He was attended in quarters by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeons M. Clymer</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">B. A. Vanderkieft</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. David Ahl</name>. It was found that a conoidal musket ball had shattered the left olecranon and outer condyle, and had flattened itself against the latter. There had been
    considerable bleeding, and the joint was already swollen and tender. The battered projectile and some bone splinters were extracted, and the limb was put up in a felt trough or angular splint, a large fenestrum being cut out opposite the wound, and
    kept at rest at an angle of 130°. There was very considerable inflammatory reaction and copious suppuration; but the inflammation was kept within bounds and there was little destructive action in the tissues about the joint.  At the end of five
    weeks, it was practicable to commence passive motion, cautiously, and by <date type="duty" when="1862-09-25">September 25th</date> the General was able to rejoin the army, "with his arm still in a bandage" (<hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>ATES, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, p. 428), and took command of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">2d division, Twelfth Corps</name>.  He was again wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>; but served to the end of the war with very tolerable motion of the elbow.  He was subsequently elected Governor of <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name>, and died <date type="death" when="1873-02-09">February 9, 1873</date>, aged 53 years.</p>
   <p/> 
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
