<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3617">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">R&#8212;&#8212;, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e3617</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">59</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>miscellaneous injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>trephining</term>
                    <term>depression of parietal bone, depressed fragment of vitreous plate</term>
                    <term>general anesthetic, ether</term>
                    <term>wounded in street affray</term>
                    <term>wounds of head from thrown stones</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-09">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding,
                edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc2.0025">
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="222">Private John
                    R&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="162">Co. H, 2d Michigan
                    Volunteers</name>, aged 41 years, was wounded on <date type="injury"
                    when="1865-07-17">July 17th, 1865</date>, in a street affray, receiving four
                wounds of the head from stones thrown at him. He was admitted to <name
                    type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., on
                    <date type="admit" when="1865-07-18">the following day</date>. He was perfectly
                conscious, yet had marked contraction of the pupils, with accelerated pulse, and a
                tremulous voice. There was considerable ecchymosis about the orbits. The first wound
                examined was over the frontal eminence, and penetrated no further than the
                aponeurosis of the occipito-frontalis muscle. The second was in the centre of the
                coronal suture, and slightly denuded the pericranium. The third was in the right
                temporal region, and likewise was a scalp wound. The fourth was on the right
                parietal eminence; and, upon a close examination, it was discovered that a minute
                depression of the bone, half an inch in diameter, existed, evidently produced by a
                blow from the sharp edge of the stone. The patient was a stout, muscular man, in
                good health; he suffered no nausea, and little pain. He was <date type="operation"
                    when="1865-07-18">immediately</date> placed under the influence of ether, and
                    <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D.W. Bliss</name>, <name
                    type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, after shaving the scalp, made a
                crucial incision three inches in length, having the wound at the intersection of the
                incisions, and then, reflecting the flaps, applied the crown of a trephine and
                removed a disk of bone, which was found to include, with remarkable exactness, a
                depressed fragment of the vitreous plate. Between the diploe and depressed lamina
                there was a coagulum. The dura mater was uninjured. The wound was partly closed by
                four sutures, an opening being left over the perforation, into which a pledget of
                charpie was inserted. The patient recovered favorably from the an&#230;sthetic, and
                was put to bed and ordered to observe perfect quiet and strict diet. The case
                proceeded without an unfavorable symptom. On July 23d, the sutures were removed. On
                    <date when="1865-07-24">July 24th</date>, the compress of charpie was taken
                away, and a healthy granulating surface appeared beneath. These facts in regard to
                the case were reported by <name type="person" key="290">Assistant Surgeon Charles A.
                    Leale</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> The
                pathological specimen was presented to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army
                    Medical Museum</name> by the operator, and is represented in Photograph No. 87
                of the Surgical Section of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
                    Museum</name>, and in the accompanying wood-cut, (<hi rend="initialcap"
                >F</hi>IG. 24.) The disk is seven-eighths of an inch in diameter, and is slightly
                reduced in the illustration. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-08-24">August 24th,
                    1865</date>, the patient was transferred to Harper Hospital at <name
                    type="place">Detroit, Michigan</name>. The case continued to progress favorably,
                and the man recovered without a bad symptom. He was discharged from service on <date
                    type="servicedischarge" when="1865-09-08">September 8th, 1865</date>. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001361.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 24.&#8212;External and internal views of a button of
                bone removed for a depressed fracture by a blow from a stone.&#8212;<hi
                    rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1452, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head></figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
