<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e16616">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Sims, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e16616</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">394</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc> 
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>excisions at the knee joint for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions at the knee joint</term>
     <term>fatal instances of intermediary excision at the knee joint</term>
     <term>ball entered knee joint below patella on inner and anterior aspect, fractured inner
      condyle and opened joint, extracted four inches from point of entrance</term>
     <term>whole joint suppurating mass, pus far down under gastrocnemius and between the muscles of
      thigh</term>
     <term>lung infiltrated with pus, single large abscess upon surface of inferior lobe</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2014-07-21">corrected caption for figure</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-29">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 627.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal J.
     Sims</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B, 4th Ohio</name>,&#185; aged 23 years,
    was wounded at <name type="battle" key="77">Mine Run</name>, <date type="injury"
     when="1863-11-27">November 27, 1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered the right knee
    joint just below the patella, on the inner and anterior aspect, fracturing the inner condyle and
    opening the joint, passed downward and forward, and was extracted about four inches from point
    of entrance. He was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="501">Second Division
     Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-12-05"
     >December 5th</date>. &#34;At the time of admission the joint and thigh were very much inflamed
    and discharging pus copiously, and the man was much prostrated and terribly anxious as to the
    result of the wound. But after being washed and fed and otherwise cared for, he appeared much
    recruited. On <date type="operation" when="1863-12-08">the 8th of December</date> the operation
    of excision of the knee joint was performed by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E.
     Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who removed one inch of
    the femur and about one and a half inches of the tibia and fibula. The h&#230;morrhage was
    slight, but the condition of the tissues was not very satisfactory. The patient endured the
    operation well under the influence of chloroform, and reacted well. On the following day he
    complained of severe pain over the lung on the right side of the chest, which continued for
    several days. On the 10th, he had a severe chill at night, which was followed by two, more
    severe, on the 11th. Stimulants were freely given with raw eggs well beaten up, and beef essence
    for diet. He continued to have chills till the night of the 13th, when he was seized with a very
    severe one, from which he never rallied. He died on the morning of <date type="death"
     when="1863-12-14">December 14, 1863</date>. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination
    showed no attempt at repair, there being considerable sloughing, while on the inside of the
    thigh there were numerous small abscesses. The heart and left lung were healthy, but the right
    lung was infiltrated with pus, and a single large abscess appeared upon the surface of the
    inferior lobe. There was no pus nor abscess found in the liver, but it was very much
    softened.&#34; The history, with the <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> specimen, represented in
    the cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 246), was contributed to <name type="hospital"
     key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="134">the operator</name>. <name
     type="person" key="288">Surgeon <choice>
      <sic>J. B. Brinton</sic>
      <corr>J. H. Brinton</corr>
     </choice></name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who examined the limb
    two days after the patient's decease, found &#34;the whole joint one suppurating mass; pus
    extending up and down, far down under the gastrocnemius and up between the muscles on the inside
    of the thigh; a long abscess in the sheath of the vessels, extending up to the middle of the
    thigh; small clot in femoral artery, thin and three inches long; none in femoral vein;
    surrounding tissues of vessels hardened in some places where pus had not readied; long membrane
    of femoral vein of dirty gray color and softened; clot in saphena vein.&#34;</p>
   <p>&#185; See <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, War Department, S. G. O.. Washington, 1865,
    p. 59; <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ULBERTSON (<hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>.), <hi rend="italic"
     >Excision of the Larger Joints of the Extremities</hi>. Prize Essay, in <hi rend="italic"
     >Trans. Am. Med. Assoc.</hi>, Philadelphia, 1876. Supplement to Vol. XXVII, p. 184, Case
    13.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001616.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 245.&#8212;Bones of right knee excised. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4212.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
