<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18906">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">D&#8212;&#8212;, Thomas</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e18906</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">445-446</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the spine</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the spine</term>
          <term>gunshot injuries of the lumbar vertebr&#230;</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the apophyses of the lumbar spine</term>
          <term>musket-ball fractures of the third lumbar vertebra</term>
          <term>ball lodged in body of third lumbar vertebra</term>
          <term>lower end of kidney injured</term>
          <term>peritonitis</term>
          <term>collection of pus where ball impinged against peritoneum</term>
          <term>third lumbar vertebra fractured by conoidal ball</term>
          <term>chipped superior articular process of fifth lumbar vertebra</term>
          <term>fractured spinous process and transverse process of fourth lumbar vertebra</term>
          <term>tetanus with opisthotonos and trismus</term>
          <term>necropsy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-20">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private Thomas
          D&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization">Co. F, 1st Michigan
          Sharp-shooters</name>, aged 19 years, received a gunshot wound of the lumbar region, at
          <name type="BATTLE" key="254">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-24"
          >June 24th, 1864</date>. He was admitted, on <date type="admit" when="1864-06-24">the same
          day</date>, to the field hospital of the 3d division, Ninth Corps, and, on <date
          type="transfer" when="1864-07-01">July 1st</date>, sent to <name type="hospital" key="175"
          >Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington. Stimulants were freely administered, with
        subcutaneous injections of sulphate of morphia. Tetanus, in the form of opisthotonos and
        trismus, appeared on <date type="injury" when="1864-07-04">the 4th</date>. Death resulted on
          <date type="death" when="1864-07-05">July 5th, 1864</date>. At the necropsy, a conoidal
        ball was found to have entered on the left side, over the posterior part of the crest of the
        ilium, passed upward and inward, and lodged in the left side of the body of the third lumbar
        vertebra. The anterior crural nerve was injured, as was also the lower end of the left
        kidney. There was limited peritonitis, and a small collection of pus, say a drachm, about
        where the ball impinged against the peritoneum, at lower end of kidney. The intestines were
        not injured. The pathological specimen is No. 2762, Section I, A. M. M., and was
        contributed, with a history of the case, by <name type="person" key="459">Assistant Surgeon
          George A. Mursick</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
      </p>
      <p> The adjoining cut represents the lumbar vertebr&#230;, with the third fractured by a
        conoidal ball, which is attached. The missile appears to have passed from the left directly
        through the intervertebral notch between the third and fourth vertebr&#230;, chipping the
        superior articular process of the fifth and the adjacent portion of the spinous process of
        the fourth, fracturing the left transverse process of the fourth, and emerging through the
        body of that vertebra on the right side. Life continued long enough for incipient caries to
        present itself. The specimen was contributed to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army
          Medical Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>, <name
          type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, without an history. A comparison of the
        specimen with the registers and case-books of <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver
          Hospital</name>, and with <name type="person" key="70">Dr. Lidell</name>'s excellent paper
          <hi rend="italic">On Injuries of the Spine</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Amer. Jour. of Med.
          Sci.</hi>, October, 1864, Vol. XLVIII), does not permit a reference of this specimen to
        any of the histories recorded there. It corresponds closely to several of the recorded
        cases, and more than one history has been attached to it; but some vital discrepancy between
        the history and specimen has been subsequently detected. The history of the case that
        compares most closely with the specimen represents the patient as alive a fortnight after
        the preparation was on the shelves of the Museum; and, in other abstracts, where dates
        agree, there is discordance as to position and extent of lesions. The specimen was received
        from <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, <date type="specimen"
          when="1864-06-18">June 18th, 1864</date>. </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001450.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 198.&#8212;Lumbar vertebr&#230;, the third fractured by a
          musket ball, which is attached. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2532, Sect. I, A. M.
          M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
