<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41127">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ryckman, Samuel</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41127</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">173</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>left lung apex was mass of tubercle the size of walnut</term>
       <term>pericardium contained fluid</term>
       <term>liver firm and fatty</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of lower ileum thin and congested, valvul&#230; conniventes almost obliterated, Peyer's patches dull-slate color but not prominent or ulcerated</term>       
       <term>large intestine extensively ulcerated from c&#230;cum to anus, some deep ulcers with irregular outlines and dark blue-stone colored bases</term>
       <term>transverse colon ulceration very superficial</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 380.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Samuel Ryckman</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company C, 6th Michigan cavalry</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-07-30">July 30, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-10-27">October 27th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-10-28">sixteen hours after death</date>: Height five feet ten inches; no rigor mortis; emaciation extreme. The brain was somewhat soft; it weighed forty-seven ounces and a half. The mucous membrane of the trachea was pale. The right lung weighed fifteen ounces and three-quarters; its upper lobes were healthy, the lower lobe somewhat congested, and a tenacious mucus exuded from the bronchial tubes on pressure. The left lung weighed fourteen ounces and a half; in its apex was a mass of tubercle the size of a walnut, which was just beginning to soften; the lower lobe was in a state of venous congestion, the mucous membrane of its bronchial tubes inflamed; the bronchial glands were large, soft and black. The pericardium contained two drachms of fluid. The heart was healthy; it weighed seven ounces and a quarter. The liver was of firm consistence, pale-yellow color, and fatty; it weighed fifty-seven ounces and three-quarters; the gall-bladder contained ten drachms of bile. The spleen was firm, of a dark-mulberry color on section, and weighed ten ounces and a half. The pancreas weighed two ounces and three-quarters. The kidneys were slightly congested; the right weighed five ounces and a quarter, the left three and three-quarters. The upper portion of the small intestine was healthy; in the lower part of the ileum the mucous membrane was thin, soft, and congested; the valvul&#230; conniventes were almost obliterated; Peyer's patches were of a dull-slate color, but not prominent or ulcerated. The large intestine was extensively ulcerated from the c&#230;cum to the anus; some of the ulcers were very deep, their outlines exceedingly irregular, their bases of a dark blue-stone color; no solitary glands were visible, and no diphtheritic membrane was present. In the transverse colon the ulceration was very superficial.&#8212;<name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>&#8432; </p>
   <p>&#8432; September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief &#34;<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>,&#34; to which the reader is referred.&#8212;(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
