<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41305">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Quackenbush, Peter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41305</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">184</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Carver Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>pain in right side, <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion, other evidence of pleurisy with effusion</term>
       <term>pleuritic adhesions, old on left and recent on right side</term>
       <term>left lower lobe greatly congested</term>
       <term>right pleural cavity about half full of fluid</term>
       <term>pericardium contained fluid</term>
       <term>liver enlarged and fatty</term>
       <term>near ileocæcal valve Peyer's patches thickened and spongy at their centres</term>
       <term>in ascending colon large ulcers with ragged edges and black pigment</term>
       <term>ulcers less numerous and smaller in transverse colon, again larger in descending colon</term>
       <term>above ileocæcal valve Peyer's patch thickened, with tumefaction of solitary follicles</term>
       <term>transverse colon presented minute follicular ulcers</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>The notes were forwarded, with the specimens, to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> from <name type="hospital" key="167"><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ARVER <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon Oliver A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 426.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Peter Quackenbush</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 111th New York volunteers</name>; age 48; admitted from the depot hospital of the 2d Army Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-07-05">July 5, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  The patient had a senile look, and was considerably emaciated; pulse about 80; tongue moist but covered with a gray fur; anorexia; severe diarrhœa.  He continued about the same until July 10th, when he began to improve, the diarrhœa being somewhat checked and his appetite better.  July 26th, he was attacked by a severe pain in the right side, with <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion, and other evidence of pleurisy with effusion.  The diarrhœa now became aggravated, the anorexia returned, and the patient died <date type="death" when="1864-08-01">August 1st</date>.  Treatment: Opiates and astringents were freely given to relieve the diarrhœa, and stimulants were administered from the first. When pleurisy set in a blister was applied to the right side of the chest. Diet: Milk, beef-essence, &amp;c.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-08-01">four hours after death</date>: The left lung was bound firmly to the chest by old pleuritic adhesions; its lower lobe was greatly congested; pleuritic adhesions, which seemed quite recent, existed also on the right side; the posterior portion of the right lung was in a state of hypostatic congestion; the right pleural cavity was about half full of fluid. The heart appeared to be normal; a partially washed clot was found in its right side; the pericardium contained about three ounces of fluid. The liver was enlarged, pale, and apparently fatty; the gall bladder was filled with viscid bile. The spleen was enlarged and very soft. The kidneys were of about the normal size; their cortical substance appeared very pale. The mucous membrane of the stomach was thickened and congested; that of the small intestine was also congested, especially within three feet of the ileocæcal valve, where Peyer's patches were considerably thickened and presented a spongy appearance at their centres. In the ascending colon there were several large ulcers with ragged edges, which contained a quantity of black pigment; the mucous membrane was considerably thickened and softened; in the transverse colon these ulcers were less numerous and smaller; in the descending colon they again became larger.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon O. P. Sweet</name>.  [Nos. 353 to 355, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  No. 353 is a portion of the ileum taken just above the ileocæcal valve, showing a slightly thickened Peyer's patch and some tumefaction of the solitary follicles.  No. 354 is a portion of the ascending colon, presenting a number of oval ulcers with abraded edges, varying from the size of a pin-head to that of a five-cent piece.  No. 355 is a portion of the transverse colon, presenting a number of minute follicular ulcers.]</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
