<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e9572">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Wisner, Walter</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e9572</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">387</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>   
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>tracheal mucous membrane deep dull-purplish red</term>
                                        <term>trachea and bronchi contained thin bloody fluid instead of normal secretion</term>
                                        <term>lymphatic glands at bifurcation of trachea large and engorged with black blood</term>
                                        <term>intestines diseased throughout</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches enlarged, elevated, and ulcerated, no ulcers larger than head of pin</term>
                                        <term>solitary glands also affected, mucous membrane near valve modulated with shot-like eminences</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of end of ileum dark-red color</term>
                                        <term></term>
                                        <term></term>
                                        <term></term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00194">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 194.&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="722">Private Walter
                                        Wisner</name>, <name type="organization" key="232">Co. F,
                                                6th Mich. Cav.</name>; age 28; was admitted <date
                                                type="admit" when="1863-07-30">July 30, 1863</date>,
                                        with typhoid fever, and died <date type="death"
                                                when="1863-08-03">August 3</date>.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-08-04">eighteen hours after
                                        death</date>: The brain weighed fifty-three ounces; both lobes of
                                        the cerebrum were highly congested, especially in their
                                        superior and anterior portions, which were in part of a
                                        brilliant crimson color. The tracheal mucous membrane was of
                                        a deep dull-purplish red; the trachea and bronchi contained
                                        a thin bloody fluid instead of the normal secretion; the
                                        veins under the mucous membrane of the larynx were
                                        distended; the lymphatic glands at the bifurcation of the
                                        trachea were large, soft and engorged with black blood. The
                                        lungs were of a delicate pink color; the external and
                                        lateral portions of the upper lobes and the whole of the
                                        lower lobes were doughy, semi-solidified and engorged with
                                        dark blood mixed with a frothy bronchial secretion; the
                                        right lung weighed twenty-five ounces, the left twenty-four
                                        ounces. The cavities of the heart were free from clots,
                                        except a very thin wafer-like formation on the tricuspid
                                        valve. The liver was flabby and somewhat congested; the
                                        spleen, sixteen ounces, was grayish-purple in color and
                                        unusually firm. The intestines were diseased throughout; the
                                        mucous membrane of the upper portion was flaccid, softened
                                        and easily torn, the valvul&#230; conniventes of an
                                        orange-ochre color; Peyer's patches were enlarged, elevated
                                        above the surrounding mucous membrane, whitish in color and
                                        ulcerated, none of the ulcerated points being larger than
                                        the head of a pin; the solitary glands were also affected
                                        and, in the neighborhood of the valve, the mucous membrane
                                        was completely modulated with shot-like eminences; the
                                        mucous membrane of the last six feet of the ileum, which was
                                        the part chiefly involved, was of a dark-red color and its
                                        veins were very prominent. The kidneys were slightly
                                        congested, soft and flaccid.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg.
                                                  Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization"
                                                  key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital"
                                                  key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington,   D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
