<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e16482">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Hays, G. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e16482</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">392</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>excisions at the knee joint for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions at the knee joint</term>
     <term>fatal instances of intermediary excision at the knee joint</term>
     <term>wounded in both knees</term>
     <term>ball fractured condyles of the femur and patella of left knee</term>
     <term>amputation at lower third of left thigh performed in field</term>
     <term>ball fractured patella and denuded condyles of femur and head of tibia of right
      knee</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 619.—<name type="person" key="1215">Corporal G. W.
     Hays</name>, <name type="organization" key="162">Co. K, 2d Michigan</name>, aged 19 years, was
    wounded in both knees, at <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-17">June 17, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B.
     Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported: "He was
    admitted to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-06-20">June 20th</date>, suffering from amputation at the lower third
    of the thigh, performed on the field for a shot wound of the knee joint by a ball, which
    fractured the condyles of the femur and the patella. The right knee was also wounded, a ball
    entering the joint, fracturing the patella, and denuding the condyles of the femur and the head
    of the tibia. Extensive suppuration followed in the right knee, and an abscess burrowed half way
    up the thigh; the joint itself became entirely disorganized and much swollen." On <date type="operation" when="1864-06-24">June 24th</date>, resection of about two-thirds of the
    condyles of the femur, with the entire patella and the articular face of the tibia, was
    performed by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> Sulphuric ether was used as the anaesthetic. The
    stump of the left thigh progressed very satisfactorily towards healing, while the resected joint
    commenced to fill up with healthy granulations also and looked well in other respects. Profuse
    suppuration of healthy looking pus, however, continued. The constitutional treatment was mainly
    directed towards supporting the strength of the patient, and consisted of stimulants, tonics,
    and nourishing diet. The right thigh and leg were supported and kept in place by means of a wide
    board, to which a bag of bran was attached and so arranged as to embrace the parts on either
    side, it being readily adjusted and kneaded to suit the manipulations during dressing. The
    entire extremity, from the foot to the great trochanter, was confined in a Scultetus' bandage.
    The patient did tolerably well up to June 30th, from which date he became drowsy and was only
    waked with difficulty. He continued so, with intervals of wakefulness, until his death, which
    occurred on <date type="death" when="1864-07-02">July 2, 1864</date>, from exhaustion. There
    were no pyæmic symptoms. The <choice>
     <orig>exsected</orig>
     <reg>excised</reg>
    </choice> patella and condyles of the femur were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="158">the operator</name> and are represented in
    the cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 244).³</p>
   <p>³ <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, War Department, S. G. O., Washington, 1865, p.
    59; <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ULBERTSON (<hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">Excision of the Larger Joints of the Extremities</hi>. Prize Essay, in <hi rend="italic">Transact. Am. Med. Assoc.</hi>, 1876. Supplement to Vol. XXVII, p. 184, Case 17.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001615.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 244.—The patella and condyles of the right femur.
      <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3046.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
