<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41839">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Franklin, Robert</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41839</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">259</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Freedman's Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>mulatto</term>
       <term>consumption</term>
       <term>lungs coated with lymph, contained tubercles and vomic&#230;, lobes firmly interadherent</term>
       <term>fluid in pleural cavities</term>
       <term>heart large and covered with excess adipose tissue, aorta atheromatous</term>
       <term>lower surface of liver dark-green and contained miliary tubercles, gall-bladder empty</term>
       <term>spleen contained tubercles</term>
       <term>ileum had large scooped-out tubercular ulcers, deposits of tubercle on peritoneal surface opposite ulcers</term>
       <term>tubercular ulcers in c&#230;cum and vermiform appendix</term>
       <term>ascending and transverse colon had scooped-out ulcers with irregular edges and penetrated to peritoneum</term>       
       <term>large ulcers of ileum, hypertrophied villi around edges of ulcers, tubercular deposits on peritoneal surface corresponding with ulcers</term>
       <term>abdominal parietes dark-green color</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-24">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>One of eight cases observed at the <name type="hospital" key="440"><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>REEDMAN'S <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., during 1865, 1866, and 1867.&#8432;  In none of them were the patients soldiers. Five are of interest as examples of tubercular ulceration of the intestines. Besides the specimens from these cases, several other examples of tubercular ulceration of the intestines are preserved at <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, which were obtained from autopsies of colored women who died at the same hospital during the period mentioned. . . . In all of them extensive tubercular deposits were found in the lungs and other organs. Most of the specimens are portions of the ileum with tubercular ulcers of the mucous membrane and miliary tubercles on the peritoneal surface opposite:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 835.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Robert Franklin</name>; mulatto; age 33; admitted <date type="admit" when="1866-02-03">February 3, 1866</date>.  Consumption.  Nothing of special interest was developed in the progress of the case.  Died, <date type="death" when="1866-03-29">March 29th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1866-03-30">twenty hours after death</date>: Height six feet; approximate weight 160 pounds; a stout muscular man; rigor mortis well marked; no emaciation; abrasions on the lower extremities. The brain weighed forty-eight ounces; its membranes were slightly congested; there were four drachms of fluid in each lateral ventricle; the choroid plexus was congested, the pineal gland enlarged and contained calcareous deposits; the substance of the brain was slightly softened; the cerebellum was also somewhat softened; in the posterior foss&#230; of the cranium there was half an ounce of fluid. The right lung was coated with croupous lymph, congested, and contained much crude tubercle and a few vomic&#230;; its lobes were firmly interadherent; it weighed twenty ounces; there were six ounces of fluid in the right pleural cavity; the left lung was slightly adherent to the diaphragm, its lobes interadherent; its lower lobe was hepatized, its upper lobe congested; the lung contained a small amount of tubercles; it weighed thirty-five ounces; the left pleural cavity contained four ounces of fluid. The pericardial sac contained five ounces of serum. The heart was large and covered with an excessive amount of adipose tissue; its valves were very dark and congested; the organ was very fatty and weighed thirteen ounces; the aorta atheromatous. The liver weighed seventy-six ounces; its upper surface was normal in color, its lower surface dark-green and contained a few miliary tubercles; the gall-bladder was empty. The spleen contained a small quantity of tubercles, was very firm, and weighed fourteen ounces. The pancreas was of a greenish color and very soft; it weighed five ounces. The kidneys were very fatty and weighed eight ounces each. The mucous membrane of the stomach was thickened. The duodenum and jejunum were normal. The ileum presented a number of large scooped-out tubercular ulcers; on the peritoneal surface opposite the ulcers were deposits of tubercle. The c&#230;cum and vermiform appendix exhibited a few tubercular ulcers. In the ascending and transverse colon there were a few scooped-out ulcers with irregular edges, which penetrated to the peritoneal coat. The large intestine was eight feet long, the small intestine thirty-three feet. The abdominal parietes were of a dark-greenish color.&#8212;<name type="person" key="3420">Hospital Steward Samuel S. Bond</name>.   [No. 774, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, is from this case.  The specimen is a portion of the ileum with several large ulcers; the villi around the edges of the ulcers are hypertrophied. There are tubercular deposits on the peritoneal surface corresponding with the ulcers.]</p>
   <p>&#8432; During this period two of the hospital stewards on duty in <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, <name type="person" key="3421">D. S. Lamb</name> and <name type="person" key="3420">S. S. Bond</name>, were frequently sent to the <name type="hospital" key="440">Freedman's Hospital</name> for the purpose of making autopsies. A considerable number of specimens illustrative of the diseases of the freedmen were thus obtained.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
