<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31215">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Fisher, R.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31215</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ee">Emily Edwards</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">564</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
       <term>excisions at the shoulder</term> 
       <term>excisions of the head and portions of the shaft of the humerus</term>
       <term>primary excisions of the upper extremity of the humerus for shot injury</term> 
       <term>successful operations</term>
       <term>excised the head and part of shaft of humerus</term>
       <term>excision of shoulder joint from gunshot wound</term> 
       <term>four inches of upper end of humerus removed, arm useless</term>
       <term>ball entered breast near fourth rib, passed diagonally through lung and shoulder joint</term>       
       <term>phthisis pulmonalis</term>
       <term>tuberculosis</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#ee" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1540.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal R. Fisher</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 7th New York Heavy Artillery</name>, aged 32 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-08">June 8, 1864</date>. He was admitted to a Second Corps hospital, and, on <date type="operation" when="1864-06-10">the 10th</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. W. Wishart</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">140th Pennsylvania</name>, excised the head and one inch of the shaft of the humerus by a straight incision through the middle of the deltoid. The patient was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-12">the 12th</date>, and was finally discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-05-25">May 25, 1865</date>. <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, noted on his discharge papers: "Excision of right shoulder joint from gunshot wound. <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon J. H. Armsby</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of Ira Harris' Hospital, <name type="place">Albany</name>, contributed to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> a photograph of <name type="person" key="xxx">Fisher</name>, taken at <name type="place">Albany</name>, represented in the cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 436), and also specimen No. 384, Section I, A. M. M. This specimen consists of a cast of the right thorax and arm, eleven months after the excision of four inches from the upper extremity of the humerus. The cicatrix is six inches in length, is parallel with the long axis of the arm, and has split the deltoid. The position whence the head of the humerus was removed is marked by a decided impression.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner R. L. Rea</name>, of <name type="place">Chicago</name>, <date type="pension" when="1866-12-17">December 17, 1866</date>, reported: "Had four inches of the upper end of the right humerus removed; arm useless." The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Chicago Board</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Drs. W. A. Knox</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">J. M. Woodworth</name>, and <name type="person" key="xxx">S. J. Jones</name>, <date type="pension" when="1870-06-01">June 1, 1870</date>, report: "Resection of four inches of the right humerus, including the head. No increase from this cause, but the applicant is in the last stage of tuberculosis, which was probably brought about by exposure in the service.  Fisher died <date type="death" when="1870-07-24">July 24, 1870</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. W. R. Marsh</name>, formerly Surgeon <name type="organization" key="xxx">2d Iowa</name>, testifies "that Fisher's death was caused by phthisis pulmonalis supervening upon a gunshot wound, etc., that the cicatrix of said wound indicates that the ball entered the right breast near the fourth rib and passed diagonally through the right lung and through the shoulder joint."</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001719.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 436.—Cicatrix one year after excision at the shoulder.</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
