<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41011">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wray, M. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e41011</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">162</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>&#339;dema of legs</term>
       <term>measles</term>
       <term>pericardium contained two ounces of fluid</term>
       <term>valvul&#230; conniventes in duodenum and jejunum not well developed</term>
       <term>solitary glands and glands of Peyer appeared normal in ileum</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 347.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private M. H. Wray</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company H, 136th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 35; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-19">February 19, 1863</date>.  Diarrh&#339;a.  This patient was sent to field hospital in <name type="place">Virginia</name> several months ago with &#339;dema of the legs; subsequently he had an attack of measles, and this was followed by diarrh&#339;a. When admitted he was extremely emaciated, complained of pain and tenderness over the abdomen; had frequent stools; pulse scarcely perceptible; skin cold and cadaverous; tongue moist and free from any fur; feet cold.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-02-25">February 25th</date>.  Treatment: Blue mass and opium, Dover's powder, &#38;c.  Diet: Boiled milk, toast and tea, beef-tea, brandy.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-02-26">nineteen hours after death</date>: Height five feet nine inches; no rigor mortis. The brain weighed fifty-five ounces and a half; it was full of blood, and the vessels of the pia mater were injected. The right lung weighed twelve ounces and a half, the left eleven ounces; both lungs contained an excess of black pigment, and were congested hypostatically. The heart weighed seven ounces and three-quarters, and contained mixed clots which weighed two ounces. The pericardium contained two ounces of fluid resembling mucilage of acacia. The liver weighed thirty-eight ounces, was full of blood, of a reddish coffee-color and firm consistence, the acini indistinct; the gall-bladder contained two drachms of a very viscid and dark-green bile. The spleen weighed two ounces and three-quarters, was of a dark-red color and normal <choice><sic>con-consistence</sic><corr>consistence</corr></choice>; it contained a small nodule of cheesy matter. The pancreas weighed two ounces and a half. The suprarenal capsules were very small and tough. The left kidney weighed four ounces and a quarter, the right four ounces; they were both very dark colored and tough. The stomach was slightly congested in the fundus and toward the pyloric orifice; its mucous lining was soft. The duodenal glands were slightly enlarged. The valvul&#230; conniventes in the duodenum and jejunum were not well developed; the upper part of the jejunum was congested, the lower part of a light slate-color; the solitary glands were enlarged; the mucous membrane of the ileum was soft, and deeply congested, but both the solitary glands and the glands of Peyer appeared to be normal. The mucous membrane of the c&#230;cum was soft and dark colored. Congested patches were noticed at the splenic and sigmoid flexures of the colon; in the latter the mucous membrane was brownish-red.   <name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
