<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8312">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Ruoss, G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8312</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">183-184</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball entered anterior outer aspect of thigh below great trochanter, comminuted upper and
      middle thirds of femur, escaped posteriorly near middle of gluteal fold</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>erysipelas, commenced near wound, spread over entire surface of leg and foot</term>
     <term>pus formed on thigh above knee, opened to sinus connecting with seat of fracture</term>
     <term>extensive periostitis</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 373.—<name type="person" key="1019">Private G.
     Ruoss</name>, <name type="organization" key="240">Co. G, 7th New York</name>, aged 27 years,
    was wounded near <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-31">March 31, 1865</date>, and admitted to the field hospital of the 1st
    division, Second Corps, where <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon F. M. Hammond</name>, <name type="organization" key="364">126th New York</name>, noted: "Shot fracture of right thigh." On
     <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-01">the day following the injury</date> the wounded man was
    sent to the Depot Hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name>, and <date type="transfer" when="1865-04">several days afterwards</date> he was conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where he entered <name type="hospital" key="174">Campbell
     Hospital</name>, and subsequently <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>.
     <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported his admission to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood
     Hospital</name>
    <date type="transfer" when="1865-09-12">September 12th</date>, and his condition as follows:
    "The patient was suffering from great deformity of the right limb, the result of a shot wound of
    the upper third of the thigh, fracturing the femur. When admitted he had so far recovered as to
    be able to sit up, and his constitutional state was tolerably good. The fractured parts had
    firmly united but with great deformity; the wound of entrance had healed, but there were still
    some discharges from sinuses in the thigh, and small fragments of necrosed bones were daily
    removed. The prospects of usefulness of the limb are unfavorable; otherwise the patient is doing
    tolerably well." At the closing of <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>,
     <date type="transfer" when="1866-05-01">May 1, 1866</date>, the patient was transferred to the
     <name type="hospital" key="89">Post Hospital</name> at Washington, where he was operated on by
     <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who described the injury and operation as follows: "The wound was
    caused by a minié ball, which entered on the anterior and outer aspect of the thigh about
    three inches below the great trochanter, passed inward and a little downward, comminuting
    portions of the upper and middle thirds of the femur, and escaped posteriorly near the middle of
    the gluteal fold. On <date type="operation" when="1866-06-08">June 8th</date>, the patient was
    etherized and a triangular incision, three by three and a half inches, was made on the upper and
    outer side of the thigh, and several pieces of bone were removed. On September 30th the wound
    had almost healed. Three sinuses, evidently leading to necrosed bone, however, still existed,
    two of which were located on the upper and one on the lower surface. The patient's health was
    not very good, having suffered from several attacks of diarrhœa, and a severe attack of
    erysipelas which commenced near the wound and soon spread over the entire surface of the leg and
    foot. On December 31st, the sinuses were still open and discharging, and there was great
    deformity, with about five inches shortening, and almost complete anchylosis of the knee joint."
     <name type="person" key="1020">Assistant Surgeon J. Brooke</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who took charge of the patient in November, 1867, reported the
    termination of the case: "I found the limb in much the same condition as described by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>, except that a collection of pus, which had formed
    on the inner aspect of the thigh just above the knee, had been opened and a sinus found to
    connect with the seat of the fracture. This sinus, as well as those already described by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>, remained open, and the patient continued extremely
    feeble, became greatly emaciated, and suffered much from diarrhœa and frequent attacks of
    almost total loss of appetite. These symptoms continued until his death, which occurred on <date type="death" when="1868-06-27">June 27, 1868</date>. At the <hi rend="italic">autopsy</hi> the
    liver was found to be enormously enlarged, weighing ten pounds and ten ounces, and the right
    lung contained a small mass of calcareous matter." The injured femur, with the os innominatum
    and patella attached, and portions of the tibia and fibula were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="1020">Dr.
    Brooke</name>, and constitute specimen 5450 of the Surgical Section. The femur is imperfectly
    united, with great displacement and a deposit of foliaceous callus, and shows that extensive
    periostitis has taken place, and the patella and upper portions of tibia and fibula also show
    similar pathological changes. The photograph represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 140) was obtained at the <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>,
    and contributed by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon Bontecou</name>. Other photographs of
    the patient, taken at the same hospital and at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
     Museum</name>, are represented by No. 40, Vol. 8, of <hi rend="italic"><choice>
      <sic>Photo's</sic>
      <corr>Photos</corr>
     </choice> of Surgical Cases, S. G. O.</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Card <choice>
      <sic>Photo's</sic>
      <corr>Photos</corr>
     </choice></hi>, Vol. 2, p. 21, and Vol. 3, p. 27, and <hi rend="italic">Surgical Photograph
     Series</hi>, Nos. 139, 178, 179, and 292.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001561.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 140.—Shot fracture of upper third of right femur.
     [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
