<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9203">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Private J. Shimrock</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9203</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">191-192</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>fatal cases of shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>femur broken near junction of lower and middle thirds</term>
     <term>obstruction of iliac and femoral veins</term>
     <term>missile found at lower and inner side of thigh</term>
     <term>femoral artery contained clot of blood (embolus), completely occluded</term>
     <term>an&#230;mia</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>py&#230;mia</term>
     <term>py&#230;mic rigors and sweats,</term>
     <term>h&#230;morrhage</term>
     <term>suppuration profuse</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 392.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1029">Private J.
     Shimrock</name>, <name type="organization" key="419">Co. A, 55th Ohio</name>, aged 20 years,
    was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury"
     when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon G. Suckley</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported that he was left in the hands of
    the enemy, and described his injury as "a shot fracture of the femur." <date type="admit"
     when="1863-05-15">Twelve days after being wounded</date> the man was paroled and admitted to
    the Eleventh Corps field hospital at <name type="place">Brook's Station</name>, and <date
     type="transfer" when="1863-06-15">one month later</date> he was transferred to the <name
     type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name> at Washington. <name type="person" key="70"
     >Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, contributed
    the specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 153) and made the following report of the case:
    "Examination at the time of admission showed that the right femur was broken near the junction
    of the lower with the middle third, and that union had not yet taken place. There was a copious
    discharge of thin pus from the wound of the soft parts. The fracture had been treated in a
    simple straight fracture-box, and the limb was still in it when the patient was brought to this
    hospital. He stated that the bullet had not yet been extracted from the wound. He was pale,
    thin, and weak, with a frequent pulse. His tongue was smooth, dry, and red, and he complained of
    diarrh&#339;a, but said this was an old affair, and that he had also had chills and fever some
    time back. The prognosis was very unfavorable. The broken limb was placed in Hodgen's splint;
    pills of camphor and opium were given to control the diarrh&#339;a, and the system was supported
    with a nourishing diet, using eggs, milk, beef tea, farina, etc., together with milk-punch. June
    18th, diarrh&#339;a checked; tongue continues red and smooth; has considerable irritability of
    the stomach. The pills were suspended, but the supporting treatment continued. 22d, secondary
    h&#230;morrhage from the wound, to the extent of about three ounces, occurred this morning;
    there was also slight bleeding yesterday, some branch of the profunda being the probable source.
    Two drachms of solution of persulphate of iron was injected into the bottom of the wound through
    a catheter, and the h&#230;morrhage did not again occur. 24th, complained of pain in the thigh,
    was restless, and had some diarrh&#339;a. Gave one-grain opium pills every four hours until the
    26th, when the diarrh&#339;a was again checked. Suppuration continued profuse; tongue smooth and
    red. <date type="operation" when="1863-07-02">July 2d</date>, patient appeared to be slowly
    failing. Fluctuation having been detected above the internal condyle of the femur, an incision
    was made and about two ounces of pus evacuated. Two grains of quinine was prescribed three times
    a day, and six ounces of whiskey daily was substituted in place of the milk-punch, which, the
    patient thought, did not agree with him. 8th, patient began to exhibit night sweats, with
    increase of pallor and an&#230;mia; suppuration profuse, unhealthy and fetid; necrosed bone at
    the bottom of the wound firmly impacted. 18th, had a chill, followed by a hot and sweating
    stage. Administered ten grains of quinine three times a day: chills did not return for four
    days. 20th, patient very pale and feeble, with smooth red tongue; in addition to quinine he
    takes muriated tincture of iron, and porter two pints daily, with nourishing diet. 21st,
    diarrh&#339;a returned and was checked by pills of opium. 22d and 23d, chills occurring at
    irregular intervals, associated with hot flushes and profuse perspiration. <date
     type="operation" when="1863-07-25">25th</date>, some unhealthy fetid pus was evacuated from the
    inner side of the thigh by incision. 27th, had py&#230;mic rigors and sweats again; is much
    emaciated and very pale; pulse 120 and feeble; tongue glazed and of bright red color. 29th,
    continuance of py&#230;mic rigors and sweats, the perspiration being very profuse; left leg and
    thigh &#339;dematous and blue colored, the superficial veins looking like dark blue knotted
    cords; all of which denotes obstruction of the left iliac and femoral veins. The patient
    continued to sink, and died of exhaustion on <date type="death" when="1863-07-31">July 31,
     1863</date>. <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> twenty hours after death: Fracture of right
    thigh firmly united; necrosed bone closely surrounded by involucrum; muscles of right thigh
    extensively infiltrated with pus. The missile, a conical and much flattened bullet, was found at
    the lower and inner side of the thigh. The femoral artery opposite the seat of the injury
    contained an oval-shaped clot of blood (embolus) which completely occluded it; no other
    abnormity of the artery was noticed. On examination of the left thigh a metastatic abscess was
    found in the popliteal space containing about an ounce of pus, and the external iliac and
    femoral veins were discovered to be distended with coagulated blood. The femoral and iliac veins
    of the injured limb appeared to be normal. The liver was somewhat enlarged, nutmegged and fatty;
    kidneys beginning to be granular; spleen enlarged, softened, and reddish brown in color; lungs
    containing some frothy serum, otherwise natural; left ventricle of heart containing some
    coagulated blood." The specimen consists of the lower half of the injured femur with a battered
    piece of lead attached, and exhibits a fragment four inches long by one and a half wide, which
    preserved the vitality of its periosteal surface. The effusions from this fragment connect, as a
    bridge, the broken shaft; its internal surface is carious. Besides this, other and smaller
    fragments are entangled in the newly formed bone, some of which are necrosed and some serve as
    bonds. A wet preparation of portions of the common and external iliac and femoral arteries of
    the right side, showing an embolus in the latter near the seat of the fracture of the thigh, was
    also contributed by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon Lidell</name>&#185;, and constitutes
    Specimen 3454 of the Surgical Section of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
     Museum</name>.</p>
   <p>&#185; Dr. <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL, in an article on <hi rend="italic">Thrombosis
     and Embolism</hi>, in the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Medical Sciences</hi>, 1872,
    Vol. LXIV, N. S., p. 343, gives a minute account of this important case.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001569.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 153.&#8212;Fracture of right femur at junction of middle and
     lower thirds. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1536.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
