<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8006">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wetzel, I.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8006</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">180</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>ball entered anterior limb below Poupart's ligament, fracturing femur near trochanters,
      exited at apex of <choice>
       <sic>nates</sic>
       <corr>natis</corr>
      </choice></term>
     <term>bone united with shortening, foot everted and limb turned outward</term>
     <term>incomplete anchylosis of knee joint</term>
     <term>body of ilium diseased</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 366.—<name type="person" key="1014">Private I.
     Wetzel</name>, <name type="organization" key="413">Co. I, 184th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 21
    years, was wounded in the left thigh during the siege of <name type="BATTLE" key="254">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-10-03">October 3, 1864</date>. He was
    admitted to a field hospital of the Second Corps, and transferred to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-08">five days
     afterwards</date>. In July, 1865, <name type="person" key="1015">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. A.
     Bobbins</name> reported the following description of the injury and its result: "A conical ball
    entered the anterior aspect of the limb one inch below Poupart's ligament, passed backward,
    fracturing the femur near the trochanters, and made its exit at the apex of the left <choice>
     <sic>nates</sic>
     <corr>natis</corr>
    </choice>. The limb was treated in Hodgen's splint without extension. The bone is now united
    with three and a quarter inches shortening; the foot is everted and the limb slightly turned
    outward. Incomplete anchylosis of the knee joint exists, and there is still a discharge of
    healthy pus amounting to about one ounce daily. The patient is not yet able to use crutches, but
    from present appearances he soon will be." The patient was discharged from service on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-21">August 21, 1865</date>, and pensioned. Various
    Pension Examiners, at successive dates, certified to "shortening of the limb and partial
    anchylosis of the knee;" and in <date type="pension" when="1877-03">March, 1877</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. J. Y. Shindell</name> reported as follows: "I find the left knee
    joint quite stiff, also evidences of occasional abscesses in the muscular portions of the leg.
    He says that about once a year matter does form, and that he continually wears bandages around
    the thigh as a support." In <date type="pension" when="1877-09">September, 1877</date>, the
    Examiner stated: "The pensioner's general physical condition is not good. He is now confined to
    his bed, and has been for the last two weeks, on account of his wound, which is again
    suppurating. * * * But the greatest trouble now seems to be in the hip joint and its
    neighborhood. On probing the opening a little above the joint the body of the ilium seems to be
    of a honey-combed nature, diseased, and, no doubt, the cause of these frequent attacks of
    suppuration which occur every three or four months. His leg trouble will very likely cause death
    some time." The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-03-04">March 4, 1879</date>.
    The wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 136) represents a photograph taken at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> on <date type="photo" when="1865-07-06">July 6, 1865</date>. (<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 67, A. M. M.)</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001559.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 136—Result of shot fracture of upper third of left
     femur. [From a photograph]</head>
   </figure>



  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
