<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e6096">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Snow, Oscar</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e6096</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">340-341</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>rose-colored spots</term> 
                                        <term>bowels were loose, tender, tympanitic</term>
                                        <term> dull mentally</term> 
                                        <term>no idea of his condition</term>
                                        <term> mucous membrane of colon dark in color but not ulcerated</term>
                                        <term/>
                                        <term/>
                                        <term/>
                                        <term/>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated, large intestine also implicated</term>
                                        <term>parotid infiltrated with pus</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00031">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 31.—<name type="person" key="614">Private Oscar Snow</name>, <name type="organization" key="510">Co. H, 3d Vt.</name>;
                                        age 20; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-10-01">Oct. 1, 1861</date>, with typhoid fever. He had
                                        been sick a week, but he was so dull that he could give but
                                        little information concerning the early part of his
                                        sickness. A bath was ordered for him, and Dover's powder at
                                        night. Next day his face was flushed, pulse 135, full, skin
                                        hot and dry, tongue slightly moist but thickly coated brown;
                                        he had slight delirium, some deafness and ten or twelve
                                        characteristic rose-colored spots; his bowels were loose,
                                        tender and tympanitic. From this time the condition of the
                                        patient gradually changed for the worse. His bowels for some
                                        time were not loose, but tenderness, meteorism and
                                        borborygmus were present throughout; on October 12 he had
                                        three involuntary passages. His pulse, which at first was
                                        rapid and full, lost its <choice><orig>fulness</orig><reg>fullness</reg></choice> but retained its rapidity,
                                        becoming small, weak and fluctuating. His tongue became dry,
                                        and on the 9th he was unable to protrude it; on the same day
                                        sordes appeared on the teeth. The rose-colored spots
                                        disappeared on the 11th. From being somewhat dull mentally,
                                        with occasional mild delirium, he fell into a prostrate
                                        condition, lying on his back with his lower jaw dropped and
                                        his eyes open, taking no notice of anything going on around.
                                        On the 8th his breathing became hurried; mucous and sibilant
                                        râles were heard in the right lung, and on the 12th a
                                        leathery creaking sound was distinguished over both lungs.
                                        On the 11th the parotid gland was found to be swollen. The
                                        treatment consisted of quinine, turpentine, brown mixture,
                                        nourishment and stimulants. On the evening of the 13th his
                                        face was ashen-gray in color, lips cold and bloodless, head
                                        and extremities cold; there was some deafness and it was
                                        very difficult to arouse him; he had also a mild delirium,
                                        speaking of going home, and had no idea of his condition.
                                        His pulse, about 140, was weak and barely perceptible at the
                                        wrist; the superficial circulation was almost
                                        suspended—an impression made with the fingers
                                        remained a long time. He had no hemorrhage from the nose or
                                        bowels; his bowels moved occasionally involuntarily, the
                                        passages being very thin; the abdomen was acutely tender and
                                        borborygmus frequent. His respiration varied from fifty to
                                        sixty per minute; a rattling sound was heard in the throat
                                        during expiration, as though from mucus which he had not
                                        strength enough to eject; his breath was very offensive for
                                        the first time since his illness. His urine, acid and
                                        albuminous, had a specific gravity of 1011, and contained
                                        mucus, epithelium, urates and a few blood-discs. The parotid
                                        gland continued much swollen. On the evening of <date type="death" when="1861-10-14">the 14th</date> he
                                        aroused himself and spoke very rationally; his eyes shone
                                        brilliantly for a few minutes; he tried to rise from bed,
                                        but fell back from weakness; the rattling sound in the
                                        bronchial tubes increased, and after a few deep-drawn
                                        breaths he was dead. <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi>
                                        examination fourteen hours after death: Side of face
                                        swollen; parotid infiltrated with pus. The pleural cavities
                                        contained a number of large blood-clots; the derivation of
                                        the hemorrhage was not ascertained. The lungs were
                                        congested, but were not closely examined for want of time.
                                        The stomach contained a pint of very offensive yellowish
                                        matter; its mucous membrane was thick and congested. The
                                        liver and gall-bladder were enlarged but healthy; the spleen
                                        and kidneys enlarged and congested. The peritoneum was much inflamed. The glands
                                        of Peyer and the solitary glands of the ileum were much
                                        ulcerated. A foot and a half from the ileo-cæcal
                                        valve the ileum presented a diverticulum about four inches
                                        long, as wide as the gut from which it was derived, and like
                                        it, blackened and much ulcerated. The mesenteric glands were
                                        enlarged, the mesentery much congested and inflamed. The
                                        mucous membrane of the colon was dark in color but not
                                                ulcerated.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary
                                                Hospital</name>, Georgetown, D. C.</hi>
                                </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
