<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16914">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">E——, John</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16914</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">278</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>recovery with disability</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>hemiplegia</term>
          <term>difficulty in articulation, tripping of one foot in walking</term>
          <term>pistol ball caused compound fracture of both tables of os frontis near temporal
            bone</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private John
          E——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. C, 39th New York Volunteers</name>,
        aged 35 years, was wounded in a melee in a railroad car, near <name type="place">Chicago,
          Illinois</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-11-16">November 16th, 1862</date>, by a
        pistol ball, which caused a compound fracture of both tables of the <hi rend="italic">os
          frontis</hi>, right side, near the border of the temporal bone. He arrived at <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> on <date type="admit" when="1862-11-26">the 26th</date>, and was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square
          Hospital</name>, being quite delirious. There was much tumefaction, and extensive
        suppuration had already commenced. His strength, appetite, and secretions were normal, his
        pulse slightly accelerated and tense. An examination revealed a wound of the scalp, two
        inches in length, crossing the coronal suture at right angles, two inches above the border
        of the temporal bone. On the morning after admission, the delirium was so intense that it
        was impossible to keep the patient in the ward. There was occasional difficulty in
        articulation and a tripping of the left foot in walking, denoting slight hemiplegia. The
        memory was somewhat impaired, but lucid intervals occurred. The constitutional symptoms had
        remained the same, denoting irritation rather than compression of the brain. On <date type="operation" when="1862-11-22">the 22d</date>, the tumefaction having somewhat
        subsided, a further examination revealed another wound of the scalp, one and a half inches
        below the first, and a ball imbedded in the cranium. Ether was administered and an incision
        made through the integument. The trephine was then applied, and the portion of the cranium
        containing the ball was removed, as also a fragment of the inner table, triangular in shape,
        three-eighths of an inch in length and one-fourth of an inch in width at the base. The
        latter was found driven into the substance of the brain, piercing the dura mater and
        standing point downward, its broad base displacing the meningea media. After the operation
        the patient rose from the table, perfectly sane, and walked to his bed. Cold water dressings
        were applied, laxatives administered, and low diet ordered, and by the 25th he was improving
        rapidly, there having been no delirium since the operation. On <date type="injury" when="1862-12-10">December 10th</date>, the general health of the patient was good, and
        the wound across the coronal suture had nearly closed by healthy granulations. The wound of
        operation had healed by first intention, except at the place where the flaps met; at that
        point there was healthy granulation going on. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-01-06">January 6th, 1863</date>, he was discharged from the service, having
        entirely recovered. The specimen removed is a disk of bone, one-half an inch in diameter,
        with fracture and depression of both tables, and was contributed by <name type="person">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> It is
        figured in the wood-cut.</p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001424.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 140.—Disk with a depressed gunshot fracture its
          centre. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 422, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
