<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e19135">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Metz, J. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e19135</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">464</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the upper third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>fatal primary amputations in the upper third of the leg</term>
     <term>ball entered leg anteriorly, produced compound comminuted fracture at upper third of
      tibia and fractured fibula.</term>
     <term>leg amputated at upper third</term>
     <term>an&#230;mic at operation</term>
     <term>secondary h&#230;morrhage</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>abscess above knee</term>
     <term>small intestine with pseudo-membrane</term>
     <term>pus extended to dorsum of ilium</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 728.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1280">Private J. H.
     Metz</name>, <name type="organization" key="109">Co. G, 9th Regiment Veteran Reserve
     Corps</name>, aged 33 years, was wounded in the left leg, near <name type="FORT" key="xx">Fort
     Stevens</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Defences of Washington</name>, <date
     type="injury" when="1864-07-11">July 11, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon O.
     A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, made the following
    report of the injury: "A conoidal ball entered the limb anteriorly, passed through transversely,
    and produced a compound comminuted fracture at the upper third of the tibia, the man by his
    weight soon after fracturing the fibula. He was conveyed to <name type="hospital" key="167"
     >Carver Hospital</name>, Washington, where the leg was amputated at the upper third, by the
    lateral flap method, by <name type="person" key="1281">Medical Inspector J. Wilson</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, on <date type="operation" when="1864-07-11">the
     day of the injury</date>. The patient was an&#230;mic and very nervous at the time of the
    operation. Cold-water dressings were applied. On <date type="operation" when="1864-07-12">the
     following day</date> the clot had formed beneath the flaps, rendering it necessary to cut the
    suture and reopen the wound. The clot was then turned out and the flaps, after remaining open
    for some time, were closed up again. On <date type="operation" when="1864-07-13">July
     13th</date>, the flaps looked dark and were opened again, when a strong solution of sulphate of
    copper was applied. Sloughing commenced the next day, causing the tibia to protrude. Citrate of
    iron and quinine, with stimulants, were administered freely and the external applications
    repeated. By July 17th granulations were starting up over a portion of the surface of the flaps.
    Secondary h&#230;morrhage occurred on the following day. The patient appeared greatly exhausted,
    had very poor appetite, and was troubled with diarrh&#339;a. Dry dressings were now applied to
    the stump. On July 23d an abscess was found to have formed above the knee, after which sloughing
    extended upwards. The patient continued to sink, his diarrh&#339;a resisting all treatment;
    pulse rapid; skin of an icteric tinge. Death occurred from exhaustion, <date type="death"
     when="1864-07-28">July 28, 1864</date>. At the autopsy pus was found to have burrowed up the
    outer and posterior portion of the leg, extending to the dorsum of the ilium. The pus was of a
    dark color and contained a large quantity of free fat. The right lung adhered to the wall of the
    chest anteriorly, otherwise healthy. Both lobes of the left lung were slightly congested; heart
    normal; liver somewhat congested and gall-bladder distended with bile; spleen covered on lower
    portion with patches of lymph; stomach distended with dark fluid. The mucous membrane of the
    small intestine was thickened and covered with pseudo-membrane, easily removable." The amputated
    bones of the leg (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3166), represented in the wood-cut (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 285), were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the
     Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="1282">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. W. Merrill</name>. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001634.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 285.&#8212;Fracture of left tibia and fibula in upper
     third. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3166.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
