<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10251">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Tappan, William E.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e10251</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">575</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases allied to or associated with</term>
                                        <term>the paroxysmal and continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>cerebro-spinal fever</term>
                                        <term>clinical and post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>cases at the hospitals of Alexandria, Va.</term>   
                                        <term>pain in back of head and neck</term>
                                        <term>pain more intense and extended from head down spine and over body generally</term>
                                        <term>peevish, fretful and slightly delirious at times</term>
                                        <term>delirium with dilated pupils</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>  
                                        <term>opisthotonos</term>
                                        <term>tetanic convulsions</term>
                                        <term>lateral ventricles contained thick pus</term>
                                        <term>velum interpositum, valve of Vieussens, and membranes from optic commissure down to medulla covered with lymph and pus</term>
                                        <term>liver enlarged, yellow, and granular</term>
                                        <term>lungs congested and &#339;dematous</term>   
                                        <term>lungs showed dark-purple or blackish patches of softened tissue, some gray tinged with pink</term>
                                        <term>enlarged bronchial tubes containing pus</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2012-03-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Case at the Hospitals of <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name></hi></p><p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 72.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="826">Private William E. Tappan</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="662">Co. H, 28th
                                                Mich.</name>; age 17; admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1865-01-31">Jan. 31, 1865</date>.  Skin hot and
                                        dry; tongue dry and somewhat fissured, red at the edges and
                                        coated dark yellow in the middle; pulse quick and feeble;
                                        bowels rather loose; urine scanty and high-colored;
                                        respiration somewhat hurried; he was rational and complained
                                        of pain in the back of the head and neck. He did not rest
                                        well during the following night, and next day, although his
                                        tongue was less dry, his pulse was fuller and the pain more
                                        intense, extending from the head down the spine and over the
                                        body generally; he was peevish, fretful and slightly
                                        delirious at times, though he answered questions correctly. A blister was applied to the back of the neck and
                                        alteratives administered.  On February 2 delirium was
                                        constant; the patient muttered, tried to get up, and had
                                        occasional attacks of opisthotonos which increased in
                                        violence, but there was no paralysis; he refused all food.
                                        Wet cups were applied along the spine. Next day opisthotonos
                                        was less marked, but delirium continued with dilated pupils;
                                        the catheter was required to relieve the bladder.  On 
                                        <date type="death" when="1865-02-04">the 4th</date> the
                                        pulse became weak and intermitting; the respiration labored
                                        and accompanied with a rattling in the throat; he was
                                        semi-comatose but easily aroused; the tetanic convulsions
                                        returned with violence, and he died at 11 P. M.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: Body not
                                        emaciated. The veins of the cerebral membranes were
                                        distended with black blood; the brain was firm and slightly
                                        injected; its lateral ventricles contained thick pus and
                                        their veins were black and engorged; the velum interpositum,
                                        valve of Vieussens and the membranes from the optic
                                        commissure down the medulla as far as could be seen were
                                        covered with lymph and pus; the gray matter of the
                                        cerebellum was so pale as to be scarcely distinguishable
                                        from the white matter; the cerebellum and spinal cord were
                                        softened. The upper and lower lobes of the right lung were
                                        somewhat congested and showed dark-purple or blackish
                                        patches of softened tissue; the middle lobe was
                                        &#339;dematous, of a gray color tinged with pink, and
                                        presented at its margin a patch of shrunken liver-red tissue
                                        full of enlarged bronchial tubes containing pus; the left
                                        lung was similarly affected but in a less degree. The heart
                                        was normal. The liver was somewhat enlarged, yellow and
                                        granular; the spleen small, its trabecul&#230; and
                                        Malpighian bodies enlarged, dry and bloodless; the
                                        intestines and kidneys normal; the bladder largely distended
                                        and the overlying recti muscles of a bright-red color.</p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
