<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18273">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">McLeer, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e18273</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">441</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recovery after shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>forearm fractured, amputated at middle third</term> 
     <term>compound comminuted fractures of radius, ulna, and elbow joint</term> 
     <term>fractures of tibia and fibula, lower third</term>
     <term>no special operation on leg, yet excision of broken bone fragments</term>
     <term>leg bowed outward to marked degree, fibula prominent and thickened</term>
     <term>shortening of leg one inch</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 694.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1252">Sergeant J.
      McLeer</name>, <name type="organization" key="493">Co. C, 84th New York</name>, aged 23 years,
     was wounded by a shell in the left arm and left leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull
      Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-29">August 29, 1862</date>. He entered <name
       type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-09">several days afterwards</date>.
      <name type="person" key="339">Assistant Surgeon C. A. McCall</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge, describes the injury of the arm as a compound comminuted
     fracture of the radius, ulna, and elbow joint, and that of the leg as a fracture of the tibia
     and fibula, lower third, and reports: "On or about <date type="operation" when="1862-09-02">the 2d of September</date> I amputated the arm at
     the middle third (<hi rend="italic">Second Surgical Volume</hi>, <hi rend="initialcap">T</hi>ABLE <hi rend="initialcap">LXXVIII</hi>, p. 765, No. 167), and would have also amputated the leg, but that the
     utter prostration of the patient threatened death upon further surgical procedure. Operating on
     the leg was therefore left to a future time; but as symptoms of promise developed themselves
     afterwards, an effort was made to save the leg, which, after long and critical treatment, was
     successful, although the limb was left somewhat shortened and to a considerable extent unfit
     for useful progression. The case was one of singular interest to myself and staff, proving as
     it did the wonderful endurance of the human system and the almost strained limit to which
     conservative surgery may trust nature. It had been looked upon and classed by me as an excision
     of the lower portion of both bones of the leg: for though no special operation was performed,
     yet I know I was over half an hour cleaning out the broken fragments and adjusting loosened
     spicul&#230; before trusting it to the fracture-box." In a published account of the case&#185; it is mentioned that, under a
     tonic and stimulant treatment and the application of simple absorbent dressings to the parts,
     the stump of the arm healed rapidly. The patient was discharged from service <date
      type="servicedischarge" when="1863-07-27">July 27, 1863</date>, and pensioned. On <date type="pension" when="1880-09-22">September 22, 1880</date>,
     he was examined by the <name type="organization" key="xx">Brooklyn Pension Board</name>, who
     certified to the loss of his left arm and added: "There is evidence of a compound comminuted
     fracture of the tibia and fibula of the left leg in the lower third. Portions of both bones
     were removed. The cicatrices of entrance and exit of the missile are found upon the internal
     and anterior aspects of the part. In the latter situation, over the tibia, a firmly adherent
     cicatrix, three inches long by one inch wide, is present. The leg is bowed outward to a very
     marked degree, the fibula being very prominent and thickened. There is shortening of the limb
     of about one inch. The extensor tendons are not full in their movements, being partially bound
     down by cicatricial tissue, and the ankle is somewhat stiffened and restricted in its motion.
     The great toe is not supple, since the plantar tendons are somewhat contracted. Altogether the
     objective signs show that the original wound was of the most severe character. In manual labor,
     walking, standing, etc., the member would speedily become the seat of great swelling and pain,
     as is the case after any unusual exercise." </p>
   <p>&#185; <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>OUES (<hi rend="initialcap">E</hi>LLIOTT), <hi rend="italic">Report of some Cases of Amputations and Resections from Gunshot Wounds, performed at the Mount Pleasant U. S. General
    Hospital by</hi> <hi rend="initialcap">C. A.</hi> <hi rend="initialcap">M</hi>c<hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ALL, <hi rend="initialcap">M. D.</hi>, <hi rend="initialcap">U. S. A.</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Medical and Surgical Reporter</hi>, New York, 1862-3, Vol. IX, p. 229.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
