<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e9516">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Hanlon, R.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e9516</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">196, 198</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the lower third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>successful cases of shot fractures of the lower third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ball entered external aspect of thigh near middle, comminuting middle third of femur, splitting the lower third longitudinally nearly to knee joint</term>
     <term>abscess on inner aspect of thigh, near perinæum</term>      
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>   
     <term>anchylosis of knee</term>
     <term>three inches shortening of limb</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-29">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 402.—<name type="person" key="1055">Private R.
      Hanlon</name>, <name type="organization" key="173">Co. C, 5th Cavalry</name>, aged 21 years,
     was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="109">Beverly Ford</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-06-09">June 9, 1863</date>. On <date type="admit" when="1863-06-10">the following day</date> he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, subsequently to <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square</name>, and lastly to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Carlisle Barracks</name>, whence he was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-05-16">May 16, 1864</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="424">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. K. Smith</name> contributed the following history: "He was wounded by a
     minié ball, which entered the external aspect of the left thigh near its middle, comminuting the greater portion of the middle third of the femur, and splitting the lower third
     longitudinally nearly down to the knee joint. The missile lodged and could not be found. Ether
     was administered and the wound enlarged, and seventeen fragments of bone, comprising three
     inches of the continuity of the shaft, were removed. On <date type="operation" when="1863-06-23">June 23d</date>, an abscess opened on the
     inner aspect of the thigh, near the perinæum, through which the ball was extracted. The
     limb was bandaged in its whole length, placed on a <choice><orig>mattrass</orig><reg>mattress</reg></choice> , and kept in position by a sand bag
     on either side. Owing to the loss of bone no extension was resorted to until October 1st, at
     which time the patient was able to roll his injured limb on the <choice><orig>mattrass</orig><reg>mattress</reg></choice>, the fragments having
     united, though the callus had not yet become firm and hard. I then applied a ten pound weight,
     suspended by a cord and pulley, and succeeded in reducing the shortening one-half inch. This
     amount of extension was continued until I left <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln
      Hospital</name>, on November 8th, but was removed soon afterwards. On <date type="injury" when="1863-12-16">December 16th</date>, while
     moving about on crutches, the patient fell and refractured the bone. The surgeon in charge then
     applied a long splint to the posterior aspect of the limb, retaining it in that position and
     preventing any motion of the knee joint until the fragments had reunited. The wound healed in
     the beginning of March, 1864, but broke open again in the middle of June, and continued to
     discharge slightly until March, 1865, during which time, however, the man was able to walk
     about and to serve as a watchman at the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Government Repair Shops</name> in <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>. On <date type="pension" when="1865-06-20">June 20th, 1865</date>, the limb appeared perfectly sound, and at this period the man could walk all day without feeling tired, though there was fibrous anchylosis of the knee
     joint." Various pension examiners have certified at different dates to "anchylosis of the knee and about three inches shortening of the limb." The pensioner was paid
     <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE LXIV, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 1, opp. p. 198, represents his photograph, taken at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
      Museum</name> in <date type="photo" when="1865-06">June, 1865</date>.—(<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 55, A. M. M.)</p>
    
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001810.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  LXIV. — CONSOLIDATED  GUNSHOT  FRACTURES  OF  THE  FEMUR.   Fig 1.  Case of <name type="person" key="1055">Private R. Hanlon</name>  <name type="organization" key="173">5th U. S. Calvary</name></head> 
   </figure>

   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
