<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e4000">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Hooker, Joseph</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e4000</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">60</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>     
     <term>shot injury of foot</term>
     <term>distinguished general officer</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>   
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p>  <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 132.—<name type="person" key="929">Major-General J. Hooker</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, was wounded at the battle
     of <name type="BATTLE" key="281">Antietam</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-09-17">September 17, 1862</date>. The injury was reported by <name type="person" key="930">Assistant Surgeon B. Howard</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, as follows: "He was wounded in the right foot by a minié ball while leading his command, being on horseback at
     the time, and standing in the stirrups with his weight thrown on his right foot, which was
     turned outward. The ball struck the inner side of the foot inferiorly to the middle of the
     scaphoid bone, passing between the first and second layers of the plantar muscles, almost
     transversely across the plantar portion of the foot, and emerging inferiorly to the anterior border of the cuboid bone. The bones of the foot were
     uninjured. On the morning of September 18th, I was sent by the <name type="person">Medical Director</name> of the <name type="organization" key="377">Army of the Potomac</name> to attend <name type="person" key="929">General Hooker</name>,   *   *   then lying in a farmhouse near the battle-field. Warm-water dressings had been applied previous to my visit. There was no
     constitutional disturbance, but the foot was hot and inflamed. By means of a syringe I
     thoroughly washed out the wound with warm water, and finding it most agreeable to the patient,
     substituted cold- for warm-water dressings. The next day I found the patient very comfortable;
     the appearance of the foot had greatly improved and the inflammatory symptoms had disappeared.
     I then ordered a lotion of plumbi instead of cold-water dressings as being more likely to allay
     any irritation that might arise in the parts. Before <name type="person" key="929">the General</name> left that evening, for <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, I advised him to resume the use of tepid
     water as soon as all tendency to active inflammation should cease. On October 25th, I heard
     that tetanic symptoms had manifested themselves, but received a letter from <name type="person" key="929">the General</name> a few days afterwards stating to the contrary. On
     <date type="injury" when="1862-11-25">November 25th</date> <name type="person" key="929">the General</name>, who had returned to duty in the
     field, requested me to look at his wound, which still troubled him somewhat. I found the newly
     formed cicatrices somewhat tumefied; they were painful on pressure, and <name type="person" key="929">the General</name> was still unable to mount his horse unaided, though he persisted in
     being on active duty. On November 30th, I found there had been a steady improvement, and,
     although the step had not its former elasticity, the wound had left no serious inconvenience
     behind." <name type="person" key="929">General Hooker</name> remained in active service until
     the close of the war, and was ultimately retired <date type="servicedischarge" when="1868-10-15">October 15, 1868</date>.  </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
