<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30122">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wolff, C. M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e30122</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">573</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
     <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
     <term>excisions at the shoulder</term>
     <term>excisions of the head and portions of the shaft of the humerus</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions of the upper extremity of the humerus for shot injury</term>
     <term>successful operations</term>
     <term>excision of upper third of humerus</term>
     <term>ball passed completely through surgical neck, remains embedded in specimen</term>
     <term>ball entered anterior aspect of shoulder joint midway between coracoid and acromion
      processes, passed backward, produced compound comminuted fracture of humerus</term>
     <term>unable to use arm, disability total and permanent</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place
    names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1554.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private C. M.
     Wolff</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 5th New Hampshire</name>, was wounded
    at <name type="BATTLE" key="98">Ream's Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-08-25"
     >August 25, 1864</date>, and treated in a Second Corps hospital until <date type="admit"
     when="1864-08-28">the 28th</date>, when he was sent to <name type="hospital">Lincoln
     Hospital</name>, at Washington. <name type="person" key="1380">Acting Assistant Surgeon L. C.
     Dodge</name> reported: "Wound produced by a mini&#233; ball, which entered on the anterior
    aspect of the left shoulder joint midway between the coracoid and acromion processes, passing
    directly backward, producing a compound comminuted fracture of the humerus, the ball passing
    completely through the bone at the surgical neck. The articulating surface of the humerus was
    not implicated. At the time of admission the arm was considerably swollen as far down as the
    elbow joint; otherwise, the condition of the patient was good. <date type="operation"
     when="1864-08-30">August 30th</date>: Excision of the upper third of the humerus was performed
    to-day. A longitudinal incision six inches in length was made, commencing at the acromion
    process, and passing directly down to the posterior surface of the arm. The fragments of the
    bone were removed with the forceps, and the shaft of the humerus sawn through; the ordinary
    dressings were applied." <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon W. Lindsly</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, noted: "Ether was used as an
    an&#230;sthetic; six ligatures were used; operation performed by <name type="person" key="1380"
     >Acting Assistant Surgeon L. C. Dodge</name>." The specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
    448), contributed by <name type="person" key="1380">the operator</name>, consists of the head
    and one inch and a half of the shaft of the left humerus, excised. A conoidal ball entered the
    anatomical neck from the rear, fissured the articular surface and shattered the surgical neck,
    and remains embedded in the specimen. This patient was discharged from service <date
     type="servicedischarge" when="1864-12-03">December 3, 1864</date>, and pensioned. <name
     type="person" key="">E. D. Hudson, M. D.</name>, of <name type="place">New York</name>,&#179;
    published the following account of this case: "Three months after the operation his arm was
    healed&#8212;some atrophied; not shortened, very flexile, uncontrollable; having an interspace
    of two and a half inches, which nature had failed to restore; with inability to carry the arm
    forward across the chest; pectoral and deltoid muscles impaired; nerves, arteries, and functions
    of the forearm healthy; cannot flex the forearm much for lack of fixedness; carries his forearm
    in a sling. With apparatus anatomically prepared and applied, scapular pad, and acromion
    process, a case for the arm attached to the scapular pad, with an oscillatory shoulder joint,
    and an aponeurotic case for the forearm united to that of the arm with ginglymoid joints;
    auxiliary straps of rubber webbing for the pectoral and biceps muscles (<hi rend="initialcap"
     >F</hi>IG. 449), he was able to flex the forearm, carry his hand to his head, pronate and
    supinate the hand, draw it partially across the chest, lift weights with forearm flexed,
    exercise the forearm, and will regain the use of his arm for ordinary vocations." On <date
     type="pension" when="1864-12-05">December 5, 1864</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx"
     >Examiner Julius Nichols</name>, of <name type="place">Washington</name>, reported: "Removal,
    by resection, of the head and three and a half inches of the shaft of the humerus; will be
    partially useful in time; requires perfect rest for one year." <name type="person" key="xxx"
     >Examiner C. O. S. Gilman</name>, of <name type="place">Salem, New York</name>, reported <date
     type="pension" when="1866-09-25">September 25, 1866</date>: &#42; &#42; "he is unable to use
    the arm for any purpose; it often discharges at the joint; disability total and permanent." This
    pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1873-12-04">December 4, 1873</date>. </p>
   <p>&#179; <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>UDSON (<hi rend="initialcap">E. D.</hi>), <hi rend="italic"
     >Remarks on <choice>
      <orig>Exsections</orig>
      <reg>Excisions</reg>
     </choice>, with Cases and Plates</hi>, p. 15.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001799.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 448.&#8212;Posterior view of the head of the left humerus,
     excised for shot injury. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3161.</head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001800.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 449.&#8212;Apparatus employed in a case of excision at the
     shoulder. [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
