<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e24056">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Pero, P.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e24056</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">623-624</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term> 
       <term>excisions in the bones of the foot</term> 
       <term>primary excisions in the bones of the foot</term> 
       <term>wounded in foot, on picket duty</term>
       <term>ball entered inner side of middle of metatarsal bone of great toe, emerged over metatarsal of little toe</term>
       <term>first, second, third, and fourth metatarsal bones shattered</term> 
       <term>excision of first metatarsal bone and fragments of second, third, and fourth metatarsals</term> 
       <term>h&#230;morrhage arrested by pressure on dorsal artery</term>
       <term>tibio-tarsal articulation completely anchylosed</term>
       <term>leg amputated at middle third</term>        
       <term>chronic  diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-18">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 913.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private P. Pero</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 2d New York Cavalry</name>, aged 22 years, was wounded in the right foot, while on picket
    duty near <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon C. Powers</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">160th New York</name>, in charge of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name> Hospital, made the following report:  &#34;The ball entered at the inner side of the middle of the metatarsal bone of the great toe and emerged over that
    of the little toe. The first, second, third, and fourth metatarsal bones were shattered. The patient suffered considerable pain.
    <date type="operation" when="1864-05-07">Two days after the injury</date> excision of the first metatarsal bone was performed and the shattered fragments of the second, third,
    and fourth were removed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon C. H. Andrus</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">128th New York</name>. Chloroform was used, and the patient reacted promptly. He did well afterwards. Five days after the operation considerable h&#230;morrhage occurred, but was completely arrested by light pressure on the dorsal artery. Simple water dressings were used. The case was still doing well when the
    patient was, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-22">May 22d</date>, transferred to University Hospital at <name type="place">New Orleans</name>.&#34; <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon S. Kneeland</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter hospital, reported the result of the case as follows:  &#34;The whole foot became greatly swollen, purulent inflammation having
    occurred on the dorsal and plantar surfaces; several of the bones became disorganized and the tibio-tarsal articulation completely
    anchylosed; patient greatly reduced by the excessive suppuration; pulse 78; appetite tolerably good. He also suffered from
    chronic diarrh&#339;a and intermittent fever, from which he had recovered on <date type="operation" when="1864-06-20">June 20th</date>, when the leg was amputated at the middle
    third by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon F. Hassenburg</name>. Chloroform was used, and the h&#230;morrhage attending the operation was
    slight. Under a supporting diet and cool dressings the patient did well up to June 30th.  He died from the effects of chronic diarrh&#339;a <date type="death" when="1864-07-15">July 15, 1864</date>.&#34;</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
