<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e4532">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Elmer, E. S.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e4532</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">245</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>remittent fever</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00110">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 110.—<hi rend="italic">Mild typhoid grafted on remittent
                                                fever.</hi>—<name type="person" key="568">Private E. S. Elmer</name>, <name type="organization" key="623">Co. K, 14th N.
                                                Y.</name>; age 22; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-09-24">Sept. 24, 1861</date>, having been
                                        taken sick <date type="injury" when="1861-09">three weeks before</date> with diarrhœa
                                        followed by bilious remittent fever. On admission he had
                                        severe headache with flushed face, injected eyes and
                                        accelerated pulse. He slept little during the following
                                        night; in the morning he was covered with sweat, pulse 108,
                                        full but weak, tongue slightly yellow, bowels moved once,
                                        respiration natural; his appetite was good, but he had much
                                        thirst and was somewhat dizzy. Two grains of blue-mass and a
                                        half grain of quinine were ordered to be given every two
                                        hours. On the 26th he was not so well: his face was flushed,
                                        eyes much suffused and countenance anxious; the dizziness
                                        was increased and there was delirium; the tongue was heavily
                                        coated yellow and the appetite lost; there was also
                                        retention of urine, but the skin was moist and profusely
                                        covered with sudamina; there had been but one stool, and the
                                        patient had no pain nor tenderness. Castor oil and extract
                                        of buchu were ordered. In the evening the skin was hot but
                                        bathed in perspiration, the pulse 96, strong, the tongue
                                        coated and moist, the bowels tender and slightly tympanitic.
                                        On the 27th the face was not flushed; the skin was soft and
                                        natural, the respiration normal, the tongue moist, yellow in
                                        the centre, and the appetite good; two stools were passed
                                        and there was some right iliac tenderness; a few
                                        rose-colored spots appeared on the abdomen. One drachm of
                                        turpentine emulsion was given every three hours, with twelve
                                        grains of quinine in the forenoon. In the evening the cheeks
                                        were flushed, the eyes suffused, the pulse 96, the skin dry
                                        and hot, the tongue moist and heavily coated gray, the
                                        appetite good; two stools were passed and tympanites,
                                        borborygmus and tenderness were present. Sweet spirit of
                                        nitre and Dover's powder were given. No stool was passed on
                                        the 28th; the skin was natural, pulse 92, strong, the tongue
                                        moist and yellow, the appetite moderate; there was some
                                        difficulty in micturition but no abdominal pain nor
                                        tenderness. In the evening four or five rose-colored spots
                                        appeared on the abdomen and chest. Next day the skin was
                                        soft but rather above the natural temperature, the tongue
                                        moist and yellow-coated but red at the tip and edges; there
                                        were twelve dull red spots on the abdomen, which was
                                        slightly tympanitic but not tender. He vomited during the
                                        following night and had three stools with some tympanites
                                        and left iliac tenderness. Lead, opium and tannin were
                                        given. Slight relaxation of the bowels continued up to <date type="transfer" when="1861-10-10">October 10</date>,
                                        when the patient was sent to hospital at <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name> </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
