<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31156">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Reardon, John F.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31156</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>   
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">552</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
       <term>excisions at the shoulder</term> 
       <term>excisions of the head and portions of the shaft of the humerus</term>
       <term>primary excisions of the upper extremity of the humerus for shot injury</term> 
       <term>successful operations</term>
       <term>humerus shattered by fragment of shell</term>
       <term>shell fragment removed from lodgement under deltoid muscle</term> 
       <term>excised head and partial shaft of humerus</term>
       <term>suffered little inconvenience from mutilation</term>
       <term>shortening of arm, some atrophy of muscles</term>
       <term>limb useless for manual labor</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-11">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1529.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private John F. Reardon</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 6th New York Cavalry</name>, aged 22 years, was wounded at
    <name type="place">Culpeper</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-10-11">October 11, 1863</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-10-12">the following day</date>.  <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, found that his right humerus was shattered by a fragment of shell, which was removed from its lodgement under the deltoid muscle. It was four inches long, one inch broad, and weighed nine ounces.  <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon Bliss</name> excised the head and six inches of the shaft of the humerus through a straight incision on the outside of the limb. During the after-treatment the elbow was well supported. The patient recovered without a bad symptom, and with a remarkably useful limb.  In <date type="enlist" when="1866-03">March, 1866</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Reardon</name> was re-enlisted in the general service, and was assigned to duty as an orderly in the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>.  From that date until the present (March, 1875) he has served continuously, suffering very little inconvenience from the mutilation he has undergone. Without difficulty he can place his right hand on the top of his head; he can lift a weight of two hundred pounds or more with the injured limb without pain. The movements of the forearm and hand are not in the least impaired, and there is great freedom of all the movements of the arm except abduction.  The muscular development of the arm equals that of its fellow. No apparatus is requisite, and altogether the result is most satisfactory and successful. The case effectually disproves the dictum of the older military surgeons on the inutility of excisions of the humerus in cases in which it may be necessary to saw the shaft, below, the insertion of the deltoid. <name type="person" key="xxx">Reardon</name> was pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. O. Staunton</name> reported, December 9, 1873:  "There is about three inches shortening of the arm; some atrophy of the muscles; a large cicatrix. He has some use of the hand when the elbow is supported: but the limb is useless for purposes of manual labor."  The appearance of the excised portion of bone, presented to the Museum by <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, is represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 428).  The appearance of the limb is shown in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 3 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XIV</hi>.¹</p>
   <p>¹ An account of this case was published in the preliminary Surgical Report of Circular 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 56, with an illustration which has been frequently reproduced, <hi rend="italic">e. g.</hi> in <hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>ILROTH und <hi rend="initialcap">V</hi>ON <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>ITHA (<hi rend="italic">Handbuch</hi>); <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>RANKLIN (<hi rend="initialcap">E. C.</hi>) (<hi rend="italic">The Science and Art of Surgery</hi>, 1867, Vol. I, p. 710); <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>AMILTON (<hi rend="initialcap">F. H.</hi>) (<hi rend="italic">Princ. and Pract. of Surg.</hi>, 1872, p. 394).</p> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 428.—Head and five and a half inches of the shaft of the humerus excised for shell fracture.    <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1738.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001715.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  XIV.   RESULTS  OF  EXCISIONS  OF  THE  HEAD  OF  THE  HUMERUS.    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. <hi rend="initialcap">III</hi>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Private Reardon</name>.  <hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>PEC. 1738, <hi rend="initialcap">A. M. M.</hi></head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
