<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e19077">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Powers, Thomas</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e19077</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">468-469</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term> 
                                                                  <term>incised wounds, contusions, and miscellaneous injuries</term>
                                                                  <term>bayonet wounds</term>
                                                                  <term>bayonet entered next to middle of xiphoid cartilage</term>
                                                                  <term>bayonet wounded diaphragm and liver</term>
                                                                  <term>stabbed by refractory prisoner</term>
                                                                  <term>disability total</term>
                                                                  <term>traumatic pleurisy</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                                <p> CASE. <name type="person">Corporal Thomas Powers</name>, <name type="organization">Co. G, 2d United
                                                  States Infantry</name>, aged 40 years, was stabbed by a
                                                  bayonet in the hands of a refractory prisoner on
                                                                <date type="injury" when="1862-12-02">December 2d, 1862</date>. The bayonet entered
                                                  one-half inch to the right of the median line of
                                                  the chest, immediately next to the middle of the
                                                  xiphoid cartilage, penetrated four inches in a
                                                  direction downward and outward, entering the chest
                                                  over the costal cartilages of the eighth, ninth,
                                                  and tenth ribs. On receipt of the injury there
                                                  was prostration, vomiting for two days, difficulty
                                                  of breathing, incapacity to draw a long breath,
                                                  total absence of movement of ribs of lower part of
                                                  right chest, and decubitus on injured side; no
                                                  respiration heard on lower part of right chest;
                                                  puerile respiration above and over the whole of
                                                  the left chest, mixed, however, in some parts of
                                                  the left chest, with mucous sounds of bronchitis.
                                                  Gentle stimulants and essence of beef were given.
                                                  On December 5th, the vomiting had ceased. He was
                                                  transferred to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, on
                                                                <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-11">December 11th</date>; at that time, the wound was closed
                                                  and the orifice of it covered over by a small,
                                                  dark-colored, triangular-shaped scab. He
                                                  complained much of darting pains and stitches in
                                                  the right side. He exhibited dyspnœa and
                                                  increased frequency of the respiratory movements.
                                                  At times, the dyspnœa was so great as to compel
                                                  him to sit up in bed. There was a moderate amount
                                                  of effusion in cavity of right pleura, with
                                                  friction sounds higher up on the same side. He was
                                                  directed to keep quiet in bed, to be supported by
                                                  a nourishing diet, to take fluid extract of
                                                  cinchona, combined with iodide of potassium, and,
                                                  with a view to still further promote absorption
                                                  and combat the traumatic pleurisy, to have a
                                                  succession of blisters applied to his right chest.
                                                  About Christmas, he had a severe exacerbation of
                                                  all his symptoms, which was combated by the
                                                  application of wet and dry cups. A fresh pleurisy
                                                  was lighted up in the early part of January, 1863,
                                                  which was treated in the same way. Under the tonic
                                                  and supporting plan of treatment, he mended slowly
                                                  in spite of the relapses, and by January 25th, was
                                                  able to sit up most of the time. He was discharged
                                                  from service, at his own request, on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-02-02">February 2d,
                                                  1863</date>. He was still very feeble and wan, had
                                                  dyspnœa, and percussion showed that the pleuritic
                                                  effusion, although diminished in quantity, still
                                                  remained, but the dyspnœa appeared to be much
                                                  greater than could be accounted for satisfactorily
                                                  by the amount of the effusion. <name type="person">Examining Surgeon Frank S. Porter</name> reports, <date type="pension" when="1867-10-30">October 30th, 1867</date>: The bayonet
                                                  entered the chest on the median line, at the lower
                                                  end of the sternum, and, ranging downward and
                                                  backward, wounded the diaphragm and liver. The
                                                  result is enlargement of the left lobe of the
                                                  liver, severe cough, bloody purulent
                                                  expectoration, hæmorrhage of the bowels, with
                                                  great emaciation. Disability total. </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
