<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41412">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Shippy, Azro A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41412</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">191</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>pneumonia</term>
       <term>small tubercles in apex of lung</term>
       <term>lower lobes both lungs in first stage of pneumonia</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of lower ileum thickened and inflamed</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon and rectum thickened, inflamed, and ulcerated</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-14">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 457.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Azro A. Shippy</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 2d United States sharpshooters</name>; age 41; admitted from the depot hospital of the 2d Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-11-02">November 2, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-11-20">November 20th</date>, of pneumonia.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-11-20">ten hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis very great; body very much emaciated. Head, neck, and spinal column not examined. There were extensive pleuritic adhesions on the right side. A few small tubercles, not softened, were observed in the apex of the right lung; the lower lobe was generally in the first stage of pneumonia, but small portions of it were hepatized; there were old pleuritic adhesions on the left side posteriorly; the upper lobe of the left lung was normal, the lower lobe in the same condition as the lower lobe of the right lung. The pericardium contained about two drachms of serum. The heart was normal. The liver was normal; the gall-bladder contained about half an ounce of bile. The spleen was slightly enlarged. The pancreas and mesenteric glands normal. The cortical substance of the kidneys was pale. The mucous membrane of the stomach was congested; that of the jejunum normal; that of the lower part of the ileum thickened and very much inflamed. The mucous membrane of the colon and rectum was thickened, inflamed, and ulcerated in several places.—<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
