<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e13119">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Barnett, D. A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e13119</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">292-293</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of intermediary amputation in the lower third of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot wound of knee joint</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage when wounded, anæmic when admitted</term>
     <term>bullet entered leg at lower border of patella, removed through incision at median line posteriorly</term>
     <term>obliteration of main vessel, no circulation in foot, leg half way to knee cold and purple or tallow colored, early stages of traumatic sphacelus</term>
     <term>ball comminuted patella and passed through femur, entering at outer margin of inner condyle and dividing popliteal artery</term>
     <term>pyæmia</term>
     <term>pleural cavity with effusion of yellow pus and serum, separated into strata of upper serum and lower pus</term>
     <term>diseased spots in lung suggested embolism, somewhat triangular in shape</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>phlebitis, compared to phlegmasia alba dolens</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>   
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-21">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 472.—<name type="person" key="1095">Sergeant D. A.
      Barnett</name>, <name type="organization" key="182">Co. B, 99th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 22
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="xx">Kelly's Ford</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7, 1863</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon J. W.
      Lyman</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded his admission to
     the field hospital of the 1st division, Third Corps, with "shot wound of left knee joint." <date type="transfer" when="1863-11-09">Two
     days after the reception of the injury</date> the wounded man was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, whence <name type="person" key="200">Assistant
      Surgeon W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, reported the
     following history: "The patient was anæmic when admitted, and stated that very free
     hæmorrhage took place the moment he was wounded. He was struck by a bullet, which entered
     the leg at the lower border of the patella, and was removed through an incision at the median
     line posteriorly, four inches above the joint. An examination showed the probable obliteration of the
     main vessel, since there was no circulation in the foot, which, with the leg half way to the
     knee, was cold and purple or tallow colored, and in the early stages of traumatic sphacelus.
     This, added to the direct wound of the knee joint, rendered an operation necessary, which was
     performed on <date type="operation" when="1863-11-10">November 10th</date>. Ether was given, and the limb was removed by <name type="person" key="454">Acting Assistant Surgeon P. R. Holly</name>, at the lower third of the thigh,
     by the circular method, with a straight cut from the wound of exit to the point of the circular
     incision. The operation was well borne and there was no serious loss of blood. On examining the amputated
     leg, I found that the ball had comminuted the patella and passed through the femur, entering at the outer margin of the inner
     condyle and dividing the popliteal artery. The popliteal space contained a large quantity of
     coagulated blood, and the ends of the vessel were surrounded by a mass of pink-colored and
     semi-organized clot, sufficiently firm to prevent hæmorrhage. The patient's tongue was
     very pallid and his whole appearance anæmic. His leg soon became swollen though perfectly
     white, resembling a case of phlegmasia alba dolens. The skin was smooth and blanched; there was
     tenderness along the line of the bone and no vigorous effort at repair, the edges of the
     incision being pale. The discharge consisted of dark colored ill-looking pus, and the whole
     appearance of the stump was unfavorable; the edges gaped widely apart. On November 20th, a
     slight slough appeared on the posterior lip of the stump, and two days afterwards the patient
     had a severe chill, followed by profuse perspiration in the night and succeeded by a light
     cough. During the night of the 23d there was another severe chill, and the next day respiration
     was increased in frequency and accompanied by pain in the right side. There was no perceptible dullness on
     percussion, but on auscultation it was found that inspiration was deep and a little labored,
     while the expiration over both lungs anteriorly was prolonged almost as in phthisis. There was
     no rale, but the expiratory sound seemed to indicate that the whole lung had lost some of its
     elasticity and returned upon itself after dilatation with apparent difficulty. Expectoration
     was slight, very tough and viscid; the pulse rapid and feeble; the skin relaxed. The pulse
     became still weaker, and the respiration more hurried until almost sighing; the nervous
     depression increased. The breath had the sweet sickening smell resembling the odor of
     fermentation, which denotes pyæmia. Death occurred at 8 A. M. on <date type="death" when="1863-11-26">November 26, 1863</date>. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination
     was made six hours afterwards. On opening the right pleural cavity we found the lung coated
     with soft greenish colored lymph, and there was an effusion amounting to six ounces of yellow
     pus and serum, separating into two strata, the upper serum, the lower pus, and having (under
     the microscope) the usual pus corpuscles floating in a fluid with an abundance of unrecognizable
     debris. There seemed to be also a thin layer of pus beneath the pleura anteriorly, giving that portion of the lung a yellowish color. The upper
     lobe was apparently normal; the lower lobe posteriorly was congested, dark in color, and, on
     division, revealed nodules of tissue of various sizes in all stages of pathological changes
     from acute congestion to thorough hepatization and yellow softening. The diseased spots were in
     dimension from the size of half an English walnut to that of a split pea, the large ones having
     in the center a space white or yellow in color, and probably breaking down rapidly. The outline
     of these solidified portions, on section, suggested the idea of embolism, since they were
     somewhat triangular in shape, with the base at the pleural surface and the apex at the deepest
     portion of the lung, giving the impression that a circumscribed area of lung nourished by a
     single vessel had been destroyed by its occlusion. There was no recent effusion in the left
     pleural cavity, but changes in the parenchyma similar to those on the right side were
     discovered. An examination of the vessels of the stump revealed the existence of inflammation
     of the artery and veins. Both the femoral artery and vein at the point of their escape from the
     pelvis were normal. The femoral vein at the entrance of the saphena was filled with a
     semi-organized clot, which extended through the saphena and femoral to a point two inches from
     the cut ends of these vessels, where they had been divided on the face of the stump. (See
     left-hand figure of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XX</hi>, opposite p. 294.) These vessels, as
     will be seen, are now hard and firm dark-red cords, of course entirely impervious. The artery
     from the origin of the profunda to a point two inches from its cut termination was also
     reddened, and its inner coat softened and easily removable. The phlebitis, with its occlusion
     of the main venous trunks, accounted for the swollen and white condition of the stump, compared
     above to the condition known as phlegmasia alba dolens. In making this dissection it was
     observed that the inflammation, apparent in the artery and to some extent circumscribed (since
     its lower extremity yet contained the clot formed on the application of the ligature and was
     normal both in color and firmness, as well as that which occluded the veins), had extended
     through the coats of these vessels from without. No pus was found in the veins, and no evidence
     of inflammation except the marked redness of the coats and the firm and clotted coagulation of
     the blood within." Wet preparations of the femoral and profunda arteries (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 2246), the femoral and saphena veins (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 3991), and the popliteal artery and vein (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 2247), saved from the stump, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon Thomson</name>. Drawings of the specimens 3991 and 2246 were
     prepared by <name type="person" key="878">Hospital Steward Stauch</name>, and are represented,
     the former on the left and the latter on the right side of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XX</hi>,
     opposite p. 294.</p>
   
    <figure>
     <graphic url="cww.001817.001"/>
     <head>PLATE  XX.    FEMORAL  ARTERY  AND  FEMORAL  VEIN  AFTER  AMPUTATION.</head> 
    </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
