<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41023">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Claus, John C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e41023</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">163</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa of four months duration</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of foot</term>
       <term>ileum deeply congested</term>
       <term>numerous ulcers in large intestine, largest and most abundant in sigmoid flexure and rectum</term>
       <term>many ulcers in colon penetrated to muscular coat</term>
       <term>liver acini indistinct</term>
       <term>pleuritic adhesions, lobes of lungs interadherent, posteriorly all lobes intensely congested</term>
       <term>bronchial glands contained black pigment</term>
       <term>pancreas dark slate-color</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 350.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private John C. Claus</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company B, 43d New York volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-24">February 24, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa of four months duration; he had also a gunshot wound of the left foot, received at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>.  He was exceedingly emaciated, and had from two to four loose stools daily.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-02-28">February 28th</date>.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Daniel Weisel</name>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-03-01">thirty-eight hours after death</date>: Height five feet six inches; no rigor mortis; body very much emaciated. The brain weighed forty-eight ounces and a half; it was firm, injected with blood, the ventricles full of serum; there were old pleuritic adhesions on both sides. The lobes of the lungs were interadherent; the right lung weighed eighteen ounces, the left sixteen; posteriorly all the lobes of both lungs were intensely congested. The bronchial glands contained a great deal of black pigment. The heart weighed five ounces and a half; it was soft and flabby; there was no adipose tissue about it. The pericardium contained no fluid. The liver weighed thirty-nine ounces; it was dark-brown, firm, its acini indistinct; the gall-bladder contained two drachms of reddish viscid bile and a gall-stone quarter of an inch in diameter. The spleen weighed three ounces and a quarter; it was purple, friable, intensely congested inferiorly, its trabeculæ indistinct. The pancreas was of a dark slate-color, and weighed one ounce and three-quarters. The suprarenal capsules were large, tough, and of a dark coffee-color. The kidneys weighed four ounces each; they were dark colored, tough, and congested inferiorly. The rugæ of the stomach were indistinct. The jejunum was of a reddish slate-color; in its middle third a few inches of the tube were extremely dilated and very thin; the ileum was deeply congested. There were numerous ulcers, varying from the size of a pin's head to that of a half dime, in all parts of the large intestine; they were largest and most abundant in the sigmoid flexure and rectum; these ulcers, in the colon, were chiefly arranged in rows corresponding to the longitudinal muscular bands; many of them penetrated to the muscular coat.—<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
