<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e4773">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Haner, Abraham</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e4773</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">247-248</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>case-books of Seminary Hospital, D. C.</term>
                                        <term>remittent fever</term>
                                        <term>evidence of co-existence of typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>peritonitis</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00119">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 119.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Typhoid fever following remittent fever; prognosis
                                                favorable until the advent of
                                                peritonitis.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="577">Private Abraham Haner</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="623">Co. D, 14th N. Y.
                                                Vols.</name>; age 21; was admitted <date
                                                type="admit" when="1861-09-23">Sept. 23,
                                        1861</date>, as a case of remittent fever. He had been
                                        epileptic from infancy to the age of 19, when the fits
                                        ceased. He was taken <date type="injury" when="1861-09">two weeks before admission</date> with a
                                        convulsion. Quinine was given but the convulsions recurred.
                                        On admission his face was flushed, eyes injected, bowels
                                        loose and abdomen painful. A slight fever was present on the
                                        25th; appetite deficient, thirst considerable, pulse 88,
                                        full and strong, skin warm and moist (he had perspired
                                        profusely at night), tongue light-brown and fissured; he had
                                        a little headache and dizziness. Acetate of ammonia was
                                        prescribed with five drops of Fowler's solution four times
                                        daily. He did not sleep well at night, and on the 26th was
                                        restless, his cheeks flushed, eyes suffused, pulse 96, skin
                                        hot and moist, tongue brown and dry in the centre, fissured
                                        and moist at the edges; he had headache and slight delirium,
                                        pain in the stomach, pain and great tenderness in the iliac
                                        region, some cough and difficulty in retaining urine. The acetate of ammonia was continued and
                                        turpentine emulsion was ordered for administration every two
                                        hours. In the evening the skin was moist, the pulse 102, the
                                        tongue yellowish. Hoffmann's anodyne was prescribed in
                                        drachm doses every four hours. He slept but little during
                                        the night, and on the 27th the pulse was 96, skin hot and
                                        dry, tongue dry in the centre, moist at the edges; he had
                                        headache, anorexia, tympanites on the right side, tenderness
                                        in the right iliac region and his bowels had been moved six
                                        times. Turpentine emulsion and Fowler's solution were
                                        renewed and pills of opium, lead and tannin prescribed. In
                                        the evening the pulse was 104, the skin hot and moist but
                                        with no eruption nor sudamina, the tongue rather yellow in
                                        the centre but less fissured; the headache was lessened and
                                        the diarrh&#339;a reduced to one stool, but the
                                        tenderness and tympanites continued. Sweet spirit of nitre
                                        and wine of antimony were administered during the night. He
                                        slept well and perspired early in the morning; no stool was
                                        passed. On the 28th the skin was hot and moist, tongue
                                        brown, dry and fissured in the centre, its edges moist and
                                        white; the anorexia, headache and cough persisted, and there
                                        was partial retention of urine, with pain in the
                                        hypogastrium. Extract of buchu was given. In the evening the
                                        face was flushed, eyes bright, pulse strong and regular,
                                        skin soft but somewhat hot, tongue moist, white and
                                        fissured; bowels moved once, tender and tympanitic; the
                                        cough had subsided and the appetite was returning. Dover's
                                        powder was ordered. He slept well during the night, and on
                                        the 29th the face was somewhat flushed, eyes injected, pulse
                                        88 and strong, skin hot and moist, tongue brown and dry in
                                        the centre, moist at the edges, the bowels quiet but a
                                        little tender and tympanitic. In the evening there was
                                        slight headache; the bowels were moved once, but the
                                        tenderness and distention continued; the appetite was good.
                                        Tincture of opium and essence of peppermint were
                                        administered. On the 30th the skin was soft and its
                                        temperature decreased; the tongue moist at the edges, brown
                                        and dry in the centre, the appetite moderate; three stools
                                        were passed and there was much tympanites with marked
                                        tenderness in the right iliac region and some in the left
                                        side. On October 1 the skin was natural, the tongue slightly
                                        coated in the centre and fissured, the appetite good and the
                                        bowels quiet. He improved after this, so that from the 3d to
                                        the 6th no note of his condition was recorded. On the 7th
                                        the pulse was 85, skin natural, tongue moist but red at the
                                        tip and edges, yellow and fissured in the centre; bowels
                                        moved three times. No marked change occurred until the 10th,
                                        when the skin became hot and dry, followed on the 11th by a
                                        profuse eruption of rose-colored spots; on this day the
                                        tongue was slightly moist, yellow in the centre, the
                                        appetite good and the bowels quiet, but the abdomen was
                                        tender and tympanitic, especially in the umbilical and right
                                        iliac regions. Tincture of iron was prescribed. Fresh crops
                                        of rose-colored spots appeared at intervals until the 28th,
                                        when they faded. The heat of skin gradually lessened until
                                        on the 16th it became normal; two days later the skin was
                                        moist. The bowels were moved once or seldom twice daily, but
                                        a good deal of tenderness and distention was noted in the
                                        umbilical and right iliac regions. On the 20th extract of
                                        senna was administered and two passages followed its
                                        exhibition. The patient usually slept well and his appetite
                                        was good; the tongue was moist and clean, faintly furred or
                                        yellow-coated in the centre. He appeared to be doing well
                                        when, on <date type="injury" when="1861-10-29">the 29th</date>, he was seized with extreme tenderness of
                                        the abdomen. After a wakeful night his eyes on the 30th were
                                        dull, cheeks flushed, pulse 100, skin hot, tongue moist,
                                        brown and fissured, lips and teeth covered with sordes; he
                                        had some deafness and mental <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice>, anorexia and thirst;
                                        there was no diarrh&#339;a, but much general abdominal
                                        tenderness and some tympanites. A blister was applied to the
                                        abdomen and calomel and opium prescribed for administration
                                        every three hours. On <date type="death"
                                                when="1861-10-31">the 31st</date> the pulse was 140 and
                                        irregular and the skin bathed in perspiration, but the
                                        abdomen was less tender. Death took place on this day. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
