<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5302">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Christopher, T. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5302</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">105</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>ball entered below and behind trochanter major</term>
     <term>fragments of neck and head of femur removed</term>
     <term>acetabulum eroded</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>


   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 245.&#8212;<name type="person" key="950">Private <hi
      rend="italic">T. C. Christopher</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="391">Co. D, 18th
     South Carolina</name>, aged 21 years, a robust man, was wounded at <name type="battle"
     key="xxx">Williamsburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-05-05">May 5,
     1862</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which entered about two inches below and behind the
    left trochanter major, and passed forward, upward, and inward. He was stooping at the time he
    received the injury. He was made prisoner, and sent to <name type="place">York River</name>, and
    thence on a hospital steamer to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and
    placed in <name type="hospital" key="163">Cliffburne Hospital</name>, <date type="admit"
     when="1862-05-17">May 17th</date>. His pulse was 100, and he complained of severe pain in the
    hip and knee. The tissues about the hip were much swollen; the limb was everted, and shortened
    one and a half inches. The opening made by the bullet was very small, and discharged a thin
    sanious pus. There was no orifice of exit. The patient was etherized, and careful exploration of
    the wound revealed a fracture of the inner portion of the neck and probably of the head of the
    femur. It was decided that excision should be performed, and the patient was placed upon a
    soothing and supporting regimen preparatory to the operation. <date type="operation"
     when="1862-05-20">May 20th</date>, <name type="person" key="294">Assistant Surgeon J. S.
     Billings</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, made a curvilinear
    incision, four inches in length, one inch behind the great trochanter, that revealed the
    condition of the parts. Fragments of the inner extremity of the neck were removed piecemeal. The
    head was then removed from the cotyloid cavity, except a small fragment which was extracted from
    an intermuscular space. The ball was now discovered lying in the obturator externus muscle, and
    extracted. Little blood was lost, and reaction took place. Water dressing was applied, and a
    grain of sulphate of morphia administered. Eversion of the foot was corrected by fastening the
    limb by straps of adhesive plaster to an upright piece of wood screwed to the foot of the
    bedstead, and, the latter being raised, adequate extension and counter-extension were secured.
    On May 21st, the patient reported a comfortable night, but now had a very irritable stomach,
    with frequent vomiting. His skin was cool and clammy; his pulse small and feeble at 115. He was
    ordered aromatic spirits of ammonia in small doses, brandy, egg-nog, and beef essence, with
    sinapisms to the epigastrium. On May 23d, the irritability of the stomach had subsided. The
    patient was weaker; stimulants and concentrated nourishment were given. On May 24th, the patient
    rapidly grew weaker. Capillary h&#230;morrhage took place from the surfaces of the incision, but
    was readily checked by the application of a solution of persulphate of iron. Enemata of beef
    essence and brandy were administered, and these articles also by the mouth. The patient sank
    rapidly, and died <date type="death" when="1862-05-24">May 24th</date>, five days after the
    operation. At the autopsy, twelve hours after death, the soft parts about the seat of injury
    were found dark in color and softened. The acetabulum was eroded. A clot of blood of three
    ounces was found between the peritoneum and iliacus externus muscle. The innominatum and
    superior portion of the femur were removed, and, together with the excised fragments, forwarded
    to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, and numbered 19 of the
    Surgical Section, having been mounted among its earliest specimens, and it is represented in the
    wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 57).&#8212;(<hi rend="italic">Circ.</hi> 6, S. G. O.,
    1865, p. 62, and <hi rend="italic">Circ.</hi> 2, S. G. O., 1869, pp. 35, 135.)</p>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001532.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 57.&#8212;Transverse shot fracture of the anatomical neck of the
    left femur, with caries. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 19.</head></figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
