<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e29235">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Dearing, A. L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e29235</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">760-761</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and  complications</term>
       <term>shot wounds</term>
       <term>primary symptoms common to gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>pain</term> 
       <term>gunshot wound of thigh bone</term>
       <term>round musket ball in thigh, near hip joint</term>
       <term>ball struck bone without injuring it, passed around to opposite side</term> 
       <term>ball entered middle of <choice><sic>nates</sic><corr>natis</corr></choice>, part of ball removed at junction of upper and middle thirds of thigh at outer border of sartorius muscle</term>
       <term>knee swollen and painful</term>
       <term>considerable yet no very severe pain, severest and most continuous where ball entered and struck bone</term>         
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-27">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1104.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Captain A. L. Dearing</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. H, 5th Maine</name>, aged 28 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>.  He was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary Hospital</name>, Georgetown, on <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-08">May 8th</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H. W. Ducachet</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported:  &#34;Gunshot wound of left thigh bone.&#34;  The following account of the case was furnished by the patient:  &#34;I was wounded,&#34; says this officer,
    &#34;on <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">Sunday, May 3d</date>, by a round musket ball in my left thigh, very near the hip joint, the enemy being fifty or sixty yards
    distant. The sensation produced when the ball struck me was as though a ball of glass had been thrown with irresistible force
    and shivered to atoms against the bone of my thigh. This sensation was very distinct, and no other was felt for the instant. I
    have no recollection of falling; but found myself lying on my left side, with a strange feeling of numbness <hi rend="italic">rushing</hi> through the
    entire leg. This lasted but a few moments; the blood flowing freely, this <hi rend="italic">active</hi> numbness soon died away. I believed myself
    mortally wounded, as I had no doubt the bone was shattered to the hip joint. Dreading to fall into the hands of the enemy I
    dragged myself from the battle-field about two hundred yards, when some of our men carried me to a place of safety. Taken
    to the hospital at <name type="place">Falmouth</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-05-04">the 4th</date>, my wound was probed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon N. S. Barnes</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">27th New York</name>, on the morning of <date type="operation" when="1863-05-05">the 5th</date>. The probe struck the bone and followed the wound a short distance around it on the inside, without feeling the ball. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Barnes</name> decided that the ball struck the bone, and, without injuring it, glanced to the right, passing around to the opposite
    side from which it entered, and probably lay deep in the groin; but my thigh was so much swollen that the ball could not be
    found.  On <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-08">May 8th</date> I reached <name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary Hospital</name>, Georgetown. At length, after the swelling had subsided considerably, the
    ball was found near the groin and near the surface. It was extracted by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Ducachet</name> on <date type="operation" when="1863-05-18">May 18th</date>, but this ragged, misshapen piece of lead was so light that doubts were expressed as to its being a whole ball. The wound seemed to be doing well; there was considerable yet no very severe pain, the severest and most continuous being in that region where the ball entered and struck the bone. On May 27th a small piece of bone was discharged from the wound, indicating that the bone was more or less injured.  On May 28th I was attacked with a most intense pain on the inside of the thigh, midway between the wound and
    the opening where the ball had been extracted. This pain brought on fever and a severe headache. Chloroform liniment was
    freely applied and alleviated the pain. On <date type="operation" when="1863-05-31">May 31st</date> a piece of lead made its appearance at the opening where the ball had
    entered, and was extracted by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Miller</name>, and proved to be very nearly as large as that extracted on the 18th. This second
    piece of lead is very ragged, and holds a portion of the cloth which it had carried into the wound.  About <date type="injury" when="1863-06-01">the first of June</date> the
    nerves of my left foot, mostly in the toes, commenced troubling me, causing many sleepless nights and restless days for two
    weeks. It was like a continuous nervous toothache. A powerful chloroform liniment was freely applied, but it proved less
    effectual than cold water in easing the pain. This pain was not constant, but would burn my toes as with boiling water for ten
    or fifteen minutes, then ease away somewhat for a few minutes, and then return in full force. On June 12th a course of vigorous
    rubbing with a coarse towel was commenced on the foot and leg to the knee. On the third day the pain began to yield, and has
    now, June 24, 1863, almost ceased. My leg remains as yet almost perfectly helpless. It cannot support its own weight. My
    general health is very good.&#34;  The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-09-15">September 15, 1863</date>, and pensioned. The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Hartford
     examining board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1872-08-07">August 7, 1872</date>:  &#34;Ball entered at middle of left <choice><sic>nates</sic><corr>natis</corr></choice> and passed forward; part of the ball was
    removed at the junction of the upper and middle thirds of the left thigh at the outer border of the sartorius muscle. In its passage
    the ball struck the inner side of the femur, and in consequence of which portions of bone, with the remainder of the ball, were
    discharged through the point of entrance in the nates. The knee becomes swollen and painful from slight use.&#34;</p>
   <p></p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
