<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7893">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Binder, F.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e7893</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">356</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>entered as typhoid, but the clinical histories suggestive of malarial complications</term>
                                        <term>condition of Peyer's patches variously stated, but not ulcerated; intestines more or less affected</term>
                                        <term>frostbite of both feet</term>
                                        <term>gangrene of both feet</term>
                                        <term>yellowish liquid exuded from medulla of tibia</term>
                                        <term>consolidated mass and irregular areas of congestion in lower lobe of lung</term>
                                        <term>jejunum slate-colored</term>
                                        <term>whole ileum congested and valvul&#230; conniventes indistinct</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches thickened and congested</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-28">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00112">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 112.&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="662">Private F. Binder</name>,
                                                <name type="organization" key="468">Co. G, 131st
                                                Pa.</name>; age 27; was admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1862-12-30">Dec. 30, 1862</date>, with
                                        gangrene of both feet after typhoid fever.  About <date type="injury" when="1862-11-02">eight weeks
                                        prior to admission</date> he was attacked with chills and fever,
                                        but the disease afterwards assumed the character of typhoid
                                        fever. The condition of his feet was supposed to be due to
                                        frost-bite while sick in camp. On Jan. 7, 1863, the skin of
                                        both feet was reported as blue from the toes to above the
                                        ankles, where was an irregular border of redness; below the
                                        malleoli the parts were cold and a pin could be inserted
                                        without being felt.  Lines of demarcation were formed on the
                                        9th just above the malleoli; at this time the patient's
                                        appetite was improving and his tongue looking well, but his
                                        skin was slightly yellow and he complained of much pain,
                                        which he referred to his feet.  On the 22d his bowels became
                                        loose, there having been five stools during the day, and
                                        next day the tongue was somewhat dry. He slept well at night
                                        and had no night-sweats, but he lost flesh and continued to
                                        suffer from pain in the feet.  The right foot separated at
                                        the ankle-joint on the 26th, the stump having bled quite
                                        freely. <date type="operation" when="1863-01-27">Next day</date> both legs were amputated by "Le Noir's"
                                        operation, after which the patient reacted fairly and rested
                                        well.  On the 30th the stumps looked badly and discharged a
                                        grayish pus, while vomiting, hiccough and extreme depression
                                        were developed.  Death took place <date type="death" when="1863-02-02">February 2</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination
                                        <date type="autopsy" when="1863-02-03">twenty-four hours after death</date>: There were clots in all the
                                        arteries of the stumps except the right anterior tibial. On
                                        pressing the medulla of the left tibia a yellowish liquid
                                        exuded from the vascular foramina in the compact substance
                                        of the bone. The brain was healthy. The right lung weighed
                                        thirty-three ounces and three-quarters; in its lower lobe
                                        was a circumscribed, light-colored, consolidated mass and
                                        numerous light-colored points, about the size of pinheads,
                                        surrounded by irregular areas of congestion; a portion of
                                        this lobe was in the state of gray hepatization. The left
                                        lung weighed eighteen ounces and a quarter; on the posterior
                                        surface of its lower lobe and in the substance of the upper
                                        lobe were a number of discolored spots beneath which the
                                        lung-tissue was infiltrated with serum. The heart was pale
                                        and contained a small fibrinous clot in the right ventricle.
                                        The liver was pale and firm; the gall-bladder small; the
                                        spleen weighed seven ounces and a half and was very soft;
                                        the pancreas was of a grayish color; both kidneys were small
                                        and light-colored. The stomach was large, its mucous
                                        membrane slightly softened; the upper part of the jejunum
                                        was slate-colored; the whole of the ileum congested and its
                                        valvul&#230; conniventes indistinct; Peyer's patches
                                        were slightly thickened and some of them congested. The
                                        large intestine was congested.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="244">Ass't Surg. George
                                                  M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization"
                                                  key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital"
                                                  key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
