<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.1e10030">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">A&#8212;&#8212;, Lieutenant</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.1e10030</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address>
                                                <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                                                <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
                                                <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                                                <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                                        </address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>                                        
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="kb">Karli Burt</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="ch">Constance Hamer</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                        of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph
                                                K. Barnes and George A. Otis</editor>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1876">1876</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">164</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
                                        <term>wounds of the kidney</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change when="2011-05-13" who="#el">added TEI header; proofread; added mark-up</change>
                        <change when="2011-04" who="#kb #ch">checked OCR</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>
                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 510. "The records of military surgery show that gunshot wounds of
                                the kidney are almost always fatal, and being so considered, the
                                unfortunate victim is too often left to his fate without proper
                                attention. The following case presents several points of unusual
                                novelty and interest, and teaches the important lesson that the
                                surgeon should never abandon, as hopeless, any case of injury,
                                however unpromising it may seem. Patients do occasionally recover
                                from wounds of the kidney as well as from lumbar abscesses caused
                                from renal calculi, and should therefore always be treated with
                                proper care throughout. <name type="person">Lieutenant
                                        A&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization">2d
                                        Tennessee Infantry</name>, in perfect health, of robust
                                constitution and abstemious habits, was wounded in the battle of
                                <name type="battle">Shiloh</name>, on <date when="1862-04-06">April 6, 1862</date>, by a mini&#233;
                                ball, entering immediately below the heart, and passing out through
                                the upper portion of the left kidney. There was considerable
                                h&#230;morrhage, causing excessive prostration. In this condition he was
                                captured by the enemy and removed to <name type="name">Pittsburg Landing</name>, on <name type="place">Tennessee
                                        River</name>, several miles distant from the battle-field, where he
                                remained for six days without any attention, not even the removal of
                                his bloody clothing, or dressing of his wounds. He was then placed
                                upon a transport and conveyed to <name type="place">Louisville, Kentucky</name>, and sent to
                                hospital for treatment. During <date type="injury" when="1862-07">the month of July</date> following, while
                                his wounds were still discharging profusely, he was attacked with
                                typhoid fever, and a large abscess formed in the lower part of
                                abdomen, about one inch to the left of the linea alba, which caused
                                great pain. The <date  type="transfer" when="1862-08">second or third week in August</date> he was removed from
                                Louisville to <name type="place">Camp Chase</name>, by way of Cincinnati. Several days after
                                his arrival at Camp Chase, very much enervated from the prolonged
                                attack of fever, the abscess above referred to opened outwardly and
                                discharged an immense quantity of dark sanious fluid mixed with
                                urine. This greatly alarmed him, and the extreme mental anxiety,
                                added to his fearful nervous prostration, came near proving too
                                formidable for the unfortunate victim; but all of these difficulties
                                were <choice><orig>combatted</orig><reg>combated</reg></choice>  by a good constitution and the inflexible
                                determination of a veteran soldier to such a degree that, when an
                                exchange of prisoners was effected, he was able to proceed to
                                <name type="place">Vicksburg, Mississippi</name>, where he was released <date type="release" when="1862-10-01">about the first of
                                        October</date>. He commenced his journey homeward (<name type="place">Lynchburg, Virginia</name>),
                                travelling only during the day, resting at night, suffering much
                                from his wounds and abscess, which still continued to discharge an
                                admixture of unhealthy pus and urine. In about two weeks he reached
                                <name type="place">Knoxville, Tennessee</name>, at which place I was then on duty, manifesting
                                symptoms of very great nervous prostration. The second day after his
                                arrival at Knoxville I was called to see him, at the house of his
                                sister, at nine o'clock A. M., and found him with a severe chill,
                                followed by high febrile reaction. On examination, I found the
                                anterior wound entirely healed and cicatrized; the posterior wound
                                and abscess very irritable, manifesting no disposition to heal, and
                                both discharging, though not profusely, a thin sanious fluid, mixed
                                with urine. He complained of severe excruciating pains in lumbar
                                region, passing but little urine through the urethra&#8212;secretions
                                generally deranged. I ordered warm stimulating poultices to wound
                                and abscess, and administered one grain of extract of hyoscyamus. I
                                visited him again at four o'clock P. M.; found him restless, looking
                                pale, anxious, and alarmed; pulse irritable and frequent;
                                administered anodyne for the night. I saw him the succeeding morning
                                at nine o'clock; rested rather comfortably during the night, still
                                suffering from pains in lumbar region, but much more composed; pulse
                                regular but frequent; continued warm applications to wound and
                                abscess, and anodynes to relieve pain. For several days subsequent
                                he was annoyed with rigors simulating intermittent fever, but which
                                gradually subsided, leaving him much debilitated and troubled with
                                night-sweats, which were overcome by the use of elixir vitriol,
                                tannin, and sponging with stimulating lotions. I then placed him
                                upon nutritious diet and tonics, such as iron, tincture of bark, and
                                quinine. The discharge of urine and unhealthy pus continued for some
                                sixteen or eighteen days, when the discharge of urine ceased and the
                                pus became more laudable. Simple lint and sweet-oil dressings were
                                then substituted for the warm applications. The <date type="injury" when="1862-11">second or third week
                                        in November</date> the wound was almost entirely healed, with but slight
                                discharge, and about <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-15">the 15th of December</date> he resumed his journey to
                                <name type="place">Lynchburg</name>, and in a short time was entirely restored, with some
                                little impairment of general health. I met <name type="person"
                                        >Lieutenant A&#8212;&#8212;</name> in <date
                                        when="1863-10">October, 1863</date>, in perfect health, with
                                the exception that upon too frequent exercise or exposure he was
                                annoyed with some uneasiness and pain in lumbar region."</p>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
