<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e15868">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Scarborough, Ezra</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e15868</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">226</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>removal of fragments after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>discharged and pensioned</term>
          <term>recovered after fragments of bone, fractured by gunshot projectiles, were
            removed</term>
          <term>patients remained on Pension Roll</term>
          <term>musket ball fractured and depressed both tables of right parietal bone near
            vertex</term>
          <term>extremities paralyzed, fingers of left hand could be slightly flexed</term>
          <term>only motor nerves affected, sensation unaffected</term>
          <term>confusion of intellect, pupils symmetrical but sluggish to stimulus of light</term>
          <term>deep depression over original seat of injury</term>
          <term>paralysis of left side, more marked in leg than in arm</term>
          <term>limbs atrophied and weak but preserved natural movements</term>
          <term>severe pain in affected limbs</term>
          <term>speech much impaired</term>
          <term>disability total and permanent, later rated total and temporary</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2014-07-03">corrected typo in figure head</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal Ezra
          Scarborough</name>, <name type="organization" key="">Co. G, 15th New Jersey
          Volunteers</name>, aged 34 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE"
          key="10">Chancellorsville, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3d,
          1863</date>, by a musket ball, which fractured and depressed a portion of both tables of
        the right parietal bone near the vertex. He was sent to a field hospital; thence to <name
          type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and was admitted into <name
          type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-05-08"
          >May 8th</date>. The left upper and lower extremities were paralyzed, except the fingers
        of the left hand, which could be slightly flexed. The paralysis was limited to the motor
        nerves, those of sensation being unaffected. He complained of headache, and there was some
        confusion of intellect, though no delirium. The pupils were contracted and symmetrical, but
        sluggish to stimulus of light. The skin was soft, moist, and natural in temperature. Water
        dressings and ice were applied to the wound, a saline purgative was administered, and low
        diet was ordered. The case progressed favorably, and on the 10th, the patient could flex the
        left elbow. The pupils were still contracted and sluggish, the pulse ranging from 65 to 70.
        By the 25th, the patient had recovered control of the left arm, though it was not yet as
        strong as the right ; the pupils were still sluggish, but not contracted; the detached bone
        appeared elevated. On <date type="operation" when="1863-06-07">June 7th</date>, a detached
        fragment of the inner table, one inch in length and half an inch in width, was removed by
          <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization"
          key="132">U. S. V.</name> It consisted of diplo&#235; and the vitreous table, and when
        removed, the dura mater and the pulsations of the brain were distinctly visible. The pupils
        had become natural in size, contracting readily under the stimulus of light; the wound
        suppurated freely and looked healthy, having slightly contracted. The applications of ice
        were now discontinued. On the 12th, the pulse had risen from 65 to 80; paralysis of left leg
        had diminished in a marked degree. June 24th, paralysis was still diminishing, but the
        patient still complained of headache induced by constipation. July 8th, the brain pulsations
        were no longer visible, the patient was able to leave his bed, and on August 1st, could walk
        with the aid of a cane. He continued to improve rapidly, and on <date type="furlough"
          when="1863-08-17">the 17th</date>, had recovered sufficiently to go home on furlough. He
        was transferred to Ward Hospital, <name type="place">Newark, New Jersey</name>, on <date
          type="transfer" when="1863-11-13">November 13th, 1863</date>, and was discharged the
        service on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-12-11">December 11th, 1863</date>, and
        pensioned. On <date type="pension" when="1866-06-06">June 6th, 1866</date>, <name
          type="person">Pension Examiner E. Swift</name> reports that a deep depression existed over
        the original seat of injury. There was paralysis of the left side, more marked in the leg
        than in the arm. The limbs were atrophied and weak, although they preserved their natural
        movements. The patient suffered a great deal from headache and from severe pain in the
        affected limbs. His speech was much impaired, and he was unable to do manual labor. His
        disability was then rated total and permanent. A communication from the <name type="person"
          >Commissioner of Pensions</name>, dated <date type="pension" when="1868-01-03">January 3d,
          1868</date>, states that Scarborough was a pensioner, his disability being rated total and
        temporary.</p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001795.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 113.&#8212;Fragment removed from right parietal after
          gunshot fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1666, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
