<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e441">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Young, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e441</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">14-15</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>shot flesh wounds</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower limbs with injury of the larger blood-vessels</term>
     <term>wounds of blood-vessels treated without operation</term>
     <term>shot contusion of the popliteal artery</term> 
     <term><choice><orig>aneurism</orig><reg>aneurysm</reg></choice> after fourteen years</term> 
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>gunshot wound of leg</term>
     <term>wound of leg below knee</term>
     <term>ball entered near the head of tibia</term>
     <term>ball emerged through internal belly of gastrocnemius muscle behind internal condyle of the femur</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="Sarah Synovec" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded
    P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 23.&#8212;<name type="person" key="871">Private W. Young</name>, <name type="organization" key="108">Co. K, 4th New York</name>, aged 19 years,
     was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>, and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="174">Campbell Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-12-17">four days afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="872">Surgeon J. H. Baxter</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded: &#34;Gunshot wound of leg; patient transferred to Baltimore <date type="transfer" when="1863-01-08">January 8, 1863</date>.&#34; <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon L. Quick</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported that the patient was discharged from McKim's Mansion Hospital, <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1863-03-18">March 18,
       1863</date>, for &#34;gunshot wound of left leg, ball entering near the head of the tibia and
     emerging through the internal belly of the gastrocnemius muscle, producing lameness.&#34; The <name
      type="organization" key="xx">Boston Examining Board</name> certified, October 27, 1865: &#34;Has
     had wound of leg below knee,  &#42;  &#42;  ball emerging one inch below and behind the internal condyle
     of the femur, evidently passing across the internal saphenous vein. Cicatrices not adherent,
     but there is some loss of substance of muscle, and the veins of the leg are varicose, probably
     in consequence of the wound. Motions of joint good. He says he has pain in leg on walking or standing, and much pain in
     popliteal space while sitting.&#34; On <date type="pension" when="1876-08-25">August 25, 1876</date>, this pensioner came under the care of <name
      type="person" key="xx">Dr. J. Collins Warren</name>, at the <name type="hospital" key="xx">Massachusetts General Hospital</name>, who reported the further progress of the case to the <name type="organization" key="xx">Boston Society for
      Medical Improvement</name>, in the <hi rend="italic">Boston Medical and Surgical Journal</hi>,
     Vol. XCV, No. 18, as follows: &#34;Was wounded fourteen years ago, at the battle of <name
      type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, by a musket ball, which entered the calf of the
     left leg a little to the inside, and came out opposite the inner aspect of the knee joint.
     There was no unusual amount of h&#230;morrhage at the time, and the wound healed well, but on
     recovery a small bunch remained in the popliteal space, growing larger at times, and again
     almost wholly disappearing. One year ago it grew larger than before and began to pulsate. It
     soon filled the hollow of the knee, and during the last two months has spread rapidly on the
     inside of the thigh. The skin over the popliteal space is made tense by an ill-defined
     pulsating mass, which spreads along the course of the femoral artery to within eleven inches of
     the anterior superior spinous process of the ilium. The left knee is nineteen inches in
     circumference, while the right knee measures but thirteen and one-fourth inches. The patient
     suffers severely from pain in the calf and foot, which is relieved only by frequent
     subcutaneous injections of morphine. A pound cannon-ball applied to the femoral diminishes but
     does not arrest pulsation in the vessel. Heavy pressure with the hand arrests pulsation
     entirely. August 30th: The patient was etherized and pulsation in the femoral was arrested by
     two hospital tourniquets applied, near the apex of Scarpa's triangle, alternately every fifteen
     minutes for twelve hours. During this period the patient was kept profoundly etherized, about a
     pound and a half of ether having been consumed for that purpose, with the exception of a few
     minutes during the afternoon, when some beef-tea and brandy were administered. The pulse during
     this time gradually rose from the normal rate to about 120, but subsided somewhat after
     nourishment had been taken. On removing the tourniquets pulsation had ceased, although on
     auscultation a slight murmur was heard beneath the tumor. At midnight there was no return of
     the pulsation, but the next morning a slight pulsation was observed, which gradually increased
     to its previous force. September 10th: Pressure was applied as before by tourniquet without
     ether, the patient preferring to bear the pain, and was continued for twenty hours, but had no
     effect upon the pulsations, which reappeared after it was removed. <date type="operation" when="1876-09-19">September 19th</date>: The patient
     was etherized, the sac laid open, the clots, which were numerous, everted, and the artery tied
     at each end. It was found that the sac extended to the point of bifurcation of the popliteal
     artery. Two ligatures were therefore necessary at this point. The patient rallied well from the
     operation, and for the first week the wound healed rapidly. An attack of erysipelas arrested
     the healing process and reduced the patient greatly. On <date type="death" when="1876-10-03"
      >October 3d</date>, h&#230;morrhage occurred from the upper end of the wound during the
     afternoon, and although digital pressure was immediately resorted to by an attendant, and in a
     few minutes the tourniquet was applied, the patient sank, and died the same evening. <name
      type="person" key="xx">Dr. Fitz</name> showed the specimen, which consisted of the aorta from
     its origin, the left femoral, and a portion of the <choice><orig>aneurism</orig><reg>aneurysm</reg></choice> in continuity. The fatal
     h&#230;morrhage had resulted from the sloughing of the walls of the artery at the upper end of
     the <choice><orig>aneurismal</orig><reg>aneurysmal</reg></choice> sac, where the ligature had been applied. There was no alteration of the inner
     surface of the femoral artery, but the fibrous tissue was indurated around it, corresponding
     with the region where compression had been applied. The entire inner coat of the thoracic aorta
     was thickened, wrinkled, elevated in patches of an opaque grayish-white color, and the canal
     was dilated, especially that of the arch. Just above the c&#339;liac axis these alterations
     ceased abruptly, the interior of the abdominal aorta being smooth and yellow, its walls
     evidently in a normal condition. The specimen was particularly interesting from the absence of
     changes at the point of compression and the presence of chronic inflammatory conditions of the
     thoracic aorta, such as are associated with the formation of <choice><orig>aneurisms</orig><reg>aneurysms</reg></choice> in a young man in whom a
     popliteal <choice><orig>aneurism</orig><reg>aneurysm</reg></choice> had arisen directly or indirectly from a traumatic cause.&#34; </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
