<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8101">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Lowery, J. S.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e8101</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">180-181</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>missile entered middle of thigh, cut out in field above trochanter</term>
     <term>limb shortened, thigh cannot flex to pelvis</term>
     <term>perfect consolidation of the ends of the fractured femur</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 367.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1016">Lieutenant J. S.
      Lowery</name>, <name type="organization" key="392">Co. D, 146th New York</name>, aged 21
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="115">Bethesda Church</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1864-06-03">June 3, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon W. E. DeWitt, <choice><orig> jr.</orig><reg> Jr.</reg></choice></name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded his admission to a
      Fifth Corps field hospital, with a "severe wound of the right thigh caused by a mini&#233; ball." <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>,
      <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported that the patient entered <name
       type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-07">June 7th</date>, and described his injury as a "shot fracture of the
     upper third of the femur," but gave no account of any treatment but that of simple dressings.
      <name type="person" key="1017">Dr. T. M. Flandrau</name>, late Surgeon <name
      type="organization" key="392">146th New York</name>, who attended <name type="person"
      key="1016">Lieutenant Lowery</name> at the field hospital, gives the following details: The
     patient was wounded by a rifle ball while on picket duty. The missile entered at the middle of
     the thigh, toward its inner aspect, and was cut out on the field by <name type="person"
      key="xx">Assistant Surgeon G. H. Fossard</name>, <name type="organization" key="392">146th New
      York</name>, above the trochanter. The femur was fractured in its upper third. The patient was
     brought six miles on a stretcher to the field hospital of the 2d division, Fifth Corps, where I determined not to amputate, and supported the limb on
     folded blankets, so that it was very comfortable. He was then carried by some men belonging to
     the Quartermaster's Department fifteen miles further to the White House, and placed on a
     steamboat and sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>. He was left on his stretcher while on board of the transport
     and was not removed from it until placed on a bed in <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory
      Square Hospital</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-07">four days after receiving the injury</date>. At the latter place, <name type="person" key="271">Acting Assistant Surgeon T. O. Bannister</name> had immediate charge of
     the case. According to the patient's statement the limb was placed in a box, little extension
     being used and no counter-extension. Three or four small pieces of bone were discharged within
     a short time, and another small piece was cut since from under the skin. An abscess was opened
     on, the outer side of the thigh, the scar of which is conspicuous in the photograph. When the
     patient left the hospital he used crutches, the wound having closed in four or five weeks and
     the bone united firmly. He continued to use his crutches until the following April. The limb is shortened two and
     five-eighths inches; the thigh cannot be fully flexed on the pelvis, but the limb is strong,
     sound, and freely movable, with the afore-mentioned exception. When wearing a boot slightly
     thickened in the sole he limps but little. Lately he has walked six miles without difficulty,
     and is actively engaged in business." In a previous communication <name type="person"
      key="1017">Dr. Flandrau</name> stated that the very expeditious recovery of the patient was,
     no doubt, to be attributed in a large measure to his good fortune of having unusually
     comfortable transportation. <name type="person" key="1016">Lieutenant Lowery</name> became a
     pensioner from the date of his discharge from service, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-01-13">January 13, 1865</date>. Various surgeons have examined him at regular intervals, and
     certified to lameness, etc., as resulting from the injury, up to <date type="pension" when="1872-04">April, 1872</date>, since when he has
     been exempted from further examinations, owing to the permanent character of his disabilities.
     He was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. A photograph of the patient was prepared under the direction of <name type="person" key="1017">Dr.
      Flandrau</name>, who contributed it to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
      Museum</name>. It is numbered 265 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Photographic Series</hi>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
