<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e35001">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Quick, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e35001</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>   
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">767</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and complications</term>       
       <term>hæmorrhages and ligations</term>      
       <term>hæmorrhages and ligations of arteries</term>
       <term>ligations of the common carotid artery</term>
       <term>wound in face</term>
       <term>ball passing behind condyle of lower jaw, exit on side of nose</term>   
       <term>eye closed but uninjured</term>
       <term>secondary hæmorrhage from mouth and nostril</term>
       <term>diarrhœa with discharges being thin
        and light colored</term>   
       <term>artery ulcerated through anteriorly</term>
       <term>patient quite insensible</term>
       <term>wound sunken and glassy</term>   
       <term>No attempt at union of the inner coats of the vessel was discovered</term>          
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-17">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-02-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1106.—<name type="person" key="1495">Corporal J.
    Quick</name>, <name type="organization" key="430">Co. G, 38th New York</name>, aged 21 years,
    was wounded in the face, at the, battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>, a ball passing behind
    the left, condyle of the lower jaw and making its exit on the left side of the nose. The
    wounded man was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="163">Eckington Hospital</name>, at,
    <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, five days after receiving his injury, his face being very much swollen on the left
    side and the left eye being closed but uninjured. The treatment consisted of rest, aperients,
    low diet, and lead-wash locally. No fever ensued, the swelling abated, and the patient did
    very well until December 25th, when secondary hæmorrhage occurred at 4 P. M. The blood
    gushed from his mouth and left nostril, amounting to a quart in a few minutes. <name type="person" key="1496">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. N. Fisher</name>, assisted by <name type="person" key="1423">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. Edelin</name>, quickly plugged the nares with
    bits of muslin strung on threads and thrust into the nostril, which promptly stopped the
    hæmorrhage. It occurred again, however, and was controlled by thrusting in more of the
    tampon. The patient slept pretty well all night, being carefully watched and having his head
    well elevated. At 10 A. M. on December 26th he commenced bleeding again, the blood spouting
    from the wound at the side of the nose. A compress then applied over the orifice, and snugly
    bandaged, controlled the hæmorrhage. On the <date type="operation" when="1862-12-27">morning of the following day</date> the patient had another free attack of
    hæmorrhage, but it was promptly checked by increased pressure on the compress, after
    which, on consultation, it was determined to tie the common carotid artery. <name type="person" key="1496">Acting Assistant Surgeon Fisher</name> accordingly ligated that vessel just
    above the omo-hyoid muscle, the patient not being etherized. The plugs were then removed from
    the nostril and the compress from the face, and no hæmorrhage recurred. The patient was
    put to bed, and the face and fresh wound were dressed with cold water. With the aid of an
    anodyne the patient slept well during the following night. The next morning his pulse was 120,
    a very slight pulsation being detected in the left temporal artery and that side of the head
    preserving its warmth. He was now also afflicted with diarrhœa, the discharges being thin
    and light colored. Beef tea and stimulants were ordered. On December 30th the pulse had
    increased to 150; patient's mind wandering; very restless; diarrhœa still continuing.
    Opium pills were now prescribed and the stimulants continued. On <date type="death" when="1863-01-02">January 2, 1863</date>, the patient was quite insensible, but gave answers
    when aroused; diarrhœa still continuing; stools frequent and involuntary; skin cold;
    pulse 140 and weak; wound looking sunken and glassy. In addition to opiates vegetable
    astringents were now ordered. Being unable to swallow solids and feeling choked by swallowing
    liquids, he was ordered oysters, which he ate greedily and swallowed readily. On January 4th
    the patient was still in a stupor; skin cold; pulse 146; some little redness about wound of
    face; wound of neck suppurating. In the afternoon a sanious discharge came on from the place
    of operation, giving reason to fear hæmorrhage from the artery. Ihe oozing from the neck
    continued, and the patient's condition was about the same on <date type="death" when="1863-01-05">the following day</date> until 2.30 P.
    M., when the attending surgeon was called in haste and found that the carotid had given way
    and the blood was gushing per saltum from the wound. Death supervened in a few minutes. At the
    post-mortem examination the artery was found to have ulcerated through anteriorly where the
    ligature was applied. No attempt at union of the inner coats of the vessel was discovered, and
    no fibrinous deposit was found on the cardiac side, it having doubtless been forced out by the
    hæmorrhage. The distal side was, however, occupied by a plug extending up to the
    bifurcation of the vessel. The history of the case, together with the injured portion of the
    ligated artery (<hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 898), represented in the annexed cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 421), was contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by the operator.</p>
   
  <figure>
   <graphic url="cww.001673.001"/>
   <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 421—Left common carotid; ulceration of artery without formation of clot. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 898.</head>
  </figure>  
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
