<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2646">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Billington, Hiram</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e2646</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">226</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>seminary hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>delirium</term> 
                                        <term>rose-colored spots</term>
                                        <term>head hot and painful in temporal regions</term> 
                                        <term>abdominal tenderness</term> 
                                        <term>slight relaxation of the bowels</term>
                                        <term>mind at times disturbed</term>
                                        <term>acute tenderness in both iliac regions</term>
                                        <term>typhoid cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>pneumonia</term>                                                                                
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00038">
                        
                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 38.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"
                                                >Delirium and rose-colored spots on the 9th and
                                                following days; intestinal symptoms not severe. A
                                                favorable change on the 16th day is interrupted by
                                                the occurrence of pneumonia; improvement on the 32d
                                                day.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="498">Private Hiram Billington</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="630">Co. F, 2d Me.</name>;
                                        age 29; admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-10-07">Oct.
                                                7, 1861</date>. Diagnosis&#8212;typhoid fever.
                                        He was taken with headache on <date type="injury" when="1861-10-01">Oct. 1</date> and with pain in the
                                        back on the 3d, but had no chill, diarrh&#339;a nor
                                        eruption. On the evening of the 7th he was somewhat dull,
                                        his face flushed dark-red, pupils dilated, head hot and
                                        painful in the temporal regions where the arteries throbbed
                                        strongly; tongue red at the tip and coated in the middle;
                                        skin hot and moist; he had pain in the back, slight cough,
                                        abdominal tenderness and slight relaxation of the bowels;
                                        pulse 100. Cold water was applied to the head and five
                                        grains each of calomel and jalap given at once. Next day he
                                        had two thin stools, his tongue was cleaning and his pulse
                                        lowered to 90, but to the headache, flushed face and other
                                        symptoms of the previous day some deafness was added.
                                        Quinine was ordered. The dilatation of the pupils continued
                                        on the 9th with increasing dimness of vision and
                                        musc&#230; volitantes; the patient muttered in his
                                        sleep, and even when awake his mind was at times disturbed;
                                        he had a dry cough and pain in the chest, but his
                                        respiration was not accelerated; his bowels were moved
                                        twice, and he had acute tenderness in both iliac regions but
                                        no borborygmus nor tympanites; his skin was hot and moist
                                        and showed a few rose-colored spots on the chest and
                                        abdomen; his tongue was quite red, moist and clean, and he
                                        had anorexia and great thirst; pulse 88; urine chemically
                                        and microscopically normal. He was very drowsy on the 10th
                                        and had violent delirium in the afternoon. Next day a few
                                        more rose-spots came out, the skin became warm and dry and
                                        the tongue very dry, hard and fissured; two thin stools were
                                        passed with gurgling but no tympanites. On the 12th the red
                                        spots had become darker in color; there was less delirium,
                                        but the eyes were somewhat suffused and the expression
                                        stupid. Turpentine emulsion and spirit of Mindererus and of
                                        nitre were given. On the 13th the mind was clear and the
                                        countenance natural, but there was some dizziness at times;
                                        pulse 80, steady; skin soft and warm; tongue dry in the
                                        centre, moist at the edges, quite pale and slightly coated;
                                        the anorexia continued, but the thirst was lessened; three
                                        stools were passed. The bowels were moved but once on the
                                        14th and were quiet on the 15th, on which day a few more
                                        rose-spots appeared. During the night he slept well, and on
                                        the l6th the skin was moist and warm; the tongue cleaning
                                        from tip and edges but still coated in the centre; the
                                        bowels continued quiet. Citrate of iron and quinine was
                                        given. During the ten days which followed there was but
                                        little change in the patient's condition; the bowels were
                                        quiet or moved once daily, with more or less of tenderness;
                                        the skin was warm and moist in the day-time and frequently
                                        bathed in perspiration at night, and the tongue was moist;
                                        but on the 25th, after a sleepless night, the tongue became
                                        dry and fissured, and complaint was made of cough and pain
                                        in the pr&#230;cordia, near which submucous and sibilant r&#226;les were heard. A blister was applied, and on the 27th one
                                        drachm of Epsom salt and a half grain of tartar emetic were
                                        given three times daily. Next day there was mucous
                                        expectoration with <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> over the lower part of the left
                                        lung, and the patient became delirious. Brandy-punch was
                                        substituted for the tartar emetic mixture. On the 29th the
                                        patient was very drowsy, moaned frequently and muttered in
                                        his delirium; his tongue was coated with scales, dry in the
                                        centre, pale and moist at the edges; the teeth and gums were
                                        thickly covered with sordes; the skin was hot and moist;
                                        pulse 96; respiration 33, short, quick and somewhat labored;
                                        r&#226;les were heard in the lower parts of the lungs, and to a
                                        less extent in the upper parts; the expectoration was
                                        rust-colored; the bowels were moved twice and were tender
                                        and tympanitic. Calomel and opium in repeated doses were
                                        ordered on the 30th. On the 31st there was much cough with
                                        rusty sputa. A slight improvement was manifested on November
                                        1. He slept well during the following night, and on the
                                        morning of the 2d looked bright although very weak; some
                                        thirst continued, but there was a slight appetite, and the
                                        teeth, gums and lips were clean; the tongue was moist,
                                        deeply fissured and covered with white patches; the urine
                                        contained a trace of albumen. Slight salivation occurred on
                                        the 4th, on which day the urine was found to be normal. The
                                        last entry with regard to the case, dated on the 7th, shows
                                        the patient as having rested well during the preceding night
                                        and as being bright and cheerful at the morning visit, the
                                        pulse 88 and of good strength, the skin soft and warm, the
                                        tongue soft, moist, fissured and coated; some cough
                                        continued and the bowels were moved twice, but there was no
                                        tenderness. He was transferred to hospital at <name type="place">Alexandria,
                                                Va.</name>, on <date type="transfer" when="1861-12-20">December
                                                20</date>. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
