<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e4374">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Beninger, Christopher</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e4374</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">243-244</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>remittent fever</term>       
                                        <term>malarial attack</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00105">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 105.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Record given in full. The existing malarial attack
                                        appears to have ended on <date when="1861-10-07">October 7</date>, when the pulse
                                                had fallen to 80 and the skin and tongue were in
                                                natural condition, leaving the patient, however,
                                                with a diarrh&#339;a, suggesting a congested and
                                                perhaps ulcerated condition of the bowels, and some
                                                pulmonary engorgement. The typhoid fever is unmarked
                                                by prominent symptoms; its influence, other than in
                                                the appearance of the rose-colored spots, seems only
                                                to have prolonged the period needful to a return to
                                                health. It is noticeable that on October 16, while
                                                the rose-spots were yet fading, the patient was
                                                permitted to be out on pass.</hi>&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="563">Corporal Christopher
                                                Beninger</name>, <name type="organization" key="530"
                                                >Co. D, 3d Mich.</name>; age 26; had been liable to
                                        attacks of intermittent fever since <date when="1858">1858</date>. He was admitted
                                                <date type="admit" when="1861-09-28">Sept. 28,
                                                1861</date>, as a case of typhoid fever. He had been
                                        taken sick three days before with chills, fever and pain in
                                        the back, and had taken quinia; face flushed, eyes dull,
                                        lids dropped; pulse 104, small, easily compressed; skin
                                        moist, slightly above natural temperature; tongue moist,
                                        slightly coated white; anorexia and irritability of stomach
                                        manifested by unsuccessful efforts at vomiting; tenderness
                                        over entire abdomen, slight tympanites in right iliac
                                        region, no stool; dull, heavy head-pain; nervous twitchings
                                        of muscles; no cough but respiration hurried, 30 per minute.
                                        During the examination a violent chill came on; the
                                        extremities became cold, the pulse small and at times
                                        imperceptible at the wrist, the cheeks cold, the breathing
                                        hurried and interrupted, the eyes turned upward; some stupor
                                        was also noted. Quinia, opium and calomel were ordered to be
                                        given every four hours. 29th, <hi rend="italic">morning</hi>: Slept some; face congested; eyes suffused;
                                        pulse 120, quick, feeble; some pain in head and limbs; some
                                        deafness and stupor; skin of natural temperature; tongue
                                        dry, brown, moist at edges; anorexia; epigastric and general
                                        abdominal tenderness; tympanites; derangement of liver; no
                                        cough. Milk-punch, beef-essence and blue-mass and opium were
                                        ordered. <hi rend="italic">Evening</hi>: Feeling better;
                                        face flushed; eyes suffused; head dull and heavy; pulse 120,
                                        full and strong; skin moist; tongue moist at edges, brown
                                        and dry in centre; anorexia; slight tenderness in abdomen,
                                        particularly in right iliac region; some tympanites and
                                        borborygmus; no stool; no cough. Dover's powder was given.
                                        30th, <hi rend="italic">morning</hi>: Slept well; cheeks
                                        congested; eyes dull; head-pain; pulse 112, quick, small;
                                        skin hot and moist; tongue moist at edges, dry in the
                                        centre; anorexia; tympanites; slight tenderness in right
                                        iliac region, marked in left; much soreness in right
                                        hypochondriac region; two stools. Ordered three grains of
                                        calomel, one of opium and one-sixth of a grain of antimony
                                        every three hours. <hi rend="italic">Evening</hi>: Drowsy;
                                        face congested; eyes dull; head-pain; pulse 112, strong;
                                        skin above the natural temperature, covered with
                                        perspiration; tongue slightly moist at tip and edges, dry
                                        and brownish in centre; four stools; slight tympanites;
                                        tenderness im left iliac region. Ordered astringents.
                                        October 1, <hi rend="italic">morning</hi>: Head-pain; pulse
                                        112, quick, strong; skin moist, slightly above the natural
                                        temperature; tongue moist at edges, dry and white in centre;
                                        appetite small; several stools; some cough; pain in right
                                        lung; respiration 30. Ordered beef-essence and astringents.
                                                <hi rend="italic">Evening</hi>: Ordered one grain of
                                        quinia and two grains of Dover's powder every three hours.
                                        2d: Slept some; face congested; eyes dull; slight head-pain;
                                        pulse 105, quick and strong; skin hot and moist; tongue
                                        moist, coated white in patches in centre; some appetite;
                                        slight tenderness; no tympanites: paroxysms of coughing;
                                        mucous expectoration streaked with blood; respiratory murmur
                                        in lower lobes of right lung entirely lost. Veratrum viride
                                        and sweet spirit of nitre were ordered to be taken every
                                        hour. 3d: Slept some; head-pain and slight delirium; pulse
                                        112, quick, strong; skin somewhat hot; tongue moist, clean
                                        but for a few yellowish patches in centre; some appetite;
                                        two stools; much cough; viscid mucous expectoration streaked
                                        with blood; respiration 35; respiratory murmur absent over
                                        lower part of right side; some <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion on both
                                        sides. 4th: Slept but little; some head-pain; pulse 108,
                                        strong; skin hot; tongue moist, covered with yellowish
                                        patches in centre; vomiting; anorexia; three stools; some
                                        cough; mucous expectoration streaked with blood; respiration
                                        30 but deeper; <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> decreased in left lung, increased in
                                        right. Fifteen drops of veratrum viride were given during
                                        the day. 5th: Slept well; pulse 85, full; skin soft but
                                        rather warm; tongue moist, slightly coated in centre with
                                        yellowish patches; some appetite; three stools; but little
                                        expectoration; respiration 26. Milk-punch and Dover's powder
                                        were given. 6th: Slept well; head-pain; pulse 90, full; skin
                                        of natural temperature, covered slightly with perspiration;
                                        tongue moist, coated white in centre; appetite good; some
                                        tympanites; right iliac tenderness; two stools; slight cough
                                        and expectoration; respiration 25. 7th: Slept well; looking
                                        better; pulse 80, natural; skin and tongue natural; two
                                        stools; slight cough; respiration 25; respiratory murmur
                                        absent on left side below third rib. 8th: Not so well;
                                        countenance and skin natural; pulse 85, quick; tongue moist
                                        and clean; appetite good; three stools; some cough; slight
                                        expectoration of mucus slightly tinged with blood;
                                        respiration 35; some crepitation and absence of respiratory
                                        murmur on left side, lower portion; mucous r&#226;les in middle
                                        lobe of right lung, vesicular murmur in upper portion. 9th:
                                        Slept well; pulse 80, weak; skin natural; appetite
                                        improving; two stools; respiration 26. 10th: Restless; eyes
                                        more natural, cheeks less congested; pulse 80, quick; skin
                                        natural; tongue moist, clean; appetite moderate; cough
                                        slight; two stools. Tincture of iron ordered three times
                                        daily. 11th: Stronger; slept some; eyes bright; face
                                        slightly flushed; pulse 85, quick; skin natural; tongue
                                        moist, clean; appetite good; three stools; cough slight.
                                        12th: Slept well; looking better; cheeks congested; pulse
                                        90, strong, wiry; skin of natural temperature, an occasional
                                        rose-spot appearing; tongue moist, clean; slight tenderness
                                        in right iliac region; two stools; no cough. 13th: Slept
                                        well; looking bright; pulse 90, quick; skin a little above
                                        the natural temperature; slight pain in right lung; tongue
                                        moist and clean; appetite good; six stools; no cough. 14th:
                                        Slept well; looking bright; pulse 110, quick, corded; skin
                                        of natural temperature, an occasional rose-spot appearing;
                                        tongue slightly coated yellowish in centre; appetite
                                        moderate; three stools; moderate tenderness in right
                                        umbilical and left iliac regions. 15th: Slept some; pulse
                                        80, regular, corded; skin of natural temperature, showing a
                                        few rose-spots, disappearing on pressure; tongue moist,
                                        coated yellowish-white in centre; appetite good; three
                                        stools; some umbilical tenderness; some pain in middle of
                                        right side on deep inspiration. 16th: Out on pass. 17th:
                                        Slept well; pulse 85, quick; skin of natural temperature;
                                        tongue moist, coated slightly white in centre; appetite
                                        moderate; two stools. 18th: Wakeful; pulse 86, somewhat
                                        irregular; skin covered with perspiration; slight headache;
                                        tongue moist, clean; appetite poor; two stools; some
                                        epigastric pain and tenderness. 19th: Slept well; pulse 62,
                                        regular; skin natural; tongue moist, clean; appetite
                                        moderate; three stools; pain on deep inspiration. 20th:
                                        Slept well; pulse 86, regular; skin and tongue natural;
                                        appetite good; two stools. 21st: Slept well; pulse 90,
                                        quick; skin and tongue natural; buzzing in ears; appetite
                                        good; two stools. 22d: Slept well; bright; pulse 90,
                                        somewhat quick; tongue clean; appetite good; two stools;
                                        some abdominal tenderness. 23d: Slept well; pulse 90,
                                        natural; still some pain in right side of chest. 24th:
                                        Wakeful; pulse 90, quick; skin moist; tongue white; appetite
                                        moderate; two stools; less tenderness. 25th: Slept well;
                                        pulse 90, quick; skin natural; tongue clean; appetite good;
                                        two stools; some general tenderness. <date type="duty"
                                                when="1861-10-26">26th</date>: Returned to duty.
                                </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
