<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e4042">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Vanderbeck, James</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e4042</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">72</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot wounds at the hip with fracture of the articular surfaces</term>
     <term>treated on expectant plan</term> 
     <term>incisions and removals of fragments or foreign bodies consistent with true conservative treatment</term> 
     <term>anchylosis of knee joint supervened years after injury</term>
     <term>ball entered thigh above and behind the trochanter major, passed forward and inward</term> 
     <term>fractured neck of femur</term>
     <term>leg useless for purposes of labor</term>
     <term>disability total</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-13">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
   <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 142.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private James Vanderbeck</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 145th New York</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="257">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3d, 1863</date>, by a conoidal musket ball, which entered the left thigh above and behind the trochanter major, passed forward
    and inward, fractured the neck of the femur, and made its exit at the groin. He was made a prisoner and remained in the hands
    of the enemy eleven days. He was then exchanged and conveyed to the Twelfth Corps Hospital, at <name type="place">Aquia Creek</name>. The injured
    limb was simply placed in a comfortable position without any attempt at extension. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-14">June 14th</date> the patient was removed on
    a hospital transport to <name type="place">Alexandria</name> and placed in the <name type="hospital" key="186">First Division Hospital</name>. He was in good condition. The suppuration was
    comparatively slight, and no bone splinters were found loose and none had come away. <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-17">Three days subsequently</date> he was transferred to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, and thence, on <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-12">October 12th</date>, to <name type="place">New York</name>, where he was admitted to the Ladies Home Hospital. The
    wounds were closed at this date. The patient was discharged from the hospital and from the service of the United States on
    <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-11-19">November 19, 1863</date>. On that date he walked with crutches. His limb was shortened two inches, with eversion. He was allowed
    a pension. On <date type="pension" when="1866-08-02">August 2, 1866</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. E. Bradley</name>, Examining Surgeon of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Pension Bureau</name>, reported that Vanderbeck's general
    health was good, but that there was much lameness. The fracture was firmly consolidated. <name type="person" key="xxx">Commissioner C. C. Cox</name> reports
    that Vanderbeck received his pension at the agency in <name type="place">New York City</name> on <date type="pension" when="1868-03-04">March 4, 1868</date>, and that his disability was then rated
    by the examining surgeon as total. On <date type="pension" when="1873-09-09">September 9, 1873</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Examining Surgeon T. F. Smith</name>, of <name type="place">New York City</name>, states: "Ball
    entered left nates and emerged beneath left popliteal ligament, fracturing the femur; there is union with deformity and three inches
    shortening." On <date type="pension" when="1875-09-07">September 7, 1875</date>, the <name type="organization" key="xxx">New York Examining Board</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeons T. F. Smith</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">J. F. Ferguson</name>, and <name type="person" key="xxx">M. K. Hogan</name>, report "that the knee is anchylosed and the patient is obliged to wear a sole on his shoe three inches thick, and to walk with a
    cane; the leg is useless for purposes of labor." </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
