<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e13851">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Green, E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e13851</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">310</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>cases of recovery after secondary amputation in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>ball entered above and to side of patella, fractured femur in lower third, lodged on
      inner posterior side opposite point of entrance</term>
     <term>dry gangrene of toes and dorsum of foot</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage from femoral artery</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>femoral artery destroyed popliteal space, evidently by missile</term>
     <term>lower fragment of femur at angle of thirty degrees with leg, pressed firmly against
      wounded femoral artery, preventing fatal hæmorrhage</term>
     <term>furnished with artificial leg</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 485.—<name type="person" key="1102">Private E.
     Green</name>, <name type="organization" key="449">Co. K, 119th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 35
    years, was wounded in the right thigh, at <name type="BATTLE" key="15">Rappahannock
     Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7, 1863</date>, and was admitted
    to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-11-09">two days afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W.
     Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, furnished the following
    description of the injury, and of the operation which he performed: "The missile, a conical
    ball, entered one and a half inches above and to the right of the patella, passing across the
    limb, fracturing the femur in the lower third, and lodging on the inner and posterior side,
    nearly opposite the point of entrance. The limb was treated in a skeleton fracture-box, and
    water dressings were used. On <date type="operation" when="1863-11-18">November 18th</date>, the
    ball was extracted. Hæmorrhage occurred on the following day, and again three days
    afterwards. The discharge of pus became copious about <date type="injury" when="1863-12-01">December 1st</date>, and dry gangrene of the toes and dorsum of foot appeared. The upper
    fragment of the femur protruded one and a half inches, and at every effort to extend the limb so
    as to retract the protruding bone violent hæmorrhage ensued. The patient's system was
    greatly reduced, and careful attention was paid to retain his digestive powers by a rotation of
    stimulants and nourishing diet. A slight change in the position of the limb, on December 28th,
    brought on a hæmorrhage to the amount of twenty ounces in three minutes time evidently from
    the femoral artery, which was then controlled by pressure. By January 20, 1864, sloughing of the
    heel and dorsum of foot had commenced, and the patient's system was still so much debilitated
    that a decision to operate, which had been retarded as calculated to prove fatal, was now
    arrived at as a last chance to preserve life. On <date type="operation" when="1864-01-21">the
     following day</date> the thigh was amputated at the middle third by antero-posterior flaps,
    four arteries being tied and but little blood lost. Ether was used as the anæsthetic. At
    the operation an abscess was discovered in the anterior flap extending upward for three inches,
    and the femoral artery was found to be destroyed in the upper part of the popliteal space,
    evidently by the missile. Above the point of the amputation the vessel was healthy; but no clot
    was found. The vessels of the leg were much constricted. The lower fragment of the femur was
    flexed at an angle of thirty degrees with the leg, and, by contraction of the muscles of the
    thigh, was pressed firmly against the wounded extremity of the femoral artery, thereby
    preventing fatal hæmorrhage. The flaps of the stump presented an unhealthy appearance,
    being much indurated and infiltrated with serum. Tincture of chloride of iron was applied to the
    entire surface with a view of stimulating the parts and of obtaining its hæmostatic effect
    upon the capillary vessels which failed to contract from cold and exposure to the air. A large
    tent was placed through the fourchette of the stump so as to prevent the accumulation of pus,
    the flaps being gently brought together and tepid water dressing applied. The patient improved
    daily, and was in a fair way of recovery one week after the operation." The amputated portion of
    the femur was contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="123">the operator</name>, and is shown in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 202). The specimen shows the parts about the fracture to be dead
    and stripped, and its upper half to be covered with an involucrum of foliaceous callus tolerably
    dense posteriorly, also some periosteal deposit above the condyles. The patient subsequently
    entered <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square Hospital</name>, and was discharged
     <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-07-07">July 7, 1864</date>. He was furnished with an
    artificial leg by <name type="person" key="xx">B. F. Palmer</name>, <date type="pension" when="1865-08-26">August 26, 1865</date>, and was paid as a pensioner until <date type="pension" when="1867-09-04">September 4, 1867</date>, since when he has not been heard
    from.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001600.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 202.—Shot comminution of the lower third of right
     femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 2033.</head>
   </figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
