<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5364">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Phillips, Henry</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5364</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">106-107</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>ball entered thigh, lodged against anterior surface of neck of femur</term>
     <term>ball impacted near anatomical neck of femur</term>
     <term>head, neck, and trochanter major excised</term>
     <term>pleurisy</term>
     <term>retention of urine, catheter necessary</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>sub-peritoneal abscess</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 249.&#8212;<name type="person" key="951">Private Henry
     Phillips</name>, <name type="organization" key="392">Co. I, 146th New York</name>, a robust
    man, aged 34 years, was wounded at the <name type="place">South Side Railroad</name>, near <name
     type="place">Petersburg</name>, on <date type="injury" when="1865-04-01">April 1, 1865</date>,
    by a conoidal musket ball, which entered the left thigh and lodged against the anterior surface
    of the neck of the femur. The patient was conveyed to the field hospital of the 2d division of
    the Fifth Corps, and thence by ambulance and rail to <name type="place">City Point</name>, where
    he arrived on <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-04">April 4th</date>, and was transferred by
    steamer to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and, on <date type="transfer"
     when="1865-04-06">April 6th</date>, was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas
     Hospital</name>. He was much exhausted and had considerable fever, though in frequency the
    pulse and respiration were nearly normal. The wound was painful, and the beginning of its grave
    constitutional aspect was becoming manifest. There was no shortening or deformity of the limb.
    At a preliminary exploration the ball was found impacted near the anatomical neck, and was
    extracted. The limited nature of the fracture was also ascertained, and excision was decided on.
    On <date type="operation" when="1864-04-08">April 8th</date> the patient was placed under the
    influence of ether, and <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon William F.
    Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, excised the head, neck, and
    trochanter major through a curved incision six or seven inches in length with its convexity
    forward. About twelve or sixteen ounces of blood were lost during the operation. One small
    artery required a ligature. The ball had crushed in the laminated structure of the anterior face
    of the neck, and from this cup-shaped cavity a small fissure ran up the articular surface and a
    deep fissure nearly around the neck; but the separation between the head and neck was
    incomplete. During the operation this fracture was converted into a complete one in rotating the
    bone to facilitate the exarticulation. The operation concluded, the limb was supported by
    pillows, and the patient was ordered beef tea and milk punch every three hours, and a full dose
    of opium at midnight. He had another dose of laudanum at four o'clock the next morning. On the
    9th, 10th, and 11th, there was little pain, and anodynes were not required, but concentrated
    nourishment and stimulants were assiduously administered. It was thought the nurse exceeded his
    instructions in the amount of whiskey given, for on April 12th, the patient had hiccough and
    nausea, and his breath was redolent of alcoholic fumes. He was now transferred to the immediate
    charge of <name type="person" key="208">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. Carvallo</name>. A laxative
    enema was administered, and, when the bowels were unloaded, a sinapism at the epigastrium, and
    small doses of creasote allayed the irritability of stomach. On April 13th the stomach was
    quiet, pulse 120, rather weak, and there was profuse perspiration. The patient was ordered a
    cupful of beef tea every two hours, one of milk punch every four hours, milk toast and soft
    boiled eggs at breakfast and dinner. No change the next day. On <date type="operation"
     when="1864-04-14">the 14th</date> the wound looked well. Some shreds of disorganized connective
    tissue were removed by the dressing forceps. There was some pain and difficulty in micturition.
    Small doses of tincture of the sesquichloride of iron were directed thrice daily, and chicken
    broth was added to his dietary. No entry of importance appears on the 16th. On the 17th the
    pulse was 120, respiration 32. Slight pain on right side, and signs of pleurisy on auscultation.
    There was an erythematous blush about the wound, and, in the evening, there was diarrh&#339;a,
    which was cheated by pills of opium and nitrate of silver. On the 18th the pleurisy was worse,
    the breathing more rapid, and there was retention of urine, so that it was necessary after this
    to use a catheter. April 19th the countenance was sunken, and the wound was flabby. There was a
    sore on the sacrum. The patient was moved to a Crosby Invalid Bed. He had a draught containing
    ammonia and sugar, and a blister on his side. April 20th the nurse reported a chill during the
    night. The breathing was labored. There were sordes on the teeth. At the next morning visit the
    patient was very low. He died before noon, <date type="death" when="1865-04-21">April 21,
     1865</date>, eleven days after the operation. The autopsy revealed dry pleurisy on either side;
    lungs healthy, somewhat congested posteriorly; heart and liver not abnormal. A large
    sub-peritoneal abscess in the course of psoas and internal iliac muscles, which appeared to
    originate in the obturator <choice>
     <orig>foreamen</orig>
     <reg>foramen</reg>
    </choice> and ascend along the left iliac fossa, denuding the bone of its periosteum. No
    evidences of py&#230;mia were found, though it was strongly suspected after the occurrence of
    the chill on April 20th. The pathological specimen, contributed by the operator to the <name
     type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, is represented at page 246 of the
    Catalogue of the Surgical Section of 1866, and by the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
    59). </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001534.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 59.&#8212;Fracture of head and neck of left femur by a conoidal
     musket ball. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3235, Sect. I, A. M. M. &#189;</head>
   </figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
