<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41419">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Fox, Emmanuel</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41419</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">192</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>appetite good, but craving for improper food</term>
       <term>glands of neck swollen, thin discharge from ears</term>
       <term>cranial sinuses filled with blood, subarachnoid space contained serum, vessels of pia mater injected</term>
       <term>calcareous deposits in bronchial glands</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of ileum presented patches of dirty-red color, no ulcers detected</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon and c&#230;cum thickened and inflamed, peeled off easily, in spots abraded</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of rectum much inflamed, thickened, peeled off easily, not ulcerated</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-17">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 460.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Emmanuel Fox</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company H, 48th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; age 20; admitted from <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-11-02">November 2, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears on the register of the depot hospital of the 9th Corps, admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-10-26">October 26th</date>&#8212;acute rheumatism; and on that of the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">hospital steamer Ben Deford</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-11-01">November 1st</date>; sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1864-11-02">November 2d</date>.]  He was very weak, and had frequent copious liquid evacuations, which were generally preceded by pain and followed by exhaustion; the skin was unusually cool, the pulse irregular.  Treatment: Tonics, stimulants, and warm applications to the abdomen; milk and extra diet. The patient's appetite was generally pretty good, but there was a craving for improper food. For some time the glands of the neck were swollen, and there was a thin discharge from the ears. The eyes also seemed to be affected, and for several days before death he complained of pains in the arms. For the last week he could be induced to take but little food.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-12-05">December 5th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-12-06">twenty-seven hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis disappearing; body extremely emaciated; very slight suggillation posteriorly. The cranial sinuses were filled with blood; the subarachnoid space contained an ounce of serum; the vessels of the pia mater were injected; the substance of the brain was normal. Neck and spinal column not examined. There were no pleuritic adhesions. The left lung was normal; the right lung was normal anteriorly, posteriorly several of the lobules in all the lobes were hepatized, some of them having advanced to the stage of gray hepatization. There were small calcareous deposits in several of the bronchial glands. The heart was very small, but otherwise normal. The liver was normal; the gall-bladder contained about an ounce and a half of bile. The spleen and pancreas were normal, as was also the mucous membrane of the stomach, duodenum, and jejunum. The mucous membrane of the ileum presented several patches of dark dirty-red color, but no ulcers could be detected. The mucous membrane of the colon and c&#230;cum was thickened and inflamed in patches; it peeled off easily, and there were one or two spots in which it was abraded. The mucous membrane of the rectum also was very much inflamed, softened, and thickened, peeling off easily, but not ulcerated. The kidneys were pale, but otherwise normal.&#8212;<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
