<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16647">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">C&#8212;&#8212;, L&#8212;&#8212;</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16647</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">262</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>trephining practiced, fatal termination</term>
          <term>round ball comminuted and depressed right parietal bone below sagittal suture</term>
          <term>paraplegia</term>
          <term>left side nearly insensible, tongue could protrude only partially</term>
          <term>dura mater and surface of brain torn, bleeding from branch of temporal artery</term>
          <term>pus and blood continually discharged from wound</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private L&#8212;&#8212;
          C&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. B, 2d Pennsylvania
          Reserves</name>, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="48">Chantilly, Virginia</name>,
          <date type="injury" when="1862-09-01">September 1st, 1862</date>, by a round ball, which
        comminuted and depressed the right parietal bone, two inches below the sagittal suture. He
        became insensible and remained so for about fifteen minutes, when he recovered and walked
        about. He was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>,
        Washington, D. C., on <date type="admit" when="1862-09-04">the 4th</date>, having full power
        over his limbs and a good appetite. Gradually he began to feel depressed, then confined
        himself to his bed, and finally, on <date type="injury" when="1862-09-07">the 7th</date>,
        was seized with paraplegia. On the evening of the 9th, he had become unconscious. A
        cathartic was administered, which operated freely, and the next morning the patient was
        fully conscious again and complained of pain in the head. At five o clock P. M., of <date
          type="operation" when="1862-09-11">the following day</date> he was unable to move, and his
        voice thick and inarticulate. His left side was nearly insensible, but warm, and he could
        protrude his tongue only partially. On examining the wound, a depression of the size of a
        twenty-five cent piece was found, but evidently no ball lodged in the brain. Chloroform was
        administered, and the fragments being so pressed into each other, that neither elevator nor
        forceps could remove them, the trephine was applied by <name type="person" key="1101"
          >Surgeon I. Moses</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, and the
        bone sawed nearly through, which loosened the pieces so that they were readily removed. The
        dura mater and surface of the brain were torn. Bleeding from a small branch of the temporal
        artery was easily checked, and the parts were covered with ice-cold water. Three and a half
        hours after the operation he had considerably improved; the severe pain which he had
        complained of for days previous to operation and the paraplegia were relieved. He slept
        soundly on the night of the 11th, but on the following morning a constant gurgling in his
        throat could be heard. Pus and blood were continually discharged from the wound, which
        looked well. He sank rapidly, became comatose on the morning of <date type="death"
          when="1862-09-13">the 13th</date>, and died in the afternoon of that day. The pathological
        specimen, No. 131, Sect. I, A. M. M., shows a partially trephined segment of the right
        parietal bone, with five fragments, embracing one square inch. The outer table and
        diplo&#235; were cut through, but not removed, by the trephine applied on the sound bone at
        the edge of the fracture. The specimen and history were contributed by <name type="person"
          key="1101">Surgeon I. Moses</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
      </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001412.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 126.&#8212;Segment of parietal bone with fragments,
          from a case of trephining after gunshot fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 131, Sect.
          I, A.M.M.</head>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
