<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e20941">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Holmes, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e20941</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">545</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>recoveries after secondary amputations in the middle third of the leg for shot
      injury</term>
     <term>compound comminuted fractures of tibia and fibula at lower third</term>
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>leg removed half way between ankle and knee</term>
     <term>supplied with artificial leg</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 793.—<name type="person" key="1316">Private W.
     Holmes</name>, <name type="organization" key="506">Co. D, 18th Massachusetts</name>, aged 20
    years, was wounded in the right leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. He passed from a field hospital to
     <name type="hospital" key="174">Campbell Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-27">two weeks after receiving the injury</date>, and <date type="transfer" when="1863-06">six months afterwards</date> he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Mower Hospital, Philadelphia</name>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon J.
     Hopkinson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter,
    recorded the following history: "The patient was suffering from a compound comminuted fracture
    of the tibia and fibula at the lower third. He also complained of diarrhœa, for which chalk
    mixture and laudanum were administered. Dead bone was discovered by the probe. The leg had been
    operated on and several pieces of bone removed. At the time of admission, <date type="admit" when="1863-06-20">June 20th</date>, it was very much enlarged and disfigured by cicatrices. The
    wound was dressed with warm-water poultices every hour. On <date type="operation" when="1863-07-15">July 15th</date> a large ulcer had broken out on the limb and a large piece
    of bone was taken away. Warm-water dressings were still continued, and the foot was kept
    elevated. On the following day the ulcer was found to be extending, and bread and milk poultices
    were ordered to be applied. Subsequently chlorate of potassa and muriatic disinfecting lotion
    were used. On July 19th, creasote was applied to the ulcer; warm-water dressings continued; bone
    now in a sad state. On <date type="operation" when="1863-07-22">July 22d</date> the leg was
    removed by flap operation by <name type="person" key="1315">Assistant Surgeon C. R.
     Greenleaf</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, half way between the
    ankle and the knee. The flaps were brought accurately together and dressed with water dressing.
    On the following day the patient felt easy, having slept well during the night after taking a
    half grain of morphia; pulse 100, full and soft. On July 26th the dressing was removed; stump
    looking well and patient doing well. Extra diet was given, and porter daily. The stump healed
    rapidly and the patient's general health was excellent. On <date type="furlough" when="1863-09-30">September 30th</date> the stump had entirely healed and the patient went home
    on furlough." He was subsequently transferred to Haddington Hospital, and later to Ladies Home,
     <name type="place">New York City</name>, where he was supplied with an artificial leg of the
    "Ely" pattern, and whence he was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-04-12">April 12, 1864</date>, and pensioned. In his subsequent applications for commutation he
    described the condition of the stump as continuing in a "healthy state." The amputated bones of
    the leg (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2594), contributed by <name type="person" key="1315">the
     operator</name>, are represented in the annexed wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 320)
    and exhibit the seat of the fracture, the fibula being firmly consolidated, and much callus
    being effused about the tibia, but caries having prevented firm union. The pensioner was paid
     <date type="pension" when="1881-03-04">March 4, 1881</date>. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001645.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 320.—Bones of the right leg seven months after
     fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2594.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
