<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40751">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Litzenberg, James</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e40751</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">119</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
     <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances
      observed</term>
     <term>from Satterlee Hospital, West Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</term>
     <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
     <term>rheumatism</term>
     <term>German</term>
     <term>apex of lung with tubercle the size of marrow-fat pea and several small ulcerated
      cavities</term>
     <term>tubercles about size of pepper grains in lung apex and upper lobe</term>
     <term>spleen had evidences of old inflammation</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ATTERLEE <hi rend="initialcap"
     >H</hi>OSPITAL, <name type="place">West Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</name>, <name type="person"
     key="137">Surgeon Isaac I. Hayes</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
    in charge. Autopsy made by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Joseph Leidy</name>, Professor of
    Anatomy in the <name type="organization" key="xxx">University of Pennsylvania</name>. At the
    time of the organization of this hospital a number of the leading teachers and medical
    practitioners of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> volunteered their services as ward
    physicians, and accordingly received contracts as acting assistant surgeons. To <name
     type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Leidy</name> was assigned the task of conducting the autopsies, and
    a report of the results was forwarded by him, at the time, to <name type="organization"
     key="xxx">the Surgeon General</name>. This report was accompanied y a number of valuable
    pathological specimens, which have been preserved in the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army
     Medical Museum</name>. . . . [Many] patients were sent to Satterlee hospital from the <name
     type="organization" key="xxx">Army of the Potomac</name> . . . and had contracted their disease
    . . . during the ill-fated Peninsular campaign.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 172.&#8212;<name type="person" key="87">Private James
     Litzenberg</name>, <name type="organization" key="97">company A, 26th Pennsylvania
     volunteers</name>; age 40; German; admitted from <name type="place" key="#Washington"
     >Washington, D. C.</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-12">December 12, 1862</date>.
    Diarrh&#339;a. [The register of <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver hospital</name>,
    Washington, shows that this man was admitted to that hospital <date type="admit"
     when="1862-11-20">November 20, 1862</date>&#8212;diagnosis rheumatism&#8212;and transferred to
    another hospital <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-11">December 11th</date>.] Died, <date
     type="death" when="1863-01-22">January 22, 1863</date>. <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi>
    <date type="autopsy" when="1863-01-22">the same day</date>: The body looked as if the patient
    had been, before his illness, of great vigor and muscular strength, but was now emaciated. Brain
    healthy. Right lung with old adhesions to the costal pleura; the apex with a tubercle the size
    of a marrow-fat pea and several small ulcerated cavities; left lung with a few tubercles about
    the size of pepper grains in its apex and scattered at the back part of the upper lobe.
    Pericardium with about a teacupful of liquor. Heart flabby, with a large white clot in the right
    ventricle. Spleen flabby, reddened, and roughened on the surface, (apparently the evidences of
    an old inflammation;) structure very soft purplish red. Solitary and agminated glands of the
    ileum slightly enlarged, and opaque white. Colon with the mucous membrane soft, grayish, with a
    few red streaks of inflammation and a few ecchymosed spots. Remaining organs apparently
    healthy.&#8212;Acting Assistant Surgeon Joseph Leidy. [Nos. 84 and 85, Medical Section, <name
     type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case. The specimens are
    successive portions of the ileum, showing pin-head enlargement of the solitary follicles and
    slight thickening of Peyer's patches.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
