<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31676">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Stanley, Cyrus</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31676</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ab">Andy Barner</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">100</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>ball voided at stool</term>
       <term>wounded and made a prisoner</term>
       <term>ball entered below last rib and to right of vertebra, penetrated abdominal cavity and lodged</term>
       <term>voided ball at stool after ten days</term>
       <term>partial paralysis of right side, loss of motion in right foot</term>
       <term>missile entered right loin, passed through upper part of right kidney, lodged in bowels and remained for ten days, then discharged</term>
       <term>incomplete paralysis of right side</term>
       <term>affected by incomplete control over leg and arm, no power of endurance</term>
       <term>muscles wasting away, shrunken, and flabby</term>
       <term>severe pain in back of neck and spinal column</term>       
       <term>disability total and permanent</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-30">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#ab" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 298.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Cyrus Stanley</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 39th Indiana</name>, is alleged to have been wounded at <choice><sic>Stone River</sic><corr>Stone's River</corr></choice>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-31">December 31, 1862</date>. His name does not appear upon the list of casualties, and he is supposed to have been made a prisoner.  At all events, he was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-03-20">March 20, 1863</date>; on <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-05">May 5th</date>, was transferred to Convalescent Hospital at <name type="place">Fort Wood, New York Harbor</name>, and, on <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-12">May 12th</date>, to DeCamp Hospital. Here <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon James W. Dickie</name> has noted upon the descriptive list that &#34;the ball entered half an inch below the last rib and four inches to the right of the vertebra, penetrated the abdominal cavity, and lodged. The patient voided the ball at stool ten days after the reception of the injury. When admitted, the wound had healed and the general health of the patient was good. He suffered, however, from partial paralysis of the right side, and &#339;dema, and loss of motion in the right foot. Bandages were applied over the wound and counter-irritation made to the abdomen; full diet ordered.&#34;  <name type="person" key="xxx">Stanley</name> was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-06-03">June 3, 1863</date>, and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner Manuel Reed</name>, of <name type="place">Portland, Indiana</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1869-03-28">March 28, 1869</date>: &#34;The missile entered the right loin, passed through the upper part of the right kidney, and lodged in the bowels, where it remained for ten days, at the end of which time it (an ounce musket ball) was discharged. From the effects of the said wound he is permanently disabled. There is incomplete paralysis of the right side. He is affected, in laboring, by not having complete control over the leg and arm, and not having power of endurance. The muscles are wasting away, shrunken, and flabby. He also has constant pain in the back of the neck and in the spinal column, often so severely that he is confined to his bed for days. His entire system is very much debilitated. Disability total, of the second grade, and permanent.&#34;  This pensioner was last paid <date type="pension" when="1872-09-04">September 4, 1872</date>.</p>       
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
