<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e28923">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Leigh, George</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e28923</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted:
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">860-861</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>py&#230;mia</term> 
     <term>shell fragment carried away portion of foot</term> 
     <term>amputation at ankle joint on field</term>     
     <term>leg reamputated at junction of middle and inferior thirds</term>     
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-06-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1224.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1517">Private George
      Leigh</name>, <name type="organization" key="566">Co. C, 3d Artillery</name>, aged 19 years,
     was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="5">Robinson's Ford</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1863-09-23">September 23, 1863</date>, by a shell fragment which carried away a portion
     of the right foot. Amputation at the ankle joint was performed on the field by a modification
     of Syme's method. The heel being injured, the flap was taken from the dorsum of the foot. On
      <date type="admit" when="1863-09-25">September 25th</date> he was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton
      Hospital</name>, Washington. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>, <name
      type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported: "His general condition was then far from satisfactory, as he was pale and very feeble. He was put upon the
     use of stimulants, tonics, and a good diet. Simple dressings were applied to the stump and he
     was directed to take an anodyne at night.  September 29th: Half of the flap sloughed off; granulations pale; discharge thin and serous;
     Labarraque's solution, diluted, was applied to the stump.  October 11th: had a severe chill this
     morning, and complains of a good deal of pain in the right knee; twenty grains of sulphate of
     quinine and an ounce of whiskey were given every six hours.  12th: had another severe chill;
     knee red, hot, and very much swollen, pulse frequent and weak, tongue dry and coated,
     complexion assuming a bronzed hue; quinine repeated, and five grains of citrate of iron and
     quinine, in pill, ordered to be given night and morning. A lotion of acetate of lead and opium
     was applied to the knee and lime water to the stump.  13th: had another chill today, but it was not so severe as the others; temperature of inflamed knee lessened; had
     slept well during the night; no change in the treatment.  14th: swelling of the knee much less;
     treatment unchanged.  15th: had a slight chill about noon, but his general appearance is much
     better; same treatment continued.  18th: had vomiting, produced apparently by the large doses of
     sulphate of quinine, which were discontinued; but the other treatment was continued.  20th:
     bowels constipated; five grains aloes and fifteen of rhubarb were ordered.  25th: swelling disappearing from knee rapidly; stump looks much better; granulations more fluid and healthy;
     discharge more laudable.  October 30th: decided daily improvement; continued the stimulants,
     together with the citrate of iron and quinine, and the lead and opium lotion to the knee and
     lime water to the stump. The knee joint remained slightly swollen, hot, and tender for a long
     time; indeed, the symptoms of inflammatory action in it did not entirely disappear till about
     the first of February, 1864.  February 20th: the amount of mobility at the knee is small (false
     anchylosis); patella now adherent; knee natural in size and shape. Stump sore on account of
     having bruised it recently; general condition excellent.  March 29th: the stump has refused to
     heal; there is an indolent excavated ulcer about the size of a franc piece situated at the
     posterior part of the face of the stump. The stump is otherwise unserviceable on account of the
     delicate character of its covering, which had been taken from the dorsum of the foot. There
     being now no prospect that it would ever become useful, the leg was reamputated about the
     junction of the middle with the inferior third by the double-flap method, the anterior flap
     being considerably shorter than the posterior one. The tibia was sawn off obliquely, as
     directed by Sanson; an&#230;sthetic sulphuric ether.  April 18th: patient's general condition
     excellent." This soldier was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-09-17">September 17,
      1864</date>, and pensioned; he died <date type="death" when="1871-09-13">September 13,
      1871</date>. The amputated stump was contributed to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army
      Medical Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="70">Dr. Lidell</name>, and is numbered 2165
     of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>.</p>  
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 354.&#8212;<hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>YMES'S amputation at the ankle.   [After <hi rend="initialcap">E</hi>SMARCH.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
