<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e10170">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Stowell, Marshall</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e10170</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">574</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases allied to or associated with</term>
                                        <term>the paroxysmal and continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>cerebro-spinal fever</term>
                                        <term>clinical and post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>cases at the hospitals of Alexandria, Va.</term>                                           
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>lips covered with sordes</term>
                                        <term>pain in head, abdominal tenderness and vomiting</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
                                        <term>choroid plexus roughened by pseudo-membrane</term>
                                        <term>brain covered with patches of opaque green lymph</term>
                                        <term>ventricles filled with serum and pus</term>
                                        <term>lungs crepitant, dark-red color, smaller tubes contained muco-pus</term>
                                        <term>mesenteric glands enlarged</term>
                                        <term>ileum was congested mesenteric side but not ulcerated</term>
                                        <term>mucous membrane of colon presented bluish oval dark spots from transverse colon to rectum</term>                                        
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2012-03-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                        
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>                        
                        <p> <hi rend="italic">Case at the Hospitals of <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name></hi></p><p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 69.&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="823">Private Marshall Stowell</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="727">Co. E, 189th N. Y.</name>; age 16; was admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1864-11-30">Nov. 30, 1864</date>, with typhoid
                                        fever. He was restless and noisy, his face flushed, eyes
                                        suffused, tongue dry, swollen and with the papill&#230;
                                        much enlarged in the middle and at the base, mouth and
                                        throat dry and sore, teeth and lips covered with sordes,
                                        pulse frequent and irregular, skin hot and dry; but there
                                        was no diarrh&#339;a.  He was treated with cold to the
                                        head, sinapisms to the feet and abdomen, hyosciamus,
                                        brandy-punch, beef-tea and a few doses of turpentine and
                                        chlorate of potash.  On December 10, having been alternately
                                        restless and quiet in the meantime, he was seized with pain
                                        in the head, much abdominal tenderness and vomiting, morning
                                        and evening, of a thick brownish liquid. The tenderness
                                        increased and the patient became very
                                        irritable&#8212;pulse 130&#8212;until the 13th, when
                                        there was less pain, some appetite and a better pulse, 100.  But on the 16th he became somewhat comatose. As there had
                                        been no stool for a week oil of turpentine was given with
                                        the effect of producing a full natural evacuation; but the
                                        coma gradually increased with quickened and labored
                                        breathing, and he died <date type="death" when="1864-12-20">December 20</date>.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: Body emaciated; face
                                        pale; surface showing a little stasis but no
                                        petechi&#230; or spots. The surface of the brain was
                                        congested and covered with patches of opaque green lymph;
                                        the lateral, middle and fourth ventricles were filled with
                                        serum and sticky pus; the substance of the brain was not
                                        softened. The posterior and lower portion of the right lung
                                        was mostly crepitant but of a dark-red color, and its
                                        smaller tubes contained muco-pus; the posterior and upper
                                        part of the left lung was dark-red and softened but
                                        crepitant. The right side of the heart was distended with a
                                        firm white clot and with thick but fluid black blood. The
                                        liver was pale and had yellowish spots extending from its
                                        surface into its substance; the spleen, about the size of
                                        the fist, was firm and of a light red-brown color. The
                                        kidneys were fatty and granular; the bladder distended,
                                        reaching to within three inches of the umbilicus. The
                                        mesenteric glands were enlarged. The ileum was congested on
                                        its mesenteric side but not ulcerated. The colon contained a
                                        moderate quantity of f&#230;ces of normal appearance and
                                        presented oval dark spots of a bluish tinge on the mucous
                                        membrane from the transverse colon to the rectum.  [<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 520, Med. Sect., <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
                                        Museum</name>, shows part of the left lateral ventricle, the
                                        choroid plexus, roughened by pseudo-membrane, with shreds of
                                        lymph hanging from various parts of the ventricular
                                        lining.]</p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
