<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2278">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Thompson, William E.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e2278</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">221-222</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>clinical records</term>          
          <term>continued fevers</term>
          <term>delirium</term> 
          <term>unconsciousness</term>
          <term>floccilatio</term>
          <term> bed-sores</term>
          <term>rose-spots</term>
          <term>vibices</term>
          <term>subsultus</term>
          <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
          <term>iliac tenderness</term>
          <term> meteorism</term>
          <term>gurgling and relaxation of the bowels</term>
          <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
          <term>typhoid cases</term>
          <term>typhoid fever</term>          
          <term>purulent discharge from ears</term>
      </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00024">
      
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 24.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Presenting delirium,
        unconsciousness, <choice><orig>floccitatio</orig><reg>floccilatio</reg></choice>, subsultus, slight diarrh&#339;a, rose-spots, sudamina, bed-sores and vibices. 
            Improvement manifested about 35th day.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person" key="484">Private William E. Thompson</name>, <name type="organization"
              key="619">Co. C, 9th Pa. Vols.</name>; age 19; was taken about <date type="injury" when="1861-08-22">August 22, 1861</date>, with
          pain in the head and back, epistaxis, chill, fever and diarrh&#339;a, and was admitted
            <date type="admit" when="1861-09-12">September 12</date> as a case of typhoid fever;
          pulse 100, quick; skin hot and dry; tongue dry at the tip and coated gray at the base; the
          patient was dull-looking and had subsultus, relaxed bowels, right iliac tenderness and
          intestinal gurgling. Dover's powder was given. On the 13th the skin was hot but moist with
          perspiration; rose-colored spots appeared. Next day the skin was again hot and dry, but
          covered with profuse sudamina; the cheeks were flushed, the tongue dry, smooth, cracked
          and protruded with difficulty, and the patient stupid but restless. Toward evening on the
          15th a few more rose-spots came out; sordes appeared on the teeth; the bowels continued
          slightly relaxed and there was right iliac tenderness; the patient was haggard; he turned
          his head from side to side, muttered, and had subsultus tendinum. No change occurred on
          the 16th, but on the 17th more rose-spots made their appearance and the patient became
          drowsy. On the 19th his pupils were dilated and he was unable to articulate. Next day the
          pulse was 112, irritable and full; the skin dry and husky; the rose-spots and sudamina had
          disappeared; the tongue was rough, dry and brown; the gums and teeth covered with sordes; right iliac tenderness, meteorism, gurgling and relaxation of
          the bowels continued, and the patient muttered and groaned, but had no subsultus. He was
          greatly emaciated and prostrated, and for some days lay on his back with his eyes
          half-closed; sometimes partly delirious, picking at the bed-clothes, and at other times
          unconscious. Meanwhile the pulse became more rapid, rising to 128 on the 23d, and the
          circulation of the skin languid. He vomited on the evening of the 22d, and after this his
          bowels became more quiet. Bed-sores appeared over the sacrum. Turpentine, Dover's powder,
          astringents and stimulants had been used in the treatment. On the 25th the pulse was 114
          and stronger, the tongue cleaning and the mind clearer, but the skin continued hot and
          dry, and vibices appeared profusely on the chest; the bowels remained quiet. The patient
          was sponged with alcohol and turpentine; warm bottles were applied to the feet and soft
          pads to the sacrum over the sores. In the evening the eyes became brighter and the skin
          moist, the pulse having meanwhile fallen to 100. Next day the patient was tranquil, the
          tongue moist and cleaning at the edges; the bowels were moved by an enema. A purulent
          discharge came from the right ear. The left ear became similarly affected on the 28th. The
          appetite returned on the 29th, and after this improvement continued. The patient was
          furloughed <date type="furlough" when="1861-10-31">October 31</date>. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
