<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e6841">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Cotter, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e6841</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">152-153</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the hip joint</term>
     <term>coxo-femoral amputations</term>
     <term>reamputation at the hip joint</term>
     <term>exarticulations at the hip for diseased conditions succeeding previous amputations</term>
     <term>primary amputation of thigh at middle third, at field hospital</term>
     <term>fistulous discharge from stump</term>
     <term>two open sinuses from necrosed fragments of femur, offensive discharge</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 329.—<name type="person" key="975">Private W.
     Cotter</name>, <name type="organization" key="401">Co. E, 9th New Hampshire</name>, aged 27
    years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-07-30">July 30, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon J. Harris</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="345">7th Rhode Island</name>, recorded his admission to the
    field hospital of the 2d division, Ninth Corps, and noted: "Fracture of thigh, lower third;
    amputation of thigh at middle third." From the field hospital the patient was transferred to
     <name type="place">City Point</name>, and thence to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1864-08-03">August 3d</date>. <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon W. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the pathological specimen, shown in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 107), with the following history by <name type="person" key="214">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. Gibbons</name>: "The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name> with primary amputation of right thigh, lower
    part of middle third. The operator had made a long posterior skin flap, which was turned up over
    the muscles and bone, and attached to the integument anteriorly by means of several sutures.
    When first seen the stump was greatly swollen, partly from a retention of pus by the bag-like
    flap. A couple of sutures were removed and the pus evacuated. On August 4th, an incision was
    made in the dependant portion to admit of free drainage, and poultices were ordered. Appetite
    and sleep were not greatly disturbed, and there was not as much irritative fever as in most
    similar cases. Ordered stimulants, tonics, and generous diet. August 13th, swelling much
    reduced; constitutional irritation less. Ligature of femoral artery separated. The poultices
    were alternated with flannel dressings till September 1st, when wet cloths were substituted.
    Flaps mostly united; appetite poor; sleep disturbed; stump painful. Ordered morphia at bed-time.
    September 13th, patient sits up and walks about with some assistance. Stopped the stimulant.
    September 28th, stump doing well; swelling gone; dead bone felt with the probe. Had an attack of
    diarrhœa, which lasted but a few days. The irritability of the stomach was a source of
    continual complaint for two or three months. The various stomachics relieved but temporarily;
    nevertheless there was marked improvement, especially during November, the patient being about
    on his crutches daily. <date type="operation" when="1864-11-29">November 29th</date>, divided
    the cicatrix (but a small fistulous opening was still remaining) and removed a sequestrum nearly
    six inches long. It was attended with some difficulty, yet not as much as was experienced in
    similar cases. The sequestrum consists of the entire bone at the lower extremity, but tapers to
    two or three points at the other; the circumference is complete for three inches. In its centre,
    surrounding the medulla, was found a beautiful transparent flake of new bone. The femur
    contained, as in like cases, a large amount of new bone. July 16, 1865, the cavity left in the
    stump has never entirely closed, but continues to discharge, and refuses to heal, though various
    stimulating injections have been resorted to. It is over three inches deep. The patient is in a
    promising state of health." On <date type="transfer" when="1865-11-02">November 2d</date>,
    the patient was transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>.
     <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported that he was doing well on December 31st, but that there was
    still a "fistulous discharge from the stump." At the closing of the <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, on <date type="transfer" when="1866-05-01">May 1, 1866</date>, the patient was transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="98">Washington Post Hospital</name>, where the specimen represented in the adjacent cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 108) was removed. <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon
     W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who performed the
    operation, reported as follows: "Two sinuses lead to the interior of new bone, which have
    failed to close since the date of the first operation. On <date type="operation" when="1866-06-06">June 6, 1866</date>, resection of four inches of femur from the end of the
    stump, after previously made incisions into the soft parts, was performed. Ether was used, and
    the incisions were united by silver sutures. June 30th, wound has healed kindly, two-thirds by
    first intention, leaving a sinus on the under surface of the stump still discharging. September
    30th, although mostly healed the stump is still indurated. Two sinuses, evidently leading to
    necrosed fragments of femur, are still open and keep up an offensive discharge. Small
    intercellular abscesses form occasionally. Patient in good condition." He was discharged
    from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1866-10-15">October 15, 1866</date>, and
    pensioned. In the following year he was reported as having been treated for a time at the <name type="place" key="xx">Bellevue Hospital, New York City</name>, where Drs. <name type="person" key="xx">H. B. Sands</name> and <name type="person" key="xx">F. H. Hamilton</name> are said to
    have removed several pieces of necrosed bone. On <date type="admit" when="1871-10-05">October 5,
     1871</date>, the pensioner entered the <name type="hospital" key="446">Providence
     Hospital</name> at Washington, with the stump still in a diseased condition; and <date type="operation" when="1871-10-15">ten days afterwards</date>
    <name type="person" key="976">Dr. N. S. Lincoln</name> exarticulated the remaining part of the
    femur, consisting of the head, neck, and trochanteric portions, which was also contributed to
     <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, and is represented in the annexed cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 109). The femoral vessels were respected, go that the
    disarticulation might be said to have resembled an excision or enucleation rather than a
    reamputation. The patient was able to be about in a short time; and on April 22, 1872, he
    visited the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, and a photograph was
    made of the stump, which is copied in the adjoining wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG.
    110). The pensioner subsequently entered the National Military Asylum at <name type="place">Hampton, Elizabeth City County, Va.</name>, where <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner C.
     McDermont</name> certified the following: "The right leg has been amputated at the hip
    joint. This was the third amputation performed on the limb. Since the last operation he has been
    troubled with abscesses in and about the cicatrix, which have not healed, though a year has
    almost elapsed since the disarticulation was made. It is my belief that the tissues of the
    wounded limb have been diseased and never free from ulceration since he was wounded. His general
    health has been considerably impaired by the constant irritation and drain upon his system."
    This pensioner died at <name type="place">Queenstown, Ireland</name>, <date type="death" when="1874-01-21">January 21, 1874</date>, while on furlough from the Asylum. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001551.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 107—Cylindrical sequestrum of right femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 252. ½</head>
   </figure>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001552.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 108—Resected extremity of the right femur from a case of
     osteomyelitis. <hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 4954. ½</head>
   </figure>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001553.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 109—Exarticulated head and trochanters of right femur
     after osteomyelitis. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 5946. ½</head>
   </figure>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001554.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 110—Cicatrix six months after coxo-femoral
     disarticulation and reamputation. [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>



  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
