<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2126">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Husang, Joseph</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e2126</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">220</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>rose-colored spots</term> 
                                        <term>anorexia</term>
                                        <term>night-sweats</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid cases</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-05-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00018">
                        
                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 18.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"
                                                >Cerebral symptoms slight; diarrh&#339;a abated
                                                after occurrence of perspirations; rose-colored
                                                spots on 13th and 15th days and on 17th and 22d,
                                                accompanied by sudamina and followed by
                                                convalescence.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person"
                                                key="477">Private Joseph Husang</name>, <name
                                                type="organization" key="624">Co. E, 19th
                                                Iowa</name>; age 19; had a chill followed by fever
                                        on August 27, 1861, and was admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1861-09-04">Sept. 4</date> as a case of
                                        typhoid fever. On the morning of the 5th he had slight fever
                                        and anorexia; pulse 84, skin dry, tongue coated brown in the
                                        middle and dry; the mind was clear. Quinine was given. In
                                        the evening there was moderate fever, the pulse 84 and
                                        strong, face flushed, skin dry and hot, tongue very red,
                                        flabby and coated white, appetite poor, bowels moved four
                                        times; the patient was weak and dizzy and had headache.
                                        Dover's powder was ordered. No marked change took place on
                                        the two following days; the face became flushed towards
                                        evening. On the 7th the skin was somewhat moist, and next
                                        day an eruption of rose-spots was observed. On this day, the
                                        8th, he had six thin painless stools; he became restless,
                                        talking in his sleep, and in the evening drowsy. Pills of
                                        acetate of lead and opium were administered. On the 9th a
                                        slight cough was developed with mucous and sibilant r&#226;les;
                                        the abdomen became somewhat tender and the rose-spots
                                        disappeared. In the evening the pulse was 68; the tongue
                                        moist and heavily coated brown at the base; the skin warm
                                        and moist; the bowels were moved once during the day without
                                        pain, but some tenderness was present; anorexia continued
                                        and epistaxis was noted. Next day there was one painless
                                        stool; a few rose-spots appeared; and in the evening, while
                                        the skin was perspiring the tongue became dryer and there
                                        was some cough, flushing of the face and headache. Friction
                                        with alcohol was applied to the skin. The perspiration
                                        continued on the 11th, during which there was one stool at
                                        night and one during the day, and the patient became weak
                                        and exhausted. Aromatic sulphuric acid was ordered and the
                                        body sponged with alcohol and nitro-muriatic acid. On the
                                        12th the skin became dry and a profuse characteristic
                                        eruption appeared. The lead and opium was omitted. Next day
                                        night-sweats were reported and some improvement in the
                                        appetite; but the tongue continued dry and brown. Blue-pill
                                        three times daily and oil of turpentine were ordered. On the
                                        14th the tongue was cracked, and although there had been no
                                        night-sweats, the skin was warm and moist; the bowels were
                                        quiet and the appetite improved; in the evening there was a
                                        slight cough with diminution of the appetite. The
                                        night-sweats returned on the 16th, when also the tongue
                                        became moist and less coated, the bowels remaining quiet.
                                        Whiskey-punch was ordered. Next day the skin and tongue
                                        again become dry; rose-spots and sudamina appeared and the
                                        bowels were moved twice; a slight flushing of the face was
                                        noted in the evening, as also on the evening of the
                                        following day. On the 19th the tongue assumed a gray, moist
                                        coating; the skin was warm and sweating; the bowels moved
                                        once; rose-spots were present but no sudamina, no tenderness
                                        nor tympanites. From this time he gradually improved. Thus,
                                        on the 24th, the report is as follows: Rested well; pulse
                                        98; tongue red, moist, slightly coated; bowels regular;
                                        appetite good. He was able to walk about on <date
                                                type="transfer" when="1861-10-01">October 1</date>
                                        and was transferred to <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name> </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
