<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30256">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Woods, E. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e30256</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">580</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
     <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
     <term>excisions at the shoulder</term>
     <term>excisions of the head and portions of the shaft of the humerus</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions of the upper extremity of the humerus for shot injury</term>
     <term>successful operations</term>
     <term>ball entered outer anterior aspect of shoulder, comminuted upper portion of humerus,
      fracture extending into joint</term>
     <term>ball entered shoulder below coracoid process, passed backward, fractured humerus in upper
      portion</term>
     <term>arm shortened three-fourths inch, slight atrophy</term>
     <term>operation of resection of proximal humerus with the head</term>
     <term>arm useless for manual labor</term>
     <term>furnished with artificial limb</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-28">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place
    names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1560.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private E. H.
     Woods</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. G, 6th Maine</name>, was wounded at <name
     type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3,
     1863</date>, and was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="165">Mount Pleasant
    Hospital</name>, Washington. <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon E.
     Coues</name> reported: &#34;The patient, a very robust muscular man, aged 24 years, was
    admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-05-08">May 8th</date>. A mini&#233; ball had entered the
    outer anterior aspect of the shoulder, passed backward and inward, and badly comminuted the
    upper portion of the humerus, the fracture extending up into the joint. Operation of resection
    of five and a half inches of the humerus with the head was performed, <date type="operation"
     when="1863-05-15">May 15th</date>, by <name type="person" key="339">Assistant Surgeon C. A.
     McCall</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>&#34; The specimen (<hi
     rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 454) consists of the head and three and a half inches of the right
    humerus. The anterior face of the shaft and posterior portion of the head are carried away, and
    the articular surface is split in two vertically. It was contributed by <name type="person"
     key="339">the operator</name>. The patient recovered and was discharged the service, and
    pensioned <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-11-13">November 13, 1863</date>. At <date
     type="pension" when="1863-11-13">that date</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner T. B
     Smith</name>, of <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, reported: &#34;Ball
    entered the shoulder an inch below the coracoid process, and passed backward, fracturing the
    humerus in the upper portion. Resection of the head and about three inches of the shaft in
    consequence. Hand motions perfect, but unavailable for labor by reason of uselessness of the
    arm; may improve much in a couple of years.&#34; In <date type="pension" when="1865-11"
     >November, 1865</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. E. D. Hudson</name>, of <name
     type="place">New York</name>, furnished this man with an artificial limb, and reported that
    there had been an excision of five inches of the shaft and head of the humerus through a linear
    incision, posteriorly, of the deltoid, and that the arm was shortened three-fourths of an inch,
    with slight atrophy. The general condition of the arm was excellent, the interspace being mainly
    filled with new growth of the continuity. The usefulness of the apparatus while under
    observation was very satisfactory. <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Hudson</name> contributed a
    photograph, represented in the accompanying cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 453), showing
    the mode of adaptation of the apparatus to the limb, and another giving a view of the patient,
    showing the cicatrix, which will be found on page 2, Vol. IX, <hi rend="italic">Contributed
     Photographs</hi>, A. M. M. In <date type="pension" when="1867-06">June, 1867</date>, <name
     type="person" key="xxx">Examiner A. H. Agard</name>, of <name type="place">Sandusky,
     Ohio</name>, reported: &#34;The excised end or stump has not formed a joint, but plays all
    about, rendering the arm quite useless for purposes of manual labor.&#34; The pensioner was paid
     <date type="pension" when="1874-03-04">March 4, 1874</date>.</p>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001802.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 453.&#8212;Apparatus employed in case of excision at the
    shoulder. [From a photograph.]</head></figure>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001803.001"/><head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 454.&#8212;Upper extremity of right humerus excised for shot
    fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1148.</head></figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
