<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31437">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Law, E. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31437</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="cd-mg">Corey Day and Martine Gouw</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">838</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and injuries of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the elbow joint treated on the expectant plan</term>
       <term>anchylosis of elbow joint, result of shot wound</term>
       <term>immobility of elbow joint, loss of power of supination</term> 
       <term>arm left straight and pronated, usefulness destroyed</term>
       <term>shot wound of elbow joint, disability increased due to neglect in management</term>
       <term>ball entered arm at insertion of biceps, escaped between olecranon and inner condyle</term> 
       <term>joint anchylosed in slightly flexed position</term>
       <term>ulnar nerve divided, hand dependent upon ulnar nerve paralyzed, radial side of hand weak</term>          
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#cd-mg" when="2011-02-20">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1760.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Pt. E. W. Law</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. A, 1st Massachusetts</name>, aged 21 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Oak Grove</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-06-25">June 25, 1862</date>, and sent to <name type="hospital" key="160">St. Elizabeth Hospital</name>, Washington; returned to his regiment at <name type="place">Fort Worth, Virginia</name>, and subsequently discharged and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon F. LeB. Monroe</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">1st Massachusetts</name>, certified on his discharge papers: "Anchylosis of the right elbow joint, the result of shot wound. There is immobility of the joint, probably permanent, with loss of the power of supination."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner G. S. Jones</name>, of <name type="place">Boston</name>, recorded, <date type="pension" when="1862-10-14">October 14, 1862</date>: "Anchylosis of right elbow joint. The arm has been left in a straight and pronated position, and its usefulness destroyed. It is the result of a shot wound of the elbow joint, and his disability is increased in consequence of neglect in its management."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiners Fry</name>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Treadwell</name>, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Chase</name>, of <name type="place">Boston</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1871-08-09">August 9, 1871</date>: "A ball entered the right arm at the insertion of the biceps, and escaped from between the olecranon and the inner condyle, its course being directly through the joint, which latter is anchylosed in a slightly flexed position. The ulnar nerve was divided, and connections have never been re-established. That part of the hand dependent upon the ulna for nervous power is paralyzed, and the flexor power of the radial side of the hand is so much weakened as to destroy the usefulness of the member."  This pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1874-06-04">June 4, 1874</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
