<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e29138">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Tetlow, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e29138</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">716</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and  complications</term>
       <term>shot wounds</term>
       <term>effect of missiles and projectiles on bony structure</term>
       <term>contusions of bone</term> 
       <term>shot wound of leg</term>
       <term>ball entered outer side of popliteal space, did not emerge</term>
       <term>missile impinged upon under side of internal condyle, no further injury to bone, killing periosteum</term>
       <term>constitutional fever and chill</term> 
       <term>periosteum gone on inner side and end of internal condyle, external condyle, and external portion of articular surface of tibia</term>
       <term>joint full of pus, lower third of femur dissected up with pus</term>
       <term>necrosis of bone</term>        
       <term>autopsy performed</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-26">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1054.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. Tetlow</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 23d New Jersey</name>, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon G. Burr</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported his admission to the field hospital of the 1st division, Sixth Corps, with &#34;shot wound of leg.&#34;  <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon G. F. French</name> reported the following result of the injury:  &#34;The patient was admitted to hospital at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-19">December 19th</date>. He had been wounded by a ball entering on the outer side of the right popliteal space and not emerging. He was a strong and healthy man, his pulse being 90 and full; appetite fair; knee tender, very little inflamed, and slightly swollen.  By December 22d the inflammation about the knee was increasing; pulse 98; appetite flagging.  On the next day there was high constitutional fever with great swelling and pain about the knee; patient hectic and had a chill.  On <date type="operation" when="1862-12-24">December 24th</date> a round ball was found lying loose in the wound and was extracted without incision; under portion of internal condyle felt to be bare.  <date type="operation" when="1862-12-29">December 29th</date>, knee more inflamed and swelled; constitutional fever about the same; pulse 100 and weak. Pus was detected and let out by a free incision, giving much relief. Egg-nog ordered for the patient.  On the following day he was more comfortable but seemed exhausted, and was delirious at times; pulse weak.  On December 31st he had a chill with pain in the stomach, and two days afterwards he was delirious; pulse very feeble and slow.  His death occurred at 5 P. M. on <date type="death" when="1863-01-02">January 2, 1863</date>.  Autopsy: External condyle bared of periosteum; joint full of pus; external portion of articular surface of tibia bared also; lower third of femur dissected up with pus; periosteum gone on the inner side and end of internal condyle; bone beginning to necrose. The missile had impinged upon the under side of the internal condyle, doing no further injury to the bone than killing the periosteum over a space the size of a half dime.&#34;&#185;</p>
   <p>&#185; An abstract of this case was published by <hi rend="initialcap">J. B.</hi> <hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>ELLANGER (<hi rend="italic">Report of five cases of Gunshot Injury of the Knee Joint</hi>) in <hi rend="italic">American Journal Medical Sciences</hi>, New Series, 1863, Vol. XLVI, p. 44.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
