<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3620">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Courtwright, Peter</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e3620</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion.</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">235</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records of continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>febrile cases at Seminary Hospital, Georgetown, D. C.</term>
                                        <term>past liver and kidney disease</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00076">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 76.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Record imperfect during first four weeks; delirium;
                                                diarrh&#339;a; rose-spots from 29th to 39th day;
                                                convalescence on 40th day.</hi>&#8212;<name
                                                type="person" key="534">Private Peter
                                                Courtwright</name>, <name type="organization"
                                                key="633">Co. B, 1st Pa. Rifles</name>; age 27. This
                                        man stated that he had suffered from some kidney trouble at
                                        the age of 20, and afterwards from both liver and kidney
                                        disease. About <date type="injury" when="1861-09-12">Sept. 12, 1861</date>, he had chills followed by
                                        fever and sweating, with epistaxis, pain in the back and
                                        limbs and anorexia. He was admitted <date type="admit"
                                                when="1861-10-10">October 10</date>, when he seemed
                                        stupid; his eyes were dull; cheeks flushed; pulse 90 and
                                        quick; skin hot and dry; tongue moist, red at the tip and
                                        edges, coated whitish in centre; appetite poor; the bowels
                                        quiet, but with some gurgling and slight tenderness in the
                                        left iliac and umbilical regions; a few rose-spots were
                                        noted. Dover's powder was given.  On the 11th and 12th the
                                        general condition remained unaltered; the skin lost its heat
                                        but continued dry. Tincture of iron was ordered to be taken
                                        three times a day.  On the l3th the eyes were dull, injected
                                        and suffused and the cheeks slightly flushed; the pulse had
                                        fallen to 60; a few rose-spots appeared on the chest and
                                        abdomen; three stools were passed, and there was pain on
                                        urinating. Profuse perspiration occurred during the night,
                                        and in the morning the patient looked bright but there was
                                        some mental derangement; the pulse was 46, full and firm;
                                        six stools were passed. Astringents were ordered.  The
                                        condition on the 15th is not recorded, but on the following
                                        day there were more rose-spots, delirium, tinnitus aurium,
                                        six stools and umbilical tenderness; pulse 68. Tenderness
                                        and tympanites over the <choice><sic>tranverse</sic><reg>transverse</reg></choice> colon accompanied six
                                        stools recorded on the 17th. There was less delirium on the
                                        18th; the face had become pale and the eyes sunken; one
                                        stool was passed. Three stools were reported on the 19th and
                                        six on the 20th, on which day also some rose-spots appeared.  On the 21st, after sleeping well, the patient's tongue,
                                        which had heretofore been red at the tip and edges and more
                                        or less coated in the centre, was found to be clean and
                                        natural, his skin of normal temperature, pulse 70 and
                                        appetite good; two stools were passed. After this he
                                        improved, but a diarrh&#339;a, causing about three
                                        stools daily, persisted until <date when="1861-11-04">November 4</date>, when the bowels
                                        were reported regular.  He was able to be up and to walk
                                        about October 3Oth, and was returned to duty <date
                                                type="duty" when="1861-11-10">November 10</date>.
                                </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
