<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e4422">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Ellison, James</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e4422</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">244</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>remittent fever</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00106">
                       
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 106.—<hi rend="italic">Remittent fever not amenable to treatment by
                                                quinine; record deficient, but typhoid fever
                                                suggested by diarrhœa, tenderness in the
                                                right iliac region, brown tongue and subsequent
                                                discharge for debility.</hi>—<name type="person" key="564">Private James
                                        Ellison</name>, <name type="organization" key="586">Co. F,
                                                19th Ind.</name>; age 24. This man contracted
                                        tertian ague about <date type="injury" when="1861-08-20">Aug. 20, 1861</date>. The chills were broken up
                                        by quinia. He was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-09-04">September 4</date> as a case of
                                        typhoid fever. On the morning of the 5th the fever was
                                        slight, the pulse 72, skin natural, tongue flabby and coated
                                        yellowish-brown, appetite good, bowels somewhat relaxed and
                                        tender on pressure. Quinia was ordered. In the evening there
                                        was a moderate fever with flushed face, hurried respiration,
                                        hot and dry skin and a burning in the mouth and throat; the
                                        bowels were moved twice during the day. Dover's powder was
                                        given. He rested well during the night, and next morning was
                                        sweating and without fever; but in the evening the skin
                                        became hot and dry, the tongue pale, dry and slightly
                                        coated, and seven loose stools had been passed accompanied
                                        with umbilical pain. A similar remission and exacerbation
                                        occurred on the 7th, the dejections on this day being thin,
                                        small and lumpy. The remission on the morning of the 8th was
                                        not so well marked, although the bowels had not been
                                        disturbed during the night; the mind was clear. On the 9th,
                                        in the morning, the face was flushed, the pulse 68, the
                                        tongue pale, flabby and coated in the centre and at the
                                        back, the skin warm and dry; one thin stool had been passed
                                        without pain but with borborygmi. In the evening the pulse
                                        was 86, the skin warm and dry, the tongue pale and coated
                                        brown in the middle; there were no rose-spots; three thin
                                        small stools had been passed without pain; the appetite was
                                        improving. Dover's powder with small doses of blue-pill and
                                        citrate of iron and quinine were ordered. The 10th gave a
                                        similar record, but in the evening the tongue was dry and
                                        coated brownish, and in connection with four thin small
                                        stools passed during the day, it is stated that there was
                                        some right iliac tenderness. The blue-pill and iron were
                                        omitted and the Dover's powder and quinine continued. On the
                                        11th an acetate of lead and opium pill was given three
                                        times, but the diarrhœa continued with slight fever
                                        in the evening, and a moist tongue, coated brown in the
                                        centre, up to <date type="transfer" when="1861-10-13">the 13th</date>, when he was transferred to hospital at
                                        <name type="place">Baltimore, Md.</name> [He was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1861-10-15">October
                                                15</date> on account of general debility.] </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
