<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e13558">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Pool, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e13558</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">306-307</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>secondary amputations in the upper third of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>fatal cases of secondary amputations in the upper third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>bullet entered lateral and external part of thigh near junction of middle and upper thirds, fractured femur at its middle</term>
     <term>missile split into two pieces by contact with bone, escaped through separate openings in popliteal space</term>
     <term>broken extremities of bone necrosed</term>
     <term>femur sawn off below trochanter minor</term>
     <term>burrowing pus among muscles of thigh</term>     
     <term>discharge of pus from wound of operation in back of thigh</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-21">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-21">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 479.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1099">Private John
      Pool</name>, <name type="organization" key="449">Co. H, 119th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 23
     years, was wounded by a conoidal ball, at <name type="BATTLE" key="262">Rappahannock Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7, 1863</date>. He
     was admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington,
      <date type="admit" when="1863-11-09">November 9th</date>. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon
       John A. Lidell</name>,&#179; <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, furnished the following history, with the
     specimen (No. 2229, Sect I), to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>:
     "The bullet had entered the lateral and external part of the left thigh near the junction of
     the middle and upper thirds, and passing downward, inward, and somewhat forward, had fractured
     the femur at its middle. The missile appears to have been split, by contact with the bone, into
     two pieces, which made their escape through separate openings in the popliteal space. When
     admitted the knee was much swollen and hot; the patella floated some distance above the femoral
     condyles. He did not complain of pain, and his general condition was favorable. The wounded
     limb was propped up with long sand bags placed on either side of it, and moderate extension was
     applied by a weight hanging over the foot of the bed and attached to the foot and leg by strips
     of adhesive plaster. Counter extension was effected by elevating the foot of the bed. He was
     put upon supporting diet, and simple dressings applied. The inflammation and swelling at the
     knee gradually subsided, and, on December 1st, had entirely disappeared, the wounds in the
     popliteal space closed; the wound of entrance, however, was still open and discharging.  On the
     20th, there was a slight h&#230;morrhage of arterial blood from the wound of entrance, which
     was readily checked.  On the 28th, the limb was placed in Hodgen's splint to facilitate the
     outflow of pus.  January 8, 1864, the wound in the popliteal space reopened and the wounds, both
     of entrance and exit, discharged freely.  <date type="operation" when="1864-01-24">24th</date>, pulse 110; he was daily becoming more feeble. On exploring the wound through the orifice of exit with N&#233;laton's probe detached fragments were
     found at the seat of fracture. The patient was etherized, and through an incision about four
     inches long, made in the back part of the thigh, six detached fragments of considerable size,
     the largest about two inches long by three-fourths of an inch wide, were extracted. The superior and inferior part of the fractured femur were found to be held in proper position by
     strong splints of provisional callus, which had been thrown out on the inner and outer sides of
     the bone. The finger could be readily passed between the broken extremities of the bone, both
     ends of which were necrosed but not yet detached.  On the 25th, the thigh had swelled a good
     deal and was emphysematous, but, on the 28th, the emphysema had disappeared and the swelling
     was subsiding; the limb was again placed in Hodgen's splint.  On the 31st, he was improving in
     every respect.  On February 14th, he was doing finely; no night sweats; slept well; appetite
     good; pulse 80; discharge of pus moderate.  <date type="operation" when="1864-02-24">24th</date>, two fragments of bone were extracted. March
     1st, a diffuse inflammation, accompanied with redness and much swelling, attacked the thigh and
     spread rapidly through the limb; there was also great constitutional disturbance. After a time
     this inflammation subsided in a great measure but left him much weakened.  About April 1st,
     another attack of diffuse inflammation brought him still lower.  <date type="operation" when="1864-04-18">18th</date>, the whole limb was
     greatly swollen from the groin to the toes; a small slough on the instep separated; the knee
     joint was extended with effusion, the patella floating some distance above the femoral
     condyles. There was a profuse discharge of thin pus from the wound of operation in the back
     part of the thigh. He was much emaciated, pale, and weak; pulse frequent and feeble; tongue red
     and inclined to be dry; appetite capricious and poor, and he was subject to frequent attacks of
     diarrh&#339;a. He was steadily failing, and, there being no hope of saving his life
     without amputation, he was placed under the influence of sulphuric ether, digital compression
     applied to the femoral artery, and the thigh amputated in the upper third, by the double flap
     method, by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="132">U. S. V.</name>  The femur was sawn off about one and a half inches below the
     trochanter minor. The soft parts of the thigh were so much diseased as not to admit the
     performance of the operation at any point below. But little blood was lost during the
     operation. There was a good deal of shock, but he reacted promptly afterward. In a short time
     the stump became sloughy; he gradually failed, and died of exhaustion <date type="death"
      when="1864-04-26">April 26, 1864</date>. On examining the amputated member, extensive
     burrowing of pus was found among the muscles of the thigh, and numerous small pieces of the
     bullet and fragments of bone sticking into the soft part around the seat of fracture. The ends
     of the broken femur were not in apposition, but separated from each other by the space which
     had formerly been occupied by the fragments of bone extracted by operation. Pretty firm union
     had, however, taken place by means of a bridge of new bone which arched over the chasm in
     front. On splitting the femur open lengthwise with a saw the marrow presented a coppery-red
     color, and there were abundant, deposits of new reddish colored osseous tissue both within the
     medullary canal, endostosis, and, external to the bone, periostosis, for a considerable
     distance above the fracture. In the marrow below the fracture there was a large-sized
     chocolate-colored spot, the result, apparently, of an old extravasation of blood. The substance
     of the marrow was decidedly tougher than normal. There was a considerable deposit of new
     osseous tissue lying between the periosteum and the bone. The periosteum itself was thicker and
     redder than natural in that locality, and from it these lamin&#230; of new osseous tissue had been
     developed. The knee joint was swelled out with a straw-colored jelly-like substance; the
     synovial fringes were reddened, but the articular cartilage presented no abnormity." A drawing
     of the specimen, No. 2229, by <name type="person" key="878">Hospital Stewart E. Stauch</name>, is copied in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXVI</hi>, opposite p. 306.</p>
   <p>&#179; <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL (<hi rend="initialcap">J. A.</hi>), <hi rend="italic">On Secondary Traumatic Lesions of Bone, viz: Osteo-myelitis, Periostitis, Ostitis, Caries, and Necrosis</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">U. S. Sanitary
   Commission Memoirs</hi>, 1870, Surgical Volume I, p. 414.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001820.001" />
    <head>PLATE  LXVI __ SHOT  FRACTURE  OF  THE  MIDDLE  THIRD  OF  THE  FEMUR.    <name type="person" key="1099">Private John Pool</name>, <name type="organization" key="449">Co. H, 119th Pennsylvania</name>.    Specimen, 2229,  A. M. M.</head> 
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
