<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e8760">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Buckley, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e8760</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
         <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">188</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
       <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>recovery after shot fractures of the middle third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>ball fractured thigh at middle third</term>
       <term>profuse h&#230;morrhages</term> 
       <term>thigh two and a half inches shortened, knee stiffened</term>  
      </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
       <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-29">added figure encoding</change>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-04-20">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 383.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant J. Buckley</name>, Regimental Quartermaster of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">140th New York</name>, aged 22 years, was wounded at
    <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice><orig>Spottsylvania</orig><reg>Spotsylvania</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-08">May 8, 1864</date>, by a mini&#233; ball, which fractured the right thigh at the middle third. From the field he was, on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-12">May 12th</date>, admitted to hospital at <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, and <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-17">five days afterwards</date> he was transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary Hospital</name>, Georgetown. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H. W. Ducachet</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter, reported the character of the injury and that the patient
    remained under treatment until <date type="furlough" when="1864-11-12">November 12th</date>, when he obtained a leave of absence and departed for his home. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-01-13">January
     13, 1865</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant Buckley</name> was mustered out of service and pensioned. <name type="person" key="1017">Dr. T. M. Flandrau</name>, formerly Surgeon <name type="organization" key="xxx">146th New
      York</name>, who saw this officer at the time of the injury, and also after he left the service, communicated his observations in <date type="pension" when="1870-03">March, 1870</date>, as follows: &#34;I decided to save the limb, and, aided by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H. C. Dean</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">140th New York</name>, dressed it in Smith's anterior
    splint, suspending it from the bows of an army wagon, in which, with his servant steadying the foot, he was carried to <name type="place">Belle Plain</name>. When he reached <name type="hospital" key="156">the Georgetown Hospital</name> the thigh was found shortened five inches. During the second, third, and fourth months after the injury he was treated by an extension weight of sixteen pounds, a counter-extending band, and lateral
    sand bags. On August 20th he had three profuse h&#230;morrhages, jeopardizing his life, which were controlled without operation.
    He used crutches when leaving the hospital, but threw them aside five months afterwards. He has since been employed as a
    bookkeeper. There is two and a half inches shortening, and the knee is somewhat stiffened. A fistulous opening still exists on
    the back of the thigh and discharges a little. The limb is very useful, and the limp is not conspicuous.&#34; The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Utica Examining Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1872-01-03">January 3, 1872</date>:   &#42;   &#42;   &#42;   &#34;There has been extensive exfoliation of bone, leaving several deep cicatrices, and there is still an open sinus extending to the bone and attended with bloody sanious discharge, indicating that there is still disease
    of the bone,&#34; etc.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner C. B. Coventry</name>, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-06">September 6, 1873</date>, certified to several pieces of bone having been removed, some
    of them since the previous examination. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="187903-04">March 4, 1879</date>.  <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 1 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LX</hi>, opp., is a representation of a photograph of the pensioner, taken in <name type="place">Rome, New York</name>, <date type="photo" when="1870-03">March, 1870</date>, which was contributed by <name type="person" key="1017">Dr. Flaudrau</name>, and copied at the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>.   (<hi rend="italic">Surg. Phot. Series</hi>, No. 266, A. M. M.) </p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001806.001" />
    <head>PLATE  LX.  &#8212;  CONSOLIDATED  GUNSHOT  FRACTURES  OF  THE  FEMUR.    Fig. 1.  Case of Lieutenant J. Buckley, 140th New York.</head> 
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
