<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e24475">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Holt, H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e24475</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">634-635</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the foot</term>
     <term>shot wounds of the bones of the foot</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the foot</term> 
     <term>amputations in the foot</term> 
     <term>secondary amputations in the foot</term> 
     <term>wounded in foot</term>
     <term>ball entered top of foot, cut out from sole of foot on the field </term>
     <term>fractured fifth metatarsal bone</term> 
     <term>stiffness in jaws, inability to open mouth, trismus</term> 
     <term>opening above inner malleolus, denuded tibia</term>
     <term>removed fragments of fifth metatarsal bone with little toe</term>     
     <term>strangury</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 935.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1411">Lieutenant H.
      Holt</name>, <name type="organization" key="121">Co. F, 130th New York</name>, aged 20 years,
     was wounded in the right foot, at <name type="BATTLE" key="217">Bull Run</name>, <date
      type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>.  <name type="person" key="938">Surgeon
      C. L. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, described the injury
     as follows:  "The ball entered at the top of the foot, fracturing the fifth metatarsal bone, and
     was cut out on the field from the sole of the foot. He went on horseback to <name type="place">Centreville</name>, where
     during the afternoon of the following day he was placed in an ambulance. <date type="admit" when="1862-09-01">The next day</date> he came
     to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, taking the cars at Fairfax Station and entering <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory Hospital</name> for a day or two, <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-03">when</date> he
     removed to a private boarding-house and was attended by a private physician.  On September 28th, foot was swollen; abscesses opened, and the original wounds were all discharging freely. The
     patient was much emaciated, his countenance expressing suffering and showing the strongly
     marked hectic flush; appetite gone; thirst considerable; pulse 130, feeble and fluttering; pain
     and stiffness in the jaws, with inability to open the mouth more than to admit the tip of the
     little finger between the teeth. This condition (trismus), he stated, had been coming on for
     two or three days. Huxham's tincture, brandy, beef-essence, etc., with an occasional full dose
     of morphia was prescribed.  On October 5th another abscess opened.  <date type="operation" when="1862-10-09">October 9th</date>: The patient has
     slowly and steadily improved in general appearance since my first attendance; pulse 110 to 116
     with more strength. It was thought advisable to put the patient under the influence of ether
     and examine and perform any operation considered necessary, <name type="person"
      key="1235">Surgeons M. Clymer</name> and <name type="person" key="288">J. H. Brinton</name>, <name
      type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, being requested to see the case. The foot was
     still enormously swollen, and the probe passed readily from the wound of entrance to the
     opening below the external malleolus. In the upper opening four inches above the inner
     malleolus the probe rapped distinctly upon the denuded tibia. <name type="person" key="1235">Surgeon Clymer</name> made an incision nearly the whole length of the external side of the
     foot, and removed the fragments of the fifth metatarsal bone together with the little toe.
     Since it appeared at this stage that all or nearly all the tarsal and metatarsal bones were
     diseased, as well as the lower third of the tibia, it was decided that amputation was
     necessary, but that the patient at this time could not endure any further operation. The
     tonics, stimulants, and nourishments were now crowded as much as possible.  On October 12th the patient had somewhat
     improved. On the following day tincture of cantharides, in doses of twenty drops every four hours and to be increased if
     necessary, was prescribed in addition to his other treatment. For three or four days the
     patient steadily but very slightly improved, after which he evidently failed for a few days. He
     had taken nearly two ounces of tincture of cantharides and suffered a little of strangury. All
     remedies except his nourishment and a little brandy were now omitted, and on the following day
     compound syrup of phosphate of lime and iron was ordered.  On October 23d the patient was still
     very feeble, but looked a little brighter and had a little appetite; pulse 120 to 130. After
     this he steadily improved, and by November 1st he had a good appetite, his pulse having
     gradually lessened to from 80 to 90 per minute.  On November 8th he was dressed and able to sit
     in a chair, and about two weeks later he first went down stairs on crutches. The wounds on the
     external side of the foot had completely healed by December 21st, while the openings on the
     other side, both above and below the malleolus, were still discharging. All the openings healed
     up about December 31st, but several days after more swelling appeared toward the toes, and on
     January 3d an opening occurred over the second metatarsal bone, near the distal extremity. This discharged freely for several weeks, denuded
     bone being detected by the probe.  On January 29th the patient was able to wear his boot all
     day, and one week afterwards he walked with a cane.  By February 15th the last opening had
     closed.  On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-03-13">March 13, 1863</date>, the patient was
     mustered out of service, walking with ease by the aid of a cane and without much difficulty
     without one. He subsequently informed me by letter that he was holding a position on <name type="organization" key="xx">the staff
      of <name type="person">Brigadier General Pierce</name></name> in Massachusetts."  <name type="person" key="1411">Lieutenant Holt</name> is a pensioner, and was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-02">February, 1879</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
