<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e27445">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Corliss, J. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e27445</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">747-748</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term> 
     <term>shot wounds of nerves</term>
     <term>temperature of affected parts higher than surrounding or corresponding portions of body</term>
     <term>shot in arm directly above internal condyle</term> 
     <term>ball emerged higher, through belly of biceps, without touching artery, injury to median and ulnar nerves</term>
     <term>suffering in the median and ulnar distribution</term> 
     <term>sensation was lost or lessened in the limb</term> 
     <term>paralysis of motion in hand and forearm</term>
     <term><choice><orig>exsected</orig><reg>excised</reg></choice> median nerve at wound</term>
     <term>second and third phalanges of fingers flexed and stiff, first phalanges extended</term>
     <term><choice><orig>interosseal</orig><reg>interosseous</reg></choice> muscles and hypothenar group much atrophied, thenar muscles partially wasted</term>
     <term>disability equal to loss of arm</term>
     <term>ball passed through inner and anterior arm at junction of middle and upper thirds, apparently involving median nerve</term>
     <term>neuralgia of palmar portion of hand and fingers</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>contraction of thumb and fingers into palm of hand, extreme sensitiveness of fingers</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1089.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1473">J. H. Corliss</name>, late private, <name type="organization" key="147">Co. B, 14th N. Y. S. M.</name>, aged 27 years, shingle dresser, enlisted <date type="enlist" when="1861-04">April, 1861</date>, in good health. At the <name type="BATTLE" key="127">second Bull
      Run</name> battle, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-29">August 29, 1862</date>, he was shot
     in the left arm three inches directly above the internal condyle. The ball emerged one and a
     quarter inches higher, through the belly of the biceps, without touching the artery, but with
     injury to the median and ulnar nerves. He was ramming a cartridge when hit, and "thought he was
     struck on the crazy-bone by some of the boys for a joke." The fingers of both hands flexed and
     grasped the ramrod and gun tightly. Bringing the right hand, still clutching the ramrod, to the
     left elbow, he felt the blood and knew he was wounded. He then shook the ramrod from his grasp
     with a strong effort, and unloosened with the freed hand the tight grip of the left hand on the
     gun. After walking some twenty paces he fell from loss of blood, but, still conscious,
     attempted to walk several times and as often failed. He was finally helped to the rear, taken
     prisoner, lay three days on the field without food, but with enough water to drink, and had his
     wounds dressed for the first time on the fourth day, at <name type="place" key="xx">Fairfax
      Court House</name>. On the second day the pain began. It was burning and darting. He states
     that at this time sensation was lost or lessened in the limb, and that paralysis of motion came
     on in the hand and forearm. His statement is unsatisfactory and indistinct. Admitted to the
      <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., <date type="admit"
      when="1862-09-07">September 7, 1862</date>. The pain was so severe that a touch anywhere, or
     shaking the bed, or a heavy step, caused it to increase. The suffering was in the median and
     ulnar distribution, especially at the palmar face of the knuckles and the ball of the thumb.
     Motion has varied little since the wound, and as to sensation he is not clear. <name
      type="person" key="964">Peter Pineo</name>, Surgeon, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, now Medical Inspector <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <choice><orig>exsected</orig><reg>excised</reg></choice>
     two or three inches of the median nerve at the wound.  (See <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> <hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> No. 959.)  The man states, very positively, that the pain in the
     median distribution did not cease nor immediately lessen, but that he became more sensitive, so that even the rattling of a paper
     caused extreme suffering. He "thinks he was not himself" for a day or two after the operation.
     It seems quite certain that the pain afterward gradually grew better, both in the ulnar and
     median tracts. Meanwhile the hand lay over his chest, and the fingers, flexing, became stiff in
     this position. <date type="injury" when="1862-09-05">About a week after he was shot</date> the right arm grew weak, and finally so feeble that
     he could not feed himself. He can now, April, 1864, use it pretty well, but it is manifestly
     less strong than the other. The left leg also was weakened, but when this began he cannot tell.
     He gives the usual account of the pain, and of the use of water on the hands and in his boots,
     as a means of easing it.  Present condition, April, 1864: Wound healed; cicatrix of the
     operation two and a half inches long over median nerve. The forearm muscles do not seem to be
     greatly wasted. The <choice><orig>interosseal</orig><reg>interosseous</reg></choice> muscles and hypothenar group are much atrophied, and the hand
     is thin and bony. The thenar muscles are partially wasted. The skin of the palm is eczematous,
     thin, red, and shining. The second and third phalanges of the fingers are flexed and stiff; the
     first is extended. Nails extraordinarily curved, laterally and longitudinally, except that of the thumb. Pain is stated to
     exist still in the median distribution, but much less than in the ulnar tract, where it is excessively great. He keeps his
     hand wrapped in rags wetted with cold water and covered with oiled silk, and even tucks the rag
     carefully under the flexed finger-tips. Moisture is more essential than cold. Friction outside of the clothes, at any point of the entire surface,
     "shoots" into the hand, increasing the burning in the median sometimes, and more commonly in
     the ulnar distribution. Deep pressure on the muscles has a like effect, and he will allow no
     one to touch his skin with a dry hand, and even then is careful to exact a tender manipulation.
     He keeps a bottle of water about him and carries a wet sponge in the right hand. This hand he
     wets always before he handles anything; used dry, it hurts the other limb. At one time, when
     the suffering was severe, he poured water into his boots, he says, to lessen the pain which dry
     touch or friction causes in the injured hand. So cautious was he about exposing the sore hand
     that it was impossible thoroughly to examine it; but it was clear to us that there was
     sensibility to touch in the ultimate median distribution, although he describes sensation as somewhat lessened in this region, and states that
     he has numbness on the inner side of the palm and in the third and fourth fingers (ulnar
     tract). When the balls of the first and second fingers were touched he said he felt it; but, on
     touching those of the third and fourth fingers, he refused to permit us to experiment further,
     and insisted on wrapping up and wetting the hand. He thus describes the pain at its height: "It
     is as if a rough bar of iron were thrust to and fro through the knuckles, a red-hot iron placed
     at the junction of the palm and thenar eminence, with a heavy weight on it, and the skin was
     being rasped off his finger ends." (Mitchell, Morehouse, and Keen, <hi rend="italic">loc.
      cit.</hi>, p. 109.) The following information was received from <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, under
     charge of <name type="person" key="964">Surgeon Peter Pineo</name>, <name type="organization"
      key="132">U. S. Vols.</name>: "The ball passed through the inner and anterior part of the arm
     at the junction of the middle and upper thirds, apparently involving the median nerve. He
     entered this hospital <date type="transfer" when="1862-09-01">September 1, 1862</date>,
     suffering excruciating neuralgia of the palmar portion of the hand and fingers. The wound
     healed kindly, but the pain in the hand continued in its intensity, yielding to no treatment,
     though nervous remedies, both local and constitutional, were resorted to. The extreme suffering
     produced an exalted sensibility of the entire nervous system which manifested itself in an
     extraordinary excitability of the patient, he complaining bitterly at the least jar or noise in
     the ward. This sad condition increased in severity until <date type="operation" when="1862-12-09">December 9, 1862</date>, when the operation
     of resection of the median nerve was performed by <name type="person" key="964">Dr. Peter
      Pineo</name>, in charge of the hospital. The patient being etherized, about two inches of the
     nerve was removed and the wound closed by adhesive strips. After the effect of the ether passed
     off the patient still complained of much pain in the hand, but seemed to think it was not so
     intense as before the operation. The patient's appetite continued good through all this
     suffering, and he was allowed a liberal diet. For several days after the operation the patient
     was allowed sulphate of morphia; but it was soon entirely withdrawn. The wound healed by first intention, but there seemed to be no positive improvement in regard to the neuralgia until December 14th, five days after the operation, when
     he was moved to a separate room; after which the hyper&#230;sthesia seemed perceptibly to
     subside. <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-02-14">February 14, 1863</date>, the patient was
     discharged from the service at his own earnest solicitation. At this time he was able to walk
     about the room at night, but still suffered very much from the slightest excitement."  <name
      type="person" key="xx">Examiner J. T. Burdick</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Brooklyn</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1866-10-23">October 23, 1866</date>: "A ball perforated the arm three and a half
     inches above the condyles, injuring the median and ulnar nerve trunks. He alleges that two
     inches of the median nerve were excised by the surgeon; the existence of a longitudinal eschar
     three inches in length tends to confirm the statement. The fingers are rigidly flexed into the
     palm. The arm and hand are atrophied. In my opinion the disability is equal to the loss of the
     arm. The <name type="organization" key="xx">Brooklyn Examining Board</name>, <name
      type="person" key="xx">Drs. McCollom</name> and <name type="person" key="xx">Leighton</name>,
     reported, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-18">September 18, 1873</date>: "Contraction of thumb and fingers into palm of hand. Extreme
     sensitiveness of the fingers. Arm and hand useless."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
