<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40814">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Chollar, John A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40814</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">145</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Harewood Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic rheumatism with diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>stools frequent and bloody, became bilious</term>
       <term>peritoneal adhesions along colon, especially transverse portion</term>
       <term>large intestine ulcerated, especially sigmoid flexure and rectum</term>
       <term>follicles of colon enlarged</term>
       <term>colon ulcers under microscope contained pus-corpuscles, fat-globules, and crystals of cholesterin</term>         
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book and medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="173"><hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>AREWOOD <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="156">Surgeon Thomas Antisell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge from October, 1862, to September, 1863:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 276.&#8212;<name type="person" key="169">Private John A. Chollar</name>, <name type="organization" key="157">company K, 21st Connecticut volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-02-08">February 8, 1863</date>, from Windmill Point hospital.  Chronic rheumatism, with diarrh&#339;a.  This man had a feeble pulse and considerable &#339;dema of the feet and legs, but was not very much emaciated or prostrated when first admitted. At that time the stools were frequent and bloody; they afterward became bilious.  Treatment: At first a scruple each of Dover's powder and mercury with chalk, divided into six powders, once every four hours; afterward wine, milk-punch, and brandy in small quantities.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-02-23">February 23d</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> Peritoneal adhesions were found along the whole length of the colon, especially in the transverse portion. The stomach was distended with a liquid containing bile. The intestines were filled with f&#230;cal matter of normal consistence, and highly colored with bile. The small intestine was healthy. The large intestine was ulcerated, especially in the sigmoid flexure and rectum; the ulcers were deeply stained with biliary coloring matter; the follicles of the colon were much enlarged. The liver was normal; the gall-bladder greatly distended with bile. The spleen normal. Some of the matter from the colon ulcers, examined under the microscope, was found to contain pus-corpuscles, fat-globules, debris of tissue, and crystals of cholesterin.</p>  
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
 