<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40000">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Taylor, Alfred</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e40000</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">187</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the First Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>crepitation with auscultation over seat of pain</term>
       <term>lower lung hepatized</term>
       <term>no disease in stomach or bowels</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-04">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>The next case was forwarded on medical descriptive lists from the <name type="hospital" key="500"><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IRST <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name>
    of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon Charles Page</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 438.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Alfred Taylor</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company B, 121st Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; admitted from the hospital of the 3d Division, 1st Corps, near <name type="place">Catlett's Station, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-11-04">November 4, 1863</date>.  Diarrh&#339;a.  The patient was very much broken down, and said he had suffered from diarrh&#339;a for some time.  &#8478;. Dover's powder ten grains, nitrate of potassa four grains, calomel one grain; three times daily. Milk diet.  November 6th: He had a chill followed by fever, cough, and uneasiness in the chest.  &#8478;. Dover's powder twenty-five grains, sulphate of quinia fourteen grains, mercury with chalk twelve grains; make five powders. Take one every three hours. A mustard plaster to the chest. Flaxseed-tea and nitre to drink.  November 7th: Cough frequent; expectoration scanty; skin dry; some pain in the right side of the chest. On auscultation over the seat of pain some crepitation was discovered. To take, three times daily, a powder containing six grains of Dover's powder, two of quinine, and three of powdered camphor; also two ounces of wine every four hours.  <date type="death" when="1863-11-08">November 8th</date>, morning visit: Pulse 97; skin dry; expectoration scanty. Continue treatment. Apply a blister six inches by seven to the right side of the chest.  He died during the afternoon.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> The lower part of the right lung was hepatized. The heart and left lung were normal. No disease was detected in the stomach or bowels. The liver and spleen appeared to be healthy.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon James Robertson</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
