<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e19152">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Waters, B. G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e19152</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">465</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
       <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term> 
       <term>primary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term> 
       <term>primary amputations in the upper third of the leg for shot injury</term> 
       <term>fatal primary amputations in the upper third of the bones of the leg</term>
       <term>shot fracture of leg</term> 
       <term>leg amputated at upper third</term> 
       <term>diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>leg reamputated in lower third of femur </term>
       <term>ends of both bones exposed</term>       
       <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-07">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 730.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private B. G. Waters</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. H, 19th Maine</name>, aged 19 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-10-15">October 15, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon I. Scott</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">7th West Virginia</name>, reported that &#34;he entered the field hospital of the 2d division, Second Corps, with shot fracture of leg, caused by a mini&#233; ball, for which <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon W. J. Burr</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">42d New York</name>, performed amputation.&#34;  <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported the following result of the case: &#34;The patient was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="504">Baptist Church Hospital</name> at <name type="place">Alexandria</name>
    <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-21">six days after being wounded</date>. His left leg had been amputated at the upper third by anterior and posterior flaps on <date type="operation" when="1864-10-15">the day of
    the injury</date>. When admitted his general health was fair, although he complained of considerable pain and required opiates to
    procure sleep. The integument over the spine of the tibia was black and had commenced to slough. This continued until the
    ends of both bones were exposed and the stump around presented a large mass of sloughing tissue. Stimulating lotions were
    applied and some improvement followed; all sloughing ceased and granulations commenced; but the granulations were pale
    and flabby, the edges of the integument everted, and the patient suffered excessive pain. On November 18th, sloughing
    reappeared and extended rapidly towards the popliteal region. He was also troubled some with diarrh&#339;a, having about four
    passages daily. He was daily growing weaker from suffering and loss of appetite, and the stump became so painful that he
    would cry out frequently, complaining of spasmodic twitching. Taking these circumstances and the danger of secondary
    h&#230;morrhage into consideration, the limb was reamputated in the lower third of the femur (see <hi rend="initialcap">T</hi>ABLE <hi rend="initialcap">XL</hi>, No. 200, p. 323, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>)
    on <date type="operation" when="1864-11-24">November 24th</date>, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Assistant Surgeon W. A. Harvey</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who used sulphuric ether as the an&#230;sthetic and performed the operation by the circular method. Three days after the operation the patient's appetite had improved and he could sleep well,
    was more cheerful, and complained of but little pain. No union had yet taken place in the stump, but suppuration had commenced. On December 7th, when transferred to <name type="hospital" key="202">Prince Street Hospital</name>, he was still doing well.&#34;  The subsequent records show the patient died of exhaustion <date type="death" when="1865-04-25">April 25, 1865</date>. The stumps of the tibia and fibula, removed at the second amputation,
    together with portion of the popliteal vein, external and internal popliteal nerves, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, and constitute specimens 3445, 3446, 3447, and 3448, respectively, of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>.</p>  
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
