<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e25034">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wilson, A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e25034</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>   
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">718</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and complications</term>       
       <term>shot wounds</term>      
       <term>effect of missiles and projectiles on bony structure</term>
       <term>contusions of bone</term>
       <term>ball struck outer side of lower arm, part of ball passed through and came out posterior surface</term>
       <term>portion of ball cut out from arm</term>   
       <term>piece of metal in sinus extending upward from wound</term>
       <term>piece of ball excised from sinus, bone beneath bare of periosteum</term>
       <term>projectile penetrated arm at insertion of triceps, passed inward and upward</term>   
       <term>fragments extracted from two places in belly of biceps</term>
       <term>arm has free motion, decreased tensile strength</term>        
       <term>pensioned</term>  
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1060.&#8212;<name type="person" key="1463">Private A. Wilson</name>, <name type="organization" key="480">Co. L, 1st Minnesota</name>, aged 30 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="281">Antietam</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-09-17">September 17, 1862</date>. He was treated in <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver Hospital</name>, Washington, and on <date type="admit" when="1862-12-12">December 12th</date> was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="xx">Satterlee Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>.  <name type="person" key="137">Surgeon I. I. Hayes</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported:  "The ball, the precise character of which is unknown, struck at the outer side of the lower part of the left arm; part of it passed through the member and came out at the posterior surface. <date type="operation" when="1862-09-18">Next day</date> a portion of the ball, about the size of a dime, was cut out from the front part of the arm toward the inner side. On his admission into <name type="hospital" key="xx">this hospital</name> his arm seemed nearly well, but a small ulcer, scabbed over, marked the point of entrance of the ball, and a probe passed into this discovered a sinus extending several inches upward, a piece of metal being discovered and clearly felt at its upper extremity. His general condition was perfectly good.  <date type="operation" when="1863-01-03">January 3d</date>, having administered chloroform, I laid open the sinus before mentioned for about three inches and readily extracted a piece of ball. Its concave surface was closely applied to the outer edge of the lower flat portion of the humerus; the bone beneath was roughened and apparently bare of periosteum. On several subsequent occasions I convinced myself that the bone was dead and looked for a tedious process of exfoliation; but on January 15, 1863, thinking to pass a probe, I found the wound firmly united, and the healing process has gone on most favorably. There is no swelling, no tenderness, no orifice through which the smallest probe could be inserted, and the wound has the aspect of a healthy and rapidly healing ulcer."  <name type="person" key="1463">Wilson</name> was returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1863-04-22">April 22, 1863</date>, and discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-11-24">November 24, 1865</date>, and pensioned.  The <name type="organization" key="xx">Williamsport Examining Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1881-07-06">July 6, 1881</date>: "The projectile penetrated the left arm at the insertion of the triceps and passed inward and upward. Fragments were extracted from two places in the belly of the biceps. Some fragments of bone were removed. The arm has every motion free except tensile strength." His pension was paid <date type="pension" when="1881-12-04">December 4, 1881</date>.</p>
   <p></p>   
   <p></p>   
   <p></p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
