<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e7451">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Kagrice, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e7451</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">171</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>gangrenous osteomyelitis of femur</term>
     <term>pyæmic abscesses</term>
     <term>gunshot contusion of femur at middle third</term>
     <term>ball struck femur at middle third, contused bone without fracturing</term>
     <term>ball lodged above acetabulum</term>
     <term>hip joint uninjured</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 341.—<name type="person" key="988">Private J.
     Kagrice</name>, <name type="organization" key="403">Co. F, 198th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 30
    years, was wounded during the engagement at <name type="BATTLE" key="37">White Oak Road</name>,
     <date type="injury" when="1865-03-31">March 31, 1865</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon W. R. DeWitt</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded his
    admission to the field hospital of the 1st division, Fifth Corps, with "shot wound of left
    thigh," and his transfer to <name type="place">City Point</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-01">the following day</date>. Several days afterwards the wounded man was
    transferred to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, whence <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon W. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the specimen (<hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>,
    1866, p. 258, <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4201), with the following history: "The injury
    was a severe gunshot contusion of the left femur at its middle third. The patient was in good
    health and spirits at the time of his admission and doing well. The wound was carefully
    examined, but the ball could not be traced. On <date type="operation" when="1865-04-23">April
     23d</date>, a large abscess was opened on the anterior aspect of the thigh near the trochanter.
    On <date type="operation" when="1865-04-29">the 29th</date>, another similar incision was
    required in order to give free exit to pus. The patient, however, continued pretty well until
     <date type="injury" when="1865-05-05">May 5th</date>, when he had a chill. This recurred on May
    7th and 8th, and on the 9th, 12th, 13th, and 14th, he had two chills a day. The thigh became
    painful, the discharge thin and fetid. On May 16th, the patient became delirious, had another
    chill, and his tongue became swollen and inflamed. He died on <date type="death" when="1865-05-17">the following day</date>. At the <hi rend="italic">autopsy</hi> no pleurisy
    or effusion was found in either thoracic cavity. The lungs, liver, spleen, kidneys, and brain
    were carefully examined for pyæmic abscesses, but appeared healthy. On examining the femur
    it was found that the ball had struck it at its middle third, contused the bone without
    fracturing, and, being deflected from its course, had lodged in the hollow above the acetabulum.
    The hip joint was healthy and uninjured. A longitudinal section was made of the femur, which
    exhibited well marked gangrenous osteomyelitis,¹ the medulla being of a dirty greenish
    color, dry, pulverulent, and excessively fetid. The interspaces between the cancelli contained a
    dark greenish liquid, a quantity of which escaped in sawing the bone, and was also extremely
    offensive. The bone where the missile had struck had become necrosed and nearly separated, and
    around this partial exfoliation a ring of new bone had formed." A portion of the injured
    femur is illustrated in the adjacent wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 128). </p>

   <p> ¹ Dr. <hi rend="initialcap">J</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL in his excellent paper on <hi rend="italic">Contusion and Contused Wounds of Bone,
     with an Account of Thirteen Cases</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Am. Jour. Med. Sci.</hi>, 1865,
    Vol. L, p. 17, gives the following as the principal pathological effects of contusions of bone:
    1. Ecchymosis of the osseous tissue; 2. Ecchymosis of the medullary tissue; 3. Osteomyelitis of
    a simple character; 4. Necrotic osteitis; 5. Suppurative osteomyelitis; and 6. Gangrenous
    osteomyelitis. </p>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001557.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 128.—Shot contusion of left femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4201.</head></figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
