<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41417">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Magher, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41417</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">192</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrh&#339;a and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrh&#339;a and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Second Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrh&#339;a</term>
       <term>axillary and cervical glands enlarged</term>
       <term>old ulcers (apparently chancres) on penis</term>
       <term>fluid blood from sinuses when opened</term>
       <term>old pleuritic adhesions on both lungs</term>
       <term>apex of each lung had cretefied tubercles</term>
       <term>first stage of pneumonia</term>
       <term>bronchial glands contained large deposits of calcareous matter</term>
       <term>pericardium contained serum</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of colon and rectum extensively ulcerated and almost gangrenous</term>
       <term>liver under microscope in state of fatty degeneration</term>
       <term>cortical portion of both kidneys when examined microscopically found to be fatty</term>
       <term>adjoining pancreas several enlarged and partially cretefied lymphatic glands</term>
       <term>mesenteric glands enlarged and partially cretefied</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-17">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge.  Autopsy was made and recorded in the case-book by <name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 459.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal John Magher</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 88th New York volunteers</name>; age 24; admitted from the field <date type="admit" when="1864-10-21">October 21, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrh&#339;a.  [This man appears on the register of the depot hospital of the 2d Corps, <name type="place">City Point, Virginia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-09-24">September 24th</date>&#8212;chronic diarrh&#339;a&#8212;sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-20">October 20th</date>.]  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-11-29">November 29th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-11-29">nine hours after death</date>: Rigor mortis moderate; body emaciated; axillary and cervical glands very much enlarged; old ulcers (apparently chancres) on the penis; extensive suggillation posteriorly. The subarachnoid space contained an ounce of serum; the pia mater was injected; the brain was normal; fluid blood escaped from the sinuses when they were opened, and coagulated as perfectly as blood drawn during life. Neck and spinal column not examined. There were extensive firm, old pleuritic adhesions on both sides, and about four ounces of serum in each pleural cavity. In the apex of each lung was a deposit of cretefied tubercles; the lower lobes of both lungs were dark, congested, indurated, and crepitated very little when pressed between the fingers, but floated on water, (apparently first stage of pneumonia.) The bronchial glands contained large deposits of calcareous matter. The pericardium contained an ounce of serum. The heart was normal. The mucous membrane of the small intestine was healthy; that of the colon and rectum thickened, softened, extensively ulcerated, and of very dark color, (almost gangrenous.) The liver was normal in size, but when examined under the microscope was found to be in a state of fatty degeneration. The cortical portion of both kidneys was very pale, and when examined microscopically was found to be fatty. The spleen was very small; weight about three ounces. The pancreas was normal; immediately adjoining it were several enlarged lymphatic glands, which were partially cretefied. Many of the mesenteric glands were in the same condition.&#8212;<name type="person" key="655">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas Bowen</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
