<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30135">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Singleton, D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e30135</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>  
         <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">574</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
       <term>excisions at the shoulder</term>
       <term>excisions of the head and portions of the shaft of the humerus</term>
       <term>intermediary excisions of the upper extremity of the humerus for shot injury</term> 
       <term>successful operations</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of shoulder</term>
       <term>ball lodged in head of humerus, splitting the head and detaching splinter</term> 
       <term>head of humerus and two inches of shaft excised, then two and a half inch space between upper end of shaft and glenoid cavity</term>
       <term>slight motion of arm, limited use of forearm and hand</term>
       <term>false joint between upper end of shaft and glenoid cavity</term> 
       <term>important tendons severed by ball or by knife of surgeon</term>
       <term>arm useless for manual labor</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-02-23">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1556.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private D. Singleton</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 140th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 30 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice><orig>Spottsylvania</orig><reg>Spotsylvania</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-12">May 12, 1864</date>, and was treated in a Second Corps field hospital, and thence sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, entering <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver Hospital</name> on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-16">May 16th</date>.  He was operated on by <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon O. A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who reported as follows:  &#34;Gunshot wound of shoulder; conoidal ball lodged in head of humerus, splitting the head and detaching splinter. On <date type="operation" when="1864-08-27">May 27th</date>, a straight incision was made through the deltoid, and the head and two inches of the shaft of the humerus was removed by a chain saw. Result favorable, the wound filling with healthy granulations.&#34;  The patient was transferred, and admitted to hospital at <name type="place"><choice><orig>Pittsburg</orig><reg>Pittsburgh</reg></choice></name> on <date type="transfer" when="1864-11-16">November 16, 1864</date>, and on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-06-11">June 11, 1865</date>, was discharged the service and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner D. Stanton</name>, of <name type="place">New Brighton, Pennsylvania</name>, <date type="pension" when="1868-05-31">May 31, 1868</date>, reported:  &#34;Mini&#233; ball lodged in the head of the humerus. The head and about two inches of the shaft excised May 20, 1864. There is now a space of about two and a half inches between the upper end of the shaft and the glenoid cavity. There is still necrosis of the bone. There is very slight voluntary motion of the arm, and limited use of the forearm and hand.&#34;  On <date type="photo" when="1866-06-23">June 23, 1866</date>, <name type="person" key="1389">J. Wilson Wishart</name>, late Surgeon <name type="organization" key="xxx">149th Pennsylvania</name>, forwarded to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> a photograph exhibiting the appearance of the injured limb at that time. The arm is supported at the highest point to which he could raise the elbow by voluntary efforts. This photograph is represented by <hi rend="italic">Figure</hi> 3 in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XVIII</hi>.  <name type="person" key="1389">Dr. Wishart</name> states:  &#34;During the present month <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. S.</name> called upon me at my office, and upon examination I found a slight discharge from the point indicated in the photograph by the dark spot at the junction of the upper and middle thirds of the cicatrix. Upon introducing a probe I discovered diseased bone, which, at his request, I removed on <date type="operation" when="1866-06-21">Thursday the 21st</date> instant, through an incision in the upper part of the cicatrix. It proved to be a portion of the sawed surface of the humerus, which, with pieces previously discharged, completed about two-thirds of the circumference of the bone. A probe, introduced to the point whence the bone was extracted, entered a canal some two inches in depth, extending downward and to the inside of the humerus. Careful and repeated examination by myself and another surgeon failed to detect any communication with the humerus, or any more diseased bone. I am in hopes now that the wound will entirely close.&#34;  In a certificate for increase of pension, <date type="pension" when="1867-01-16">January 16, 1867</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner Stanton</name> reported:  &#34;There is now false joint, there being a space of two and a half inches between the upper end of the shaft and the glenoid cavity. The slight use of the hand is more than counterbalanced by the pain and soreness caused by its use. Important tendons were severed by the ball or by the knife of the surgeon.&#34;  In September, 1873, a Board, convened at <name type="place"><choice><orig>Pittsburg</orig><reg>Pittsburgh</reg></choice></name>, and composed of <name type="person" key="xxx">Drs. A. G. McCandless</name>, <name type="person" key="1389">J. W. Wishart</name>, and <name type="person" key="xxx">W. J. Elmore</name>, reported:  &#34;The arm is useless for purposes of manual labor.&#34;  The pensioner was paid <name type="person" key="1874-06-04">June 4, 1874</name>.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001828.001" />
    <head>PLATE  XVIII __ RESULTS  OF  EXCISIONS  OF  THE  HEAD  OF  THE  HUMERUS.     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. III.   Private D. Singleton.</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
