<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e323">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Crane, J. W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e323</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">12</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>shot flesh wounds</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower limbs, with injury of the larger nerves</term>
     <term>wounds of unspecified nerves</term>
     <term>injury of sciatic nerve</term> 
     <term>partial paralysis of both lower extremities</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>              
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="Sarah Synovec" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded
    P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   
    <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 17.&#8212;<name type="person" key="869">Sergeant J. W.
      Crane</name>, <name type="organization" key="324">Co. A, 79th New York</name>, aged 27 years,
     was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="253">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury"
      when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>, and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-09-06">one week afterward</date>. On <date type="transfer"
      when="1863-05-09">May 9, 1863</date>, he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xx"
       >DeCamp Hospital</name>, <name type="place">David's Island</name>, whence <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant
        Surgeon J. W. Dickie</name> reported: &#34;A ball passed through right thigh at about the junction
     of the upper and middle thirds. The wound closed about the <date type="injury" when="1863-03-01">first of March</date>, and a small abscess
     formed, about that time, a little below the wound. When the abscess healed a pain commenced in
     the left hip joint, extending to the foot. This pain was constant. No pain was felt in the
     right leg except when pressure was made on the wound. The pain was most severe in the hip and
     calf of the leg. It would at times ascend and affect the respiratory muscles, causing great
     distress and difficulty in breathing. Appetite poor when admitted, yet the patient is quite
     fleshy. Had taken considerable quantity of morphia, so much as to be free from pain. <date type="injury" when="1863-05-13">May 13th</date>,
     had recurrence of pain and dyspn&#339;a, and spasm of upper extremities. Gave chloroform, twenty drops, and repeated the dose in fifteen minutes. May 17th, had another spasm;
     same treatment. Has slighter attacks more frequently, which are relieved by exposure to cold.
     May 19th, had another spasm; two grains of sulphate of morphia given; pain checked. May 24th,
     another spasm; gave chloroform one drachm, and sulphate of morphia one grain; pain relieved. On
     the next day cauterization was performed along the course of the great ischiatic and peroneal
     nerves. May 28th, gave nine grains of sulphate of quinine and a half grain of sulphate of
     morphia, and repeated every evening. May 29th, had a recurrence, but not much spasm. June 12th,
     the cauterized surface is healed; patient improving and has but little pain. June 22d, walked
     out, supporting himself by means of canes.&#34; The patient was subsequently transferred to <name
      type="hospital" key="xx">McDougall Hospital</name>, where he was recorded as having been
     &#34;returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1863-12-28">December 28, 1863</date>.&#34; The records,
     however, do not show that he resumed active duty in the field. He was mustered out <date
      type="servicedischarge" when="1864-10-06">October 6, 1864</date>, and pensioned. The <name
       type="organization" key="xx">Hartford Examining Board</name> certified, <date type="pension" when="1871-05-03">May 3, 1871</date>:  &#42;  &#42;  &#34;The
     muscles and skin are bound down to the bone and are much impaired in action. Partial paralysis
     of both limbs, owing to the injury to the nerves.&#34; <name type="organization" key="xx">The same Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-15">September 15, 1873</date>, that &#34;owing to the injury to some nerve he suffers
     excruciating pain on slight exercise or change of temperature,&#34; and, at a subsequent
     examination, they stated that &#34;pain extends to the spine and down the other leg, and the limb
     at such times is drawn up spasmodically;&#34; also that &#34;he is confined to bed from one to three
     months every year,&#34; etc. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1876-06-04">June 4, 1876</date>. </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
