<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3427">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Devine, Patrick</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e3427</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted:
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">233</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>clinical records</term>
          <term>continued fevers</term>
          <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
          <term>typhoid fever</term>
          <term>recurring epistaxis</term>
          <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
          <term>flabby tongue</term> 
          <term>gastric irratability</term>
          <term>diarrh&#339;a</term> 
          <term>general abdominal tenderness</term> 
          <term>delirium</term>
          <term>sordes</term>
          <term>prostration</term>
          <term>inflammation of parotid</term>
          <term>rose-spots and vibices</term>
          <term>right iliac tenderness</term>
          <term>micturition difficult</term>
          <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-06-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00069">
      
        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 69.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Flabby tongue; gastric
            irritability; recurring epistaxis; diarrh&#339;a and general abdominal tenderness;
            headache; delirium; sordes; prostration; inflammation of parotid; rose-spots and
            vibices; discharged on account of typhoid fever.</hi>&#8212;<name type="person"
            key="527">Private Patrick Devine</name>, <name type="organization" key="510">Co. K, 3d
            Vt.</name>; age 18; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-10-01">Oct. 1,
              1861</date>, with typhoid fever. He had been taken, <date type="injury" when="1861-09-26">September 26</date>, with headache, chills,
          fever, diarrh&#339;a and epistaxis (which last had been of frequent occurrence during
          the previous month), and on the 28th with retention of urine. On October 2 the patient's
          face was congested; his eyes dull and heavy; pulse 112, quick and strong; skin hot and
          dry; tongue moist and coated brown; teeth covered with sordes; stomach irritable and
          unable to retain food or medicine; he had headache and pain in the back, with tenderness
          over the whole of the abdomen and slight borborygmus. Repeated doses of calomel and opium,
          with turpentine emulsion, were given. Quinine, extract of buchu and sweet spirit of nitre
          were administered on the 4th, and beef-essence, milk-punch and astringents on the 6th, as
          diarrh&#339;a began to be a prominent symptom. On the 7th the pulse was 90 and strong,
          the skin natural, the tongue slightly moist, red at the tip and edges, heavily coated
          brown and fissured in the center and at the base; eight stools were passed, and
          micturition was difficult. Rose-colored spots appeared on the following day; there was
          some mental <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> with headache and occasional delirium; cough was troublesome, and the
          diarrh&#339;a was accompanied with general abdominal tenderness which was especially
          acute in the right iliac region. Epistaxis occurred on the 11th and next day the bowels
          were quiet. With the moderation of the diarrh&#339;a the tongue became flabby and
          remained dry and brown-coated in the centre, although the appetite improved. Epistaxis
          recurred on the 14th with some headache and delirium; the tip and edges of the tongue
          became red, the lips covered with sordes and the bowels relaxed to five stools daily. Next
          day the nose bled again, some rose-colored spots appeared, and the patient was unable to
          protrude his tongue on account of swelling of the parotid gland. Epistaxis, profuse
          perspiration and vibices on the neck and chest, with headache and increased swelling of
          the parotid, but no delirium, were noted on the 17th; the diarrh&#339;a continued with
          general tenderness and some meteorism, especially marked in the right iliac region.
          Vibices were numerous on the abdomen on the 18th, and fresh rose-spots appeared on the
          20th, 22d, 23d, 25th and 28th; during these days the diarrh&#339;a moderated, but the
          tenderness continued, being sometimes general and at others specially marked in the
          umbilical and right or left iliac regions; some headache and cough were noted but no
          delirium; the appetite was good, the skin generally moist, and the tongue moist and but
          slightly coated; the patient continued unable to protrude his tongue. Epistaxis recurred
          on the 28th and on November 2d, 4th, 6th and 8th, during which days there was some heat
          and dryness of skin, with headache and tinnitus, relaxation of the bowels, abdominal
          tenderness and coated tongue, the appetite continuing good and the cough subsiding; pulse
          80 to 100. No change took place in his condition up to <date type="transfer"
            when="1861-11-18">the 18th</date>, when he was transferred to <name type="place">Annapolis, Md.</name> [whence he was
          discharged on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1861-11-29">the 29th</date> on account
          of typhoid fever]. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
