<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16656">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">H&#8212;&#8212;, P.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16656</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">263</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>trephining practiced, fatal termination</term>
          <term>conoidal ball fractured and depressed posterior portion of left parietal bone</term>
          <term>convulsions</term>
          <term>deglutition lost, tongue turned to left side</term>
          <term>fragment of bone perforated dura mater, removal followed by discharge of
            disorganized brain substance</term>
          <term>loss of speech</term>
          <term>paralysis of right side</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>pus between dura mater and brain</term>
          <term>red softening and disorganization of brain under seat of injury</term>
          <term><choice>
              <orig>sero-sanguinolent</orig>
              <reg>serosanguinous</reg>
            </choice> effusion at base of brain</term>
          <term>dura mater showed marks of inflammatory action, brown color in neighborhood of
            fracture</term>

        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private P.
          H&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization">Co. E, 9th Pennsylvania Reserves</name>,
        aged 28 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg,
          Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th, 1862</date>, by a
        conoidal ball, which fractured and depressed the posterior portion of the left parietal
        bone. He was unconscious for some time after the reception of the injury. On <date
          type="admit" when="1862-12-15">December 15th</date>, he was admitted into the <name
          type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington. D. C. A wound of scalp was
        discovered through which could be felt a portion of depressed bone; through another wound,
        two inches anteriorly, the patient stated that a portion of the ball had been extracted. No
        symptoms of brain lesion were manifest, the patient being perfectly conscious and answering
        all questions correctly and intelligently. Ice was applied to the head, but, toward evening,
        convulsions ensued followed by others at intervals during the night. The next morning a
        semi-comatose condition supervened, continuing until the 17th, when it deepened. The power
        of deglutition was lost, and the tongue turned to the left side of the month. On <date
          type="operation" when="1862-12-18">the 18th</date>, the condition being unimproved, an
        operation was decided upon. Accordingly the patient was etherized, and <name type="person"
          key="70">Surgeon John A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
          V.</name>, applied the trephine to the anterior edge of the opening in the cranium and
        removed a disc of bone. The depressed portion, about an inch long and three-fourths of an
        inch wide, and six fragments of bone were easily detached. One of the latter had evidently
        perforated the dura mater, its removal being followed by a discharge of disorganized brain
        substance. After the operation, the coma lightened somewhat and power of deglutition and
        consciousness were restored; the loss of speech, however, continued. The improvement was of
        short duration, for on the next day coma and paralysis of the right side again supervened,
        with effused blood, which was very dark, amounted, in all, to three ounces, and came from
        the longitudinal sinus. These symptoms increased in gravity continuously, the patient
        becoming more and more exhausted until <date type="death" when="1862-12-23">the 23d</date>,
        when he died. At the <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination, a thick brown-colored
        pus, to the amount of an ounce and a halt, escaped from between the dura mater and the
        brain. Under the seat of injury was found red softening and disorganization of the brain
        extending to the depth of an inch and a half. There was also considerable effusion of clear
        serum in the ventricles, and a <choice>
          <orig>sero-sanguinolent</orig>
          <reg>serosanguinous</reg>
        </choice> effusion at the base of the brain. The cerebrum generally, including both right
        and left hemispheres, was congested, the punctiform spots being unusually distinct. The dura
        mater, covering the convexity of the left hemisphere, showed marks of recent inflammatory
        action, being injected, reddened, roughened, and of a brown color in the neighborhood of the
        fracture. It was also lined by a thick layer of false membrane. The specimen is figured in
        the wood-cut. The fractured portion of the inner table of the cranium measures three-fourths
        by one inch, and is partly included in the disk removed by the trephine. The outer table is
        injured to a less extent. The specimen and history were contributed by <name type="person"
          key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
        V.</name></p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001413.001"/>
        <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 126.&#8212;Segment of left parietal, from a patient
          trephined for depressed gunshot fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 534, Sect. I, A. M.
          M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
