<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18369">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Lahany, P.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e18369</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">443</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>recovery after shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>secondary h&#230;morrhage, femoral artery ligated</term>
     <term>shot fracture of leg</term>
     <term>shot fracture of fibula</term>
     <term>ball entered middle of leg on outer side, passed backward and inward, fractured fibula,
      emerged posteriorly lower than point of entrance</term>
     <term>contraction of muscles of calf</term>
     <term>unable to bring heel to ground</term>
     <term>muscles attached to integument of back of leg, impairing action of tendo-achillis</term>
     <term>wounded through both buttocks</term>
     <term>leg below knee one-half smaller than mate</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-05">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 699.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal P.
     Lahany</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. G, 5th Vermont</name>, aged 21 years,
    was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="58">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury"
     when="1865-04-02">April 2, 1865</date>, and admitted to the field hospital of the 2d division,
    Sixth Corps, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon S. F. Chapin</name>, <name
     type="organization" key="xxx">139th Pennsylvania</name>, recorded: &#34;Shot fracture of left
    leg.&#34; <name type="person" key="411">Surgeon D. P. Smith</name>, <name type="organization"
     key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported the wounded man's entrance into <name type="hospital"
     key="214">Fairfax Seminary Hospital</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-06">April
     6th</date>, with &#34;Shot fracture of left fibula,&quot; but made no record of any surgical
    treatment in the case. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-05-30">May 30th</date>, the patient
    was transferred to Baxter Hospital, <name type="place">Brattleboro</name>, and subsequently to
    Sloan Hospital, <name type="place">Montpelier</name>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon H.
     Janes</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter,
    contributed a photograph of the patient, which is copied in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap"
     >F</hi>IG. 269), together with the following history: &#34;The wound was produced by a
    mini&#233; ball, which entered the leg on the outer side two inches below its middle, passed
    backward and inward, fracturing the fibula, and emerging posteriorly one inch lower than the
    point of entrance. Several fragments of bone were removed on the field <date type="operation"
     when="1865-04-02">four hours after the injury</date>. Secondary h&#230;morrhage occurred on
     <date type="operation" when="1865-04-09">April 9th</date>, for which the femoral artery was
    ligated in Scarpa's space by <name type="person" key="411">Dr. Smith</name>, at <name
     type="hospital" key="214">Fairfax Seminary Hospital</name>. The patient was much prostrated
    after the operation, and artificial heat was required for about a week to keep up the
    temperature of the limb. No recurrence of the h&#230;morrhage took place, and the wound closed
    rapidly after the operation. At the time of his admission to Sloan Hospital, <date
     type="transfer" when="1865-06-12">June 12th</date>, both wounds were nearly healed and he could
    walk without crutches, but could not bring the heel to the ground on account of contraction of
    the muscles of the calf. In the early part of July an abscess formed at the place of ligation,
    which healed however in a short time. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-08-11">August
     11th</date>, the patient was discharged from service, though unable to leave the hospital on
    account of an abscess at the original wound, caused by a fragment of necrosed bone. <date
     type="hospitaldischarge" when="1865-09-01">Three weeks afterwards</date> the abscess had nearly
    healed and he left the hospital in good health, but still unable to get the heel to the ground.
    This patient had also been wounded through both buttocks, at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the
     Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>, from which injury
    he had recovered in three months, when he rejoined his command for duty.&#34; Various surgeons,
    at consecutive intervals, certified to the injuries, and <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner
     F. W. Goodall</name>, of <name type="place">Bennington</name>, <date type="pension"
     when="1877-10-05">October 5, 1877</date>, adds: &#34;The left leg below the knee is one-half
    smaller than its mate, one-half smaller at the calf, and one-quarter at the ankle; muscles
    attached to the integument on back of leg, impairing the action of the tendo-achillis. I also
    find a large cicatrix in the left triangle of Scarpa, from ligation of the femoral artery.&#34;
    The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-03-04">March 4, 1880</date>.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001628.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 269.&#8212;Shot fracture of left fibula and ligation of
     femoral. [From a photograph.]</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
