<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2085">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">H——, James</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e2085</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">19-20</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>incised and punctured wounds</term>
                    <term>incised fractures of the cranium</term>
                    <term>abscess in anterior cerebrum</term>
                    <term>sabre wound on side of forehead</term>
                    <term>cleft in outer table of bone</term>
                    <term>headache, cephalalgia</term>
                    <term>autopsy performed</term>
                    <term>incised fracture of frontal bone, outer table only</term>
                    <term>abscess in anterior lobe of cerebrum</term>
                    <term>pus through all ventricles and passed between medulla oblongata and its
                        membranes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-09">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-17">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-01">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc1.0059">

            <p><name type="person" key="1139"><hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>——, <hi rend="initialcap">J</hi>AMES</name>, Private, <name type="organization" key="109">27th Company, 2d Battalion, Veteran Reserve Corps</name>, aged 22
                years, a patient at <name type="hospital" key="178">Ricord Hospital</name>,
                Washington, in an altercation with one of the hospital guards, on the <date type="injury" when="1865-01-25">25th of January, 1865</date>, received a sabre
                wound, two and a half inches in length, on the left side of the forehead, a little
                within the left frontal protuberance. A cleft, an inch long, was made in the outer
                table of the bone. The patient was conveyed into the hospital, and the wound was
                closed by silver sutures, and simple dressings were applied, and he was restricted
                to low diet. On the 25th, the man was feverish, and his bowels were constipated. He
                had a dose of salts, which was repeated on the 27th. On the 28th, he complained of
                headache, and was ordered a mixture with bromide of potassium, lupulin, and
                hyoscyamus, and was allowed full diet. On the 31st, the report says that his
                appetite was good, but he was ordered a drachm of tincture of gentian thrice daily.
                On February 2d, he was reported as having passed a restless night, and was ordered
                eight grains of Dover's powder at bedtime. On February 6th, he was very comfortable,
                and walked about the ward. On the next day, his bowels being sluggish, he took three
                grains of blue pill and six of the compound extract of colocynth, and was placed on
                light diet. On the afternoon of the 8th, he complained of headache, which was
                aggravated at night. On the next morning he was partially insensible. He was roused
                with difficulty; he answered questions slowly, but rationally. The pupils responded
                to light; the tongue when protruded, after great effort, did not deviate laterally.
                He had a dose of salts, a blister, three by five, to the nucha, and, later in the
                day, a terebinthinate enema. He had several involuntary dejections, and his urine
                dribbled away. In the evening he seemed brighter, and the control of the sphincters
                was re-established. On February 10th, he was perfectly rational. The urine and
                fæces were discharged voluntarily; the tongue when protruded deviated slightly
                to the right; the pulse was weak at 70; slight cephalalgia. February 11th, he had
                passed a bad night, and he had but little appetite. From the 12th to the 15th,
                anorexia, weak pulse, regular bowels, no aggravation of the head symptoms. On the
                16th, the patient complained of severe headache at 4 A. M., and soon after began to
                breathe stertorously. At 7 o'clock he was perfectly unconscious; the pupils were
                slightly but equally contracted, and did not respond to light; there was stertor,
                with foam about the lips. Coma became more and more profound, and at half past
                twelve on the following day, <date type="death" when="1865-02-17">February 17th,
                    1865</date>, the patient expired. At the autopsy, an incised fracture, an inch
                long, involving the outer table only, was found near the left frontal protuberance.
                The condition of the diploe beneath it is not mentioned. The left side of the os
                frontis was sent to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>.
                It is numbered Specimen 3684 of the Surgical Section, and is figured by a wood-cut
                on page 34 of the Catalogue.⃰ Two discolored spots on the specimen are stains
                from iron rust, accidentally made during the preparation of the specimen. An abscess
                was found in the left anterior lobe of the cerebrum, measuring two and one-half
                inches antero-posteriorly, and one and one-half inch laterally, the anterior and
                superior portions extending on the left nearly to the surface of the cerebral
                substance, and within six lines of the median line of the cerebrum. It contained two
                ounces of pus. Pus had also found its way through all the ventricles, largely
                distending the left lateral, and, from the fourth ventricle, had passed between the
                substance of the medulla oblongata and its membranes as low as the origin of the
                twelfth nerve. The boundaries of the upper and posterior portions of the abscess are
                indicated in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 6. Specimen 3571 of the Surgical
                Section of the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> shows the
                remaining portion of the abscess.</p>

            <p>⃰ <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Surgical Section of the United States Army
                    Medical Museum</hi>, Washington, 1866, p. 34.</p>

            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001356.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 6.—Cavity of an abscess in the cerebrum,
                resulting from a sabre wound.—<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3685, Surg. Sect.,
                    A. M. M.</head></figure>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
