<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18885">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">R&#8212;&#8212;, Joseph</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e18885</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861&#8211;65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope
            type="page">444</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the spine</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds of the spine</term>
          <term>gunshot injuries of the lumbar vertebrae</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the apophyses of the lumbar spine</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the second lumbar vertebra</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>ball impacted in spinal canal between spinous processes of first and second lumbar
            vertebrae</term>
          <term>ball buried in vertebral canal</term>
          <term>fracture of spinous process of second lumbar vertebra</term>
          <term>tetanic spasms</term>
          <term>autopsy performed</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2014-07-03">corrected typo in figure head</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-20">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.&#8212;<name type="person">Private Joseph
          R&#8212;&#8212;</name>, <name type="organization">Co. I, 86th New York Volunteers</name>,
        stout, muscular, and aged 19 years, was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory
          Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1862-08-25">August 25th,
        1862</date>, for a gunshot wound of the back, received on the night of <date type="injury"
          when="1862-08-22">the 22d</date>. Notwithstanding great pain and restlessness, he gave an
        interesting account of the manner in which he was wounded, even laughing and jesting at
        times. He stated that, not thinking himself hurt, at the time of receiving the wound, he
        walked some distance to a tree where he sat and watched the enemy until near morning, when
        he walked into camp, and, on examination, "found a hole in his blouse and then a hole in his
        back." Being night when he was admitted, an anodyne was prescribed, and cold applications
        were applied to the wound. <date type="operation" when="1862-08-26">August 26th</date>:
        passed a restless night, and morning found him wearied and anxious, very restless, with an
        occasional tetanic spasm, though not severe. He was now chloroformed, the wound was
        enlarged, and an unsuccessful search was made for the ball. The patient being removed to
        more comfortable quarters, an assistant and a nurse were left with him with directions to
        keep him partially etherized until more experienced surgical assistance could be secured.
        The services of <name type="person">Surgeon R. H. Coolidge</name> were shortly obtained,
        and, after a trial of more than one hour, he succeeded in removing the ball, which was found
        firmly impacted in the canal and between the spinous processes of the first and second
        lumbar vertebr&#230;. After carefully removing all spicul&#230; of bone, the wound was drawn
        together by adhesive straps, and cold-water dressings were applied. The administration of an
        enema of assaf&#339;tid&#230; and turpentine left the patient in a profound sleep, disturbed
        occasionally, however, by slight spasms of short duration. <date type="death"
          when="1862-08-27">August 27th</date>: bowels acted twice at night; micturition free and no
        symptoms of paralysis. There was marked increase in the severity of the tetanic symptoms.
        The enema was repeated, but had little or no effect in quieting the nervous symptoms.
        Chloroform was now brought to his relief and its use continued until ten o'clock A. M., when
        he died. At the autopsy, the ball was found to have destroyed entirely the spinous process
        of the second lumbar vertebra, and to have buried itself, apex foremost, completely in the
        vertebral canal, bruising and pressing upon the cord. The case is one of interest from the
        fact that no symptoms of paralysis followed such an injury to the spinal cord as was here
        received, and the ball was not turned in its course by the sharp edge of the spinous
        process. The pathological specimen, figured in the adjoining wood-cut, was contributed to
        the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, with the above account, by
          <name type="person">Acting Assistant Surgeon S. R. Skillern</name>. </p>

      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001449.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 197.&#8212;First three lumbar vertebr&#230;, with a conoidal
          ball which penetrated the canal and became impacted between the arches of the first and
          second. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 611, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
