<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e19762">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Coder, J. N.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e19762</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">515</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
       <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term> 
       <term>intermediary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term> 
       <term>intermediary amputations in the upper third of the leg for shot injury</term> 
       <term>fatal intermediary amputations in the upper third of the leg</term>
       <term>ball passed through leg, fracturing tibia about its middle</term> 
       <term>limb amputated below knee joint</term> 
       <term>peroneal artery h&#230;morrhage</term>       
       <term>periostitis</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-08">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 760.&#8212;<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. N. Coder</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 46th Pennsylvania</name>, was wounded in the left leg, at <name type="battle" key="68">Cedar Mountain</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-09">August 9, 1862</date>.  He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="199">Wolfe Street Hospital</name>, <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>, <date type="admit" when="1862-08-14">five days afterwards</date>, where amputation was performed by <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon S. E. Fuller</name>, who reported the following history: &#34;A rifle ball passed through the leg, fracturing the tibia
    about its middle. The limb was amputated three inches below the knee joint by the circular method, by order of <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. E.
     Summers</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of the hospital, on <date type="operation" when="1862-08-27">August 27th</date>. Three days after the operation the stump had become much
    swollen, with red streaks extending up the limb; no suppuration. Quinine and brandy were ordered internally and warm-water
    dressings were applied to the stump.  August 31st, patient much the same; treatment continued, and limb painted with
    muriated tincture of iron as far as the redness extended.  September 1st, swelling great and no suppuration; sutures removed
    and some thick dark-colored fetid matter washed out of the stump.  September 4th, redness disappeared; swelling less; no
    suppuration; treatment continued.  On September 7th some sloughing of the stump appeared, when lint wet with solution of
    chloride of soda was applied, and the parts were occasionally touched with nitric acid.  On September 14th about two inches
    of the soft parts came entirely away, leaving a granulating surface, and the patient appeared better and had good appetite.  On
    September 16th, I called at 2 A. M., found the peroneal artery bleeding freely, and applied a tourniquet to the femoral, giving
    brandy and opium internally. There was no return of the h&#230;morrhage, but the patient gradually sunk, and died <date type="death" when="1862-09-19">September 19,
    1862</date>.&#34;  The amputated tibia, showing periostitis to have covered the shaft with a delicate coating of callus, was contributed by
    <name type="person" key="xxx">the operator</name>, and is specimen 321 of the Surgical Section A. M. M.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
