<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7685">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Forman, James M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2011</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e7685</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName></note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1888">1888</date>
     <biblScope type="page">354</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>post-mortem records of the continued fevers</term>
     <term>continued fevers</term>
     <term>typhoid fever</term>
     <term>entered as typhoid, but the clinical histories suggestive of malarial complications</term>
     <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>
     <term>ileum inflamed, solitary and agminated glands ulcerated</term>
     <term>small perforation of ulcerated patch</term>
     <term>peritoneum inflamed</term>
     <term>parotid gland in state of suppuration, gangrene in front of ear</term>
     <term>deafness</term>
     <term>erysipelas  of face</term>
     <term>large intestine from valve to rectum ulcerated</term>
     <term>mesenteric glands enlarged</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
   <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00103">
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 103.&#8212;<name type="person" key="550">Private James M.
     Forman</name>, <name type="organization" key="636">Co. H, 33d Pa.</name>; age 21; was admitted
     <date type="admit" when="1861-10-02">Oct. 2, 1861</date>, having been sick for <date
     type=" injury" when="1861-09-23">nine days</date> with pain in the head, back and bones,
    chills, loss of appetite and strength, diarrh&#339;a, epistaxis, pain in the stomach, nausea and
    vomiting. A bath was ordered for him with Dover's powder at night. Next morning his face was
    flushed, eyes injected, pulse 98, full, skin hot, dry and rough, tongue heavily coated, the
    centre brownish, the tip and edges red; he had anorexia, great thirst, irritability of stomach,
    diarrh&#339;a, the bowels having been moved four times, tenderness in the right iliac region and four
    or five characteristic rose-colored spots.  The case continued for ten days without much change
    under treatment by astringents, opiates and whiskey punch. The nausea and vomiting gradually
    ceased; some degree of deafness was developed; there was occasional tympanites, and blood
    appeared in the stools for several days and on the 8th in large quantity. But on the 12th the
    diarrh&#339;a ceased, the abdominal tenderness was lessened, the tongue became moist and there were
    indications of returning appetite. About the same time, however, the right parotid gland became
    inflamed and the face much swollen. There was slight delirium on the 14th, and next day the
    swelling, which had become erysipelatous, extended over the face, nearly closing both eyes and
    presenting a small gangrenous spot on the ear and another on the cheek. The patient walked about
    the ward in high delirium, but towards evening became more quiet. At 10 P. M. he sprang up
    suddenly, knocked the pitcher containing his punch from the attendant's hand and endeavored to
    get down stairs. He was got back to bed with some difficulty and immediately thereafter began to
    fail. At midnight his pulse was rapid and almost imperceptible, his extremities cold, eyes fixed
    and jaws locked; he took no notice when called or shaken and died at 1 A. M. of <date
     type="death" when="1861-10-16">the 16th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination:
    Parotid gland in a state of suppuration; side of face dark-colored and with small patches of
    gangrene in front of the ear. The mucous membrane of the stomach was congested and softened. The
    liver and gall-bladder were large but healthy; the spleen congested, enlarged and soft. The
    ileum was inflamed; its solitary and agminated glands were ulcerated and there was a small
    perforation in one of the ulcerated patches. The large intestine, from the valve to the rectum,
    was very much ulcerated. The peritoneum was inflamed; the mesenteric glands enlarged; the
    kidneys and bladder healthy.&#8212;<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary Hospital</name>, Georgetown, D. C.</hi></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
