<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00296">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of James C. Pickett, 13 June 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
            <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00296</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of James C. Pickett, 13 June 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-06-13">June 13, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of James C. Pickett, 13 June 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-06-13">June 13, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values @ facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2013-01-14" who="#kk">checked</change>
         <change when="2013-01-08" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00296.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">now at the City</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <placeName>Washington D. C.</placeName>
              </seg> by this
                        <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and
                    states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">four</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of
                    African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Fanny</persName>, <persName>Hannah</persName>,
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName> and <persName>George</persName>
              </seg> for
                    and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Fanny</persName>,
                            <persName>Hannah</persName>, <persName>Lewellyn</persName> and
                            <persName>George</persName>,</seg> and that by said act of Congress said
                        <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                  <persName>Fanny</persName> was</seg> of
                    the age of <seg type="handwritten">thirty four years</seg> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">dark, but not very dark. <persName>Hannah</persName>, of
                        the age of fourteen years, female and good looking, mulatto.
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName>, male, dark, 11 years old.
                            <persName>George</persName>, male, mulatto—9 years old.</seg>
            </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00296.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">The mother of <persName>Fanny</persName> and grandmother
                        of her children was given to him by his father-in-law forty years ago in the
                            <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>. Your petitioner paid no price
                        or consideration for her; there was no written evidence of title nor was
                        there any record of the gift. Since the year <date when="1829">1829</date>,
                        your petitioner has resided more than 27 years out of
                            <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>, of which he was a citizen. His father
                        in law has been dead more than 20 years, and he does not believe that he can
                        produce any proof of ownership of said four persons other than long and
                        undisturbed possession of them which he has proved.</seg>
            </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">four persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">2,500</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
               <seg type="handwritten">—in the
                        aggregate—separately, the value of <persName>Fanny</persName> was
                        eight hundred dollars, of <persName>Hannah</persName>, nine hundred, of
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName> and <persName>George</persName>, four
                        hundred each.—This is his opinion.—<persName>Fanny</persName> is
                        a good cook and house servant and good looking. Such girls as
                            <persName>Hannah</persName> when two or three years older have been sold
                        in <placeName>Virginia</placeName> in high times for 1,500 dollars, though
                        she would not have been for sale. As far as your petitioner knows and
                        believes, said persons are free from any moral, mental, and bodily
                        infirmities and defects which impair the value of your petitioner's claim to
                        their service and labor and that he believes none to exist.</seg>
            </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was held to service or labor therein under
                    and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                  <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>J. C.
                                Pickett</persName>
                 </seg>
               </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00296.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>296</ab>
                    <ab>
                  <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>
               </ab>
                    <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date>
               </ab>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00296.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>, now at <placeName>Washington
                            City</placeName> claiming the value of certain persons of African
                        descent released from involuntary servitude by an act of Congress "for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>, do hereby certify that the
                        persons residents of <placeName>Maysville, Kentucky</placeName>, who have
                        given affidavits respecting the question of my loyalty to the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName>, are all gentlemen of the highest
                        respectability: <list type="handwritten">
                            <item>No 1. <persName>A. M. January</persName> is President of the
                                Branch of the Bank of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName> at
                                    <placeName>Maysville</placeName>.</item>
                            <item>2. <persName>Th. J. Pickett</persName> is a highly respected
                                citizen.</item>
                            <item>3. <persName>James Barbour</persName> is Cashier of the Bank of
                                which Mr. <persName>January</persName> is president.</item>
                            <item>4. <persName>John Shackleford</persName> is a skillful physician
                                and a man of the highest standing.</item>
                            <item>
                        <persName>Richard C. Ricketts</persName> (separate
                                affidavit)—residence, <placeName>Midway, Kentucky</placeName>,
                                is an able and respectable, Minister of the Gospel.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                     <persName>J. C. Pickett</persName>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-14">14th day of July
                            AD 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                     <persName>N. Callan</persName>
                     <lb/> a Justice of the Peace for the
                                <placeName>County of Washington DC</placeName>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00296.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="mixed">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline>
                  <placeName>Midway, Kentucky</placeName>
                  <lb/>
                        <date when="1861-02-05">Feb. 5, 1861</date>.</dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Miss <persName>Margaret</persName>:</salute>
                    <fw>A.</fw>
                    <p>I should have replied to your last letter sometime ago if I had had any thing
                        to communicate that could have been of any interest to. But I have not had
                        any thing—have nothing now. I might write about political matters and
                        prospects, but of this you hear enough every day I doubt not.
                            <placeName>Kentucky</placeName> is strong for the Union and in favor of
                        any kind of fair and equitable compromise. And if the Old Dominion is of the
                        same humor I do not think the Union is lost yet, though it will be a
                        difficult matter to get back into the federal fold, the States that have so
                        <choice><sic>precipatately</sic><corr>precipitately</corr></choice> and so unwisely left it, as I think. What are your opinions
                        and wishes? Are you for compromise or for disruption? For the first, I
                        suppose and hope.</p>
                    <p>Write to me soon. Give me some news and gossip. How is <persName>Mrs.
                            J.</persName> and the girls and the boys L &amp; M S L &amp; H. Give my
                        best regards to her and to them.</p>
                    <p>How are <persName>Fanny</persName> and her children getting on?</p>
                    <closer>Your old friend <signed>
                     <persName>J. C. Pickett</persName>
                  </signed>
                  <lb/>
                        Miss <persName>Margaret A. Washington</persName>
                        <dateline>
                     <placeName>Washington City</placeName>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00296.006.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                    <ab type="handwritten">B</ab>
                    <ab>
                  <placeName>Midway</placeName>
                  <lb/>
                        <date when="1861-02-06">Feb 06</date>
                  <lb/>
                        <placeName>KY</placeName>
               </ab>
                    <ab type="handwritten">Miss <persName>Margaret A. Washington<lb/>
                            <placeName>Washington City</placeName>
                 </persName>
               </ab>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00296.007.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>Margaret A. Washington</persName>, of <placeName>Washington
                            City</placeName>, in addition to the statement I made in the month of
                            <date when="1862-06">June last</date>, respecting the claim of
                            <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> for the value of four persons of
                        African descent, who have been released from involuntary servitude by an act
                        of Congress entitled, "An act for the release of certain persons held to
                        service or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,"
                        approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>, do now certify,
                        that after Secession had been inaugurated in the South, I received a letter
                        from said <persName>Pickett</persName>, dated <date when="1861-02-05">Feb.
                            5, 1861</date> and written by him, in which he distinctly avows Union
                        and loyal sentiments. The letter was dated at <placeName>Midway
                            Kentucky</placeName>, is hereunto annexed marked A; and also the
                        envelope marked B.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Margaret A Washington</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-14">14th day of July
                            AD 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>N Callan</persName> seal<lb/>
                      Justice of the Peace in and for the <placeName>County of
                                Washington DC</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00296.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I <persName>Andrew M. January</persName>, residing at <placeName>Maysville,
                            Mason County</placeName>, and <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>,
                        do certify that I am well acquainted with <persName>James C.
                            Pickett</persName> late of the <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>,
                        and now at <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, prosecuting, as I have
                        heard, claims for the value of certain persons of African descent, released
                        from involuntary servitude by an act of Congress entitled, "An act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>; And I further certify and have
                        no doubt that the said <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> is a person
                        loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has borne
                        true allegiance to the same, in the sense in which this term is used in the
                        second section of the said act of Congress for the release of certain
                        persons from service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16
                            1862</date>—and of all the sections in it. This opinion is founded
                        upon personal intercourse I have had with said <persName>Pickett</persName>,
                        upon general reputation and from having heard him express his disapprobation
                        of the measure of Secession adopted by the Southern States—never
                        violently, but always decidedly.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>A. M. January</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Subscribed and sworn to before me—a Justice of the Peace for
                            <placeName>Mason County, Kentucky</placeName>—this <date when="1862-07-07">4th day of July 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>L. B. Nicholson</persName>
                     <lb/> Justice of the Peace
                            for <placeName>Mason County KY</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00296.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>Thomas J. Pickett</persName>, residing at <placeName>Maysville,
                            Mason County</placeName>, and <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>,
                        do certify that I am well acquainted with <persName>James C.
                            Pickett</persName>, late of the <placeName>State of
                        Kentucky</placeName>, and now at <placeName>Washington City</placeName>,
                        prosecuting as I have heard, claims for the value of certain persons of
                        African descent, released from involuntary servitude by an act of Congress
                        entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service or labor
                        in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>; And I further certify and have
                        no doubt that the said <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>, is a person
                        loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has borne
                        true allegiance to the same, in the sense in which this term is used in the
                        second section of the said act of Congress for the release of certain
                        persons from service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16
                            1862</date>,—and of all the sections in it. This opinion is
                        founded upon personal intercourse I have had with said
                            <persName>Pickett</persName>, upon general reputation, and from having
                        heard him express his disapprobation of the measure of Secession adopted by
                        the Southern States—never violently, but always decidedly.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>T. J. Pickett</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-07">4th day of
                            July A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>L. B. Nicholson</persName>
                     <lb/> Justice of the Peace
                            for <placeName>Mason County KY</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="cww.00296.010.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I <persName>James Barbour</persName>, residing at <placeName>Maysville, Mason
                            County</placeName>, and <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>, do
                        certify that I am well acquainted with <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>
                        late of the <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName> and now at
                            <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, prosecuting, as I have heard,
                        claims for the value of certain persons of African descent, released from
                        involuntary servitude by an act of Congress entitled, "An act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>; And I further certify and have
                        no doubt that the said <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> is a person
                        loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has borne
                        true allegiance to the same in the sense in which this term is used in the
                        second section of the said act of Congress for the release of certain
                        persons from service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16
                            1862</date>,—and of all the sections in it. This opinion is
                        founded upon personal intercourse I have had with said
                            <persName>Pickett</persName>, upon general reputation and from having
                        heard him express his disapprobation of the measure of Secession adopted by
                        the Southern States—never violently but always decidedly.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>James Barbour</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Subscribed and sworn to before me a Justice of the Peace for <placeName>Mason
                            County, Kentucky</placeName>, this <date when="1862-07-07">4th day of
                            July 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>L. B. Nicholson</persName>
                     <lb/> Justice of the Peace
                            for <placeName>Mason County KY</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="cww.00296.011.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I <persName>Geo. W. Coons</persName>, residing at <placeName>Maysville, Mason
                            County</placeName>, and <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>, do
                        certify that I am well acquainted with <persName>James C.
                        Pickett</persName>, late of the <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>,
                        and now at <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, prosecuting, as I have
                        heard, claims for the value of certain persons of African descent, released
                        from involuntary servitude by an act of Congress entitled; "An act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>; And I further certify and have
                        no doubt that the said <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> is a person
                        loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and has borne true
                        allegiance to the same, in the sense in which this term is used in the
                        second section of the said act of Congress for the release of certain
                        persons from service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16
                            1862</date>—and of all the sections in it. This opinion is founded
                        upon personal intercourse I have had with said <persName>Pickett</persName>,
                        upon general reputation, and from having heard him express his
                        disapprobation of the measure of Secession adopted by the Southern
                        States—never violently, but always decidedly.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Geo. W Coons</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Subscribed and sworn to before me—a Justice of the Peace for
                            <placeName>Mason Co, Kentucky</placeName>—this <date when="1862-07-07">4th day of July, A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>L. B. Nicholson</persName>
                     <lb/> Justice of the Peace
                            for <placeName>Mason County KY</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="cww.00296.012.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I <persName>Jno Shackleford</persName>, residing at <placeName>Maysville,
                            Mason County</placeName>, and <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>,
                        do certify that I am well acquainted with <persName>James C.
                            Pickett</persName> late of the <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>,
                        and now at <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, prosecuting—as I
                        have heard, claims for the value of certain persons of African descent,
                        released from involuntary servitude by an act of Congress entitled "An act
                        for the release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16" 1862</date>; And I further certify and have
                        no doubt that the said <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> is a person
                        loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has borne
                        true allegiance to the same, in the sense in which this term is used in the
                        second section of the said act of Congress for the release of certain
                        persons from service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16
                            1862</date>—and of all the sections in it.</p>
                    <p>This opinion is founded upon personal intercourse I have had with said
                            <persName>Pickett</persName>, upon general reputation, and from having
                        heard him express frequently his disapprobation of the measure of Secession
                        adopted by the Southern States—never violently, but always
                        decidedly.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Jno. Shackleford</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Subscribed and sworn to before me—a Justice of the Peace for
                            <placeName>Mason County, Kentucky</placeName>—this <date when="1862-07-07">4th day of July 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>L. B. Nicholson</persName>
                     <lb/> Justice of the Peace
                            for <placeName>Mason County KY</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="cww.00296.013.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline>
               <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>
               <lb/>
                    <placeName>Mason County</placeName> Sct:</dateline>
                <p>I <persName>Robert A. Cochraw</persName> Clerk of the County Court within and for
                    the County and State aforesaid, do hereby certify, that <persName>S. B.
                        Nicholson</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice> before whom the foregoing and annexed affidavits of <persName>A. M.
                        January</persName>, <persName>Thos J. Pickett</persName>, <persName>James
                        Barbour</persName>, <persName>George W. Coon</persName> and <persName>John
                        Shackleford</persName> have been sworn to and subscribed, is and was at the
                    time of doing said acts, or acts, an acting Justice of the Peace within and for
                    the County and State aforesaid, duly elected, Commissioned and sworn, that full
                    faith and credit are due to his official acts and that the signature purporting
                    to be his is genuine.</p>
                <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed the seal of said
                    Court. Done at my office in <placeName>Maysville</placeName> this <date when="1862-07-04">4th day of July A. D. 1862</date>
            </p>
                <closer>
               <signed>
                  <persName>Robt A Cochraw</persName> Clerk</signed>
            </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="cww.00296.014.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>Clerk's Seal inside</ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf012r" facs="cww.00296.015.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>Richard C. Ricketts</persName>, residing at <placeName>Midway,
                            County of Woodford</placeName>, and <placeName>State of
                            Kentucky</placeName>, do certify that I am well acquainted with
                            <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>, late of the <placeName>State of
                            Kentucky</placeName>, and now at <placeName>Washington City</placeName>,
                        prosecuting, as I have heard, claims for the value of certain persons of
                        African descent released from involuntary servitude, by an act of Congress,
                        entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service, or
                        labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>: And I further certify, and
                        have no doubt, that the said <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> is a
                        person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has
                        borne true allegiance to the same, in the sense in which this term is used,
                        in the second section of the said act of Congress, for the release of
                        certain persons from service, or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th
                            1862</date>, and of all the sections in it. This opinion is founded upon
                        the personal intercourse I have had with said <persName>Pickett</persName>
                        from general reputation, and from having heard him frequently express his
                        disapprobation of the measure of Secession adopted by the Southern States,
                        never violently, but always decidedly.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>R C Ricketts</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn to, and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-05">5th day of
                            July, A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                     <persName>A. J. Roberts</persName> J. P. <persName>
                        <hi rend="underline">W. C</hi>
                    </persName>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf012v" facs="cww.00296.016.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline>
               <placeName>State of Kentucky</placeName>
               <lb/>
                    <placeName>County of Woodford</placeName> Sct:</dateline>
                <p>I <persName>Herman Birman Jr</persName>. Clerk of the County Court for said
                    County, to certify that <persName>A. J. Roberts</persName>, whose genuine
                    signature appears to the within affidavit and before whom said affidavit was
                    made, is now and was at the time he signed the same a Justice of the Peace for
                    said County (residing in the <placeName>Town of Midway</placeName>) duly
                    Commissioned and qualified as such: and that to his offical acts full faith
                    &amp; credit are due.</p>
                <p>In Witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my official Seal, the
                        <date when="1862-07-05">5th day of July A. D. 1862</date>. And in the
                    Seventieth year of the Commonwealth.</p>
                <closer>
               <signed>
                  <persName>Herman Birman Jr.</persName>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="about one word" quantity="5" unit="chars"/>
                  <lb/> By <persName>Jos. M. Birman</persName>
                        <placeName>D. C.</placeName>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf013r" facs="cww.00296.017.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>Margaret A. Washington</persName>, of <placeName>Washington
                            City, D. C.</placeName> do hereby certify that it is within my personal
                        knowledge that <persName>Fanny</persName>, a woman of African descent for
                        whose value, and also the value of her three children <persName>James C.
                            Pickett</persName> has filed a petition with the Commissioners appointed
                        under the act of Congress entitled "an act for the release of certain
                        persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>," approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th
                            1862</date>, has lived with my sister Mrs. <persName>Mary W.
                            Johnson</persName> in the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> more
                        than twenty four years; and that <persName>Fanny</persName>'s three children
                        were all born in her house and have there lived.—In my judgment
                            <persName>Fanny</persName> and her children were of the value in money,
                        at the time of their discharge from service or labor, 2,500 dollars in the
                            aggregate—separately—<persName>Fanny</persName>, eight
                        hundred dollars, <persName>Hannah</persName> nine hundred dollars,
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName> and <persName>George</persName> four
                        hundred dollars each. This is my opinion.</p>
                    <p>I am well acquainted with said <persName>Pickett</persName> and believe him
                        to be without doubt, "loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>," in
                        the sense in which these words are used in said act of Congress, approved
                            <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>.</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand this <date when="1862-06-11">11th of June
                        1862</date>.—The name "<persName>James C. Pickett</persName>" inserted
                        between lines <hi rend="underline">three</hi> and <hi rend="underline">four</hi> from the top before signing.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Margaret A. Washington</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-12">twelfth day of
                            June AD 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>N Callan</persName> JP seal</signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf014r" facs="cww.00296.018.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>Mary W. Johnson</persName> of <placeName>Washington City, D.
                            C.</placeName> do hereby declare that, the woman
                            <persName>Fanny</persName> of African descent for whose value
                            <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> has filed his petition with the
                        Commissioners appointed under the act of Congress entitled "an act for the
                        release of certain persons held to service or labor in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>," approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April 1862</date>, has resided with me
                        continuously more than twenty four years, and that her three children whose
                        value the said <persName>Pickett</persName> also claims, were born in my
                        house where they have always lived. Said <persName>Pickett</persName>
                        exercised ownership over these four persons—appeared to be the owner
                        and sole owner of them, and was so considered to be; I never heard of an
                        adverse claim or claimant. In my judgment the value of
                            <persName>Fanny</persName> and her three children,
                            <persName>Hannah</persName>, <persName>Lewellyn</persName> and
                            <persName>George</persName>, in money, at the time of their discharge,
                        would be,—for <persName>Fanny</persName>, eight hundred dollars, for
                            <persName>Hannah</persName> nine hundred dollars, for
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName> four hundred dollars, for
                            <persName>George</persName>, four hundred dollars—in the
                        aggregate, twenty five hundred dollars. This is my opinion.</p>
                    <p>I am well acquainted with Said <persName>Pickett</persName> and believe him
                        to be without doubt, "loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>," in
                        the sense in which these words are used in said act of Congress, approved
                            <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>.—Witness my hand
                        this <date when="1862-06-10">10th day of June 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>M. W. Johnson</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-12">twelfth day of
                            June AD 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>N Callan</persName> JP seal</signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf015r" facs="cww.00296.019.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>I, <persName>Thomas E. Pickett</persName>, of
                            <placeName>Maysville</placeName>, <placeName>Mason County</placeName>,
                            <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>, do hereby certify that I am 21 years of
                        age, and that I am well acquainted with <persName>James C.
                            Pickett</persName> who is claiming before the Commissioners appointed
                        under the act of Congress entitled "an act for the release of certain
                        persons held to service or labor within <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>" approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th
                            1862</date>, compensation for the release of four persons of African
                        descent, which he states that he held in the <placeName>City of
                            Washington</placeName>, at the time said act was passed. I certify
                        further that from my personal knowledge of said
                        <persName>Pickett</persName>, I do not hesitate to delcare him to be "loyal
                        to the <placeName>United States</placeName>" in the sense in which these
                        words are employed in said Act of Congress, approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>,—Witness my hand this <date when="1862-06-10">10th day of June 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Thomas E. Pickett</persName>.</signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Subscribed and Sworn to Before me this <date when="1862-06-10">10th day of
                            June 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Thomas C. Donn</persName>
                     <lb/> Justice of the Peace
                            for <placeName>Washington County</placeName>
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf016r" facs="cww.00296.020.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>
               <persName>James C Pickett</persName>
            </ab>
                <ab>No 296</ab>
                <ab>Filed<lb/>
                    <date when="1862-06-28">June 28 1862</date>
            </ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf016v" facs="cww.00296.021.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main">Case No 296.</head>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwriten">
                    <p>To the Honorable Commissioners appointed by the President of the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName> to carry into effect the act of
                        Congress entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service
                        or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>" approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <p>Your petitioner <persName>James C. Pickett</persName> respectfully represents
                        that he has claimed pursuant to said act the value of four persons viz
                            <persName>Fanny</persName>, <persName>Hannah</persName>,
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName> and <persName>George</persName>;
                            <persName>Fanny</persName> being the mother of the other three; that
                        said <persName>Fanny</persName> upon her examination before your <choice>
                            <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                            <expan>Honorable</expan>
                        </choice> Board a week or two since, said that the said boy
                            <persName>Lewellyn</persName> was to a certain degree "unhealthy", and
                        said statement it may be conduced to the price to which said boys services
                        were appraised was no higher than that of the younger boy
                            <persName>George</persName>. Your petitioner stated in his original
                        petition herein that said persons were ordinarily healthy, or something to
                        that effect which he still believes to be true. Your petitioner had seen but
                        little of <persName>Lewellyn</persName> since his birth, and nothing of him
                        for the three years and about ten months ending on the <date when="1862-05-30">30th of May last</date>, and all that he has seen or
                        heard justified him he thought in making the statement respecting his
                            (<persName>Lewellyn</persName>s) health, to be found in his first
                        petition.</p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>J. C. Pickett</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-27">27th day of
                            June AD 1862</date>
               </p>
                    <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>N Callan</persName> JP seal
                  </signed>
               </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf017r" facs="cww.00296.022.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
               <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                  <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
            </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>
                 </seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>J. C.
                                    Pickett</persName>
                    </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-13">
                     <seg type="handwritten">13th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Thomas C.
                                    Donn</persName>
                        <lb/> Justice of the Peace for
                                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName>
                                <placeName>Dictrict of Columbia</placeName>
                    </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>296</ab>
                <ab>
               <persName>James C. Pickett</persName>
            </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-13">June 13, 1862</date>
            </ab>
                <ab>in lieu of and correcting petition of <date when="1862-05-29">May 19,
                    '62</date>
            </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
