<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00471">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Mary Ann Harvey, 27 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                    <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00471</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Mary Ann Harvey, 27 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-27">May 27, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Mary Ann Harvey, 27 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-27">May 27, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Mary Ann Harvey</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Nicholas Callan</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">removed unnecessary em dashes</change>
            <change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values @ facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2013-01-28" who="#kk">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-10-19" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00471.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>M. A. Harvey</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington City D.C.</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">the following</seg>
                        person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Julia Cole</persName>, <persName>Joseph Cole</persName>
                        <persName>Robert Cole</persName>
                        <persName>William Cole</persName> and <persName>Albert Cole</persName>
                    </seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons,</seg>
                    and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons,
                        were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to
                    such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Julia</persName> was of the age of forty years
                            <persName>Joseph</persName> was of the age of nineteen years.
                            <persName>Robert</persName> was sixteen. <persName>William</persName>
                        was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">thirteen years. and
                            <persName>Albert</persName> was of the age of eleven years.</seg> and of
                    the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item>
                            <persName>Julia</persName> was forty years old light color about five
                            feet high.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Joseph</persName> was nineteen years of age of a light
                            complexion about five feet high.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Robert</persName> was sixteen years of age of a dark
                            complexion about four feet nine inches high.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>William</persName> was thirteen years old has a light
                            complexion about four feet three and a half inches high.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Albert</persName> was about eleven years old, is of a light
                            complexion about four feet one and a half inches in height.</item>
                    </list>
                    <seg type="handwritten">None of the above named persons have any marks on their
                        persons except <persName>William</persName> who is marked on the left
                        hand.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00471.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">That is to say; She inherited them from her late father
                        the late <persName>Michael Sardo</persName> last of <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>.</seg>
                </p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The deed of gift from her father to your petitioner is
                    herewith annexed.</ab>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">3,800—</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">That is to say. <persName>Julia</persName> is valued at
                        $1000. <persName>Joseph</persName> is valued at $1000.
                            <persName>Robert</persName> is valued at $800.
                            <persName>William</persName> is valued at $600 and
                            <persName>Albert</persName> at $400.</seg>
                    <list type="handwritten">
                        <item>
                            <persName>Julia</persName> is a first rate house servant an excellent
                            cook, washer, and ironer and has lived in my family for the last 19
                            years, is strictly honest truthful &amp; industrious &amp; moral.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Joseph</persName> is a first rate house servant and has been
                            hired out for which I received $8 a month he is intelligent &amp;
                            respectful, moral &amp; honest.</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>Robert</persName> has been hiring out ever since he was seven
                            years of age</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName>William</persName> and <persName>Albert</persName> have also
                            been hired out all of whom are strictly moral, honest sober &amp;
                            trustworthy. I never having heard a complaint against the character of
                            either of them.</item>
                    </list>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Your petitioner further declares that she knows of no
                        moral mental or bodily defects in either of the above named persons.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg>
                    into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said
                    act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg> does not originate in or by virtue
                    of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or
                    sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg> herein above set forth; and
                    if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Mary Ann Harvey</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00471.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <ab>Paid</ab>
                    <ab>
                        <persName>Michl Sardo</persName>
                        <lb/> to<lb/>
                        <persName>Michl R. Coombs</persName>
                        <lb/> Bill of Sale in Trust</ab>
                    <p>Received <date when="1844-08-15">15th August 1844</date>. To be Recorded and
                        the same day was recorded in Liber W.B. No. 111. Folios 162 &amp; 163 One of
                        the Land Records for <placeName>Washington County</placeName> in the
                            <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> and examined by</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. Brent. <choice>
                                <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                                <expan>Clerk</expan>
                            </choice>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00471.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents, that I, <persName>Michael Sardo</persName> of
                        the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, for and in consideration of the love and affection
                        which I have and bear to my daughter <persName>Mary Ann Harvey</persName>,
                        wife of <persName>Henry Harvey</persName> of the said City, and of the sum
                        of One dollar to me in hand paid by <persName>Michael R. Coombs</persName>,
                        son of said <persName>Mary Ann Harvey</persName>, the receipt whereof I
                        hereby acknowledge, do grant, bargain and sell unto the said
                            <persName>Michael R. Coombs</persName>, his executors, administrators
                        and assigns, my negro slave named <persName>Juliet</persName>, otherwise
                        called <persName>Juliet Jefferson</persName>, before marriage but now
                            <persName>Juliet Cole</persName> purchased by me on the <date when="1834-05-26">26th day of May 1834</date> of <persName>John S.
                            McWilliams</persName> as by his Bill of Sale recorded in Liber W.B. No
                        50 folio 144 one of the Land records of <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> in said <placeName>District</placeName>, and her
                        infant child <persName>Joseph</persName> aged about fifteen months. To Have
                        and To Hold said slave <persName>Juliet</persName>, together with all her
                        future increase, and said child <persName>Joseph</persName>, unto the said
                            <persName>Michael R. Coombs</persName>, his executors, administrators
                        and assigns forever; In trust nevertheless and to and for the following uses
                        and purposes and none other whatsoever, that is to say: the said Trustees,
                        his executors or administrators shall hold the said slave
                            <persName>Juliet</persName> and her increase, and the said child, for
                        the sole use and benefit of the said <persName>Mary Ann Harvey</persName>,
                        and shall suffer the said <persName>Mary Ann</persName> to keep possession
                        of said slaves and take to her own <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00471.005.jpg"/> use, as a feme sole and not as a feme covert,
                        all the earnings and profits of said slaves, and he shall and may at any
                        time with the written consent of said <persName>Mary Ann</persName> sell and
                        dispose of said slaves or either of them, upon the terms and conditions in
                        such written consent mentioned. And in case of the death of said
                            <persName>Mary Ann</persName>, during her coverture, shall convey said
                        slaves to the heirs at law of said <persName>Mary Ann</persName>, or to such
                        person or persons as the said <persName>Mary Ann</persName> shall by last
                        Will &amp; Testament or otherwise in writing shall direct. And in case of
                        the death of said <persName>Mary Ann</persName>'s husband during the
                        lifetime of said <persName>Mary Ann</persName>, the said Trustee shall, at
                        the request of said <persName>Mary Ann</persName>, convey to her the said
                        slaves in full legal right and property—</p>
                    <p>In Testimony whereof I have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed my seal
                        this <date when="1844-08-15">Fifteenth day of August A.D. 1844</date>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>his X mark <persName>Michael Sardo</persName> seal </signed>
                        <lb/> Signed, Sealed &amp; Delivered in presence of (the word "<hi rend="underline">
                            <persName>Juliet</persName>
                        </hi>" first interlined in the 4th line from bottom 1st page) the words
                        "before marriage but now <persName>Juliet Cole</persName>" in the 12 line
                        1st page being also first interlined— <signed>
                            <persName>B. K. Morsell</persName>
                        </signed>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>R. R. Barr</persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        <lb/>
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName> Sct:</dateline>
                    <p>Be it remembered that on this <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00471.006.jpg"/>
                        <date when="1844-08-15">fifteenth day of August A.D.
                        1844</date>—Personally appears <persName>Michael Sardo</persName>, the
                        party grantor within named, and acknowledges the within deed or instrument
                        of writing to be his act and deed according to the purport, true intent and
                        meaning thereof—</p>
                    <closer>Acknowledged before me, <signed>
                            <persName>B. K. Morsell</persName>
                        </signed> J.P.</closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00471.007.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>M. A. Harvey</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do
                        depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in
                        substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters and things
                        therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I believe
                        to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Mary Ann Harvey</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-26">
                            <seg type="handwritten">26th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>N. Callan</persName> JP seal </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>471</ab>
                <ab>The Petition of<lb/> Mrs. <persName>M. A. Harvey</persName>.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-27">May 27, 1862</date>
                </ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>Michael R. Coombs</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>Lewis Clephane</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <lb/>
                    <persName>Daniel McFarlan</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice>
                </ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
