<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00289">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Robert W. Smoot, 18 July 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00289</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Robert W. Smoot, 18 July 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-07-18">July 18, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Robert W. Smoot, 18 July 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-07-18">July 18, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Robert W. Smoot</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-12" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-11" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-29" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values @ facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2013-01-14" who="#kk">checked</change>
         <change when="2013-01-02" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="petition">
        <body>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00289.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the Honorable the Commissioners under the act entitled An Act for the release
                    of certain persons, held to service or labor in the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>
            </p>

                <p>The petition of <persName>Margaret A. Smoot</persName>, by <persName>Robert W.
                        Smoot</persName> her husband and best friend both of <placeName>Montgomery
                        County</placeName> and <placeName>State of Maryland</placeName>
                    <choice>
                        <sic>shews</sic>
                        <corr>shows</corr>
                    </choice>:</p>
                <p>That your petitioner and her said husband are loyal citizens of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>: and at the time of the passage of said
                    act to wit, the <date when="1862-04-16">16th day of April 1862</date>, the said
                        <persName>Margaret A.</persName> in her own right, had in the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, residing there and for a number
                    of years hired there a negro man slave named <persName>Frank Herbert</persName>,
                    about forty five years of age, who by reason of his African descent and acquired
                    title was a slave for life to the said <persName>Margaret A.</persName>; and by
                    the operation of the said Act of Congress hath been liberated from slavery, He
                    is about five feet ten or eleven inches high well made very <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">erect</unclear>, black, active,
                    perfectly healthy, in the prime and vigor of life, honest, industrious capable
                    and faithful. He was <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">bred</unclear> a farm hand and was a very efficient hand: his wife living
                    in this <placeName>District</placeName> the said <persName>Margaret
                        A.</persName> permitted the said <persName>Frank</persName> to come to the
                        <placeName>District</placeName> to live there for a number of years last
                    past she has hired him out as her slave and received his wages</p>

                <p>The said <persName>Margaret A</persName> acquired her title to <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00289.002.jpg"/> the said servant in the
                    distribution of the personal estate of Dr. <persName>Stephen N. C.
                        White</persName> late of <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> deceased,
                    and by the laws of <placeName>Maryland</placeName> she is advised, she is
                    entitled to the property of the said slave in her own right; and as of course to
                    the proceeds of his sale, or compensation for his liberation. The value of the
                    said slave in money, it would be difficult to fix, but your petitioner is advised he is
                    not less than fifteen hundred dollars, as neither she nor her said husband is
                    aware of any fact tending to diminish it below the highest market for a first
                    quality hand of his description</p>
                <p>Neither she nor her said husband have at any time borne arms against the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, nor in any way directly or indirectly
                    given aid or comfort to the present rebellion. The fact has been stated that the
                    said slave was residing in this <placeName>District</placeName> with the
                    permission of his owner at the time of the passage of the said act under and by
                    virtue of the claim hereinbefore stated; which claim does not originate in or by
                    virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any wise aided
                    or sustained the present rebellion against the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>
            </p>

                <p>She further states that her petition in this case was heretofore filed on or
                    about the day of <space atLeast="1"/> last past by her brother as her <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#kk">next
                    friend but</unclear> the same has been in some way mislaid and therefore she prays leave
                    to file this her additional <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00289.003.jpg"/>
                    petition in lieu and by way of supplying the said mislaid paper, and that she
                    may be allowed compensation for the said servant according to law.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                  <persName>Rob. W. Smoot</persName>
                  <lb/> for<lb/>
                        <persName>Margaret A. Smoot</persName>
               </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>I <persName>Joseph H. Bradley</persName> of the <placeName>City of
                        Washington</placeName> do on my oath say that, according to the best of my
                    knowledge and belief. I did on or about the <date when="1862-05-15">15 day of
                        May</date> last prepare for Mrs. <persName>Margaret A. Smoot</persName>
                    her brother either <persName>Daniel</persName> or <persName>Benjamin
                        White</persName> (I am not sure which) acting as her next friend, her
                    petition to the Commissioners named in the foregoing petition for compensation
                    for her negro man slave <persName>Frank Herbert</persName> named therein, and
                    that it was sworn to by her in my office before a Justice of the Peace, and
                    signed by her and her brother, and carried by myself, &amp; filed or deposited
                    by me with Mr <persName>Woodward</persName> the clerk of said Commission on the
                    same day</p>
                <p>Sworn to and subscribed by</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                  <hi rend="underline">
                     <persName>Jos. H. Bradley</persName>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
                    <dateline>
                  <date when="1862-07-18">18 July 1862</date>
               </dateline>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00289.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
               <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
               <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                  <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
            </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>Robert W Smoot</persName>
                 </seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Rob. W.
                                    Smoot</persName> for<lb/>
                                <persName>Margaret A. Smoot</persName>
                    </seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-17">
                     <seg type="handwritten">17th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                     <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>F. I.
                                    Murphey</persName> J. P.</seg>
                  </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>


                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00289.005.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                    <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                        aforesaid service or labor of <seg type="handwritten">
                     <persName>William
                                Sprigg</persName>
                        </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2"><gap reason="torn away"/></note>
               </p>
                    <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <space atLeast="1"/> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value
                        of <space atLeast="1"/>
                        <unclear reason="torn away" cert="high" resp="#jc">dollars</unclear> in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3"><gap reason="torn away"/></note>
               </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00289.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>289</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-18">18 July 1862</date> and ordered by Commissioners
                    to be filed on of <date when="1862-05-19">19th May 1862</date> as if filed that
                    day</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
