<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00697">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Harriet R. Marshall, 17 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00697</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Harriet R. Marshall, 17 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-17">June 17, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Harriet R. Marshall, 17 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-17">June 17, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Harriet R. Marshall</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Francis I. Murphey</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-07-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-07-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-05-31" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-26" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00697.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioners, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Harriet R.
                            Marshall</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Prince
                            Georges County</placeName> in the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">two persons one male the other
                        a female</seg>
                    <del>person</del> of African descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    <del>of</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">respectively of <persName>Rezin Gantt</persName> and
                            <persName>Nancy Gantt</persName>, his wife</seg> for and during the life
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rezin</persName> &amp;
                            <persName>Nancy</persName> respectively</seg> and that by said act of
                    Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons respectively were</seg> discharged
                    and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor;
                    that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Rezin</persName> was about 52 years old and said
                            <persName>Nancy</persName> about</seg>
                    <del>of</del> the age of <seg type="handwritten">fifty years as nearly as your
                        petitioner ascertains</seg> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as
                        to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each
                        one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">Said <persName>Rezin</persName> is about 5 feet 9 inches
                        high, very black, rather pleasant face, &amp; slow of speech Said
                            <persName>Nancy</persName> is copper <choice>
                            <orig>coloured</orig>
                            <reg>colored</reg>
                        </choice>, very thin face, long &amp; rather straight hair for her
                        race</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00697.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants
                        respectively</seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for
                        what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of
                        title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same
                        may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">from her mother <persName>Ellena A. H.
                            Marshall</persName> late of the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName> deceased in consideration of natural love and
                        affection, by her last will &amp; testament a true copy of which is herewith
                        filed</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servants</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Five Hundred &amp;
                        fifty</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">Said <persName>Rezin</persName> is a good farm hand and capable &amp;
                        trusty—and free from moral mental or bodily infirmities or defects
                        impairing your petitioners claim to his Services. Your Petitioner avers she
                        knows of no such infirmities or defects. Said <persName>Nancy</persName> was
                        formerly a fruitful, worthy and excellent nurse, but in the month of <date when="1861-07">July last</date> sickened, and was struck with paralysis
                        by which her value is greatly diminished. Your Petitioner knows of no other
                        infirmity or defect mental, moral or physical impairing the value of her
                        Services to your Petitioner</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons or either of
                        them</seg> into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the
                    passage of said act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof,
                    said <seg type="handwritten">Servants respectively</seg> was held to service or
                    labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or
                    labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons respectively</seg> does not originate in or by
                    virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided
                    or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">Servants respectively</seg> herein above set
                    forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion
                    the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the
                    Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Harriet R.
                                Marshall</persName></seg></signed></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00697.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>In the name of God, Amen, I <persName>Eleanor A. H. Marshall</persName> of
                        the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> being sick and weak of body
                        but of sound and disposing mind memory and understanding considering the
                        certainty of death and the uncertainty of the time thereof and being anxious
                        to settle my worldly affairs and be thereby the better prepared to leave this
                        world when it shall please God to call me hence do make and publish this my
                        last will and testament in form following that is to say.</p>

                    <p>First and principally I commit my soul into the hands of Almighty God and my
                        body to the earth to be <choice>
                            <sic>deacently</sic>
                            <corr>decently</corr>
                        </choice> buried at the discretion of my executor hereinafter named and
                        after my debts and funeral charges are paid I leave and bequeath as
                        follows,</p>
                    <p>Item, I give unto my Daughter <persName>H. R. Marshall</persName> the
                        following servants <persName>Rezin</persName>, <persName>Nancy</persName>,
                            <persName>Hannah</persName>, <persName>Isreal</persName>,
                            <persName>Frank</persName>, <persName>Mariah</persName>, &amp;
                            <persName>Easter</persName> one red chair provided she relinquishes a
                        note held by her guardian against me for $225, this property to be paid to
                        her when she arrives at the age of eighteen years.—</p>
                    <p>Item, I give to my son <persName>Geo R. H. Marshall</persName> the following
                        servants <persName>Jim</persName>, <persName>Daniel</persName>,
                            <persName>Martha</persName>, <persName>Nelly</persName>,
                            <persName>Becky</persName>, <persName>Lucy</persName> &amp;
                            <persName>Minty King</persName>, Silver can gold watch beds furniture
                        &amp; china. This property to be paid over by my Executor on the <date when="1854-01-01">first day of January 1854</date> but to be held and
                        used by my Executor as well as the property named in first Item until the
                        days therein named for payment to raise the sums necessary to pay my debts
                        funeral charges small legacies &amp;c</p>
                    <p>Item, I give and bequeath unto my <choice>
                            <sic>neice</sic>
                            <corr>niece</corr>
                        </choice>
                        <persName>Elizabeth H Clagett</persName>, the sum of one hundred dollars
                        &amp; one carpet.</p>
                    <p>Item I give to my Grandson <persName>Thomas H. Marshall</persName>, Negro boy
                            <persName>Dora</persName> &amp; one dozen tea spoons.</p>
                    <p>Item I give one hundred dollars to Ackkuck church for the purpose of erecting
                        a pulpit therein to be paid over by my Executor whenever he may find it
                        convenient within two years from my death</p>
                    <p>None of my servants named in the will are to be sold out of the <placeName>D.
                            C.</placeName></p>

                    <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00697.004.jpg"/>
                    <p>Item, All the rest and residue of my property of every description I give to
                        my son <persName>Thomas Marshall</persName> &amp; lastly I hereby constitute
                        &amp; appoint my son <persName>Thomas Marshall</persName> Executor of this
                        my last will &amp; testament.</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my seal this
                            <date when="1852-10-15">15th day of October 1852</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Eleanor A. H. Marshall</persName>
                        seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Signed sealed published and declared by <persName>Eleanor A. H.
                            Marshall</persName> the above named testatrix as and for her last will
                        &amp; testament in the presence of us who at her request and in her presence
                        and in the presence of each other have subscribed our names as witnesses
                        thereto</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>John H. Hardesty</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>Ann C. Hardesty</persName></signed>.</closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit<lb/> Orphan's Court <date when="1852-11-20">November 20, 1852</date></dateline>
                    <p>This day appeared <persName>John H. Hardesty</persName> one of the
                        subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing last will and testament of
                            <persName>Eleanor A. H. Marshall</persName> late of
                            <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid deceased, and made
                        oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God that he did see the testatrix
                        therein named sign and seal this will that she published pronounced and
                        declared the same to be her last will and testament that at the time of so
                        doing she was to the best of his apprehension of sound and disposing mind,
                        memory &amp; understanding and that he together with <persName>Ann C.
                            Hardesty</persName> the other subscribing witness respectively
                        subscribed their names as witnesses to this will in the presence &amp; at
                        the request of the testatrix &amp; in the presence of each other</p>
                    <p>And at the same time appeared <persName>Thomas Marshall</persName> the
                        Executor named and made oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that the
                        aforegoing instrument of writing is the true whole &amp; last will &amp;
                        testament of <persName>Eleanor A. H. Marshall</persName> deceased that hath
                        come to his hands or knowledge &amp; that he doth not know of any other</p>
                    <closer><signed>Test. <persName>Ed. N. Roach</persName>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Regr</abbr>
                                <expan>Register</expan>
                            </choice> Wills.</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00697.005.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit,</dateline>
                    <p>I certify that the foregoing is a true copy from the Original filed and
                        recorded in the office of the Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> aforesaid</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of Office this <date when="1862-05-30">30th day of
                            May in the year 1862</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>Moses Kelly</persName><lb/> Register of
                            Wills.</signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00697.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Harriet R. Marshall</persName></seg>
                        being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things
                        which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own
                        knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other
                        matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of
                        others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Harriet R
                                    Marshall</persName></seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-30"><seg type="handwritten">30th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>F. I.
                                    Murphey</persName> J. P.</seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab><persName>Marshall</persName> 1 Ex</ab>
                <ab>697</ab>
                <ab><persName>Harriet R. Marshall</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-17">June 17, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>B &amp; B</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
