<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00669">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Lucy B. Walker, 12 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00669</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Lucy B. Walker, 12 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-12">June 12, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Lucy B. Walker, 12 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-12">June 12, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Lucy B. Walker</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Henry Naylor</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-10" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-05-03" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00669.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy B. Walker</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten">the <placeName>County of
                            Washington</placeName>, <placeName>Dist. of Cola</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Sillah
                            West</persName>, <persName>Zilphia Hall</persName>, <persName>Thomas
                            Hall</persName>, <persName>John Hall</persName>, <persName>Hillary
                            Speaks</persName>, <persName>Sophia Ross</persName>, <persName>Philip
                            Brown</persName>, <persName>Anna Brown</persName>, <persName>Benjamin
                            Brown</persName>, <persName>Cassey Mullican</persName>, <persName>George
                            Ross</persName>, <persName>Hanibald Hall</persName> and <persName>Aisey
                            Brown</persName></seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African
                    descent of the name<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    <del>of</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten">aforesaid respectively</seg> for and during the
                        li<seg type="handwritten">ves</seg> of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons, respectively</seg> and that by said act of
                    Congress said <seg type="handwritten">Person—respectively were</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        Persons—respectively were</seg> of the age<seg type="handwritten">s</seg>
                    <del>of</del> and of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or
                        her; and if there be more than one slave, describe each one
                        separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Sillah West</persName>, about 56 years of age, Black, low in
                        Stature, about 5 feet 6 inches high, <persName>Zilphia Hall</persName>,
                        Mulatto, low in Stature, about 42 years of age, 5 feet 6 inches
                            high,—<persName>Thomas Hall</persName>, Black, about 37 years of
                        age, about 5 feet 10 inches high—<persName>John Hall</persName>, Black
                        about 33 years of age, about 5 feet 10 inches high,—<persName>Hillary
                            Speaks</persName>, Dark, about 29 years of age, about 5 feet 8 inches
                            high—<persName>Sophia Ross</persName>, Dark, about 29 years of
                        age, about 5 feet 6 inches high,—<persName>Philip Bruce</persName>,
                        Black about 22 years of age, about 5 feet 7 inches
                            high,—<persName>Anna Brown</persName>, Mulatto, about 21 years of
                        age, about 5 feet 6 inches high—<persName>Benjamin Brown</persName>,
                        Mulatto, about 18 years of age, about 5 feet 7 inches
                            high—<persName>Cassey Mullican</persName>, Copper Color, about 12
                        years of age, about 4 feet, 4 inches high—<persName>George
                            Ross</persName>, Mulatto about 10 years of age, about 4 feet
                            high,—<persName>Hanibald Hall</persName>, Copper Color, about 4
                        years of age, about 3 feet high,—<persName>Aisey Brown</persName>,
                        Mulatto, about 2 years of age, about 2 feet, 6 inches high,</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00669.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By the Will of her late Husband, <persName>Zachariah
                            Walker</persName>—Said Will having been duly provided and
                        recorded in the Register of Wills' office in the <placeName>District of
                            Columbia</placeName>, reference thereto had will fully show.—(Certified
                        Copy of said Will is hereto annexed.)</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons respectively</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">$10,900</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">To Wit:</seg> 
                            <list type="handwritten">
                            <item><persName>Sillah West</persName>, Good Farm hand, worth
                                $300.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Zilphia Hall</persName>, Good House Servant, washer,
                                Ironer , and first rate Cook, and Strictly Honest $1000.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Thomas Hall</persName>, Good Farm Hand, Carriage driver
                                House Servant and very trusty, &amp;c. &amp;c $1200.00</item>
                            <item><persName>John Hall</persName>, Good Farm Hand, Carriage Driver,
                                House Servant, very trusty &amp; polite &amp;c. $1200.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Hillary Speaks</persName>, <persName>Good Farm
                                    Hand</persName>, Carriage Driver, House Servant, polite, trustworthy, Honest and obliging $1200.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Sophia Ross</persName>, First Class House Servant
                                $1000.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Philip Bruce</persName>, Good Farm Hand, Carriage
                                driver, House Servant, trusty well behaved &amp; honest
                                $1200.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Anna Brown</persName>, Good House Servant, Washer Ironer
                                &amp;c. and well behaved $1000.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Benjamin Brown</persName>, Good Farm Hand first-rate
                                Carriage driver, House Servant and very polite—$1200.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Cassey Mullican</persName>, Good House Girl, very neat
                                and tidy in her appearance $700.00</item>
                            <item><persName>George Ross</persName>, Good House Boy, very active and
                                sprightly, (in fact a Good Boy) $600.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Hanibald Hall</persName>, Good looking
                                child—$200.00</item>
                            <item><persName>Aisey Brown</persName>, Very Good looking
                                Child—$100.00</item>
                            <item>$10,900.00</item>
                            </list>
                    <seg type="handwritten">The above, comprises a list of very <hi rend="underline">Valuable Servants</hi>, and commands readily fine prices as husbands, men get
                        $20 per month and women from $6 to $8. per month.—</seg></p>
                        <ab type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy B Walker</persName></ab>                    

                <pb sameAs="leaf001v" facs="cww.00669.003.jpg"/>
                <p><seg type="handwritten">Your petitioner has no knowledge of any infirmities or
                        defects bodily, mental, or moral of said persons, which impair the Value of
                        petitioners claim to Such Service or Labor—and that she believes none
                        such to exist—</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">She</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">She</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">She</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">Persons or either of them</seg> into the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">Persons were</seg>
                    <del>was</del> held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons or either of them</seg> does not originate in or
                    by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner
                    aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">Persons respectively</seg> herein above set
                    forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion
                    the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the
                    Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy B Walker</persName></seg></signed></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00669.004.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="will" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>In the name of God, amen, I, <persName>Zachariah Walker</persName>, of the
                        <placeName>County of Washington</placeName>, <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>, do make and ordain this my last will and
                    Testament.</p>
                <p>I give and bequeath all my property of every description Real, Personal and mixed, and all my
                    good, <choice><sic>chattles</sic><corr>chattels</corr></choice>, moneys, rights and credits, that I may die seized and possessed
                    of, or in any way or manner entitled to my beloved wife, <persName>Lucy B.
                        Walker</persName>, to do, as to her, may seem neat, and proper, with the exception,
                    of <persName>Milly</persName> <persName>Harriet</persName> and <persName>Mary</persName>, my three servants,
                    whom I wish set free, and order that they each have, one acre, of land, laid off
                    on that portion of my farm, known as the "sheep pasture" for their use and
                    benefit so long as they may choose to reside on the same, and for their natural
                    life, and as an especial mark of faithfulness to my interest. It is my request
                    that <persName>Milly</persName> may receive annually the sum of Thirty dollars
                    (30$) for her better support to be paid by my Executrix and from my estate during her natural
                    life. Also it is my desire that my wife, will use her discretion, and if from their
                    good conduct, and general deportment towards her, as faithful servants, that she
                    will liberate all the servants that may so comport themselves, after her, my
                    said wife's natural life or before if she <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00669.005.jpg"/>may think proper to do so, and on the contrary
                    should any of my servants be undutiful, disobedient and not faithful, It is my
                    request and desire that she make an example of any so offending, by inflicting
                    such punishment as she may deem necessary even to selling the same so as to
                    preserve <choice><sic>perfict</sic><corr>perfect</corr></choice> harmony and obedience.</p>
                <p>It is my wish that my beloved wife may have an eye to the comfort of my
                    relations, and should any of them come to want, that she will administer to
                    their wants by money or otherwise, as may be most convenient to her. Having
                    great confidence that it will be her pleasure to do so. Also it is my wish where
                    it may be <choice><sic>perfictly</sic><corr>perfectly</corr></choice> convenient to do so as a mark of affection and respect, long
                    cherished, for her, to pay over to <persName>Eliza Walker Young</persName>, the
                    sum of one hundred dollars (100$).</p>
                <p>And lastly I do hereby constitute and appoint my dear wife, <persName>Lucy B.
                        Walker</persName> to be sole Executrix, (with any assistant that she might
                    select) of this my last will and Testament, revoking, and annulling, all former
                    wills, by me heretofore made, ratifying and confirming, this and none other, to
                    be my last will and testament.</p>
                <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand, and affixed my seal <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00669.006.jpg"/>
                    <date when="1857-07-18">eighteenth day of July in the year 1857</date>.</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>Zach. Walker</persName> seal</signed></closer>
                </div2>                
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <p>Signed, sealed, published and declared by <persName>Zachariah Walker</persName> the above named testator as and for his last Will and
                    Testament in the presence of us who at his request, in his presence, and in the
                    presence of each other have subscribed our names as witnesses thereof</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>James L. Addison</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>A. Addison</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>J. F. Addison</persName>.</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                    <placeName>Washington County</placeName> to wit,<lb/>
                    Orphans Court<lb/>
                    <date when="1857-09-26">September 26, 1857</date>.</dateline>
                    
                    <p>This day appeared <persName>James L. Addison</persName> and <persName>A.
                            Addison</persName>, two of the subscribing witnesses to the aforegoing
                        last will &amp; testament of <persName>Zachariah Walker</persName>, late of
                            <placeName>Washington County</placeName> aforesaid, deceased, &amp;
                        severally made oath on the Holy Evangels of Almighty God, that he published
                        pronounced and declared the same to be his last will and testament, that at
                        the time of so doing he was to the best their apprehensions of sound &amp;
                        disposing mind, memory and understanding, and that they together with
                            <persName>J. F. Addison</persName> the other subscribing witness,
                        respectively subscribed their names as witnesses to this will, in the
                        presence &amp; at the <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00669.007.jpg"/>
                        request of the Testator, &amp; in the presence of each other.</p>
                    <closer>Test:
                        <signed><persName>Ed. N. Roach</persName> <choice><abbr>Reg.</abbr><expan>Register</expan></choice> Wills</signed></closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>I certify that the aforegoing is a true copy from the original will and
                        testament of <persName>Zachariah Walker</persName>, deceased, filed and
                        recorded in the office of Register of Wills for <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> aforesaid</p>
                    <p>Witness my hand and seal of office this <date when="1862-06-11">11th day
                    of June A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Moses Kelly</persName><lb/>
                            Register of Wills.</signed></closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="figure" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Cost $1.37½</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00669.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy B. Walker</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Lucy B Walker</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-12"><seg type="handwritten">12th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H. Naylor</persName><lb/>
                        J. Peace</seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>669.</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    Mrs. <persName>Lucy B. Walker</persName></ab>
                <ab>Witnesses<lb/>
                    <persName>James Bevans</persName> and<lb/>
                    <persName>Henry Naylor</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
