<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00241">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of George Mattingly, 15 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
               <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
               <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00241</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of George Mattingly, 15 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of George Mattingly, 15 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>George Mattingly</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-19" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-12-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2011-10-03" who="#jc">checked</change>
         <change when="2010-10-08" who="#rv">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00241.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main" rend="underline">PETITION.</head>
                <p>To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <persName>George Mattingly</persName> of <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName> by this his petition in writing, represents and states that
                    he is a person loyal to the United States, who, at the time of the passage of
                    the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against Ten persons
                    of African descent of the name of <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—<persName>Ann
                        Miles</persName>—<persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>—<persName>Dominick
                        Miles</persName>—<persName>Mary Bass</persName>—<persName>James E.
                        Stanford</persName>—<persName>Willis Young</persName>—<persName>Henry
                        Lee</persName>—<persName>Paris Green</persName> and <persName>Henry
                        Branson</persName>, for and during the life of said <persName>Lucy
                        Miles</persName>—<persName>Ann Miles</persName>—<persName>Adelaide
                        Miles</persName>—<persName>Dominick Miles</persName>—<persName>Mary
                        Bass</persName>—<persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—<persName>Willis Young</persName>—<persName>Henry Lee</persName>, and <persName>Paris Green</persName>, and for
                    and during the term of ten months against <persName>Henry Branson</persName>,
                
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00241.002.jpg"/>

                and that by said act of Congress said <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—<persName>Ann Miles</persName>—<persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>—<persName>Dominick Miles</persName>—<persName>Mary Bass</persName>—<persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—<persName>Willis Young</persName>—<persName>Henry Lee</persName>—<persName>Paris Green</persName> and <persName>Henry Branson</persName> were
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—<persName>Ann Miles</persName>—<persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>—<persName>Dominick Miles</persName>—<persName>Mary Bass</persName>—<persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—<persName>Willis Young</persName>—<persName>Henry Lee</persName>—<persName>Paris Green</persName> and <persName>Henry Branson</persName> were of
                    the ages of forty-five (45) years—eighteen (18) years—fourteen (14) years—two
                    (2) years—twenty nine (29) years—eighteen (18) years—thirty five (35) years—
                    thirty two (32) years—fifty five (55) years—and forty five (45) years
                    respectively, and of the personal description following:
                    <list>
                        <item><persName>Lucy Miles</persName>, height, five feet four inches, complexion, Light Copper</item>
                        <item><persName>Ann Miles</persName>, height five feet one inches complexion, Dark Copper,</item>
                        <item><persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>, height five feet three inches complexion, Light Copper</item>
                        <item><persName>Dominick Miles</persName>, height two feet six inches complexion, Light <choice><orig>Molatto</orig><reg>Mullato</reg></choice></item>
                        <item><persName>Mary Bass</persName> height five feet two inches
                            
                            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00241.003.jpg"/>
                            
                            complexion Light <choice><orig>Molatto</orig><reg>Mullato</reg></choice></item>
                        <item><persName>James E. Stanford</persName>, height five feet seven inches Complexion, Black.</item>
                        <item><persName>Willis Young</persName>, height, five feet eleven inches complexion, Dark Copper</item>
                        <item><persName>Henry Lee</persName> height, five feet six inches complexion Bright <choice><orig>Molatto</orig><reg>Mullato</reg></choice></item>
                        <item><persName>Paris Green</persName> height five feet nine inches Complexion, Black</item>
                        <item><persName>Henry Branson</persName> height, six feet one inch complexion, Black</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                
                <p>That your petitioner acquired his claim to the aforesaid service or labor of said
                        <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—<persName>Anne Miles</persName>—<persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>—<persName>Dominick Miles</persName>—<persName>Mary Bass</persName>—<persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—<persName>Willis Young</persName>—<persName>Henry Lee</persName>—<persName>Paris Green</persName> and <persName>Henry Branson</persName> in manner following:
                <list>
                    <item><persName>Lucy Miles</persName>, by Purchase in the year <date when="1841">Eighteen hundred and forty one</date>, from <persName>Fontane Beckham</persName> for the sum of Six hundred dollars. Bill of Sale Lost.</item>
                    <item><persName>Ann Miles</persName>, Born of <persName>Lucy Miles</persName> after purchase of said <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—</item>
                    <item><persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>, Born of <persName>Lucy Miles</persName> after purchase of said <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—</item>
                    <item><persName>Dominick Miles</persName>, Born of <persName>Ann Miles</persName> the daughter of <persName>Lucy Miles</persName> as aforesaid—</item>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00241.004.jpg"/>
                    
                    <item><persName>Mary Bass</persName>—by Purchase in the year <date when="1855">Eighteen hundred and fifty five</date> from <persName>A. M.
                        Hoffar</persName> for the sum of seven hundred dollars—as per Bill of Sale—</item>
                    <item><persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—by Purchase in the year <date when="1847">Eighteen hundred and forty seven</date> from Mrs  <persName>Penoply Luckett</persName> for the sum of seven hundred dollars for his mother and himself and two other children he being then three years of age—</item>
                    <item><persName>Willis Young</persName>—by Purchase in the year <date when="1861">Eighteen hundred and sixty one</date> from the Estate of <persName>George M. Bibb</persName> for the sum of four hundred and sixty five dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Henry Lee</persName>—by Purchase in the year Eighteen hundred and fifty six from Mrs. Dr. <persName>Washington</persName> for the sum of five hundred dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Paris Green</persName>—by Purchase in the year <date when="1861">Eighteen hundred and Sixty one</date>, from <persName>Edward Plummer</persName> and wife for the sum of two hundred dollars per Bill of Sale—</item>
                    <item><persName>Henry Branson</persName>—By Purchase in

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00241.005.jpg"/>
                        
                        the year <date when="1859">Eighteen hundred and fifty nine</date> from <persName>Stephen Shimm</persName> and others for a term of four years (ten months of said term being unexpired) for the sum of five hundred dollars, as per Bill of Sale—</item>
                </list>
            </p>
                
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <persName>Lucy
                        Miles</persName>—<persName>Ann Miles</persName>—<persName>Adelaide
                        Miles</persName>—<persName>Dominick Miles</persName>—<persName>Mary
                        Bass</persName>—<persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—<persName>Willis Young</persName>—<persName>Henry Lee</persName>—<persName>Paris Green</persName> and
                        <persName>Henry Branson</persName> was, at the time of said discharge
                        therefrom, of the value of Sixty nine hundred and fifty dollars in money.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>To Wit; <persName>Lucy Miles</persName>—Is healthy and strong, Is a first class
                    Cook, Washer and Ironer as well as general house servant. has no defects, moral
                    mental or bodily except occasional intemperance; is worth one thousand
                    dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Ann Miles</persName>—Is healthy and strong, Is a first class cook and
                    General house servant—Is honest and trustworthy in every particular Is
                    temperate and I know of nothing against her morals other than bearing

            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00241.006.jpg"/>
                        children without being married Is of good mental capacity and is worth One thousand dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Adelaide Miles</persName>—Is healthy and strong Is a good house servant
                    and childs nurse—Has no defects either moral, mental or bodily and is worth
                    Eight hundred dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Dominick Miles</persName>—Is a healthy, likely child worth one hundred
                    dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Mary Bass</persName>—Is healthy and strong Is a first class house
                    servant and ladies dressing Maid—Has no defects, moral, mental or bodily and is
                    worth twelve hundred dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>James E. Stanford</persName>—Is healthy and strong—Is a first class
                    cook and waiter—His services as such have averaged $14- per month for three or
                    four years past; since <date when="1861-05">April 1861</date>, has been employed
                    in the United States naval service upon one of the steamboats composing the
                    "Potomac Flotilla" at $14 per month and is worth now Eight Hundred dollars</item>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00241.007.jpg"/>
                    
                    <item><persName>Willis Young</persName>—Has been healthy ever since I purchased him—
                    was previously slightly troubled with haemorrhage—Is a first rate Body
                    servant, Waiter and Coachman—has been in the employ of <persName>Lieut Col
                        Owens</persName> of the 3rd Pennsylvania Cavalry as body servant and waiter
                    at $20.— per month since <date when="1861-08">August 1861</date>.—and has not been
                    sick during the interval <choice><abbr>altho</abbr><expan>although</expan></choice>' subject to the Exposure of Camp life—he is worth
                    One thousand dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Henry Lee</persName>—Is healthy and strong, Is a first rate Cook and
                   Waiter and is employed on the United States Steamboat Baltimore as Cook since
                        <date when="1861-04">April 1861</date> at $12.—per month—The terms of purchase
                    from Mrs Dr. <persName>Washington</persName>, were that his (<persName>Henry
                        Lee's</persName>) mother should have the privilege of purchasing him for
                    the sum I paid for him, viz: five hundred dollars I therefore value him at only
                    five hundred dollars—</item>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00241.008.jpg"/>
                    
                    <item><persName>Paris Green</persName>—Is a first rate farm hand and is worth much more
                    than I paid for him; being strong and healthy and trustworthy and understanding
                    all about farm work. I value him as worth at least three hundred dollars—</item>
                    <item><persName>Henry Branson</persName>—Is employed at the <placeName>United
                        States Navy Yard at Washington D.C.</placeName> at $1 50/100 per day—out of
                    which sum he paid me one dollar per day—supporting himself with the remaining
                    fifty cents and whatever he made by overwork—there was ten months service due
                    by him to me before the expiration of the four years for which I purchased him,
                    at the time of the passage of the Act of Congress aforesaid And I value said
                    services worth to me two hundred and fifty dollars—</item>
                </list>
                
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that he bears true and faithful allegiance


            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00241.009.jpg"/>

                to the Government of the United States, and that he has not borne arms against
                    the United States in the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort
                    thereto.</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that he has not brought said
                    persons into the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress, and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said persons were held to service
                    or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service
                    or labor</p>
                
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that his said claim to the service or
                    labor of said persons does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer
                    heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained the
                    present rebellion against the Government of the United States</p>
                
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of his said claim to the service or labor of said persons herein above
                    set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise


            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="cww.00241.010.jpg"/>

                and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the
                    Secretary of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of said Act of Congress.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                  <persName>Geo Mattingly</persName>
               </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
                <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, SS.
                    </dateline>
                    
                    <div2 type="section">
                        <p>I, <persName>George Mattingly</persName> being duly sworn, do depose and say,
                    that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in the
                    foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact;
                    and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth and stated,
                    as from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in
                    fact</p>
                    </div2>
                    
                    <div2 type="section">
                        <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me day of <date when="1862-05">May A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName>Wm R Woodward</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div2>
                </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="cww.00241.012.jpg"/>
            
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>241<lb/> 
                    <persName>George Mattingly</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Charles E. Mitchell</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>John A. Peake</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
