<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00695">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Francis Mohun, 17 June 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                <name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00695</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Francis Mohun, 17 June 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-06-17">June 17, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 5</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Francis Mohun, 17 June 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-06-17">June 17, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Francis Mohun</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>Charles Walter</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-06-24" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-06-08" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-05-31" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2013-04-26" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00695.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Francis Mohun</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington City</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of the
                    said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a certain</seg> person of African descent of the name of
                        <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Marlow</persName></seg> for and
                    during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary</persName></seg>
                    and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and from
                    all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said
                    discharge said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Marlow</persName>
                        was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">twenty seven years</seg> and
                    of the personal description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if
                        there be more than one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">rather a dark mulatto—medium size—about five feet
                        three inches in height—with a pleasant open countenance when addressed; but
                        with no particular marks, recollected—</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00695.002.jpg"/>
                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Marlow</persName></seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for
                        what price or consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of
                        title, make exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same
                        may be found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">He purchased her at the earnest solicitation of and from
                        Mr. <persName>David Barry</persName>, about sixteen years ago, when he was
                        about to sell her, as he did others of his slaves to the South—At the
                        time of purchase, she was called <persName>Lydia</persName>, but since then,
                        at what exact time your Petitioner does not recollect, she changed it to
                            <persName>Mary</persName>—</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Marlow</persName></seg> was, at the time
                    of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">One Thousand</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Mary</persName> is quite intelligent, reads and writes tolerably
                        well, understands nearly all the branches of housework, is a very good cook,
                        washer and ironer, and a good seamstress—Has been a faithful honest
                        and industrious servant, and your Petitioner avers that he knows of no
                        moral, mental or bodily infirmity or defect, which should impair the value
                        of his claim—</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary
                            Marlow</persName></seg> into the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary</persName></seg> was held to service or labor therein
                    under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary</persName></seg> does not originate in or
                    by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner
                    aided or sustained the present rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Mary Marlow</persName></seg> herein
                    above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and
                    apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary
                    of the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to
                    the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Francis Mohun</persName>.</seg></signed></closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00695.003.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                <ab>695</ab>
                <ab><persName>David Barry</persName> Bill of Sale for
                    <persName>Lydia</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1962-07-15">July 15</date></ab>
                <ab>1811 40</ab>
                <ab>170.40</ab>
                <ab><table>
                        <row>
                            <cell>275</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>185</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>90</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table></ab>
                </div2>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00695.004.jpg"/>
                <div2 type="section">
                <dateline><placeName>Washington</placeName> <date when="1848-03-13">March 13th 1848</date></dateline>
                <p>Received from <persName>Francis Mohun</persName> his six notes dated <date when="1848-03-13">13th March 1848</date> the first at 60 days for twenty
                    five dollars the 2nd at 1 year for 55 dollars the third at 2 years for 80
                    dollars the fourth at 3 years for 80 dollars the 5th at 4 years for 80 dollars
                    the 6th at 5 years for 80 dollars with <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">interest</unclear> the whole being 400. dollars in full payment of
                    for the purchase, by said <persName>Mohun</persName> for my negro girl
                            <persName><hi rend="underline">Lydia</hi></persName> aged about 16 or 17
                    for life,</p>
                <closer><signed><persName>David Barry</persName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00695.005.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Francis Mohun</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Francis Mohun</persName>.</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-06-13"><seg type="handwritten">13th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">June</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Chas. Walter</persName> J. P seal</seg></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>695 <persName>Mohun</persName></ab>
                <ab><persName>Francis Mohun</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-06-17">June 17, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>Richard Barry</persName>—<lb/>
                    <persName>R. B. Mohun</persName>—</ab>
                <ab>B &amp; B</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
