<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00240">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Nelson Conrad, 15 May 1862</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
            <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
            <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kjw">Kenneth J. Winkle</name>
<name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
               <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
               <name xml:id="rv">Robert Voss</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>cww.00240</idno>
            <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
            <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Petition of Nelson Conrad, 15 May 1862</title>
               <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
               <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 3</idno>
               <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
               <relatedItem type="original">
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Petition of Nelson Conrad, 15 May 1862</title>
                     <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date>
                     <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                     <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                     <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347 (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                  </bibl>
               </relatedItem>
               <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <person role="petitioner">
               <persName>Nelson Conrad</persName>
            </person>
            <person role="jp">
               <persName>William R. Woodward</persName>
            </person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-01-10" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-01-09" who="#kjw">blessed</change>
<change when="2012-09-27" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
         <change when="2011-10-05" who="#bj">checked</change>
         <change when="2010-10-07" who="#rv">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00240.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p>To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to Service or labor in the <placeName>district
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <persName>Nelson Conrad</persName>, Trustee for his infant
                    Children <persName>Mary L</persName> &amp; <persName>Eliza D. Corrage</persName> aged fourteen &amp; Sixteen years of
                        <placeName>Georgetown District of Columbia</placeName> by this his petition
                    in writing, represents and States that he is a person loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of said act of Congress, held a
                    claim to Service or labor against three female Servants
                    persons of African descent of the following
                    names and ages, namely, <persName>Lucy Bowls</persName>,<persName> Hanah Beson</persName>, and <persName>May Lucy
                        Beson</persName>. 
                    <list>
                        <item>No. 1 <persName>Lucy Bowls</persName>, is a woman 49 years
                    of age, five foot four inches high, not very dark color, front teeth out, of
                    rather pleasant Countenance dark Eyes</item>
                        <item>No 2 <persName>Hanah Beson</persName> is a
                    woman 22 years of age five feet two &amp; half inch high. Not Very dark Color
                    with a <choice><sic>skar</sic><corr>scar</corr></choice> on each Side of her mouth, and on her forehead caused by a burn She
                    <choice><abbr>recvd</abbr><expan>received</expan></choice> when a child, has a slight defect in her left Eye, has dark round Eyes.</item>
                        <item>No. 3 <persName>May Lucy Beson</persName>, is a daughter of <persName>Hanah
                        Beson</persName>
                    
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00240.002.jpg"/>
            
                four years old. color, bright mulatto, large keen Black Eyes. Uncommonly
                    sprightly &amp; handsome, Very large for one of her age, three feet high</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                
                    <p>That your petitioner acquired his claim as trustee to the aforesaid Services
                    or labor of said Slaves in Manner following,                 
                        <list>
                            <item>No 1. <persName>Lucy Bowls</persName>, by a deed of Conveyance from one
                        <persName>May E Waugh</persName> of <placeName>Birkley County
                        Virginia</placeName> dated <date when="1858-04-23">23rd of April
                    1858</date>. and of record in the city of <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>, the
                    amt paid for the Said <persName>Lucy</persName> a Short time previous to her
                    Conveyance was two hundred dollars ($200—)</item>
                            <item>No 2. <persName>Hanah Beson</persName>, is a daughter of <persName>Lucy
                        Bowls</persName> aged 22 years, that your petitioner acquired his claim as trustee to the
                    aforesaid Services or labor of Said Slave by a deed of Conveyance from
                        <persName>Martha A Conrad</persName> of <placeName>Birkley County
                        Virginia</placeName> bearing date <date when="1858-07">July Eighteen hundred
                        &amp; fifty Eight</date>, &amp; of record in said County, the said
                        <persName>Hanah</persName> was purchased by the said <persName>Martha A
                        Conrad</persName> of one <persName>Geo W. Hunter</persName> Jr Trustee for
                    the Sum of Seven hundred &amp; twenty five <choice><abbr>dolls</abbr><expan>dollars</expan></choice> ($725) and Conveyed to your
                    petitioner as trustee</item>
                            <item>No 3. <persName>May Lucy Beson</persName> is a daughter of <persName>Hanah Beson</persName>, aged four years was born
                    since the deed of Conveyance of her Mother <persName>Hanah Beson </persName>and
                    by law is the property of your petitioner or was at the time of the aforesaid
                    act of Congress
           
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00240.003.jpg"/>
           
                                emancipating Slavery in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName></item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the services or labor of the said <persName>Lucy
                        Bowls</persName> was, at the time of said discharge of the Value of Three
                    hundred dollars in Money. Your petitioner thinks that notwithstanding the said
                    <persName>Lucy Bowls</persName> was bought for the sum of two hundred ($200) from the fact that at
                    that time She was greatly complaining and at a very <choice><sic>criticle</sic><corr>critical</corr></choice> time of life with
                    her, now she having passed that period of life &amp; her health much
                    improved indeed your petitioner may say well, now he thinks therefore she is greatly
                    enhanced in Value. She is a woman of strict moral character, strictly honest and
                    one of the best cooks, in Short she combines all <choice><sic>nessary</sic><corr>necessary</corr></choice> qualifications for a no
                    one house servants, consequently she is very valuable.</p>
                <p>Your petitioner would state that he knows of no mental, moral or bodily
                    <choice><sic>infirmaties</sic><corr>infirmities</corr></choice> so as to impair the value of your petitioners claims to such service 
                    or labor, except that the said <persName>Lucy</persName> is occasionally
                    troubles with something of the rheumatism <choice><sic>tho</sic><corr>though</corr></choice> which seldom prevents her from
                    attending to her daily labors, indeed never has with one exception.</p>
                <p><persName>Hanah Beson</persName>, is a daughter of <persName>Lucy
                        Bowls</persName> aged 22 years, well and <choice><sic>harty</sic><corr>hearty</corr></choice>, is a woman of good moral
                    character, strictly honest, a first rate house servant in short your petitioner
                    consider the said <persName>Hanah</persName> like her mother a no one house
                    Servant,
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00240.004.jpg"/>
            
                and a woman of the best temper &amp; disposition ever met with.</p>
                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the Services or labor of said <persName>Hanah
                        Beson</persName> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the Value
                    of Seven Hundred dollars in money.</p>
                <p>Your petitioner would state that he is aware of one defect in the said <persName>Hanah</persName>
                    which would render her less value, and that existed at the time she was
                    purchased but which renders her no less <choice><sic>servisible</sic><corr>serviceable</corr></choice> and that is a slight defect in
                    her left eye.</p>
                <p>
               <persName>May Lucy Benson</persName>, daughter of <persName>Hanah
                        Benson</persName>, is a child four years old, well &amp; lovely, never
                    has had a days sickness in her life, she is the child of uncommon promise.</p>
                <p>that Your petitioner claims to the service or labor of said <persName>May Lucy
                        Benson</persName> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom of the value
                    of Two hundred &amp; fifty dollars in money.</p>
                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that he bears true and faithful allegiance to the
                    government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that he has not borne arms against the
                    <persName>United States</persName> in the present rebellion nor in any way given aid to comfort
                    thereto. And your petitioner further states and <choice><sic>alledges</sic><corr>alleges</corr></choice> that he has not brought
                    said slaves above mentioned into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                    Since the passage
           
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00240.005.jpg"/>
           
                of said act of congress: and that, at the time of the said passage thereof said
                    servants, namely <persName>Lucy Bowls</persName>, <persName>Hanah
                        Beson</persName> and <persName>May Lucy Beson</persName> was held to service
                    or labor therein under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service
                    or labor.</p>
                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges that his said claim to the service or
                    labor of said <persName>Lucy Bowls</persName>, <persName>Hanah
                        Benson</persName> and <persName>May Lucy Benson</persName> does not
                    originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against the government of
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine
                    the validity of his said claim to the Service or labor of said <persName>Lucy
                        Bowl</persName>, <persName>Hanah Beson</persName> &amp; <persName>May
                        Lucy Beson</persName> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be
                    valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and
                    report the same to the Secretary of the treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, in
                    Conformity to the provisions of said act of Congress.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Nelson Conrad</persName><lb/>
                        Trustee</signed> 
                    <signed><persName>Mary Conrad</persName></signed><lb/>
                    Witnesses
                    <signed>Rev. <persName>J. H. Ryland</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Wm H. Edees</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>Robert Marion</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="cww.00240.006.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <placeName> Washington County</placeName>, to wit, </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <persName>Nelson Conrad</persName>, Trustee of Georgetown D.C. being duly
                        sworn do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are
                        set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own Knowledge, are
                        true in Substance and in fact, and that all the several other matters and
                        things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others, I
                        believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Nelson Conrad</persName> Trustee </signed>
                        <signed><persName>Mary Conrad</persName></signed><lb/>
                        <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#jc">intentioned</unclear> before signed
                        <signed><persName>Wm R Woodward</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05"><space atLeast="1"/>day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A. D.
                            1862</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName> <choice><abbr>clk</abbr><expan>clerk</expan></choice> &amp;c</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed by <persName>Mary Conrad</persName> this <date when="1862-05-20">20th day of May A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Wm R. Woodward</persName> <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#jc">clerk</unclear></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>240<lb/>
               <persName>Nelson Conrad</persName> Trustee </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-15">May 15, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>Not stated that the slaves were for life</ab>
                <ab><persName>J. H. Ryland</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Wm H. Edes</persName><lb/>
                    <persName>Robert Benison</persName></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
