<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00934">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Luther O. Sullivan and Samuel S. Williams,
                    15 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                    <name xml:id="kk">Kathryn Kruger</name>
                <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
</respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00934</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Luther O. Sullivan and Samuel S. Williams, 15 July
                        1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Luther O. Sullivan and Samuel S. Williams, 15 July
                                1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>

                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Luther O. Sullivan</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Samuel S. Williams</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John Rowland</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-04-29" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-04-26" who="#kp">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-03-21" who="#jc">performed automated check for regular transcriptions and encoding errors and mistakes at facs</change>
            <change when="2012-12-11" who="#jc">transcribed, encoded</change>
            <change when="2013-02-18" who="#kk">checked</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00934.001.jpg"/>
            <fw>Sold by <persName>W. H.</persName> &amp; <persName>O. H. Morrison</persName>, Law
                Booksellers, <placeName>440 Pennsylvania Avenue</placeName>.</fw>
            <div1 type="act" subtype="print">
                <head type="main" rend="bold">AN ACT</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR THE RELEASE OF CERTAIN PERSONS HELD TO SERVICE OR LABOR IN THE
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>.</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of
                        the <placeName>United States of America</placeName> in Congress
                        assembled,</hi> That all persons held to service or labor within the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> by reason of African descent are
                    hereby discharged and freed of and from all claim to such service or labor; and
                    from and after the passage of this act neither slavery nor involuntary
                    servitude, except for crime, whereof the party shall be duly convicted, shall
                    hereafter exist in said District.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 2. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That all persons loyal to the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, holding claims to service or labor against persons
                    discharged therefrom by this act, may, within ninety days from the passage
                    thereof, but not thereafter, present to the Commissioners hereinafter mentioned
                    their respective statements or petitions in writing, verified by oath or
                    affirmation, setting forth the names, ages, and personal description of such
                    persons; the manner in which said petitioners acquired such claim, and any facts
                    touching the value thereof, and declaring his allegiance to the Government of
                    the United States, and that he has not borne arms against the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> during the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or
                    comfort thereto: <hi rend="italic">Provided,</hi> That the oath of the party to
                    the petition shall not be evidence of the fact therein stated.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 3. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That the President of the <placeName>United
                    States</placeName>, with the advice and consent of the Senate, shall appoint
                    three Commissioners, residents of the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>, any two of whom shall have power to act, who shall
                    receive the petitions above mentioned, and who shall investigate and determine
                    the validity and value of the claims therein presented, as aforesaid, and
                    appraise and apportion, under the proviso hereto annexed, the value in money of
                    the several claims by them found to be valid: <hi rend="italic">Provided
                        however,</hi> That the entire sum so appraised and apportion shall not
                    exceed, in the aggregate, an amount equal to three hundred dollars for each
                    person shown to have been so held by lawful claim: <hi rend="italic">And
                        provided further,</hi> That no claim shall be allowed for any slave or
                    slaves brought into said District after the passage of this act, nor for any
                    slave claimed by any person who has borne arms against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion, or in any way
                    given aid or comfort thereto, or which originates in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made, or which shall hereafter be made by any person who has
                    in any manner aided or sustained the rebellion against the Government of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 4. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That said Commissioners shall, within nine months from the
                    passage of this act, make a full and final report of their proceedings,
                    findings, and appraisement, and shall deliver the same to the Secretary of the
                    Treasury, which report shall be deemed and taken to be conclusive in all
                    respects, except as hereinafter provided; and the Secretary of the Treasury
                    shall, with like exception, cause the amounts so apportioned to said claims to
                    be paid from the Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName> to the
                    parties found by said report to be entitled thereto as aforesaid, and the same
                    shall be received in full and complete compensation: <hi rend="italic">Provided,</hi> That in cases where petitions may be filed presenting
                    conflicting claims or setting up liens, said Commissioners shall so specify in
                    said report, and payment shall not be made, according to the award of said
                    Commissioners, until a period of sixty days shall have elapsed, during which
                    time any petitioner claiming an interest in the particular amount may file a
                    bill in equity in the Circuit Court of the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName>, making all other claimants defendants thereto, setting
                    forth the proceedings in such case before said Commissioners, and their action
                    therein, and praying that the party to whom payment has been awarded may be
                    enjoined from receiving the same; and if said court shall grant such provisional
                    order, a copy thereof may, on motion of said complainant, be serve upon the
                    Secretary of the Treasury, who shall thereupon cause the said amount of money to
                    be paid into said court, subject to its orders and final decree, which payment
                    shall be in full and complete compensation, as in other cases.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 5. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That said Commissioners shall hold their sessions in the
                        <placeName>city of Washington</placeName>, at such place and times as the
                    President of the <placeName>United States</placeName> may direct, of which they
                    shall give due and public notice. They shall have power to subpœna and compel
                    the attendance of witnesses, and to receive testimony and enforce its
                    production, as in civil cases before courts of justice, without the exclusion of
                    any witness on account of color; and they may summon before them the persons
                    making claim to service or labor, and examine them under oath; and they may
                    also, for purposes of identification and appraisement, call before them the
                    persons so claimed. Said Commissioners shall appoint a clerk, who shall keep
                    files and complete record of all proceedings before them, who shall have power
                    to administer oaths and affirmations in said proceedings, and who shall issue
                    all lawful process by them ordered. The Marshal of the <placeName>District of
                        Columbia</placeName> shall personally, or by deputy, attend upon the session
                    of said Commissioners, and shall execute the process issued by said clerk.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 6.<hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That said Commissioners shall receive in compensation for
                    their services the sum of two thousand dollars each, to be paid upon the filing
                    of their report; that said clerk shall receive for his services the sum of two
                    hundred dollars per month; that said marshal shall receive such fees as are
                    allowed by law for similar services performed by him in the Circuit Court of the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>; that the Secretary of the
                    Treasury shall cause all other reasonable expenses of said Commission to be
                    audited and allowed, and that said compensation, fees, and expenses shall be
                    paid from the treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 7. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That for the purpose of carrying this act into effect there is
                    hereby appropriated, out of any money in the treasury not otherwise
                    appropriated, a sum not exceeding one million of dollars.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 8. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That any person or persons who shall kidnap, or in any manner
                    transport or procure to be taken out of said District, any person or persons
                    discharged and freed by the provisions of this act, or any free person or
                    persons, with intent to re-enslave or sell such person or persons into slavery,
                    or shall re-enslave any of said freed persons, the person or persons so
                    offending shall be deemed guilty of a felony, and on conviction thereof in any
                    court of competent jurisdiction in said District, shall be imprisoned in the
                    penitentiary not less than five nor more than twenty years.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 9. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That within twenty days, or within such further time as the
                    Commissioners herein provided for shall limit, after the passage of this act, a
                    statement in writing or schedule shall be filed with the clerk of the Circuit
                    Court for the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>, by the several owners
                    or claimants to the services of the persons made free or manumitted by this act,
                    setting forth the names, ages, sex, and particular description of such persons,
                    severally; and the said clerk shall receive and record, in a book by him to be
                    provided and kept for that purpose, the said statements or schedules on
                    receiving fifty cents each therefor, and no claim shall be allowed to any
                    claimant or owner who shall neglect this requirement.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 10. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That the said clerk and his successors in office, shall, from
                    time to time, on demand, and on receiving twenty-five cents therefor, prepare,
                    sign, and deliver to each person made free or manumitted by this act, a
                    certificate under the seal of said court, setting out the name, age, and
                    description of such person, and stating that such person was duly manumitted and
                    set free by this act.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 11. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That the sum of one hundred thousand dollars, out of any money
                    in the treasury not otherwise appropriated, is hereby appropriated, to be
                    expended under the direction of the President of the United States, to aid in
                    the colonization and settlement of such free persons of African descent now
                    residing in said District, including those to be liberated by this act, as may
                    desire to emigrate to the Republics of <choice>
                        <orig>Hayti</orig>
                        <reg>Haiti</reg>
                    </choice> or Liberia, or such other country beyond the limits of the United
                    States as the President may determine: <seg rend="italic">Provided,</seg> The
                    expenditure for this purpose shall not exceed one hundred dollars for each
                    emigrant.</p>

                <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">EC</hi>. 12. <hi rend="italic">And be it further
                        enacted,</hi> That all acts of Congress and all laws of the <placeName>State
                        of Maryland</placeName> in force in said District, and all ordinances of the
                    cities of <placeName>Washington</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Georgetown</placeName>, inconsistent with the provisions of this
                    act, are hereby repealed.</p>

                <closer>[Approved, <date when="1862-04-01">April 16, 1862</date>]</closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00934.002.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>L. O.
                        Sullivan</persName></seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington
                            D.C.</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim to
                    service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">Three</seg> person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Barney Grimsby Breant</persName>,
                            <persName>Charlotte Hudley</persName> and <persName>Rose
                        Lee</persName></seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> and that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">persons were</seg> discharged and freed of and from all claim of your
                    petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of said discharge said
                        <seg type="handwritten"><persName>B. Grimsby Breant</persName> was of the
                        age of about 17 years, <persName>Charlotte Hudley</persName></seg> of the
                    age of <seg type="handwritten">fifteen years and <persName>Rose Lee</persName>
                        was of the age of thirteen years—</seg> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The first named <persName>B. Grimsby Briant</persName> is
                    about 5 ft. 7 or 8 in. high of a tawny or copper <choice>
                        <orig>colour</orig>
                        <reg>color</reg>
                    </choice> fine teeth &amp; well made:</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten">the 2nd named, <persName>Charlotte
                        Hudley</persName>, about four feet eight inches high, black, fine teeth and
                    slender made: and <persName>Rose Lee</persName> is about four feet four inches
                    high, thick-set, well made and black, with fine countenance—</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="cww.00934.003.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg>
                    in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state
                        how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">To the 1st named one,
                            <persName>Grimsbly</persName>, by gift from petitioner's mother some six
                        years ago, and bequest as appears in her last will, admitted to <choice>
                            <sic>probat</sic>
                            <corr>probate</corr>
                        </choice> in the <choice>
                            <abbr>clk's</abbr>
                            <expan>clerk's</expan>
                        </choice> office of the County Court of the County of <placeName>Fauqr.
                            Va.</placeName> To the 2nd named one,
                            <persName>Charlotte Hudley</persName>, by deed of conveyance from
                            <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">Mister</unclear>
                        <persName>J. B. Sullivan</persName> recorded in said <choice>
                            <abbr>Clk's</abbr>
                            <expan>Clerk's</expan>
                        </choice> office of the County Court of <placeName>Fauquier Co.
                            Va.</placeName> To the 3rd named one,
                            <persName>Rose Lee</persName>, was born his of a slave woman acquired by
                        marriage some 15 years ago—</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">—persons—</seg> was, at the time of said
                    discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Thirty five
                        hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any there be, touching the value of
                        the petitioner's claim to the service or labor of the person, as may enhance
                        the same, and also such facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and
                        bodily infirmities or defects of said person, as impair the value of the
                        petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and conclude such statement
                        with an averment that the petitioner knows of no other infirmities or
                        defects of said person which impair the value of petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and that he believes none other to exist. If the
                        petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect, then his statement touching
                        the value of his claim should conclude with an averment that he has no
                        knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Barney Grimsby Briant</persName>'s valuable qualifications as
                        Body and dining room servant, &amp; cook, together with his known qualities
                        of truthfulness &amp; reliability &amp; freedom from all defects of both
                        mind &amp; body would command even a higher price than the one set upon him
                        of $1500. <persName>Charlotte Hudley</persName> is particularly valuable as
                        a Lady's maid &amp; first rate seamstress and general knowledge of every
                        thing pertaining to housekeeping. such qualifications would command $1500.
                        in the South.—<persName>Rose Lee</persName>, being a good nurse,
                        chambermaid general house servant &amp; reliable in every was as well as
                        freedom from defects in both <gap reason="illegible" extent="six or seven words" quantity="24" unit="chars"/>
                        <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#jc">a valuable money</unclear>
                        price or value.</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg>
                    into the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said
                    act of Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was held to service or labor therein under
                    and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>L. O.
                                Sullivan</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00934.004.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>L. O. Sullivan</persName></seg> being
                        duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and things which
                        are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge,
                        are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several other matters
                        and things therein set forth and stated, as from the information of others,
                        I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>L. O.
                                    Sullivan</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-14"><seg type="handwritten">14th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J.
                                    Rowland</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>934</ab>
                <ab><persName>L. O. Sullivan</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-15">July 15, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00934.006.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Saml S. Williams</persName>
                        Trustee</seg> of <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Washington
                            City</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg>
                    petition in writing, represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the <placeName>United States</placeName>,
                    who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held a claim
                        <del>to service or labor</del> against <seg type="handwritten">Three</seg>
                        person<seg type="handwritten">s</seg> of African descent of the name of <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Barney Grimsby Briant</persName>,
                            <persName>Charlotte Hudley</persName> and <persName>Rose Lee</persName>
                        —</seg> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>B. Grimsby Briant</persName>, <persName>Charlotte
                            Hudley</persName> and <persName>Rose Lee</persName>—</seg> and
                    that by said act of Congress said <seg type="handwritten">parties were</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">B Grimsby
                        Briant</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">about 17 years.
                            <persName>Charlotte Hudley</persName> fifteen and <persName>Rose
                            Lee</persName> about 13 years of age</seg> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" sameAs="n1">Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note></p>
                <ab type="handwritten">The first named <persName>Grimsby</persName> is about 5 ft 8
                    in high, of a tawny or copper <choice>
                        <abbr>col</abbr>
                        <expan>color</expan>
                    </choice> fine teeth &amp; well made</ab>
                <ab type="handwritten">The second <persName>Charlotte</persName> is about four feet
                    Eight inches high, black, fine teeth &amp; slender made and <persName>Rose
                        Lee</persName> is about 4 feet four inches high thick set well made &amp;
                    black with good countenance—</ab>

                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="cww.00934.007.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons—</seg>
                    in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" sameAs="n2">Here state
                        how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">By deed of conveyance in Trust to secure the payment of
                        two thousand dollars with interest due Dr. <persName>Thos. Lawson</persName>
                        Late Surgeon <choice>
                            <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                            <expan>General</expan>
                        </choice> U. S. Army executed by <persName>L. O. Sullivan</persName> the
                        owner</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to <del>the service or labor of</del> said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">two thousand</seg> dollars in
                        money.<note type="government" place="foot" sameAs="n3">Here state such
                        facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the
                        service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">with interest from <date when="1861-02-12">Feby 12th, 1861</date>.</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">persons—<gap reason="illegible" extent="one word" quantity="6" unit="chars"/></seg> was held to service or labor therein
                    under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">the</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">persons</seg> herein above set forth; and if the
                    same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of said
                    claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>S. S.
                                Williams</persName><lb/> Trustee</seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00934.008.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Saml S. Williams</persName>
                            Trustee</seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several
                        matters and things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition,
                        as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the
                        several other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>Saml S
                                    Williams</persName><lb/> Trustee</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-15"><seg type="handwritten">15</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H.
                                    Naylor</persName> J.P.</seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>934.</ab>
                <ab>Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>S. S. Williams</persName><lb/> Trustee</ab>
                <ab>3<lb/>
                    <list>
                        <item>Three Slaves</item>
                        <item><persName>Grimsby</persName></item>
                        <item><persName>Charlotte</persName></item>
                        <item><persName>Rose</persName></item>
                    </list>
                </ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-15">July 15: 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00934.009.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <ab>934</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date></ab>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="cww.00934.010.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="petition" subtype="handwritten">
                <p>To the <placeName>United States</placeName> Commissioners appointed under the act
                    of Congress entitled "An act for the release of certain persons held to service
                    or labor in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>" approved <date when="1862-04-16">April 16th 1862</date>.</p>
                <p>Your petitioners <persName>John E. Kendall</persName> and <persName>John A.
                        Rowland</persName> of the <placeName>City of Washington</placeName> in the
                        <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> beg leave to represent that one
                        <persName>Luther O. Sullivan</persName> of said
                        <placeName>District</placeName> heretofore, to wit: On the <date when="1859-04-06">6th day of April A.D. 1859</date> by his certain deed of
                    Indenture of that date duly executed and recorded in Liber J. A. S. No 172 folio 267 et <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#kp"/> one of the land
                    records of <placeName>Washington County</placeName> in the
                        <placeName>District</placeName> aforesaid conveyed to one <persName>Charles
                        S. Wallach</persName> who is now a non-resident of the said
                        <placeName>District</placeName>, one negro boy named <persName>Grousby
                        Grimsby</persName> a slave for life, aged about 14 years at the date of said
                    deed and the negro girl named "<persName>Lotty</persName>" also a slave for
                    life, aged about 12 years at the date of said deed, in trust to secure the
                    payment of two negotiable promissory notes drawn and executed by the said
                        <persName>Sullivan</persName> dated <date when="1859-04-06">April 6th
                        1859</date> payable respectively, one for $200 and the other for $800, in
                    two and four months after date. Your petitioners represent that they are now the
                        <hi rend="underline">bona fide</hi> holders and owners <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="cww.00934.011.jpg"/> of the said notes and that they are both passed
                    due and unpaid. That said negroes your petitioners have been informed, at the
                    time of the execution of said deed<note type="editorial">Here the petitioner
                        offers a caret to indicate an insertion, although there is no text above the
                        caret.</note> belonged to and were in the possession of the said
                        <persName>Sullivan</persName> in said <placeName>District</placeName> and
                    continued so to be up to and at the date of the passage and approval of the said
                    Act of Congress under and by virtue of which they became free. That the said
                        <persName>Sullivan</persName> has filed with the clerk of and presented to
                    your Commission his petition praying payment to him of such compensation as may
                    be allowed by law in consequence of the manumission of said Slaves. Your
                    petitioners therefore and in consequence of the said promissory notes remaining
                    unpaid and in consideration of all the premises, claim the benefit of the <hi rend="underline">proviso</hi> in the 4th section of said Act of
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>Your petitioners hereby declare that they bear true faith and allegiance to the
                    Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and that they have not
                    borne arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present
                    rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><persName>Jno. E. Kendall</persName></signed>
                    <signed><persName>J. A. Rowland</persName></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="cww.00934.012.jpg"/>
            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName><lb/> To wit</dateline>
                    <p>I <persName>John A. Rowland</persName> being duly sworn do depose and say
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge are true in substance and in
                        fact, and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, I believe to be true in
                        substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>JA Rowland</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn &amp; subscribed before me the <date when="1862-12-12">twelfth day of
                            December AD 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>D Rowland</persName><lb/> Justice of the Peace</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName><lb/>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName></dateline>
                    <p>I <persName>John E. Kendall</persName> being duly sworn do depose and say
                        that all the several matters and things which are set forth and stated in
                        the foregoing petition, as of my own knowledge, are true in substance and in
                        fact, and that all the several other things therein set forth and stated, as
                        from the information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in
                        fact.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Jno. E. Kendall</persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed to before me this <date when="1862-12-13">13th day of
                            December AD. 1862</date></p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>D Rowland</persName><lb/> Justice of the Peace</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
