<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00882">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Harriet E. Muncaster and Julian Magruder, 11 July 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00882</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Harriet E. Muncaster and Julian Magruder, 11 July 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 6</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Harriet E. Muncaster and Julian Magruder, 11 July 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-07-11">July 11, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Harriet E. Muncaster</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Julian Magruder</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John W. Baker</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
<change when="2013-02-28" who="#jc">blessed</change>
<change when="2013-02-13" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-01-16" who="#jc">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-12-18" who="#nnk">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00882.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the <placeName>District
                        of Columbia</placeName>."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Harriet E.
                            Muncaster</persName> by her next friend <persName>Julian Magruder</persName>
                        of <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName>, and <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName></seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> petition in writing,
                    represents and states, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> is a person loyal
                    to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, who, at the time of the passage of
                    the said act of Congress, held a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">a negro man named <persName>Sam</persName>, calling
                        himself <persName>Samuel Martin</persName> a</seg> person of African descent
                        <del>of the name of</del> for and during the life of said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Sam</persName></seg> and that by said act of
                    Congress said <seg type="handwritten"><persName>Sam</persName> was</seg>
                    discharged and freed of and from all claim of your petitioner to such service or
                    labor; that at the time of said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">of
                            <persName>Sam</persName> he was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">about Forty three years</seg> and of the personal
                    description following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here
                        describe the person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than
                        one slave, describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">He is somewhere about five feet Eight, or nine inches
                        high black: stout, strong, healthy, bred as a farm hand; and capable of any
                        farm work: for some years past has been engaged (say for ten years) in driving
                        a cart or dray, and at the time of the passage of said act was receiving
                        four dollars a week, wages, boarding himself</seg></p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00882.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">servant man</seg> in
                    manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here state how
                        the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">in the distribution of the personal Estate of
                            <persName>Zadok Magruder</persName> late of <placeName>Montgomery
                            County</placeName> deceased, who was the father of your petitioner, and
                        her said <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">near</unclear> friend
                            <persName>Julian Magruder</persName>: your Petitioner is a married woman
                        the wife of <persName>Otho Z. Muncaster</persName> of <placeName>Montgomery
                            County Maryland</placeName>; but both by the laws of said State and by
                        marriage settlement, she has a separate Estate in her personal
                        property</seg></p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">negro man</seg> was, at the time of said discharge
                    therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">Seventeen hundred</seg>
                    dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state
                        such facts, if any there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to
                        the service or labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such
                        facts, if any, touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects
                        of said person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such
                        service or labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the
                        petitioner knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which
                        impair the value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he
                        believes none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or
                        defect, then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude
                        with an averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or
                        defect.</note><seg type="handwritten">She could have got that price for him
                        in the fall of <date when="1860">1860</date>, but he was not for sale; and
                        he was worth quite as much at the time of the passage of said act</seg></p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, and that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not borne
                    arms against the <placeName>United States</placeName> in the present rebellion,
                    nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">she</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">negro man</seg> into
                    the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName> since the passage of said act of
                    Congress; and that, at the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">negro man</seg> was held to service or labor therein
                    under and by virtue of your petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">negro man</seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any
                    transfer heretofore made by any person who has in any manner aided or sustained
                    the present rebellion against the Government of the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    validity of <seg type="handwritten">her</seg> said claim to the service or labor
                    of said <seg type="handwritten">negro man</seg> herein above set forth; and if
                    the same be found to be valid, that they appraise and apportion the value of
                    said claim in money, and report the same to the Secretary of the Treasury of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName>, in conformity to the provisions of
                    said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H Muncaster</persName> <persName>Harriet E Muncaster</persName></seg></signed>
                            <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J Magruder</persName> <persName>Julian Magruder</persName></seg></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00882.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline><placeName><seg type="handwritten">State of Maryland</seg> <del>District of Columbia,</del></placeName><lb/>
                    <seg type="handwritten"><placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> to wit</seg><lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic"><del><placeName>Washington County</placeName>,</del> ss.</hi></dateline>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                    <p><seg type="handwritten">We <persName>Harriet E. Muncaster</persName>, and
                                <persName>Julian Magruder</persName></seg> being duly sworn, do
                        depose and say, that all the several matters and things which are set forth
                        and stated in the foregoing petition, as of <del>my</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">our</seg> own knowledge, are true in substance and
                        in fact; and that all the several other matters and things therein set forth
                        and stated, as from the information of others, <del>I</del>
                        <seg type="handwritten">we</seg> believe to be true in substance and in
                        fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>H Muncaster</persName> <persName>Harriet E Muncaster</persName></seg></signed>
                        <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J Magruder</persName> <persName>Julian Magruder</persName></seg></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="mixed">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-07-08"><seg type="handwritten">8th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg> A. D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer><signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>John W. Baker</persName> J. P.</seg></signed><lb/>
                        (Signed by) 
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Here add the certificate of the clerk of the Court under seal that the
                        Justice certifying the oath is at the time of so doing a Justice <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="2"/></p>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="statement" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>State of Maryland</placeName> <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> Sct</dateline>
                    <p>I hereby certify that <persName>John W Baker</persName> Gentleman before whom
                        the aforegoing affidavit was made and whose genuine signature is thereto
                        subscribed was at the time thereof one of the <placeName>State of
                            Maryland</placeName>'s Justices of the peace in and for
                            <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName> duly commissioned and sworn</p>
                    <p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto subscribed my name and affixed the
                        seal of the Circuit Court for said County this <date when="1862-07-08">8th day of July AD. 1862</date></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName>James G. Hening</persName> <choice><abbr>Clk</abbr><expan>Clerk</expan></choice><lb/>
                        Circuit Court for <placeName>Montgomery County</placeName></signed></closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>882<lb/>
                    <persName>Harriet E. Muncaster</persName></ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-07-11">July 11th 1862</date></ab>
                <ab>B &amp; B</ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
