<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="cww.00504">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Petition of Joseph W. Webb, 28 May 1862</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <name xml:id="kp">Kenneth M. Price</name>
                    <name xml:id="bj">Brittany Jones</name>
                    <name xml:id="nnk">Nima Najafi Kianfar</name>
                    <name xml:id="jc">Janel Cayer</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>cww.00504</idno>
                <distributor>Civil War Washington</distributor>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
            </address>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                            3.0 Unported License
                            (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be
                            credited to Civil War Washington, made available non-commercially, and
                            distributed under the same terms. Requests for permission for commercial
                            publication or other use should be emailed to the project team.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Petition of Joseph W. Webb, 28 May 1862</title>
                    <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                    <idno>Microcopy 520, Reel 4</idno>
                    <orgName>National Archives and Records Administration</orgName>
                    <relatedItem type="original">
                        <bibl>
                            <title>Petition of Joseph W. Webb, 28 May 1862</title>
                            <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date>
                            <idno>Record Group 217.6.5</idno>
                            <orgName>Records of the Accounting Officers of the Department of the
                                Treasury, 1775–1978, National Archives and Records
                                Administration</orgName>
                            <note type="project">Within the National Archives' Archival Description
                                Catalog, see ARC Identifier 4644616 / MLR Number A1 347
                                (http://arcweb.archives.gov).</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                    <note type="project">Our transcription is based on a digital image of a
                        microfilm copy of the original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person role="petitioner">
                    <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName>
                </person>
                <person role="jp">
                    <persName>John H. Johnson</persName>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-08-14" who="#jc">removed underlining of signature and deleted extra text from oath page</change>
            <change when="2013-02-11" who="#jc">blessed</change>
            <change when="2013-02-10" who="#kp">blessed</change>
            <change when="2012-12-28" who="#jc">updated tei header; fixed values for @facs as
                necessary; automated checking across files for extra spaces in elements and other
                encoding inconsistencies and for regular transcription errors</change>
            <change when="2011-10-29" who="#nnk">proofed</change>
            <change when="2011-03-17" who="#bj">transcribed, encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="petition">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="cww.00504.001.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="petition" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">PETITION.</head>
                <p rend="bold">To the Commissioners under the act of Congress approved the <date when="1862-04-16">16th of April, 1862</date>, entitled "An act for the
                    release of certain persons held to service or labor in the District of
                    Columbia."</p>

                <p>Your Petitioner, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName>
                    </seg> of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <placeName>Washington City</placeName>
                    </seg> by this <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> petition in writing, represents
                    and states, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> is a person loyal to the
                    United States, who, at the time of the passage of the said act of Congress, held
                    a claim to service or labor against <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William Harrod</persName> a</seg> person of African descent of the
                    name of <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William Harrod</persName>
                    </seg> for and during <del>the life of said</del>
                    <seg type="handwritten"> a term of years not yet expired—to wit for the
                        term of those years and nine months from the <date when="1860-07-23">23rd
                            day of July 1860</date>,</seg> and that by said act of Congress said
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William Harrod</persName> was</seg> discharged and freed of and
                    from all claim of your petitioner to such service or labor; that at the time of
                    said discharge said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William</persName> was</seg> of the age of <seg type="handwritten">thirty for years—</seg> and of the personal description
                        following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n1">Here describe the
                        person, so as to identify him or her; and if there be more than one slave,
                        describe each one separately.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">a stout, medium sized man, in height about five feet,
                        six inches, of dark brown <choice>
                            <orig>complection</orig>
                            <reg>complexion</reg>
                        </choice>, intelligent and, active and an excellent coachman and House
                        Servant.</seg>
                </p>

                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="cww.00504.002.jpg"/>

                <p>That your petitioner acquired <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> claim to the
                    aforesaid service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William Harrod</persName>
                    </seg> in manner following:<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n2">Here
                        state how the claim was acquired, when, from whom, and for what price or
                        consideration; and, if held under any written evidence of title, make
                        exhibit thereof, or refer to the public record where the same may be
                        found.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">by purchase of the said over a fixed term of years from
                        Mrs. <persName>Jane Turnbull</persName>—of the said city of
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName> &amp; Mrs. <persName>Sophia <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low" resp="#nnk">Krumbhaar</unclear></persName> of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                        to whom he belonged</seg>
                </p>

                <p>That your petitioner's claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William</persName>
                    </seg> was, at the time of said discharge therefrom, of the value of <seg type="handwritten">nine Hundred</seg> dollars in money.<note type="government" place="foot" xml:id="n3">Here state such facts, if any
                        there be, touching the value of the petitioner's claim to the service or
                        labor of the person, as may enhance the same, and also such facts, if any,
                        touching the moral, mental, and bodily infirmities or defects of said
                        person, as impair the value of the petitioner's claim to such service or
                        labor, and conclude such statement with an averment that the petitioner
                        knows of no other infirmities or defects of said person which impair the
                        value of petitioner's claim to such service or labor, and that he believes
                        none other to exist. If the petitioner specify no such infirmity or defect,
                        then his statement touching the value of his claim should conclude with an
                        averment that he has no knowledge of any such infirmity or defect.</note>
                    <seg type="handwritten">that said <persName>William</persName> is an excellent
                        coachman and House Servant and was worth by the month for his
                        services—at least—twenty five Dollars—and that petitioner
                        has no knowledge of any moral, mental, or bodily infirmities that in any way
                        impair the value of the said <persName>William</persName>
                    </seg>
                </p>

                <p>Your petitioner hereby declares that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> bears true
                    and faithful allegiance to the Government of the United States, and that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not borne arms against the United States in
                    the present rebellion, nor in any way given aid or comfort thereto.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">he</seg> has not brought said <seg type="handwritten">William</seg> into
                    the District of Columbia since the passage of said act of Congress; and that, at
                    the time of the passage thereof, said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William</persName>
                    </seg> was held to service or labor therein under and by virtue of your
                    petitioner's claim to such service or labor.</p>

                <p>Your petitioner further states and alleges, that <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William</persName>
                    </seg> does not originate in or by virtue of any transfer heretofore made by any
                    person who has in any manner aided or sustained the present rebellion against
                    the Government of the United States.</p>

                <p>And your petitioner prays the said Commissioners to investigate and determine the
                    value of <seg type="handwritten">his</seg> said claim to the service or labor of
                    said <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William</persName>
                    </seg> herein above set forth; and if the same be found to be valid, that they
                    appraise and apportion the value of said claim in money, and report the same to
                    the Secretary of the Treasury of the United States, in conformity to the
                    provisions of said act of Congress.</p>

                <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                        <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>J W Webb</persName>
                        </seg>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="cww.00504.003.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="billofsale" subtype="handwritten">
                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <ab>Paid $100</ab>
                    <ab><persName>Jane Turnbull</persName> &amp; <persName>Sophia
                            Krumbhaar</persName>.<lb/> to<lb/>
                        <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName>
                    </ab>
                    <ab>Bill of Sale of Negro<lb/> &amp; Deed of manumission</ab>

                    <ab>Received <date when="1860-12-11">11th December 1860</date>. To be Recorded,
                        and same day was Recorded, in Liber J. A. S. No 203, Folios 513, 514 &amp;
                        515, one of the Land Records, of <placeName>Washington County</placeName>,
                        in the <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>. And examined by,</ab>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Jno. A. Smith</persName>
                            <lb/>clerk.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="cww.00504.004.jpg"/>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Know all men by these presents that we <persName>Jane Turnbull</persName> and
                            <persName>Sophia Krumbhaar</persName> of <placeName>Washington
                            County</placeName> in the <persName>District of Columbia</persName> for
                        and in consideration of the sum of four hundred dollars current money of the
                            <placeName>United States</placeName> to wit in hand paid by
                            <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName> of said County and District at and
                        before the sealing and delivery of these presents, the receipt whereof is
                        hereby acknowledged, have granted bargained and sold, and by these presents
                        do hereby grant bargain and sell unto him the said <persName>Joseph W.
                            Webb</persName>, his executors, administrations and assigns for the term
                        or period of three years and nine months from the date hereof our colored
                        salve <persName>William</persName> aged about thirty five years. To Have and
                        To Hold the said slave <persName>William</persName> unto him the said
                            <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName>, his executors administrators and
                        assigns for and during the said term a period of three years and nine months
                        from the date hereof—at the expiration of which said term of three
                        years and nine months it is expressly understood and agreed by and between
                        the parties hereto that the said <choice>
                            <orig>coloured</orig>
                            <reg>colored</reg>
                        </choice> man <persName>William</persName> shall be manumitted, set free and
                        forever discharged from all manner of servitude or service to our heirs,
                        executors, administrators and assigns and from all persons whatever, and do
                        hereby declare him to be free and manumitted from and after the expiration
                        of the said term of three years and nine months as aforesaid</p>

                    <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="cww.00504.005.jpg"/>

                    <p>In Witness whereof We have hereunto subscribed our names and affixed our
                        seals this <date when="1860-07-23">23rd.—day of July eighteen hundred
                            and sixty.</date></p>

                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Jane Turnbull</persName> seal</signed>
                        <signed><persName>Sophia Krumbhaar</persName> seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <p>Signed sealed &amp; delivered in the presence of</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Sam'l Drury</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>W. B. Cobb</persName></signed>
                        <lb/>as to Mrs. <persName>Jane Turnbull</persName>'s signature.
                                <signed><persName>Wm. H. Butler</persName></signed>
                        <signed><persName>L R Krumbhaar</persName></signed><lb/> as to
                            <persName>Sophia Krumbhaar</persName>'s signing </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline><placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>
                        <placeName>Washington County</placeName>, to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>On this <date when="1860-07-23">23rd day of July 1860</date>, before the
                        subscriber a Justice of the Peace in and for the County and District
                        aforesaid personally appears <persName>Jane Turnbull</persName> party to the
                        foregoing instrument of writing, and acknowledges the same to be her act and
                        deed for the purposes therein mentioned.</p>
                    <closer>Acknowledged before <signed><persName>Sam'l Drury</persName> JP
                            seal</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section" subtype="handwritten">
                    <dateline>State of <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName><lb/> City and county of
                            <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> to wit:</dateline>
                    <p>On the <date when="1860-07-25">twenty fifth day of July 1860</date>, before
                        the subscriber a justice of the Peace in and for the county and State
                        aforesaid, personally appeared <persName>Sophia Knumbhaar</persName> party
                        to the foregoing instrument of writing and acknowledged the same to <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="cww.00504.006.jpg"/> be her act and deed, for
                        the purposes therein mentioned.</p>
                    <p>In witness whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and seal this day and date
                        above written.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>Wm. H. Butler</persName> E. D. J. P. seal
                            <lb/>Alderman</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="cww.00504.007.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="statement" subtype="mixed">
                <dateline><hi rend="bold">State of Pennsylvania</hi>, <hi rend="italic"><placeName>COUNTY OF PHILADELPHIA</placeName>, ss.</hi></dateline>
                <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>John P. McFadden</persName></seg> Prothonotary of the District
                    Court of said County, Do CERTIFY, that <seg type="handwritten">
                        <persName>William H Butler</persName></seg> before whom the annexed <seg type="handwritten">acknowledgment</seg> was mad, was at the time of so doing
                    an Alderman and ex officio Justice of the Peace of the <seg type="handwritten">City &amp; County</seg> of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>, duly
                    commissioned and qualified to administer oaths and affirmations, and to take
                    acknowledgments, &amp;c. and to all whose acts, as such, full faith and credit
                    are and out to be given, as well in Courts of Judicature as elsewhere, and that
                    his signature thereto is genuine.</p>
                <p>IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, I have hereunto set my hand and affixed the Seal of said
                    Court, this <date when="1860-07-25">
                        <seg type="handwritten">25th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">July</seg>
                        A.D. 18<seg type="handwritten">60</seg>
                    </date>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed><seg type="handwritten"><persName>J. P.
                        McFadden</persName></seg></signed><lb/> PROTHONOTARY.</closer>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="cww.00504.008.jpg"/>

            <div1 type="oath" subtype="mixed">
                <head type="main">[<hi rend="italic">Form of the Oath for the Verification of the
                        Petition.</hi>]</head>

                <dateline>
                    <placeName>District of Columbia</placeName>,
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington County</placeName>, ss.</hi>
                </dateline>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>I, <seg type="handwritten">
                            <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName>
                        </seg> being duly sworn, do depose and say, that all the several matters and
                        things which are set forth and stated in the foregoing petition, as of my
                        own knowledge, are true in substance and in fact; and that all the several
                        other matters and things therein set forth and stated, as from the
                        information of others, I believe to be true in substance and in fact.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>J W Webb</persName>
                            </seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>

                <div2 type="section">
                    <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1862-05-01">
                            <seg type="handwritten">27th</seg> day of <seg type="handwritten">May</seg> A.D. 1862</date>.</p>
                    <closer> (Signed by) <signed>
                            <seg type="handwritten">
                                <persName>Jno. H. Johnson</persName> J. P. seal</seg>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div2>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="cover" subtype="handwritten">
                <note type="editorial">The following note, about the filing of the petition, has
                    been imaged twice in the National Archives microfilm, but the note occurs in
                    only one place in the petition: written horizontally on the final page, the Oath
                    for the Verification.</note>
                <ab>504<lb/> Petition of<lb/>
                    <persName>Joseph W. Webb</persName><lb/> Under the "Act of <date when="1862-04-16">16th<lb/> of April 1862</date>"<lb/> manumission.</ab>
                <ab>Filed <date when="1862-05-28">May 28, 1862</date></ab>
                <ab><persName>William B Webb</persName>
                    <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                    </choice></ab>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
