<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3029">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Nunn, Jarvis</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e3029</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K.Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">45</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>miscellaneous injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>blows</term> 
                    <term>fracture of the skull resulting from blows from muskets</term>
                    <term>compound fracture of skull</term>
                    <term>blow from muzzle of musket in hands of a comrade</term>
                    <term>wound and fracture situated above and to outside of frontal eminence</term>
                    <term>coma profound, pupils dilated to almost extent of iris</term>
                    <term>depressed fracture of the frontal bone</term>
                    <term>dark coagulum on removing skull-cap</term> 
                    <term>dull frontal headache and swelling of parotid gland, no obtuseness of intellect, side of the face was œdematous</term>
                    <term>wound covered with yellow pus, beneath depressed fracture of frontal bone</term>
                    <term>anomaly of right lung, divided into only two lobes and lung emphysematous</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc2.0010">           
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="1158">Private
                        Jarvis Nunn</name>, <name type="organization" key="768">Co. A, 12th Kentucky
                        Volunteers</name>, aged 18 years, was admitted into the <name type="hospital" key="191">Old Hallowell</name> branch of the military
                    general hospitals at <name type="place">Alexandria, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1865-02-01">February 1st, 1865</date>, with a compound fracture of the skull by a blow
                    from the muzzle of a musket in the hands of a comrade. The wound and fracture
                    were situated a little above and to the outside of the left frontal eminence.
                    There was no disturbance of the mental faculties, and no especial derangement of
                    the physical functions at the date of the patient's admission, except slight
                    constipation, which was overcome by a cathartic.  On February 4th, a slight
                    febrile movement, with a dull frontal headache and swelling of the left parotid
                    gland was observed; but there was no obtuseness of intellect. On the following
                    day, the left side of the face was œdematous. The eyes, particularly
                    the left eye, being watery. The bowels were soluble. The wound had now commenced
                    to suppurate, the discharge being fetid. Cold applications were made to the
                    head.  On the 7th, the pupils were dilated, and the tongue was protruded with
                    difficulty.  On February 8th, the patient was delirious, deaf, unable to
                    articulate, or to protrude his tongue. He could be roused with difficulty from
                    his comatose state. The respiration was at 44, and the pulse thready at 115. It
                    was necessary to evacuate the urine by a catheter.  On the 9th, the coma became
                    profound; respiration 36; pulse 123; pupils widely dilated, and irresponsive to light.  On Februrary 10th, the respiration was very labored, the face and neck œdematous; the eyelids firmly
                    closed; but, when forcibly separated, revealing the pupils dilated to almost the extent of the iris. The urine and
                    fæces were discharged involuntarily. The surface was covered by a profuse sweat.
                    The radial pulse was imperceptible.  Death took place at three o'clock in the
                    afternoon of <date type="death" when="1865-02-10">February 10th, 1865</date>.   At
                    the autopsy there was found, on the left side of the sinciput, a wound covered
                    with yellow pus, and beneath, a depressed fracture of the frontal bone; and on
                    removing the skull-cap a dark coagulum. The dura mater was not inflamed, but was
                    separated from the bone for some distance around the fracture. The anomaly of
                    the right lung being divided into two lobes only was noticed. This lung was
                    emphysematous, and the bronchial mucous membrane on this side was thickened and
                    discolored. The tissue of the left lung was crepitant, but red and slightly
                    softened. The structure of the spleen was softened.   The case was reported by
                        <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name></p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
