<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31396">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Darragh, H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31396</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="cp">Chang Pang</persName>   
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">535</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds of the shoulder joint</term>
       <term>decapitations of the humerus for shot injury</term>
       <term>primary decapitations of the humerus for shot injury</term>
       <term>unsuccessful operations of primary decapitation of the humerus</term>
       <term>resection of head of humerus, performed prior to admission</term> 
       <term>gangrene</term>
       <term>emaciation</term>
       <term>wound in shoulder, for which head of humerus resected</term> 
       <term>upper extremity of humerus drawn up by muscles of glenoid cavity</term>
       <term>coracoid process of scapula fractured</term>
       <term>excision of head of humerus performed in the field</term>
       <term/>        
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#cp" when="2011-02-20">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1508.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal H. Darragh</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 106th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 40 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-18">June 18, 1864</date>, and, after treatment in the base hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name>, was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. F. Burdick</name> reported: "The above soldier had undergone resection of the head of the humerus, and I saw him but once, and that was just previous to his death. The resection was performed prior to his admission to this hospital. He was very much emaciated; respiration was difficult; the arm was gangrenous.  Death occurred <date type="death" when="1864-07-14">July 14th</date>.  There is no record of treatment or diet. <name type="person" key="xxx">Medical Cadet Strickler</name> informs me that he has had fifteen drops of tincture of chloride of  iron three times a day, and simple water-dressing to the wound. Brandy was daily administered, at frequent intervals."  The  autopsy was made, on <date type="autopsy" when="1864-07-14">the day of the patient's death</date>, by <name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name>, who contributed a pathological  preparation from the case, with the following history: "Body is very much emaciated; <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> rigidity not very well marked; height five feet seven inches. The external surface of the right arm is gangrenous for a distance of six inches above the elbow. He has had a wound in the right shoulder, for which the head of the humerus has been resected. The upper extremity of the humerus, which was denuded for about half an inch, was drawn up by the muscles in contact with the glenoid cavity. The coracoid process of right scapula was also fractured. Wound slightly gangrenous. Right lung firmly adherent to the walls of the thorax and to the diaphragm. On section of the upper and lower lobes a large amount of a frothy fluid exuded. The lining membrane of the bronchi was very much congested. Left lung healthy. Right lung weighed twenty-one ounces; left, eleven and a half ounces. Spleen very much enlarged, firm, not pulpy, weighed nine ounces. Pericardium healthy. Heart: both ventricles contained a fibrinous clot; heart weighed nine ounces. Liver weighed fifty-one ounces, small and contracted; measured seven and a half by six and a quarter and three and a half inches; mottled and convoluted, more resembling the brain than the liver."  The specimen consists² of "portions of right scapula and humerus, from a subject on whom excision of the head of the humerus had been performed in the field. The wound was gangrenous at the time of death, and the specimen shows no reparative effort."</p>
   <p>² <hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 2838, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Surgical Section</hi>, Army Medical Museum, 1866, p. 85.</p> 
   <p/>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
