<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30000">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">M——, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e36040</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="at">Alex Thomas</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">354</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>injuries of pelvis</term>
     <term>injuries of parts contained in the pelvis</term>
     <term>wounds of the genital organs</term>
     <term>wounds of the urethra</term> 
     <term>shots wounds</term>
     <term>traumatic stricture</term>
     <term>taken prisoner for eight days</term>
     <term>ball perforated apex of chest and lung, fractured scapula</term>
     <term>incontinence and retention of urine, frequent use of catheter </term>
     <term>ball passed through natis, scrotum, and urethra</term>
     <term>decreased power of arm, disability one-fourth</term>
     <term>unable to walk but short distance, disability three-fourths</term>
     <term>ball entered over middle third of clavicle, exited over middle third of scapula</term>
     <term>ball entered lateral to scrotum in groin, cut urethra, exited from natis</term>
     <term>obliged to use catheter to draw off urine, locomotion interfered with, disability total</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-09-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-08-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#at" when="2011-02-25">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1020.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Captain John M——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">79th New York Militia</name>, aged 38 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="127"><name type="BATTLE" key="6">Bull Run</name></name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-07-21">July 21, 1861</date>, and again <date type="injury" when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>. On the last occasion he was taken prisoner and remained in the hands of the enemy for eight days. He was paroled and rejoined his regiment, and was promoted major <date type="promotion" when="1862-11-17">November 17, 1862</date>, and lieutenant-colonel <date type="promotion" when="1863-02-17">Febuary 17th, 1863</date>. He was mustered out at the expiration of his term of service, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-05-31">May 31, 1864</date>, and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. E. MacDonald</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, formerly of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">79th New York</name>, <date type="pension" when="1865-07-05">July 5, 1865</date>, makes the following statement: "At the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="6">Bull Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-07-21">July 21, 1861</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. M——</name> received a very serious wound from musket ball, which perforated the apex of the left chest and lung and fractured the left scapula. He made a rapid recovery, however, from so severe a wound, and reported for duty in an extremely short time."   *   *   "At the second battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull Run</name>, <date when="1862-08-30">August 30, 1862</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. M——</name> received a wound from a minié ball, which passed through the right natis, the scrotum, and the urethra. On this occasion, the nature of the wound did not permit him to escape from the field, and he remained eight days in the hands of the enemy. Much to the surprise of many surgeons, myself among the number, he survived to be removed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and again to be of service to his regiment. I have carefully examined his condition recently, and find that he is still obliged to make frequent use of the catheter to relieve his bladder, and often suffers from both incontinence and retention of urine. It is my opinion that he will never cease to be subject to temporary difficulties of like nature."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner T.F. Smith</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1866-01-30">January 30, 1866</date>: "A ball perforated the apex of the left lung, fracturing the left scapula, in consequence of which he has not full power of the left arm; disability from this, one-fourth. Another ball passed through the right natis, scrotum, and the urethra. He is obliged to use a catheter continually in order to draw off the urine. Whenever he performs hard labor the wound breaks open. He is unable to walk but a short distance. Disability from this, three-fourths."  <name type="person" key="xxx">The same examiner</name>, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-17">September 17, 1873</date>, reports: "Ball entered over middle third of the left clavicle and made exit over the inner border of the middle third of the left scapula; no disability. Ball entered to the left of the scrotum in the groin, cutting the urethra, and made its exit from the right natis. He is obliged to use a catheter to draw off the urine; locomotion considerably interfered with; disability total."  This pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1873-12-04">December 4, 1873</date>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
