<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41332">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Hilgert, Jacob</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41332</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">186-187</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Columbian College Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>diarrhœa and consumption</term>
       <term>chronic bronchitis</term>
       <term>severe cough, large quantities of muco-purulent <choice><orig>sputa</orig><reg>sputum</reg></choice> streaked with blood</term>
       <term><choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion over upper third of lung, tubular respiration heard</term>
       <term>both lungs contained numerous minute tubercles, cavity about size of orange near apex of lung</term>
       <term>large and puckered cicatrix-like depression on surface of upper lobe of lung</term>
       <term>pleuritic adhesions</term>
       <term>tubercular ulcers of both small and large intestines, mesenteric glands enlarged</term>
       <term>upper lobe of lung shows large number of minute tubercles, cavity size of orange at top of lobe</term>
       <term>upper lobe of left lung presented large and much puckered cicatrix-like depression on convex surface</term>
       <term>upper jejunum presented three small tubercular ulcers</term>
       <term>upper ileum presented large oval tubercular ulcer</term>
       <term>lower ileum presented Peyer's patch as seat of three small tubercular ulcers</term>
       <term>lower ileum, ileocæcal valve, and part of cæcum had transverse ulcer just above valve</term>
       <term>cæcum thickened and ulcerated</term>
       <term>vermiform appendix deeply ulcerated</term>
       <term>transverse colon presented deep ulcers</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>The notes of the next case were forwarded, with the specimens, from <name type="hospital" key="157"><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>OLUMBIAN <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>OLLEGE <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="126">Surgeon Thomas R. Crosby</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 434.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Jacob Hilgert</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company E, 104th Pennsylvania volunteers</name>; admitted from <name type="hospital" key="164">Stone hospital</name> <date type="admit" when="1865-01-10">January 10, 1865</date>.  Diarrhœa and consumption.  [This man is borne on the register of <name type="hospital" key="164">Stone hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-12-09">December 9, 1864</date>—chronic bronchitis—sent to <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Columbian hospital</name> <date type="transfer" when="1865-01-10">January 10th</date>.]  He had a distressing diarrhœa, together with a severe cough, and expectorated large quantities of muco-purulent <choice><orig>sputa</orig><reg>sputum</reg></choice> streaked with blood. There was <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion over the upper third of the right lung, and tubular respiration was heard on both sides.  Treatment: Cod-liver oil with six ounces of whiskey daily.  Diet: Milk, beefsteak and toast. The cod-liver oil appeared to increase his diarrhœa, and, January 16th, fusel-oil in five-drop doses was substituted, to be taken in his whiskey.  January 25th: The expectoration is more copious, and his strength is failing; appetite very poor; he has four or five stools daily.  He died <date type="death" when="1865-02-06">February 6th</date>.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. D. Vosburgh</name>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1865-02-07">fourteen hours after death</date>: Both lungs contained numerous minute tubercles; near the apex of the right lung there was a cavity about the size of an orange, and on the surface of the upper lobe of the left lung a large and much puckered cicatrix-like depression was observed; there were pleuritic adhesions on the right side. Both small and largo intestines presented tubercular ulcers. The mesenteric glands were enlarged.   [Nos. 480 to 487, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  No. 480 is the upper lobe of the right lung, the cut surface of which shows a large number of minute tubercles. At the top of the lobe there is a cavity the size of an orange, with distinct firm walls.  No. 481 is the upper lobe of the left lung, presenting on its convex surface a large and much puckered cicatrix-like depression.  No. 482 is a portion of the upper part of the jejunum, presenting three small tubercular ulcers.  No. 483 is from the upper part of the ileum of the same patient, and presents a large oval tubercular ulcer the long diameter of which is transverse to the gut.  No. 484 is from the lower part of the ileum of the same patient, and presents a Peyer's patch which is the seat of three small tubercular ulcers.  No. 485 is the lower extremity of the ileum, with the ileocæcal valve and part of the cæcum; there is a transverse ulcer just above the valve, and the cæcum is thickened and ulcerated.  No. 486 is the vermiform appendix, which is deeply ulcerated.  No. 487 is a portion of the transverse colon, which is thickened, and presents a number of deep ulcers.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
