<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e21769">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Martin, M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e21769</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">583</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot wound of foot, penetrated ankle joint</term>
     <term>ball entered in front midway between malleoli, exited posteriorly above external
      malleolus, comminuting lower ends of tibia and fibula</term>
     <term>amputation decided upon, patient declined all operative interference</term>
     <term>patient had chill each day</term>
     <term>lower extremities of both bones of leg shattered</term>
     <term>yellow face and conjunctivæ</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-12">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 830.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal M.
     Martin</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. D, 28th Massachusetts</name>, aged 27
    years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="79">Hatcher's Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-25">March 25, 1865</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon F. M.
     Hammond</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">126th New York</name>, reported his
    admission to the field hospital of the 1st division, Second Corps, with "shot wound of left
    foot" <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-04">Ten days after the reception of the
     injury</date> the patient was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas
     Hospital</name>, Washington, whence <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon W. F.
     Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the
    pathological specimen shown in the annexed wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 334), with
    the following history: "The wound penetrated the ankle joint. The ball entered in front,
    about midway between the malleoli, and made its exit posteriorly and a little above the external
    malleolus, comminuting in its course the lower ends of the tibia and fibula. There was marked
    constitutional disturbance, headache, high fever, rapid pulse, and loss of appetite. But little
    swelling or inflammation in the joint, however, took place, and not much discharge. The day
    subsequent to the patient's admission the joint was carefully examined, when both bones were
    found to be much comminuted and amputation was decided as the only resort giving a fair chance
    of recovery. The patient, however, positively declined all operative interference. Towards
    evening he had a slight chill. On April 7th there was nausea and vomiting, and on the following
    day he had three chills, followed by fever and profuse sweats. Nausea and vomiting continued,
    the fluid ejected being tinged with bile; the discharge from both wounds, however, retained its
    healthy appearance. On April 9th, 10th, 11th, and 12th the patient had a chill each day, and on
    the latter day there was marked yellowness of the face and conjunctivæ; slight cough and
    delirium. On April 13th there was another chill; pulse 110, respiration 38; severe pleuritic
    pain in the right side of the chest. Death occurred on <date type="death" when="1865-04-14">April 14, 1865</date>. Rigor mortis was well marked at the autopsy, also the yellow hue of the
    skin and conjunctivæ. On opening the thoracic cavity nearly a pint of intensely yellow
    fluid was found in the right pleural cavity. Each lobe of the right lung presented numerous
    patches varying in size from half an inch to two inches in diameter, most of which on incision
    gave exit to pus; the left lung contained similar patches in both lobes. The spleen was much
    softened, being almost semifluid in consistence; liver enlarged but apparently healthy; other
    thoracic and abdominal viscera normal." The specimen (No. 253) consists of the <choice>
     <orig>astragalus</orig>
     <reg>talus</reg>
    </choice> and the lower halves of the tibia and fibula of the injured limb, the extremities of
    both bones of the leg being shattered.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001648.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 334.—Shattered bones of the left ankle joint. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 253.</head>
   </figure>
   <p/>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
