<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41308">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Butler, Walter</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41308</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">185</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Carver Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>typhoid fever</term>
       <term>petechiæ on abdomen</term>
       <term>diarrhœa</term>
       <term>pleural cavity obliterated by old adhesions</term>
       <term>anterior mediastinum emphysematous</term>
       <term>glands of Peyer congested and solitary follicles enlarged below middle of ileum</term>
       <term>mucous membrane thickened increasingly from transverse to descending colon, sigmoid flexure, and rectum</term>
       <term>follicular ulcers throughout colon, transverse colon especially, coalesced into large eroding excavations</term>
       <term>adherent pseudomembrane between ulcers</term>
       <term>pin-head enlargement of solitary follicles and slightly thickened Peyer's patches in ileum</term>
       <term>follicular ulcers extended into excavations exposing muscular coat, in transverse colon especially</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>The notes were forwarded, with the specimens, to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> from <name type="hospital" key="167"><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ARVER <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C., <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon Oliver A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 427.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Walter Butler</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company B, 56th Massachusetts volunteers</name>; admitted from the field hospital of the 1st Division, 9th Corps, <date type="admit" when="1864-07-05">July 5, 1864</date>.  Typhoid fever.  The patient was considerably emaciated; petechiæ were seen on his abdomen; his tongue was thickly coated in its centre with a dark fur; pulse about 120 per minute; slight diarrhœa. These symptoms seemed to yield readily to the ordinary treatment of typhoid fever.  About July 20th, he was able to walk about the ward, slowly convalescing. From imprudence in eating and drinking he was again, July 25th, attacked with severe diarrhœa, which caused him to sink rapidly. He had now anorexia; red, dry tongue; pulse about 80.  Treatment: Opiates and astringents to relieve the diarrhœa; brandy.  Diet: Boiled milk, beef, beef-essence, &amp;c.  He became greatly emaciated, and died <date type="death" when="1864-08-02">August 2d</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-08-02">four hours after death</date>: Emaciation great; rigor mortis slight. The right pleural cavity was obliterated by old adhesions; the areolar tissue in the anterior mediastinum was emphysematous. The lungs contained much black pigment, and their upper portion was congested. The right side of the heart contained a large fibrinous clot which adhered firmly to the tricuspid valve; there was no clot in the left side; the valves were healthy; the pericardium contained half an ounce of fluid. The liver appeared to be normal; the gall-bladder was nearly filled with bile. The spleen was about the normal size, pale, and very firm. The kidneys were normal. The suprarenal capsules were dark colored. The walls of the stomach were thin and pale. The small intestine appeared healthy down to about the middle of the ileum, below which the glands of Peyer were congested, the congestion increasing in intensity downward; the solitary follicles of the lower portion were enlarged. The mucous membrane of the transverse colon was thickened and softened, the thickness greatly increasing in the descending colon, sigmoid flexure, and rectum; the thickened membrane presented a peculiar spongy appearance; there were follicular ulcers throughout the colon, which, in the transverse colon especially, had coalesced into large eroding excavations.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon O. P. Sweet</name>.   [Nos. 356 to 359, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  No. 356 is a portion of the ileum, with pin-head enlargement of the solitary follicles and two very slightly thickened Peyer's patches.  No. 357 is from the ascending, No. 358 from the transverse, and No. 359 from the descending, colon; in these specimens the intestinal walls are somewhat thickened, and there are numerous follicular ulcers, which, in the transverse colon especially, have extended into irregularly oval excavations exposing the muscular coat; between the ulcers there is some adherent pseudomembrane.]</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
