<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e24611">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Sanford, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e24611</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">642-643</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>miscellaneous injuries</term> 
       <term>contusions and sprains</term>
       <term>accidentally hurt in back</term>
       <term>inflammation of kidneys and tissues of lumbar region</term> 
       <term>difficult to stand</term> 
       <term>partial paralysis of superior and inferior extremities, bowels, and bladder</term> 
       <term>disability permanent, incapacitates for all manual labor</term>
       <term>irregularity of the bowels, constipation or diarrhœa</term>
       <term>inability to retain urine, at times inability to pass it</term> 
       <term>requires passing of catheter once or twice a week</term> 
       <term>unable to feed, dress, or undress himself</term>
       <term>pain in back and legs, with loss of sleep</term>
       <term>emaciation</term>        
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-19">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 941.—<hi rend="italic">Contusion of the spine.</hi>—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. Sanford</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 32d Massachusetts</name>, aged 37 years, was accidentally hurt in the back on <date type="injury" when="1862-09-12">September 12, 1862</date>. He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="214">Fairfax Seminary Hospital</name> <date type="admit" when="1862-09-13">the following day</date>, where he was discharged from service on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1862-12-08">December 8, 1862</date>.  <name type="person" key="411">Surgeon D. P. Smith</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, certified to the following disability:  "An injury of the lumbar vertebræ which has resulted in inflammation of the kidneys and of the tissues of the lumbar region, rendering it difficult for him to stand."  The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Boston Examining Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1862-11-27">November 27, 1862</date>:  "Partial paralysis of the superior and inferior extremities, bowels, and bladder from injury to spine. The paralysis of the inferior extremities is no worse than a year ago, perhaps the legs are a trifle smaller. The paralysis of the arms has increased somewhat. The disability is permanent and incapacitates him for all manual labor."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. W. H. Wallace</name>, of <name type="place">East Boston</name>, testified, <date type="pension" when="1880-03-29">March 29, 1880</date>:  "The pensioner is suffering from an injury of the spine, partial paralysis of the upper and lower extremities, great irregularity of the bowels
    sometimes obstinate constipation, at others diarrhœa; also inability to retain the urine and at times inability to pass it. He requires the passing of a catheter once and often twice a week, and is unable to feed, dress, or undress himself fully two-thirds
    of the time. There is emaciation and loss of sleep from pain in back and legs. He will never be any better."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
