<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e15965">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Eastlick, George W.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  </edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e15965</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor>
                                                  <name>Center for Digital Research in the
                                                  Humanities</name>
                                                  <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                                  </distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl>
                                                  <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                                                  <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                                                  <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                                  <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                                  <date when="1870">1870</date>
                                                  <biblScope type="page">231</biblScope>
                                                  </bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term> 
                                                    <term>removal of fragments after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                                                    <term>recovered after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                                                    <term>defective vision</term>
                                                    <term>partial or complete loss of vision</term>
                                                    <term>conoidal ball fractured and depressed left parietal eminence</term>
                                                    <term>ball fractured both tables of skull and split upon sharp edge of outer table</term>
                                                    <term>rendered insensible by blow for four hours</term>
                                                    <term>mental confusion, loss of memory</term>
                                                    <term>deficiency in strength and sensibility of right arm, persistent and increasing contraction of fingers</term>
                                                    <term>after operation sensibility returned to right arm and right hand recovered strength</term>
                                                    <term>vertigo</term>                                                    
                                                    <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>                                                                  
                                                    <term>vision in left eye is impaired and intolerant of light</term>                                                             
                                                    <term>disability rated two-thirds and permanent</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>                                                
                                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="xx">Private George W. Eastlick</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. C., 29th
                                                                                Ohio Volunteers</name>, aged 30 years, was wounded at the
                                                  battle of <name type="battle" key="xx">Port Republic, Virginia</name>, <date type="operation" when="1862-06-09"><date type="injury" when="1862-06-09">June 9th,
                                                                                1862</date></date>, by a conoidal ball, which fractured and
                                                  depressed the cranium at the left parietal
                                                  eminence. He was rendered insensible by the blow,
                                                  and remained in that state for about four hours,
                                                  when he recovered sufficiently to leave the field.
                                                  The ball, which had fractured both tables of the
                                                  skull and split upon the sharp edge of the outer
                                                  table for two-thirds of its length, was readily
                                                  removed on the field.  On <date type="admit" when="1862-06-15">June 15th</date>, he was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="94">Cliffburne Hospital</name>, Washington. His
                                                  general condition was good, but there was
                                                  considerable mental confusion, loss of memory,
                                                  marked deficiency in the strength and sensibility
                                                  of the right arm, slight but persistent and daily
                                                  increasing contraction of the fingers. The wound
                                                  looked healthy and was granulating. Absolute quiet
                                                  was enjoined, and laxation and light diet ordered;
                                                  but the unfavorable symptoms evidently increased.  On <date type="operation" when="1862-06-23">June 23d</date>, ether was administered, and <name type="person" key="294">Assistant
                                                    Surgeon John S. Billings</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, made a <choice><orig>crucial</orig><reg>cruciate</reg></choice> incision over the seat of injury, cut away a small
                                                  portion of the sound bone with the bone-gouge
                                                  forceps; then introduced the elevator into the
                                                  opening, and removed the depressed portions of
                                                  bone, comprising a circle of about three-fourths
                                                  of an inch in diameter. <date type="injury" when="1862-06-23">Half an hour after the
                                                  operation</date> it was found that sensibility had
                                                  returned to the right arm, and that the right
                                                  hand, which had previously been powerless, had
                                                  recovered its strength. No untoward symptoms
                                                  supervened, and the wound, which was kept open for
                                                  two weeks to permit the free escape of pus, healed
                                                  rapidly.  On July 9th, while holding a candle and
                                                  assisting in dressing a patient, he was suddenly
                                                  seized with vertigo, and was immediately compelled
                                                  to lie down. A full saline cathartic was given,
                                                  and low diet ordered. No further cerebral symptoms
                                                  occurred, and by the 20th he was perfectly
                                                  convalescent.  He was discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1862-08-05">August 5th, 1862</date>.  The case is reported by <name type="person" key="294">Assistant Surgeon J. S.
                                                                  Billings</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>  In <date type="pension" when="1867-09">September, 1867</date>, <name type="person">Pension
                                                                                  Examiner John F. Ray</name> reports that the vision in
                                                  the left eye is impaired and intolerant of light.
                                                  His disability is rated two-thirds and permanent.</p>                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
