<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18722">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Morse, William B.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e18722</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
          Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United
            States Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
            Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">434</biblScope></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the spine</term> 
          <term>gunshot wounds of the spine</term>
          <term>fractures of the dorsal vertebræ</term>
          <term>posture simulating pleurosthotonos</term>
          <term>contusion of one side</term>
          <term>concussion of spinal cord</term>
          <term>numbness and tingling in arm, thigh, and leg</term>
          <term>curious limp in walking gait</term>  
          <term>deficiency of power of extensor muscles to support the body</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private William B. Morse</name>, <name type="organization">Co. A, 40th New York Volunteers</name>, aged 20 years, was
        admitted to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-06-15">June 15th, 1863</date>, from the field hospital of the
        Army of the Potomac, at Potomac Creek. He said that he had been injured in the battle of
        <name type="BATTLE" key="257">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3d, 1863</date>, by the explosion of a shell; that he was lying on the ground
        on his right side, in line of battle, under a heavy artillery fire, when something hit him
        violently on the left side and knocked him senseless. When he came to, his mouth was filled
        with clotted blood. He spat blood for two days, with a cough which had not yet entirely left
        him. His left side was swelled up, and was tender from the armpit all the way down to the
        hip. He could not move the left leg at all, the thigh included, and had but partial use of
        the right one. Sensation also was nearly abolished in the left lower extremity. The motion
        and sensation of the left upper extremity were considerably impaired. He had not had any
        difficulty in holding or voiding his urine. He stated that the left side appeared to be
        badly bruised, but the skin was not broken. When admitted to hospital, the partial paralysis
        still continued and was most marked in the left lower extremity. He had dyspnœa and
        cough, but no expectoration. The left thorax was much shrunken and tender under pressure.
        The left shoulder had fallen down a good deal below the level of its fellow on the opposite
        side. There was lateral curvature of the spine, and his posture in bed bore a strong
        resemblance to that produced by pleurosthotonos of the left side. Nothing abnormal was
        detected by auscultation and percussion. There was no swelling or ecchymosis of the injured
        side, or evidence that the ribs had been fractured. He complained of much soreness in the
        walls of the left thorax and left side generally, and the motion of the left arm seemed to
        be much impaired on that account. His intellect was clear, and he presented no symptoms
        whatever diagnostic of a cerebral lesion. He was thin and rather pale; bowels constipated.
        He was manifestly suffering from the consequences of extensive contusion of the left side
        and concussion of the spinal cord. Dry cups were ordered to be applied daily over the spine
        and the bowels to be kept open with laxatives. He was allowed full diet. The dry cupping
        seemed to benefit him very much and the paralysis was rapidly disappearing. By <date type="injury" when="1863-08-15">August 15th</date>,
        he was up and going about on crutches. The cups were discontinued, and acetate of strychnia
        prescribed in small doses. This remedy was discontinued at the end of a month, as it
        appeared to do him but little, if any, good. During the fall and winter he continued to
        improve slowly, and, by the <date type="injury" when="1864-03">middle of March</date>, threw his crutches aside, preferring to walk
        with the aid of a cane only. <date type="injury" when="1864-04-10">April 10th, 1864</date>: He stands erect; the falling down of the left
        shoulder, the shrinking of the left side, and the posture simulating pleurosthotonos have
        entirely disappeared. The left thigh is a trifle smaller and more flaccid than the right
        one. At times, he has a feeling of numbness and tingling in the left arm, but none in the
        right, and the same abnormal sensations in the left thigh and leg, but not in the right. He
        presents a curious limp in his gait in walking. His body sinks very low on placing its
        weight on the left limb, from deficiency in the power of the extensor muscles, as compared
        with that of the flexor muscles of the limb, to support the body at its proper height in
        walking, and thus a strange hobbling is produced like that in some cases of rupture of the
        ligamentum patellae. He was discharged from service on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-04-18">April 18th, 1864</date>. </p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
