<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3564">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Morrison, William</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e3564</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">234-235</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever cases with mmore or less evidence of malarial affection</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>fever cases of Seminary Hospital, Georgetown, D. C.</term>
                                        <term>boil appeared on forehead</term>
                                        <term>rose-colored spots appeared on face</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00074">
                        
                        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 74.—<hi rend="italic"><choice><orig>Dulness</orig><reg>Dullness</reg></choice> and drowsiness for a day or two;
                                                diarrhœa and dry skin persisting;
                                                rose-colored spots and vibices; tongue flabby and
                                                coated yellow; moist skin, and convalescence on 38th
                                                day.</hi>—<name type="person" key="532">Private William Morrison</name>, <name type="organization" key="633">Co. E, 1st Pa.
                                                Rifles</name>; age 38; had a chill about <date type="injury" when="1861-10-01">Oct. 1,
                                                        1861</date>, followed by fever and perspiration, slight headache,
                                        anorexia and some cough. He was admitted on <date type="admit" when="1861-10-10">the 10th</date> as a case
                                        of typhoid fever. Next day he was dull and drowsy, but
                                        without any sign of congestion about the face; his pulse was
                                        80 and feeble, skin hot and dry, tongue slightly moist, red
                                        at the tip and edges and heavily coated with yellowish fur
                                        in the centre; he had intense abdominal tenderness, but only
                                        one stool during the previous twenty-four hours. Emulsion of
                                        turpentine and tincture of iron were ordered in repeated
                                        doses. On the 12th the eruption appeared; the skin was of
                                        natural temperature, the tongue slightly moist but coated
                                        with yellowish fur, and the appetite good; two stools were
                                        passed, and the patient had some abdominal tenderness and
                                        cough. He slept well and next day was brighter mentally.
                                        From this time till the end of the month his general
                                        condition remained unchanged. The tongue was flabby and
                                        always more or less yellow-furred; the appetite usually
                                        good; the bowels moved from one to seven times daily, with
                                        general and occasionally umbilical and left iliac
                                        tenderness, and with slight tympanites on the 10th and 29th;
                                        the skin, usually hot and dry, showed some vibices on the
                                        19th and 20th; on the 22d rose-colored spots appeared on the
                                        face and did not fade until the 29th, when some epistaxis
                                        occurred; there was more or less cough with some mucous
                                        expectoration; the pulse beat generally about 75 per minute.
                                        On the 30th quinine was ordered in three-grain doses every
                                        two hours. Next day the pulse was lowered from 80 to 60, and
                                        the diarrhœa increased from one to seven stools;
                                        otherwise the patient's condition appeared unaltered.
                                        Astringents were given, and in the course of four or five
                                        days the diarrhœa became lessened to one or two
                                        stools daily. On November 4 a boil appeared on the patient's
                                        forehead. On the 7th the skin is recorded for the first time as being moist; pulse 75;
                                        tongue cleaning; appetite good; bowels tender and moved
                                        twice. Cod-liver oil and wine were ordered on the 10th. The
                                        daily record of symptoms ceases on the 11th. The patient was
                                        transferred to <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1861-12-20">December 20</date>. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
