<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e22026">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Brennan, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e22026</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">588-589</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations at the ankle joint</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint</term>
       <term>excisions at the ankle joint for shot injury</term> 
       <term>intermediary excisions at the ankle joint</term> 
       <term>accidental wound of ankle joint</term>
       <term>ball entered ankle posterior and inferior to internal malleolus, ruptured capsular ligaments, cut between articular surfaces of the tibia and <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>, lodged within joint</term>
       <term>resection of ankle joint</term>        
       <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-13">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 846.— "<name type="person" key="xxx">Private J. Brennan</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 16th West Virginia</name>, aged 18 years, was admitted to hospital at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name> on <date type="admit" when="1862-10-06">October 6, 1862</date>, with a wound of the right ankle joint, received accidentally the night previous. On examination it was found
    that a pistol ball had entered the ankle three-fourths of an inch posterior and inferior to the internal malleolus, passed forward
    and upward, rupturing the capsular ligaments and cutting its way between the articular surfaces of the tibia and <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice> and
    lodging within the joint. He was in good health at the time of the injury and evidently suffered no great amount of pain. He
    was freely purged and a light and nutritious diet enjoined. The question of procedure was exceedingly perplexing. The single
    small bullet hole and the slight local and constitutional symptoms presented a case apparently well adapted to the performance
    of resection, while the want of success attending this operation was a serious argument against its performance. It was decided,
    however, to resect the joint, which was done on <date type="operation" when="1862-10-09">October 9th</date>. The patient being under the influence of chloroform, two lateral
    incisions were made about four inches in length, terminating three-fourths of an inch below the malleoli. The lips being drawn
    asunder, a chain saw was then applied to the tibia and about one-third of an inch of the extremity removed; the extremity of
    the fibula, on a level with the tibia, was removed through the opposite opening, and through the same aperture a portion of the
    articular surface of the <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice> was taken away. By this method the division of the extensor tendons and of the anterior
    tibial artery was avoided. The posterior tibial was uninjured. The incisions were closed with silver wire sutures, and the
    bones were held in apposition by means of adhesive strips extending down the sides of the leg and embracing the sole of the
    foot. Lateral splints of binders board were applied. The hæmorrhage was trifling, no vessels having to be tied.  On the following day there was considerable febrile excitement; pulse 100; skin hot and dry. Small doses of antimony and morphia
    were administered.  On the next day the patient appeared more comfortable but complained of slight pain; pulse diminished in
    force and frequency.  On October 12th the patient was comfortable; skin cool and moist; pulse 80 per minute. Discontinued
    the medicine.  On October 13th suppuration was established and the patient was comfortable; limb suspended by means of
    Smith's anterior splint; lateral splints retained. From this time the dressings were daily removed.  By October 16th the patient
    was doing well and the wound was discharging freely; diet light, though nutritious.  Four days later he began to take solid
    food.  On October 27th the incisions were filled with granulations. The dressings were continued to November 25th, when
    Smith's splint was removed, the lateral splint being still applied. The patient remained in bed until December 20th, when he began to move about on crutches. The lateral splints were removed in the early part of February, at which time he moved
    about freely and with little embarrassment. In dressing, the toes of the injured side were extended so as to be on a line with
    those of the sound side. The advantage of this is apparent when a shoe with a high heel is worn. The elasticity of the instep
    thus brought into play compensates in a great measure for the anchylosis."  The case is reported by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
    The subsequent records in the case show the patient was mustered out at the expiration of his term of service, <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-06-16">June 16, 1863</date>.  There is no record of his ever having applied for pension.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
