<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e20612">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Scott, G. B.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e20612</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">530</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the leg for shot injury</term>
     <term>fatal intermediary amputations in the lower third of the leg</term>
     <term>wound of ankle joint, affecting internal malleolus and bones of foot</term>
     <term>ball entered over inner malleolus, not extracted</term>
     <term>incisions over external malleolus allowed free flow of pus and daily extraction of
      fragments of bone</term>
     <term>leg amputated at lower third</term>
     <term>erysipelas, none beyond knee</term>
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>chills, two daily, with diaphoresis</term>
     <term>periosteum of fibula detached and dark green color</term>
     <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 778.—<name type="person" key="1310">Corporal G. B.
     Scott</name>, <name type="organization" key="503">Co. K, 8th New York Cavalry</name>, aged 19
    years, was wounded in the right lower extremity, at <name type="BATTLE" key="109">Beverly
     Ford</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-06-09">June 9, 1863</date>. He was conveyed to
     <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-06-10">the following
     day</date>, whence <name type="person" key="76">Surgeon G. S. Palmer</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, contributed the pathological specimen (No. 1347)
    represented in the adjoining wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 307), with the following
    description and result of the injury: "The wound was of the right ankle joint, affecting the
    internal malleolus and bones of the foot. The ball entered over the inner malleolus and was not
    extracted. Incisions with the knife were made over the external malleolus, allowing the free
    flow of pus, and fragments of bone were daily extracted. The leg was amputated at the lower
    third on <date type="operation" when="1863-06-20">June 20th</date>. The patient never recovered
    from the shock of the operation. On the second day he had a severe chill, followed by profuse
    sweating. His tongue became dry and he complained of great thirst; pulse 130; appetite
    capricious. The flaps of the stump grew whitish around the ligatures, and a watery offensive
    discharge commenced to escape from the stump. On the third day the anterior flap became tawny,
    having a decided tendency to slough, and the limb became decidedly erysipelatous. On June 24th,
    profuse diarrhœa set in and the patient complained of pain in the loins, but his mind was
    yet clear and he was in excellent spirits. The stump now had no sensation in it whatever. The
    chills followed each other in rapid succession, the patient having as many as two daily,
    followed in each case by diaphoresis. He rested well until the evening of June 29th. On the
    following day twenty-five drops of laudanum were administered, which produced a quiet slumber.
    On awakening from this he became delirious and very restless; pulse 183 and compressible;
    respiration thirty-five per minute and labored; fever intense. He died on the morning of <date type="death" when="1863-07-01">July 1, 1863</date>. The wound at no time discharged purulent
    matter, but profuse, thin, and offensive fluid, staining the dressings with a dirty blood color,
    The flaps retained their proper relations, the ligatures not loosening. No erysipelas existed
    beyond the knee, which was slightly swollen. At the <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi>
    examination the stump was found to have become blackened, the epidermis being readily detached
    from its base, and a large bleb full of brownish serum was discovered on the inner side of the
    knee. The anterior flap was perfectly black, and the muscles in the posterior flap had become a
    softened pultaceous mass. The periosteum of the fibula was detached and of a dark green color;
    the muscles were affected as far up as the union of the tibia and fibula. The anterior portion
    of the fibula and the crest of the tibia were dotted with a reddish color, the rest of the bones
    being pure white." The specimen consists of the amputated lower extremities of the bones of the
    leg, the external malleolus being broken off. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001642.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 307.—The lower portions of the bones of right leg.
      <hi rend="italic">Spec.</hi> 1347.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
