<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e35005">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Thurston, L. D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e35005</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page"/>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>struck by a fragment of shell</term>
     <term>severe but superficial wound of the integuments on the outer side</term>
     <term>areola of purple congestion</term>
     <term>abscess</term>
     <term>weary and helpless decubitus and great mental despondency</term>
     <term>severe hæmorrhage</term>
     <term>circular patch of sphacelus</term>
     <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
     <term>typhoid condition</term>
     <term>wound black and offensive</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-02-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
    and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p>In <date type="injury" when="1863-02">February, 1863</date>, a number of cases of hospital
    gangrene occurred at the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D.
    C., and were observed by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who, in a special report to the Surgeon
    General, gives the following interesting account of the pathology and treatment of the cases. In
    several instances later information has been added to the cases cited by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>: <!--<ref xml:id="n01" target="#n48" n="1" /> --></p>
   <p>"On the 26th of December, 1862, about two hundred wounded from the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg    
   </name> were received into the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>.</p>

   <p>"CASE II.—<name type="person" key="xxx">L. D. Thurston</name>, Private, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. A, I6th New Hampshire</name>, aged 42 years, was struck by a
    fragment of shell on <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>, at <name type="battle" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, which caused a severe but superficial wound of
    the integuments on the outer side of the left thigh. When seen, February 17, 1863, there was a
    wound at the middle of the thigh, on its outer aspect, three and a half inches long by two and a
    half wide, exposing the muscular tissue slightly, the surface of which was glazed and dry. On
    the <date type="operation" when="1863-02-10">10th of Februrary</date> it had been found
    desirable to open an abscess three inches below the left greater trochanter. On the 13th this
    had assumed an unhealthy look, and when I saw it on the 17th the incision made by the lancet,
    half an inch in length, was surrounded by a border of sphacelus one inch in width, and by an
    areola of purple congestion, in which there seemed to have occurred a complete stasis of the
    circulation. There was no pus, but a discharge of very fetid dark-colored serum. There was no
    swelling, ulceration, or aversion of edges of the incision, which, although mortified, remained
    as sharp as when first made. There was profound nervous prostration, which was indicated by his
    rapid, feeble, and irritable pulse: by his sallow hue; his haggard and anxious expression of
    countenance; his weary and helpless decubitus and great mental despondency. He was treated
    internally with stimulants, the most condensed and nourishing food, and citrate of iron and
    quinine; nitric acid was applied locally, followed by a weak solution of creasote, three drops
    to the ounce of water, as an antiseptic dressing. The sphacelus extended in all directions
    rapidly, unchecked by this treatment, from which I hoped little, since it was impossible to
    bring the acid into contact with the diseased tissues, although it was injected into the
    incision. The constitutional symptoms also became more grave. On the night of the 20th there was
    quite a severe hæmorrhage from the incision, oozing slowly, and very difficult to restrain,
    since it was caused by the erosion of vessels at a distance from the small incision. There was
    now a circular patch of sphacelus surrounding this small incision, three inches in diameter. On
    February 23d he was removed to the ward in the brick building. The original wound, hitherto
    unaffected, now began to be black and offensive. The sphacelus extended from these two centres
    at the rate of one inch daily, preceded by the above-mentioned areola of purple stasis. No
    treatment, local or constitutional, produced the least effect. Stimulants were given in every
    possible form, until the stomach refused to retain them. Pure nitric acid was freely applied to
    the diseased surfaces with no benefit. He fell into a typhoid condition, with muttering
    delirium, subsultus tendinum, etc., and finally expired <date type="death" when="1863-02-28">February 28th</date>. The sphacelus then
    extended from the trochanter major to three inches above the outer condyle, and from the median
    line in front to a corresponding point behind. There had never been any ulceration, but the
    tissues seemed to perish <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>. The incision made by the lancet was yet plainly seen in the
    cen tre of any extensive surface of mortification. This man was 42 years old, had had chronic
    diarrhœa, and was in a feeble state of health when wounded. No benefit was observed from
    any treatment. He took in addition to the nutrients and tonics the acid mixture with tincture of
    opium. [A wet preparation of the thigh, exhibiting the ravages of hospital gangrene, is <hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 1001 of the <hi rend="italic">8urgical Section</hi>, A. M. M.] * * *</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
