<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e17100">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Rall, Henry</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e17100</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">428-429</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the tibia and fibula</term> 
     <term>shot contusions of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recoveries after shot contusions of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot contusions of the tibia and fibula</term> 
     <term>shot wound of leg</term> 
     <term>ball passed across spine of tibia, bruised and denuded periosteum</term>
     <term>shot fracture of tibia with union and loss of bone substance</term>     
     <term>inflamed cicatrix</term>
     <term>usefulness of limb well nigh destroyed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 657.—<name type="person" key="1223">Corporal H. Rall</name>, <name type="organization" key="370">Co. D, 15th New York Heavy Artillery</name>,
     aged 22 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="96">Old Church</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-30">May 30, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon L. W. Read</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported his entrance into the field hospital of the 3d division, Fifth Corps, with "shot wound of left leg." <name type="person" key="1225">Surgeon B. B.
      Wilson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, contributed the pathological specimen (No. 4337 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>, A. M. M.), with
     the following history: "This young man was admitted to this hospital on <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-04">June 4th</date>. He had been wounded by a minié ball, which passed across
     the spine of the tibia about four inches from the head of the bone, bruising it and denuding it
     of periosteum along the track of the ball. He was somewhat debilitated when admitted, but being
     young and of good constitution, his general condition was not unfavorable. He was treated with
     applications of cold water and ice dressings to the wounded limb, and stimulating and
     supporting constitutional remedies. During the month of June and the beginning of July the limb
     was highly inflamed, and there was profuse suppuration and some sloughing in the vicinity of
     the wound; with considerable sympathy of the general system as manifested by chills, great
     debility, loss of appetite, and general febrile action. In <date type="operation" when="1864-07">the month of July</date>, deep-seated
     fluctuation having been observed in the course of the shaft of the tibia, the pus was evacuated
     by free incisions in the direction of the length of the limb, with great relief to the patient.
     The periosteum was found to be extensively separated and the shaft of the bone necrosed. During
     the months of September, October, November, and December his condition gradually improved as
     the process of formation of the involucrum and the separation of the necrosed portion went on.
     A number of cloacæ formed in the line of the incisions for liberating pus, through which the
     necrosed bone could be felt gradually becoming detached from the living portion. The limb was,
     during this time, for the most part treated with emollient poultices. About the first of
     January the upper part of the shaft of the tibia could be distinguished at the position of the
     original wound, and about March 1st, upon seizing it with a forceps the whole dead mass could
     be moved within the sheath of the investing new bone. The operation for the removal of necrosed bone was performed by <name type="person" key="1224">Surgeon A. N. Dougherty</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, on <date type="operation" when="1865-03-14">March 14, 1865</date>, by turning back the soft parts on each side from an
     incision through the centre of the cloacæ, and cutting away with the mallet and chisel
     sufficient of the new growth to permit the sequestrum to be lifted directly from its bed. It
     was found to consist of the entire shaft of the tibia from one epiphysis to the other, except
     small portions eroded by the absorbents. The after-treatment consisted of simple water dressings
     with slightly stimulating applications, and was unmarked with any noteworthy complication. On
      <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-06-06">June 6, 1865</date>, the patient was discharged on
     certificate of disability, being able to walk with ease and comfort, though the wound was not
     entirely healed. In <date type="photo" when="1865-07">July</date> a photograph was taken, of which the adjoining wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 257) is a copy. He left the hospital in <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1865-07">July</date> and returned in <date type="pension" when="1865-08">the following month</date>, asking to be employed under contract. Since that date he has been doing duty
     as chief nurse of one of the wards of this hospital, being in robust health, though his limb
     was not yet entirely healed." The specimen, consisting of a sequestrum nine inches long and eleven smaller pieces of necrosed
     bone, is shown somewhat reduced in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 1 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXXI</hi>, opposite page 428.  <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner T. F. Smith</name>,
     of <name type="place" key="xx">New York City</name>, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-22">September 22, 1873</date>, certified: "Shot fracture of left tibia, with union and great loss of bone substance, leaving a
     cicatrix over the anterior surface of the bone nine inches in length, red, unhealthy, and
     ulcerating," etc. The <name type="organization" key="xx">Brooklyn Examining Board
     </name>reported, <date type="pension" when="1877-09-08">September 8, 1877</date>: "We find an adherent, chronically inflamed cicatrix
     extending along the anterior face of the left tibia from below its head to within three inches
     of the ankle. There is tenderness on pressure. He requires the application of a bandage, and
     complains of pain in damp or cold weather. The usefulness of the limb is well nigh destroyed."
     The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-03-04">March 4, 1880</date>.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 257.—Appearance of limb fourteen months after injury.    [From a photograph.]</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001822.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  LXXI. __ TUBULAR  SEQUESTRA  AND  PIECES  OF  NECROSED  BONE  FROM  TIBIA.    Fig. 1._<name type="person" key="1223">Corporal Henry Rall</name>, <name type="organization" key="370">D. 15 New York H. A.</name>,   Spec. 4337,  A. M. M.</head>
   </figure> 
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
