<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e9218">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Backoven, Peter W.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e9218</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">385</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>   
                                        <term>Peyer's patches in lower ileum elevated, covered with small ulcerations, and some congested</term>
                                        <term>upper large intestine purple, paler towards rectum</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00183">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 183.—<name type="person" key="711">Private Peter W.
                                                Backoven</name>, <name type="organization" key="503">Co. G, 8th N. Y. Cav.</name>; age about 21;
                                        admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-08-18">Aug. 18,
                                                1863</date>; died <date type="death" when="1863-08-26">26th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: Body not much
                                        emaciated; rigor mortis great. The brain weighed fifty-one
                                        ounces and a half; the surface of the cerebellum was
                                        slightly red and the vessels of the pia mater filled with a
                                        purplish liquid; the interior of the brain was normal. The
                                        larynx and trachea were pale, the portions between the rings
                                        of a light purple hue. The œsophageal mucous
                                        membrane was pale gray in the upper part, becoming tawny or
                                        purplish further down, and considerably corrugated both
                                        longitudinally and transversely. The right lung weighed
                                        eleven ounces and a half, the left twelve ounces and a half;
                                        both were somewhat congested in their lower lobes. The heart
                                        was healthy, its right ventricle contained a fibrinous clot;
                                        the liquid of the pericardium was decidedly reddish in color
                                        and measured six drachms. The liver weighed fifty-seven
                                        ounces, its surface purple with a few scattered yellowish
                                        maculæ, its section paler than usual but firm; the
                                        mucous membrane of the stomach near the pylorus was somewhat
                                        marbled; the spleen, nineteen ounces and a half, was firm
                                        and of a chocolate color; the pancreas was normal. Peyer's
                                        patches in the lower part of the ileum were elevated, white
                                        and covered with small ulcerations, a few of the patches
                                        were congested; the large intestine was purple in its upper
                                        part, becoming paler towards the rectum. The kidneys were
                                        firm; on section a small quantity of venous blood flowed
                                        from the cut edges of the pyramids; the right supra-renal
                                        capsule was yellowish-white internally and did not contain
                                        the usual brown fluid; the left capsule was darker in color
                                        and contained a small quantity of brownish
                                                fluid.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. Harrison
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
