<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e705">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Washburn, Calvin</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2010</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e705</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
                    Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                <date>2010</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2010 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
                    this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.</title>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                    <date when="1879">1879</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">103</biblScope></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>morbid appearances observed in fatal cases</term>
                    <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term> 
                    <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
                    <term>from Baxter Hospital, Burlington, Vermont</term>
                    <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
                    <term>severe pain in abdomen</term> 
                    <term>cavity of the thorax contained a large quantity of serum</term> 
                    <term>both lungs filled with tubercles</term>                    
                    <term>cyst in liver, lower portion of right lobe</term>
                    <term>colon extensively ulcerated, nearly eaten through in two places</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2012-12-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">Stacey Berry Enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
            <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">Alyssa Olson Encoding and editing</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body>
            <p>The following case is extracted from the case-book of <hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>AXTER <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Burlington, Vermont, Acting Assistant Surgeon Samuel W. Thayer in charge:</p>
            <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 96.—<name type="person" key="77">Private Calvin Washburn</name>, <name type="organization" key="87">company K, 2d Vermont volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="transfer" when="1864-02-12">February 12, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  [This man appears on the regimental returns of the 2d Vermont as taken on sick report, <date type="admit" when="1864-01-01">January 1, 1864</date>, with chronic diarrhœa. The disease resisting treatment, he was admitted, <date type="admit" when="1864-02-02">February 2d</date>, to <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., where he was treated for the same disease, and thence transferred to this hospital.]  At the time of admission he was very much emaciated. He stated that he had suffered from chronic diarrhœa <date type="injury" when="1863-08">about six months</date>, but had improved very much while in hospital in Washington. His pulse was feeble; his tongue pale. Ordered a nutritious diet and stimulants. He apparently continued to improve, and had a good appetite. About midnight, <date type="injury" when="1864-03-29">March 29th</date>, the attending surgeon was summoned and found him complaining of a severe pain in the abdomen, respiration hurried, pulse rapid and feeble. Gave quarter of a grain of sulphate of morphia and stimulants.  Died <date type="death" when="1864-03-31">March 31st</date>, at 8 o'clock P. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-04-01">twelve hours after death</date>: The cavity of the thorax contained a large quantity of serum. There were pleuritic adhesions on the right side. Both lungs were filled with tubercles. The liver was somewhat softened, and a cyst was found in the lower portion of its right lobe. The colon was extensively ulcerated and nearly eaten through in two places.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
