<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18333">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Potter, G. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e18333</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
         <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>         
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
        <date when="1883">1883</date>
        <biblScope type="page">442</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
       <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
       <term>fatal cases of shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
       <term>ball entered outer side of leg at upper third of fibula, exit on anterior aspect, gouged tibia and fibula</term> 
       <term>tibia exposed</term>        
       <term>necrosis of tibia, middle third</term>
       <term>liver exceedingly fatty</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>
       <term>osteomyelitis of femur, middle third</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
       <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-05">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>  
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 697.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Musician G. H. Potter</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 60th Ohio</name>, aged 14 years, was wounded in the right leg, before <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-07-16">July 16, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon P. A. O'Connell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded the following description of the injury at the field hospital of the 3d division, Ninth Corps: "A ball entered the outer side of the limb about the upper third of the fibula; exit below on anterior
    aspect, gouging tibia and fibula." The wounded man was conveyed to the Depot Hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name> <date type="admit" when="1864-07-17">the day after the injury</date>,
    and <date type="transfer" when="1864-07-24">one week later</date> he was transferred to <name type="hospital" key="214">Fairfax Seminary Hospital</name>. <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge of the latter, made the following report: "On entering the hospital the lad was in fine spirits, though somewhat anæmic; wound looking well. On August 5th, the wound assumed an indolent appearance and the discharge became greater and more fetid. Bromine was thoroughly applied in the ordinary way and at first checked the progress of the disease. But the patient appeared to
    have no recuperative energy and a tendency to subcutaneous sloughing was evinced, which, by <date type="operation" when="1864-08-12">the 12th of August</date>, had increased
    so far as to necessitate the slitting up of the integuments and a second rigorous application of bromine. It was observed during
    the operation that the tibia was exposed and a superficial area of bone was being thrown off. The patient was exceedingly
    irritable, appetite capricious. The wound still presented a gluing and unhealthy appearance, and the tendency to undermining
    continued in spite of all efforts to check it. The patient gradually sank.  By <date type="injury" when="1864-09-15">September 15th</date>, violent and persistent vomiting
    came on, and from this time until the date of his death, <date type="death" when="1864-09-26">September 26, 1864</date>, he was almost entirely sustained by beef tea enemata.
    He had no chills and no discoloration of skin, and his mind at all times was clear.  Autopsy: emaciation extreme; limb not
    much swollen; foot somewhat œdematous; ulcer extending from four inches below the knee to the ankle joint; femoral vein
    healthy; internal organs all healthy except the liver, which was exceedingly fatty. The outer surface of the tibia at the middle
    third was dead and much blackened from the action of the vapor of the bromine, and the living bone around its borders was
    covered with several roughened spiculæ of bone. Upon opening the tibia the upper and lower thirds were found to be quite
    healthy, but the middle third was the seat of varied diseased action. The walls at this point were partially necrosed, of a
    greyish slate color, roughened, and so thin that at one point they appeared to be nearly destroyed. The medullary substance at
    this place was shrunken, of a blackish grey color, and closely adherent to the posterior and lateral walls of the cavity. No
    new deposit of bone was seen. The tissues both above and below this point had taken on active efforts of repair. The cavity
    of the medulla was much contracted by delicate cancelli extending from either side, and the original walls of the cavity for the
    extent of a full inch either way were vascular and thickened. The medulla lying in the diminished calibre of canal was of a
    lively red color, filled with blood, and presented all the appearance of a highly nourished medium. As above observed, no
    inflammation was noticed in either extremity of the affected bone. Upon examination of the femur an interesting appearance
    was presented. The walls of the bone were much thickened and dotted with reddish spots; the enlarged nutritious arteries and
    the periosteum were also thickened, vascular, and easily detached. When the bone was opened the upper two-thirds of the
    medulla were found to be acutely inflamed, which as usual was more intense towards the neck of the bone than elsewhere."
    The tibia and fibula of the injured leg, contributed, with the history, by <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>, constitute specimen 2633 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>
    of <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>.¹</p>
   <p>¹ <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LLEN (<hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">Remarks on the Pathological Anatomy of Osteomyelitis, with Cases.   Gunshot Wound of the Rigid Leg; phagedena; no pyæmia;</hi>
    in <hi rend="italic">American Journal Medical Sciences</hi>, 1865, Vol. XLIX, N. S., p. 44.</p>  
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
