<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31633">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Meyer, M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31633</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">92</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>ball entered near terminal extremity of eleventh rib, passing backward and slightly upward to left of spinal column</term>
       <term> fæcal matter passed from both entrance and exit wounds</term>
       <term>furloughed, did not return, recorded as deserter</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-20">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 279.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private M. Meyer</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. G, 145th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 32 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice><orig>Spottsylvania</orig><reg>Spotsylvania</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-10">May 10, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball. He was received into the field hospital of the Second Corps on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-12">May 12th</date>, and, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-13">the 13th</date>, he was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="512">3d division hospital</name> at <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria</name>.  <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reports the case as follows: "Ball entered near the terminal extremity of the eleventh rib, passing backward and slightly upward, and one and one-fourth inches to the left of the spinal column. On admission, fæcal matter was passing from both entrance and exit wounds; the bowels were constipated, and there was considerable pain in the regions of injury; anodynes were administered; the appetite was poor; liquid diet was prescribed, and detergent dressings were applied to the wound.  On May 19th, an enema of warm water and oil was given, and the bowels moved several times; anodynes were continued, with liquid diet; dressings the same. No further movement of the bowels occurred till May 23d; bowels then quite relaxed; lead and opium pill given May 24th; bowels checked, and no more movement until May 27th; an enema was administered, and the bowels moved freely; anodynes were continued, with liquid diet; bowels then moved nearly every day.  May 28th, several small pieces of bone came out at the posterior opening of the wound.  June 1st, no discharge of fæcal matter from wound.  June 3d, bowels relaxed; lead and opium pills given, one every four hours, until the diarrhœa was checked.  June 5th, bowels regular; patient suffering less pain; appetite quite good.  June 10th, a little gas escaped from the bowels through the external wound; same treatment continued.  June 15th, a very little fæcal matter came out at the wound; anodynes and liquid diet continued; bowels regular.  July 1st, Up to this time no more fæcal matter or gas had escaped from the bowels; patient feeling pretty well, and appetite good, requiring little opiate medicine.  July 11th, a piece of bone made its appearance at the anterior opening, and was taken out, one-half inch in length, one-fourth in breadth, and of the thickness of the rib.  July 20th, the patient was doing well, appetite good, and some solid food was allowed; bowels regular; slight suppuration from wound. The patient was able to go about the house and yard.  September 1st, continued to improve."  <date type="furlough" when="1864-09-09">September 9th</date>, furloughed for thirty days, and, not returning, was recorded as a deserter <date type="desertion" when="1864-10-20">October 20, 1864</date>.  He is not a pensioner.</p>          
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
