<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e6473">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Duryea, William</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2011</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e6473</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName></note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1888">1888</date>
     <biblScope type="page">344</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>post-mortem records</term>
     <term>continued fevers</term>
     <term>typhoid fever</term>
     <term>condition of Peyer's patches not stated, ileum or small intestine ulcerated and large intestine affected</term>
     <term>injuries of the upper extremities</term>
     <term>gunshot flesh wound of forearm</term>
     <term>large ulcers of lower ileum</term>
     <term>large ulcers surrounded by red areolæ and penetrating to the muscular coat near ileo-cæcal valve</term>
     <term>solitary follicles slightly enlarged in mucous membrane of large intestine</term>
     <term>mesenteric glands enlarged</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
   <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00048">
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 48.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private William Duryea</name>, <name type="organization" key="89">Co. I, 109th N. Y.</name>; age 21; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-05-14">May 14, 1864</date>, with a gunshot flesh wound of the left forearm, which healed kindly.  On <date type="furlough" when="1864-05-18">the 18th</date> he was furloughed for thirty days, and on his return, June 18, he was placed on light hospital duty, his wound unfitting him as yet for active service.  On <date type="injury" when="1864-07-28">July 28</date> he was taken with headache and
    nocturnal delirium; his pulse 100 and his tongue coated with a dark fur. A few days later some
    difficulty of breathing was noted, with slight diarrhœa and twitchings of the tendons, the
    delirium having meanwhile become constant.  His condition remained unchanged, but for progressive
    weakness, until <date type="death" when="1864-08-07">August 7</date>, when he died.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1864-08-07">six hours after death</date>: The lungs were congested. The
    heart was pale and contained no clots. The liver was of normal size but congested; the gall
    bladder filled with viscid bile; the spleen dark-colored, slightly enlarged and congested; the
    kidneys normal. The mucous membrane of the stomach was light-colored, thickened and softened.
    The lining membrane of the small intestine was soft and somewhat thickened down to the lower
    portion of the ileum, in which there were large ulcers at different points some distance from
    each other; near the ileo-cæcal valve it was greatly thickened and congested, and presented very
    large ulcers surrounded by red areolæ and penetrating to the muscular coat. The mucous membrane
    of the large intestine was greatly congested and its solitary follicles slightly enlarged. The
    mesenteric glands were enlarged.  [<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 352, Med. Sect., <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, ulceration of ileum, was obtained from
    this case.]—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="589">Act. Ass't Surg. O. P. Sweet</name>,
      <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
