<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e14416">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Ruffin, Thomas</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  </edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e14416</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor>
                                                  <name>Center for Digital Research in the
                                                  Humanities</name>
                                                  <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                                  </distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl>
                                                  <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                                                  <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                                                  <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                                  <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                                  <date when="1870">1870</date>
                                                  <biblScope type="page">204</biblScope>
                                                  </bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term> 
                                                    <term>penetrating gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                                                    <term>missiles extracted from within the cranium</term>
                                                    <term>projectiles penetrated cranial cavity, even imbedded in substance of cerebral hemispheres</term>
                                                    <term>penetrating gunshot fractures of the head terminated fatally</term>
                                                    <term>conoidal ball struck skull near junction of coronal and sagittal sutures, passed along latter and fractured both tables</term>
                                                    <term>no paralysis, pupils normal, delirium occurred at intervals</term>
                                                    <term>inner table shattered, spiculæ lodged in membranes and driven into substance of brain</term>
                                                    <term>flattened piece of missile found in anterior right lobe, level with corpus callosum, beneath entrance wound</term>
                                                    <term/>
                                                    <term/>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0270">                                                
                                                  <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="1603">Colonel <hi rend="italic">Thomas
                                                  Ruffin</hi></name>, <name type="organization" key="808">1st North Carolina Cavalry</name>, aged 37 years, was wounded at <name type="battle"><choice><orig>Bristow Station</orig><reg>Bristoe Station</reg></choice>, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-10-14">October 14th, 1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which struck the skull, near the junction of the
                                                  coronal and sagittal sutures, and passed along the
                                                  latter a distance of four inches, fracturing both
                                                  tables.  He was admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="187">2d division hospital</name> at <name type="place">Alexandria</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-10-15">the following day</date>, being perfectly conscious. No paralysis
                                                  existed and the pupils were normal.  On the 17th
                                                  there was slight delirium occurring at intervals.
                                                  The bowels being constipated, half an ounce of
                                                  castor oil was administered. He retained full <choice><sic>possesion</sic><corr>possession</corr></choice> of his faculties until a minute before
                                                  his death, which occurred suddenly on <date type="death" when="1863-10-18">the 18th</date>.  On the
                                                  removal of the skull-cap, it was found that the
                                                  inner table was shattered for a space of one and a
                                                  quarter inches in diameter; spiculæ being lodged
                                                  in the membranes and driven into the substance of
                                                  the brain. As this organ was taken from the cavity
                                                  for special examination, two ounces of blood
                                                  collected in the back of the skull; and two clots
                                                  containing somewhat more than an ounce of fluid,
                                                  with about three ounces of a sero-purulent
                                                  character, were found lying upon the left anterior
                                                  lobe, beneath the dura mater. A flattened piece of
                                                  the missile was found in the right anterior lobe,
                                                  on a level with the corpus callosum, directly
                                                  beneath the wound of entrance.  The pathological
                                                  specimen is No. 1734, Sect. I, A. M. M.  The
                                                  fractured and depressed portion measures
                                                  three-fourths by one inch. A fissure one inch in
                                                  length runs downward in the centre of the frontal
                                                  bone. The fragments removed consist entirely of
                                                  diploë and inner table. The fragments of the outer
                                                  table remain in situ.   The specimen and history
                                                  were contributed by <name type="person" key="1602">Acting Assistant Surgeon T. H.
                                                  Stillwell</name>.</p>                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
