<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16905">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">D——, John F.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16905</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">277-278</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>recovery with disability</term>
          <term>ball struck parietal bone posteriorly to coronal, emerging four inches from point of
            entrance</term>
          <term>depression of external plate, fissure extended posteriorly from depressed portion of
            bone</term>
          <term>partial paralysis of arm, paralysis agitans of opposite forearm</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>

      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private John F.
          D——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. E, 178th New York Volunteers</name>,
        aged 37 years, was accidentally wounded on <date type="injury" when="1863-07-12">July 12th,
          1863</date>, by a conoidal ball, which struck the parietal bone half an inch posteriorly
        to the coronal, and one inch to the left of the sagittal sutures, passing backward, and
        emerging about four inches from the point of entrance. He was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-07-13">the next day</date>, in a somewhat stupid and restless condition, with
        anxious countenance. Partial paralysis of arm, and paralysis agitans of forearm of the
        opposite side existed. An examination of the wound revealed depression of a small portion of
        the external plate, one-half inch in length by one quarter of an inch in width. A fissure
        extended one inch and three-fourths posteriorly from the depressed portion of the bone. The
        fracture of both tables could be readily recognized by the pulsating motion of the fluid
        which had accumulated in the cavity. <name type="person">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, applied the trephine over the depressed
        portion. Great difficulty was experienced from the detached portions of the inner table
        moving under the trephine. These fragments were removed by means of forceps. The dura mater
        was abraded at several points, but not torn through. After the operation, the wound was
        carefully cleansed, water dressings were applied, the patient placed in a semi-recumbent
        position, and quiet enjoined. A gradual improvement took place, and by <date type="injury" when="1863-07-29">July 29th</date> the case presented all indications of a speedy
        recovery. Paralysis steadily diminished. He was sent to the <name type="hospital">DeCamp
          Hospital, New York Harbor</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-29">October 29th,
          1863</date>, and transferred to the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve
          Corps</name>, <date type="duty" when="1865-03-03">March 3d, 1865</date>. The specimen is
        figured in the wood-cut, and shows a disk and five fragments of bone. One and a half square
        inches of the internal table were removed. The specimen and history were contributed by
          <name type="person">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
          V.</name>
      </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001423.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 139.—Disk and fragments removed for gunshot fracture
          of the parietal bone. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1474, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
