<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31798">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Vandermark, W. E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31798</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="at">Alex Thomas</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">364</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the pelvis</term>
       <term>injuries of the genital organs</term>
       <term>wounds of the penis</term>
       <term>wounds of the urethra</term>
       <term>urethral <choice><orig>fistules</orig><reg>fistulae, fistulas</reg></choice></term> 
       <term>immediate retention of urine, early hæmatocele</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of penis and scrotum</term>
       <term>ball entered buttock behind great trochanter, passed up penis from base to corona glandis, and emerged</term>
       <term>collection of urine in scrotum</term>
       <term>urine passed by meatus, by wound of exit, and by artificial opening in scrotum, and catheter used</term>
       <term>ball and buckshot struck gluteal region posterior to trochanter major, emerged anteriorly through genital organs in four pieces</term>
       <term>scrotum distended with blood</term>
       <term>unable to void urine, catheter produced intense pain during evacuation, chloroform administered</term>
       <term>bone pieces discharged from wound of penis at scrotum</term>
       <term>ball entered natis, exited at side of scrotum, cutting urethra in its course</term>
       <term>testis swollen and tender, urine passes through fistulous opening on side of penis just behind glans</term>       
       <term>disability total</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#at" when="2011-02-25">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1058.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. E. Vandermark</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 126th New York</name>, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>, and was treated in a Second Corps field hospital until <date type="transfer" when="1863-05-09">the 9th</date>, when he was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>.  <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, noted as follows: "The ball entered on the left buttock four inches behind the great trochanter, and passed up the penis from the base to the right portion of the corona glandis, where it emerged. There had been a collection of urine in the scrotum, which had been freely laid open. The urine passed by the meatus, by the wound of exit, and by the artificial opening in the scrotum. A catheter was used, and the wound did well."  This patient was transferred to <name type="place">New York Harbor</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-29">October 29th</date>, and returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1863-12-08">December 8th</date>, but was soon sent to <name type="place">Convalescent Camp</name>, and thence to <name type="place">Campbell Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1864-02-09">February 9, 1864</date>, and registered as a case of "gunshot wound of the penis  and scrotum."  He was transferred to the <name type="organization" key="109">Veteran Reserve Corps</name> in <date when="1864-03">March</date>, and was finally discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-11-15">November 15, 1865</date>, and pensioned.  The following special report of this case was made, on <date type="pension" when="1871-06-13">June 13, 1871</date>, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. H.W. Sawtelle</name>: "He was wounded by a conoidal ball and buckshot, which struck the left gluteal region three and a half inches posterior to the trochanter major, and, passing to the right and forward, emerged anteriorly through the genital organs, in four pieces—one from the right side of the penis, just behind the corona glandis, which was thought to have followed the course of the urethra; another through the left testis; and two through the body of the penis close to the scrotum.  The scrotum soon became enormously distended with blood, which was evacuated on the field <date type="operation" when="1863-05-04">twenty-four hours after the injury</date>. From the first the patient was unable to void the urine, and the use of a catheter produced such intense pain during each evacuation of the bladder that the administration of chloroform was necessary from May 4th to July 17, 1863. Two small pieces of bone discharged from the wound of the penis at the scrotum, through which opening the urine partially escaped for one year.  I saw this man in <date type="pension" when="1871-03">March, 1871</date>, and found the wounds healed, except the one at the cervix penis, where a small fistulous opening existed, through which urine escaped. The motions of the hip-joint were somewhat circumscribed, so that he walked with a slight limp; his general health was good. He had suffered continuous pain in the urethra and hip; it was much aggravated in damp weather, and micturition increased the pain in the urethra. The invalid stated that he had been obliged to suspend his business as a driver of a milk-wagon on account of the greatly increased pain and swelling it caused in the hip and wounded testis."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Pension Examiner J. O. Stanton</name>, of <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, reported, <date when="1872-05-15">May 15, 1872</date>: "Ball entered the left natis and made its exit on the left side of the scrotum and right of the penis, cutting the urethra in its course. His disability is total."  <date type="pension" when="1873-09-09">September 9, 1873</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner Stanton</name> continues: "The left testis is now slightly swollen and tender. Urine still passes through the fistulous opening on the right side of the penis just behind the glans. Shot wound of the inner portion of the upper third of the right thigh; this wound does not disable him at present."  <name type="person" key="xxx">This pensioner</name> was paid on <date when="1873-09-04">September 4, 1873</date>.</p>      
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
