<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e7472">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Smith, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e7472</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">112</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">                   
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term> 
                    <term>contusion of the skull without fracture</term>
                    <term>intracranial abscess</term>
                    <term>suppuration following gunshot contusions of the cranium</term>
                    <term>conoidal ball caused contusion of parietal bone</term>
                    <term>convulsive paroxysms, soporose condition, delirium, and coma</term>
                    <term>plate of bone separated by exfoliation from inner table and adherent to dura mater immediately beneath position of original wound</term>                   
                    <term>brain substance softened beneath position of wound, contained small abscess</term>
                    <term>arachnoid acutely inflamed</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-06-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>            
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0096">            
                <p><name type="person" key="375"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>MITH, <hi rend="initialcap">W</hi>ILLIAM</name>, Private, <name type="organization" key="593">Co. G, 4th New York Heavy Artillery</name>,
                    aged 18 years, was wounded, at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="255">Hatcher's Run, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-31">March
                        31st, 1865</date>, by a conoidal ball, which caused a contusion of the left
                    parietal bone.  He was, on <date type="admit" when="1865-04-01">the following day</date>, admitted to the hospital of the
                        Second Corps. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-05">April 5th</date>, he
                    was transferred to the <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory Hospital</name>,
                    Washington, D. C., and on <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-09">April
                        9th</date>, sent to the <name type="hospital">Cuyler Hospital, Philadelphia</name>, Pennsylvania.  On
                    admittance no osseous lesion could be detected. The case progressed favorably
                    until <date type="injury" when="1865-04-16">April 16th</date>, when the patient had two or three slight convulsive paroxysms,
                    lying in a somewhat soporose condition during the intervals. He afterwards
                    became delirious, and finally almost completely comatose. The muscles of the
                    left side of the body were observed to be in a state of spasmodic contraction,
                    and a large collection of pus formed beneath the left side of the scalp,
                    anterior to the wound, and was opened on <date type="operation" when="1865-04-29">April 29th</date>. The pathological condition
                    was supposed to be, that an abscess, resulting from the original shock to the
                    brain substance, was exciting irritation, and would probably eventually burst
                    into one of the lateral ventricles. Mercurials, tartarized antimony, and the
                    fluid extract of veratrum viride were exhibited internally, while the head was
                    kept somewhat elevated.  Death ensued on the night of <date type="death" when="1865-04-30">April 30th, 1865</date>, one month from the reception of
                    injury.  An autopsy was made <date type="death" when="1865-05-01">about fourteen hours after death</date>, with the following
                    results: there was no fracture of the skull to be detected when the scalp was
                    removed, and the bone was not bared beneath the abscess, which has been
                    described as having formed a few hours before death, but was manifestly necrosed
                    just below the original wound. On removing the skull cap it was found that a
                    plate of bone, about one inch long and three-quarters of an inch broad, had been
                    separated by exfoliation from the inner table, and was adherent to the dura
                    mater immediately beneath the position of the original scalp wound. The brain
                    was removed with the membranes entire, but a moderate quantity of blood and
                    serum being found beneath the dura mater and the skull. On reflecting the dura
                    mater of the <hi rend="italic">right</hi> hemisphere, the arachnoid over the middle lobe of the
                    cerebrum was found to be acutely inflamed, presenting an abundant deposit of
                    soft coagulable lymph. The membranes of the left side presented merely a slight
                    pearliness, and the adhesion of the dura mater to the sequestrum, already
                    referred to. The brain substance on the right side was healthy; on the left side, it was softened beneath the position of the wound, and, at the depth of
                    about three-quarters of an inch, was a small abscess, not larger than a small
                    hickory-nut. All other parts of the body examined appeared normal. The muscular
                    contraction on the same side of the body as the wound was now accounted for by
                    the existence of intracranial disease upon the opposite side.   The case is
                    reported by <name type="person" key="374">Henry S. Schell, Assistant Surgeon</name> <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. Army</name>. </p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
