<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e18079">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Lynn, M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e18079</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">438</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recovery after shot fractures involving both bones of the leg treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot fracture of leg</term> 
     <term>compound fractures of tibia and fibula at middle third</term> 
     <term>ball entered at posterior and inner side of calf of leg, escaped in front</term>
     <term>fragments of bone removed at different times</term>     
     <term>adherent cicatrix caused impaired use of limb</term>
     <term>fractured space filled with cartilaginous tissue</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-04">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
       <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 688.—<name type="person" key="1247">Private M.
      Lynn</name>, <name type="organization" key="97">Co. I, 26th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 26
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="10">Chancellorsville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>. He was admitted to the field hospital of the 2d division, Third Corps, where <name type="person" key="xx">Assistant Surgeon E. Marshall</name>, <name type="organization" key="328">124th New York</name>, recorded "shot fracture of left leg." <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
     reported as follows: "The patient entered <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-15">June 15th</date>, with
        compound fracture of tibia and fibula at the middle third, caused by a minié ball entering at
     the posterior and inner side of the calf of the leg and escaping in front. At the time of his
     admission the leg was in a fracture box; the wound suppurated freely; patient's general
     condition good. Previous to his entrance to this hospital several detached fragments of bone
     had been removed, and a portion of the bullet had also been extracted; subsequently about half
     a dozen more fragments of bone were removed at different times. Splints and water dressings
     were used. About July 1st, the fracture had united, and one month later there was firm union of
     the bones and the wound was healing rapidly. On <date type="furlough" when="1863-09-22">September 22d</date>, the patient received a furlough
     and was allowed to go to his home for two months. The orifice of entrance healed about the 1st
     of October, and before the patient was transferred to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, in <date type="transfer" when="1864-04">April, 1864</date>, the orifice of exit had also closed. The atrophy of the
     wounded limb had disappeared entirely and the muscles of the leg acted freely, the patient
     being able to walk well with out the aid of a cane and without limping. There was no
     shortening, and no deformity aside from some loss of osseous tissue at the seat of the
     fracture. The patient stated that the wounded limb had not caused him to feel sick at any time.
     He made the best recovery of any case of shot fracture of the leg that has come under my
     observation."  After his transfer the patient was admitted to McClellan Hospital, whence he was returned to duty <date type="duty" when="1864-05-31">May 31st</date>, to be discharged. He was mustered out of service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-06-18">June 18, 1864</date>, and pensioned. The <name type="organization" key="xx">Philadelphia Examining Board</name> at different dates certified to the injury, and reported
     that an adherent cicatrix resulted, causing impaired use of the limb; also that the fractured
     space had filled with cartilaginous tissue. The pensioner has been exempted from further
     examinations since 1873. He was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-12-04">December 4, 1879</date>.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
