<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31457">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Selvoir, M.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31457</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kb">Karli Burt</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">164</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the kidney</term> 
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>ball entered at left ninth rib anteriorly, emerged to left of spinous process of twelfth dorsal vertebra</term>
       <term>severe pain in testicle</term> 
       <term>hæmorrhage into pelvis of kidney, urine discolored and partly coagulated</term>
       <term>pus observed with urine</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#kb" when="2011-02-19">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 511.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private M. Selvoir</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 5th New Hampshire</name>, aged 27 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx"><choice><orig>Farmsville</orig><reg>Farmville</reg></choice></name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-04-06">April 6, 1865</date>, by a round ball, which entered at the left ninth rib anteriorly, five inches from the median line, passed backward, and emerged half an inch to the left of the spinous process of the twelfth dorsal vertebra.  He was conveyed to the field hospital of the Second Corps, thence, on <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-06">the 19th</date>, by the <name type="hospital" key="xxx">hospital transport State of Maine</name>, to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, entering <name type="hospital" key="152">Finley Hospital</name>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Dusenbury</name>¹ reports that the patient stated that for a number of days after the injury he was confined to bed, and complained of severe pain in the left testicle. There was slow, steady hæmorrhage into the pelvis of the kidney, which found its way out with the urine, partly discolored and partly coagulated. After the subsidence of the hæmorrhage some pus was observed with the urine, which soon disappeared, with other troublesome symptoms, when the wounds healed rapidly, so that by July 1st they were entirely healed, with slight tenderness over the cicatrices. The patient was able to go about without inconvenience, and on <date type="duty" when="1865-08-01">August 1st</date> did guard duty about the hospital.  <date type="transfer" when="1865-08-29">August 29th</date>, he was transferred to <name type="place">Concord</name>, and mustered out of service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-09-06">September 6, 1865</date>. He is not a pensioner.</p> 
   <p>¹ <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>USENBURY (<hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">Cases of Gunshot Wounds of the Abdomen involving Viscera</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Am. Jour. Med. Sci.</hi>, 1865, N. S., Vol. L, p. 400.</p>    
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
