<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e14502">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">B——, J. R.</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e14502</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">205</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term> 
                    <term>penetrating gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                    <term>missiles extracted from within the cranium</term>
                    <term>projectiles penetrated cranial cavity, even imbedded in substance of cerebral hemispheres</term>
                    <term>penetrating gunshot fractures of the head terminated fatally</term>
                    <term>presence of balls within cranial cavity unsuspected during life</term>
                    <term>conoidal ball entered above inner canthus of left eye, fractured frontal bone, passed backward and right, and lodged at posterior angle of right orbit</term>
                    <term>right eye inflamed and bulging appearance</term>
                    <term>coma and fever</term>
                    <term>disorganization of anterior left cerebral hemisphere, extended to left lateral ventricle</term>                    
                    <term>autopsy performed</term>
                    <term>both lateral ventricles filled with purulent sanguineous fluid, base of brain covered with pus</term>
                    <term>fracture and comminution of the intraorbital septa and of orbital plate of frontal bone</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2013-07-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.273">            
                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="1607">Sergeant J. R. B——</name>, <name type="organization" key="809">Co. A, 55th Virginia Regiment</name>, aged 26 years, was wounded
                    at <name type="battle" key="xx">Poplar Grove Church, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-10-01">October
                        1st, 1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which entered just above the inner
                    canthus of the left eye, fractured the frontal bone, passed backward and to the
                    right, and lodged at the posterior angle of the right orbit.  He was conveyed to
                    the hospital of the first division, Fifth Corps, and on <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-08">October 8th</date> was sent to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington.  The right eye was inflamed,
                    and had a bulging appearance. No bad symptoms occurred until <date type="injury" when="1864-10-26">October 26th</date>, when
                    the patient vomited. He became comatose and feverish on the evening of the 28th,
                    and died on the following morning, <date type="death" when="1864-10-29">October
                        29th, 1864</date>.  At the autopsy disorganization of the anterior lobe of
                    the left hemisphere was found extending to the left lateral ventricle; both
                    ventricles were filled with a purulent sanguineous fluid, and the base of brain
                    was covered with pus.  The pathological specimen is No. 3373, Sect. I, A. M. M.  A
                    section of skull, showing fracture and comminution of the intraorbital septa,
                    and of the right orbital plate of the frontal bone.   The specimen and history
                    were contributed by <name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name>.</p>            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
