<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e17232">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">V——, Edward</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  </edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e17232</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor>
                                                  <name>Center for Digital Research in the
                                                  Humanities</name>
                                                  <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                                  </distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl>
                                                  <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                  of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                                                  <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph
                                                  K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                                                  <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                                  <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                                  <date when="1870">1870</date>
                                                  <biblScope type="page">303</biblScope>
                                                  </bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term> 
                                                                  <term>hernia cerebri after gunshot fractures of the skull</term> 
                                                                  <term>fungus cerebri</term>    
                                                                  <term>ball struck above right eyebrow, comminuting both tables</term>
                                                                  <term>on battlefield six days, brain matter oozed from wound</term>
                                                                  <term>autopsy performed</term>
                                                                  <term>meninges and brain exhibited congestion and inflammation</term>
                                                                  <term>extensive fracture of right supra-orbital arch, small fragment of bone attached</term>
                                                                  
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>                                                
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-09-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text
                                                  extracted and transformed from larger
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private Edward V——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. D, 55th Ohio
                                                                Volunteers</name>, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="127">Bull Run, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-08-29">August 29th, 1862</date>, by a conoidal ball,
                                                  which struck half an inch above the right eyebrow,
                                                  and the same distance from the median line of the
                                                                  <hi rend="italic">os frontis</hi>, comminuting and carrying away both
                                                  tables to the extent of one and one-fourth to two
                                                  and one-fourth inches. He was wounded while in the
                                                  act of discharging his gun, staggered considerably
                                                  under the shock, but recovered immediately, so
                                                  that he fired, loaded, and fired a second time
                                                  before he fell. He lay on the field for six days,
                                                  during which time a considerable amount of brain
                                                  matter oozed from the wound. He was afterward
                                                  conveyed to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and admitted, on <date type="admit" when="1862-09-07">the 7th
                                                                  of September</date>, into the <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory Hospital</name>, where the
                                                  wound was dressed for the first time. Half of the
                                                  plates composing the frontal sinus were found
                                                  turned in upon the brain, and about one-third of
                                                  the ball was battered up against the fractured
                                                  edge of the bone. When the missile and fragments
                                                  of bone were removed a large quantity of fœtid
                                                  pus and a teaspoonful of cerebral matter exuded.
                                                  The most remarkable feature of the case was that
                                                  there were no symptoms of injury to the brain,
                                                  either in articulation, memory, sight, or
                                                  animation. The wound was dressed with adhesive
                                                  strips to keep the eyebrow from falling on the
                                                  cheek. On the morning of <date type="operation" when="1862-09-08">the 8th</date>, a hernia
                                                  cerebri, an inch in diameter, made its appearance,
                                                  pulsating with the heart's action. The depressed
                                                  walls of the frontal sinus were now removed by
                                                                <name type="person">Assistant Surgeon J. D. Hall</name>, <name type="organization">24th New York
                                                                                Volunteers</name>, the operation being attended with
                                                  slight hæmorrhage, a plentiful discharge of pus,
                                                  and the escape of a teacupful of softened brain
                                                  matter. On the 9th, the tongue was covered with a
                                                  thick white fur; lips red, pulse nearly normal. No
                                                  change occurred until the 19th, except that the
                                                  wound became more painful, though it continued
                                                  perfectly healthy. The hernia had gradually
                                                  receded when, on <date type="injury" when="1862-09-20">the 20th</date>, a colliquative
                                                  diarrhœa set in, which, though arrested by
                                                  astringents and opiates greatly reduced his
                                                  strength; his mind, however, continued perfectly
                                                  clear. Tonics, with nouishing diet, were
                                                  administered, but he failed to rally, and died on
                                                  the morning of <date type="death" when="1862-09-25">the 25th</date>. At the autopsy a large
                                                  clot was found between the dura mater and the
                                                  skull, at the coronal suture; and the meninges and
                                                  brain exhibited a much greater degree of
                                                  congestion and inflammation than any recent
                                                  symptoms had indicated. The ventricles, on
                                                  section, were found filled with serum and pus. The
                                                  pathological specimen is No. 276, Sect. I, A. M. M.  The cranium shows an extensive fracture of the
                                                  right supra-orbital arch; a small fragment of the
                                                  bone is attached. The entire arch is removed,
                                                  leaving an opening into the cranium, two and
                                                  one-half inches long and one and one-fourth wide,
                                                  extending from the inner angle of the orbit to the
                                                  anterior inferior angle of the right parietal. The
                                                  orbital plate of the right superior maxilla is
                                                  fractured and depressed and a fissure an inch long
                                                  extends down the body of the bone. The specimen
                                                  and history were contributed by <name type="person">Surgeon William Clendenin</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
