<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e2132">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Walters, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e2132</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">36-37</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>shot flesh wounds</term>
     <term>shot wounds of lower extremities not attended by lesions of bones, joints, great vessels or nerves</term>
     <term>complications of shot flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>tetanus</term>
     <term>stiffness and pains in jaws and neck, jaws seemingly tied</term>
     <term>severe cramps in abdomen, muscles hard and tense, muscles of back rigid and prominent</term>
     <term>strumous diathesis, scrofulous abscesses</term> 
     <term>ball struck plantar surface of foot at first interosseous space, going directly through dorsum, produced flesh wound</term>
     <term>no relaxation of muscular spasm</term>      
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-02-22">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>   
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p>  <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 77.—<name type="person" key="902">Sergeant W.
      Walters</name>, <name type="organization" key="343">Co. B, 87th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 29
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="259">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-08">May 8, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="884">Surgeon N. R.
      Moseley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported his admission to
      <name type="hospital" key="172">Emory Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1864-05-16">May 16th</date>, with "shot wound of foot."  <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon J. H. Taylor</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported
     the following result of the injury: "The patient was admitted to Summit House Hospital, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-20">May 20th</date>, having been wounded by a ball striking
     the plantar surface of the left foot at the first interosseous space, one and a half inches
     from the metatarso-phalangeal joints, going directly through on the dorsum and producing a flesh wound. Cold-water
     dressings were applied. The patient is of strumous diathesis, having scars on the side of his
     neck, the remains of scrofulous abscesses.  <date type="injury" when="1864-05-30">May 30th</date>, at 8 A. M, he was in excellent health; at
     <choice><orig>12 A. M.</orig><reg>12 P. M.</reg></choice> he complained of stiffness and pains in the jaws and neck; great pain, referred to articulation of
     left inferior maxilla with temporal bone, together with constant fixed pains at the
     epigastrium, shooting around to the spine; jaws seemingly tied, as the patient expressed; mouth
     gradually closing; twitching of facial muscles; some difficulty of respiration, but none of
     deglutition.  Treatment: Bowels unloaded by injections; brandy and quinine given in large quantities, milk-punch and beef-tea by mouth and rectum.
     Liquor of morphia, one half ounce, was given every two hours for eight hours or ten hours, but
     with no effect. Injected one grain of sulphate of morphia, dissolved in one drachm of water,
     hypodermically just over the temporal region; but even this failed to produce any narcotic
     effect. Counter-irritation was used at the spine with the chloroform and covered with oiled silk, but so severe
     was the burning pain that it soon had to be discontinued.  On May 31st, the patient was attacked
     with severe cramps in the abdomen, the muscles here becoming hard and tense, the muscles of the
     back rigid and prominent; great pain, referred to chest in inspiration; pupils contracted.
     There was profuse perspiration over the entire body from the commencement of the disease; pulse natural. A solution of sulphate of atropia, one grain to an
     ounce of water, was now injected, in quantities of one drachm, a little to the left of the
     median line of the neck at first, and subsequently on each side of the spine, below the scapula,
     at intervals of one half, one, and two hours, in all seven or eight times. The pupils were now
     dilated, but there was not the slightest relaxation of muscular spasm; perspiration still
     profuse. An effort to rouse him from this state with cold douche had but little effect. The
     spasms continued to increase in frequency and violence until 3 A. M. on <date type="death" when="1864-06-01">June 1, 1864</date>, when he died."  </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
