<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e1018">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">King, W. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e1018</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">21-22</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>shot flesh wounds</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower limbs unattended by primary injury of the large nerves or
      blood-vessels</term>
     <term>lodgement of missiles in soft parts</term>
     <term>ball and fragments of knife driven into anterior side of middle thigh</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 34.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. H.
     King</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 17th Maine</name>, aged 24 years, was
    wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Bartlett's Mill</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-27">November 27, 1863</date>, and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="202">Prince Street Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-12-04">one week afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant
     Surgeon J. Cass</name> contributed the specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 4), with the
    following history: "He was wounded by a musket ball which struck two pocket knives, breaking
    them and driving the fragments with the ball into the anterior side of the middle third of the
    left thigh. A hundred fragments of the knives and four of the ball were removed on the field.
    Lime-water dressings applied to the wound, and fifteen drops of tincture of iron given before
    meals. On December 13th, he suffered considerable pain in the wound, and on <date type="operation" when="1863-12-14">the following day</date> an incision was made two and a half
    inches from the wound, and a jagged piece of ball an inch long and three- fourths of an inch
    wide was extracted. 16th, complained of strangury and some pain in the limb. A teaspoonful of
    spirits of nitre given three times a day. 17th, was restless during the night; sweats profusely,
    and had a chill this morning. Gave morphia and whiskey, also half an ounce of castor-oil. Has
    had no stool for forty-eight hours; pulse 115 and feeble; tongue coated; very thirsty; some
    soreness in inguinal glands. Prescribed extract of ginger and turpentine ten drops each, to be
    repeated in six hours if it does not operate, and gave tonics and stimulants. 18th, pulse 100,
    tongue moist and coated. Sweats all the time, and vomited in the night. Bowels moved freely and
    urinates more freely; appetite better. There is a greater discharge of pus from the wound. 19th,
    pulse 115 and feeble; vomited considerable during the day. Ordered two quinine pills to be taken
    before meals, and an anodyne injection at bedtime. 20th, about the same; had a chill yesterday;
    granulations are pale and flabby. 21st, pulse 140 and very feeble; great prostration; had a
    chill this morning and is delirious. Takes stimulants every hour. <date type="death" when="1863-12-22">22d</date>, rested well, but is more prostrated and shows tendency to coma.
    Died at 4.30 P. M. Autopsy eighteen hours after death: On cutting through the muscles of the
    thigh, an inch and a half from the surface and an inch from the main channel of the wound, a
    sliver of horn from a knife-handle was found, half an inch long and one-sixteenth of an inch
    wide; also a brass rivet one-sixteenth of an inch in diameter and one-fourth of an inch long. In
    another place two pieces of horn from the other knife-handle, one three-eighths of an inch long
    and one-fourth wide, and the other one-eighth each way, were found; also a piece of a blade
    one-fourth of an inch long and one-eighth wide; and two pieces of brass, one being three-eighths
    of an inch long and one-sixteenth wide at one end and tapering to a sharp point at the other,
    and the other piece measuring one-eighth of an inch each way. Opposite the external wound the
    periosteum was found in places thickened, inflamed, jagged, discolored, slightly ossified, and
    separated from the bone for the space of two and a quarter inches longitudinally, and one inch
    transversely, with some pus beneath it." Dr. Cass also contributed five inches of the shaft
    of the femur of the injured thigh, which constitutes specimen 1985 of the Surgical Section of
    the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>. It is sawn longitudinally, and
    shows the shaft to be denser than usual and apparently somewhat hypertrophied. (See <hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1866, pp. 258, 617.) </p>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001513.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 4.—Fragments of ball and pocket knife extracted from
    thigh. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3236.</head></figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
