<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e5962">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">McVaugh, Jos.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e5962</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">339</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated, large intestine also implicated</term>  
                                        <term>abscess on surface of kidney</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00026">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 26.—<name type="person" key="609">Private Jos. McVaugh</name>, <name type="organization" key="649">Co. D, 147th
                                                Pa.</name>; age 45; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-07-28">July 28, 1863</date>. He was very
                                        feeble and delirious, with an inclination to stupor; his
                                        tongue very dry and red; skin cool and clammy; pulse 113,
                                        small and weak; bowels moved about ten times daily; abdomen
                                        hard and tender, especially in the right iliac region. In
                                        the progress of the case the stools became less frequent,
                                        but all the other symptoms increased in severity; the
                                        passages during the night before death were involuntary. He
                                        died <date type="death" when="1863-08-02">August 2</date>.
                                                <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination seven
                                        hours after death: The brain weighed forty-five ounces; the
                                        pia mater was somewhat congested and the choroid plexuses
                                        filled with minute air-bubbles. The trachea was greenish but
                                        contained healthy sputa; the mucous membrane of the
                                        œsophagus was pale yellow-stained near the cardiac
                                        orifice and presented numerous whitish points. The right
                                        lung weighed eleven ounces and was slightly engorged in its
                                        upper and middle lobes. The left lung weighed fifteen
                                        ounces; its upper lobe was much shrunken and contained but
                                        little air; towards its apex was a small circular elevation
                                        about the size of a chestnut, surrounded by a livid purplish
                                        zone about three inches in diameter; on opening this spot a
                                        quantity of air escaped and a few drops of bloody fluid; the
                                        lower lobe was engorged with venous blood. The heart
                                        contained a small fibrinous clot in the right cavities and a
                                        mixed clot in the left; the pericardium contained two
                                        drachms of bloody fluid. The stomach was unusually firm and
                                        its mucous membrane pale-red in color throughout. The liver
                                        weighed fifty-three ounces and was slightly congested; the
                                        gall-bladder contained ten ounces of bile of a brownish-ochre color, filled with a flaky substance which
                                        did not precipitate. The spleen weighed five ounces and was
                                        flabby, soft and of a mulberry color. The right kidney
                                        weighed five ounces; its external surface was of a bluish
                                        color spotted with numerous dark-blue points; an abscess
                                        about the size of a horse chestnut, with ecchymosed walls,
                                        containing discolored pus, was found on the anterior surface
                                        near the outer margin. The left kidney weighed five ounces
                                        and a half; it was much congested; a small cyst containing
                                        serum was found on its anterior surface. The small intestine
                                        was healthy to within three feet of the ileo-cæcal
                                        valve, but from this point downward the mucous membrane was
                                        of a reddish-purple color, thin and somewhat softened;
                                        Peyer's patches were discolored and ulcerated, especially near the valve, where patches of a
                                        dark-blue stone color, fully an inch in diameter, were
                                        eroded. The large intestine was greenish but free from
                                        ulceration; the solitary glands were white and
                                                conspicuous.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. Harrison
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                                </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
