<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e10451">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">McMahon, J.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e10451</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">223-224</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>primary amputations in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>recoveries after primary amputation in the middle third of the femur</term>
     <term>ball caused fracture of femur extending into knee joint</term>
     <term>amputation performed at middle third</term>
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>femur in state of necrosis and protruding</term>
     <term>pyæmia</term>
     <term>osteomyelitis of femur</term>
     <term>furnished with artificial limb</term>
     <term><term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term></term>
     <term>large sequestrum of bone removed three months after amputation</term>
     <term>pure bromine applied</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ak" when="2014-10-08">proofed figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 435.—<name type="person" key="1068">Private J.
     McMahon</name>, <name type="organization" key="432">Co. I, 6th New York Cavalry</name>, aged 23
    years, was wounded in the left leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="xx">Todd's Tavern</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-07">May 7, 1864</date>. He was admitted to a field hospital of the
    Cavalry Corps, where amputation was performed but not recorded, and <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-12">five days afterwards</date> he was transferred to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>. <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W.
     Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, made the following report
    of the case: "The wound was caused by a musket ball, which caused a fracture of the femur
    extending into knee joint, for which amputation was performed at the middle third, by the
    circular method, <date type="operation" when="1864-05-07">within an hour</date>, chloroform
    being used. He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>
    <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-12">May 12th</date>, at which time a large slough existed on
    the anterior flap, which soon separated, exposing the end of the bone. There was no vigorous
    effort at repair, the granulations being pale and flabby. The patient's general condition was
    unfavorable; he was much depressed and very pallid, and had a severe diarrhœa. On June
    20th, the cellular tissue of the stump again began to slough, and, on the 22d, it was found
    requisite to apply pure bromine. On the 23d most of the sloughs separated, and, by the next day,
    the stump was clean and the granulations more florid and healthy. One inch and a half of the end
    of the femur was in a state of necrosis and protruding. On <date type="operation" when="1864-08-11">August 11th</date>, a sequestrum, nine inches in length, was removed by
    extraction, leaving a deep cavity in the stump, which was bounded externally by a large and firm
    cylinder of new bone. The patient's improvement was then rapid, and, by November 1st, he was
    considered convalescent. This man had remained for weeks as pale as death and so feeble as to be
    unable to lift his head from his pillow. He seemed daily on the verge of the chill of
    pyæmia, and his case was recognized and pointed out as one of osteomyelitis of the femur,
    from which if death did not result a long exfoliation would be removed." On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-05-18">May 18, 1865</date>, the patient was discharged from
    service, and several weeks after he was furnished with an artificial limb by the firm of <name type="person" key="xx">A. A. Marks</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">New York City</name>.
    In his application for commutation, dated <date type="pension" when="1870">1870</date>, the
    pensioner stated that the amputation was performed by <name type="person" key="xx">Assistant
     Surgeon S. C. Sanger</name>, <name type="organization" key="432">6th New York Cavalry,</name>
    also that the stump was in a healthy condition. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. The sequestrum (<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4281) was
    contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>, and is shown, reduced in size one-third, in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 4 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXIX</hi>, opposite.</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001811.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE LXIX. __ TUBULAR SEQUESTRA FROM AMPUTATIONS OF THE FEMUR. 4
    Spec. 4281. Surgical Section, Army Medical Museum.
    </head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
