<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11564">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Gold, Edward W.</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e11564</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">848</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>diseases attributed to non-miasmatic exposures</term>
                                        <term>other diseases attributed to exposure</term>
                                        <term>congestion and inflammation of the spinal membranes</term>
                                        <term>history of injury to spine, proximate or immediate cause was evidently subsequent exposure to vicissitudes and inclemencies of weather</term>
                                        <term>attack was beginning of permanent disability from loss of power in affected limbs and tremors, which were recorded as paralysis agitans</term>
                                        <term>injured by mule in small of back</term>
                                        <term>passed blood per rectum</term>
                                        <term>abscess of hand, arm became swollen</term>
                                        <term>nervous debility</term>
                                        <term>paralysis agitans</term>                                        
                                        <term>paraplegia</term>
                                        <term>legs and arms tremulous and powerless, arm atrophied</term>
                                        <term>frequent pains in small of back and cramps below knees, chiefly at night</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-05-09">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-03-01">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body>                        
                        <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 10.—<name type="person">Private Edward W. Gold</name>, <name type="organization">Co. F, 90th Pa. Vols.</name>; age 33;
                                enlisted <date type="enlisted" when="1863-07">July, 1863</date>.  In <date type="injury" when="1863-11">November following</date> he was hurt by a
                                        mule in the small of the back, and passed blood per rectum
                                        freely for two days after the injury; but at <date type="duty" when="1863-11">the end of two
                                                weeks</date> he was returned to duty.  Soon after this he woke one
                                        night chilled and wet by a leak in the roof of his quarters.
                                        He was confined to bed for several days with loss of power
                                        but not of sensation in his legs. Gradually power returned
                                        and he became able to walk with aid. In <date type="injury" when="1864-02">February, 1864</date>, he
                                        had an abscess in his right hand, during the progress of
                                        which the arm became swollen, and after the closure of the
                                        wound made for the discharge of matter the fingers
                                        continued flexed.  <date type="admit" when="1864-02">At this time</date> his legs again became weak,
                                and he was sent to <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name>, Washington. He was
                                        exposed to cold in the cars for eleven hours and to a heavy
                                        rain-shower during his conveyance in an ambulance to the
                                        hospital. For some time after admission his condition did
                                        not improve, but later he began to recover power over his
                                        legs.  He was transferred to <name type="hospital">Satterlee hospital,
                                                Philadelphia</name>, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-03">May 3</date>.—diagnosis: nervous
                                debility, and on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-31">the 31st</date> to <name type="hospital">Turner's Lane</name>.  The records of
                                        the latter hospital report the patient on July as having
                                        frequent pains in the small of his back and cramps below the
                                        knees, chiefly at night; sensation was not materially
                                        altered, but the legs and arms were tremulous and powerless,
                                        the right arm being in addition considerably atrophied.  On <date type="injury" when="1864-08-03">August 3</date> it was stated that the patient was able to walk
                                        for the first time since falling into this paralytic condition.  On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-11-21">November 21</date> he was discharged because of
                                        paralysis agitans and paraplegia. </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
