<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e16821">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Aseltyne, M. B.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e16821</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">405, 736 (Part 2, Volume 2)</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>amputations at the knee joint</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations at the knee joint</term>
     <term>fatal cases of intermediary amputation at the knee joint</term>
     <term>wounded in foot</term>
     <term>ball entered anterior surface of foot, fractured cuneiform bones, extracted on field
      through orifice of entrance</term>
     <term>gangrene</term>
     <term>leg amputated at knee joint, retaining patella after disarticulating joint</term>
     <term>pyæmia</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-30">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 649.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private M. B.
     Aseltyne</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. F, 10th Vermont</name>, aged 22 years,
    was wounded in the left foot, at <name type="battle" key="77">Mine Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-27">November 27, 1863</date>, and entered the <name type="hospital" key="512">Third Division Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-12-04">one week afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="738">Acting
     Assistant Surgeon A. P. Crafts</name> reported: "A conical ball entered the anterior
    surface of the foot, fractured the cuneiform bones, and was extracted through the orifice of
    entrance, on the field. At the time of the patient s admission there was much tumefaction and
    inflammation of the foot and leg, which at first seemed to yield to treatment. But, on December
    10th, evidences of gangrene began to show themselves, and <date type="operation" when="1863-12-14">four days afterwards</date> the leg was amputated at the knee joint by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
     V.</name> The operation was performed by the circular method, and by retaining the patella
    after disarticulating the joint. Chloroform constituted the anæsthetic. Simple dressings
    were used to the stump, and tonics and stimulants, including iron and quinine, and acetate of
    ammonia were given in the treatment. On December 20th, there were symptoms of pyæmia. The
    patient's countenance became sallow and anxious, a severe chill occurred, and hiccough set in,
    followed by loss of appetite and by profuse sweating. Death supervened on <date type="death" when="1863-12-27">December 27, 1863</date>. At the <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi>
    examination the liver, kidneys, spleen, and intestines were found healthy, the lungs much
    discolored, and some effusion in the cavity of the chest. There was also great hypertrophy of
    the heart and some effusion within the pericardium." A section of the stump, made by <name type="person" key="288">Surgeon J. H. Brinton</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S.
     V.</name>, showed the femur to be healthy, although denuded of periosteum for six inches above
    the joint. The synovial membrane on the crucial ligament was congested, and the cartilage of the
    femur was thinned and softened, the whole color being changed and absorption commencing. The
    ligature of the popliteal artery had partially sloughed, and the base of the long internal clot
    had come down and projected through the opening made by sloughing in the walls of the vessel.
    The artery, showing its condition as described, was contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by the operator. A wet preparation of it constitutes specimen 1989
    of the Surgical Section, and a chromo-lithographic representation is shown on <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE. <hi rend="initialcap">XXII</hi>, opposite page 736 of the <hi rend="italic">Second Surgical Volume</hi>.</p>
   <figure><graphic url="cww.001619.001"/><head>PLATE XXII. 2, LIGATION OF POPLITEAL.</head></figure>


  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
