<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e2770">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Rapp, D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e2770</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">44-46</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>complications of shot flesh wounds of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage</term>
     <term>ligations of blood-vessels of the lower limbs after flesh wounds</term>
     <term>ligation of the femoral artery</term>
     <term>bullet entered posterior aspect of thigh, below gluteal fold</term>
     <term>bullet divided both femoral artery and vein</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage at injury, immediate want of sensibility in leg and foot</term>
     <term>gunshot wound of left thigh</term>
     <term>free communication between divided artery and vein permitted arterial blood to return by
      vein, evinced by pulsation backward toward heart</term>
     <term><choice>
       <orig>aneurism</orig>
       <reg>aneurysm</reg>
      </choice> developed at divided proximal vessels</term>
     <term>traumatic <choice>
       <orig>aneurism</orig>
       <reg>aneurysm</reg>
      </choice></term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 98.—<name type="person" key="916">Private D. Rapp</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="350">Co. K, 7th Indiana</name>, aged 20 years, was wounded at
     <name type="BATTLE" key="272">Robinson's Creek</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-30">November 30, 1863</date>. He was admitted to the field hospital of the 1st division, First
    Corps, where <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon G. W. Metcalf</name>, <name type="organization" key="368">76th New York</name>, noted: "Gunshot wound of left
    thigh." On <date type="transfer" when="1863-12-06">December 6th</date>, the wounded man was
    transferred to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington. <date type="operation" when="1863-12-09">Three days afterwards</date> he was operated on by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon W. Thomson</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who furnished the following detailed report of the case: "He was
    a well developed and very muscular man and had been apparently in good health. At the moment of
    injury he was retreating, and was struck by a bullet on the posterior aspect of the left thigh a
    short distance below the gluteal fold, which passed through the limb to the inside of the bone,
    divided both femoral artery and vein, and made its exit three and a half inches below Poupart's
    ligament, at the point of election in ligating the femoral in Scarpa's space. There was profuse
    hæmorrhage at the time of injury, and an immediate want of sensibility in the leg and foot.
    When examined on the 7th of December, the whole limb was found warm and the collateral
    circulation had been established; but there was no pulsation in either of the tibial arteries.
    At the superior margin of the wound of exit there was a small tense swelling, which pulsated
    synchronously with the systole of the heart. An <choice>
     <orig>aneurismal</orig>
     <reg>aneurysmal</reg>
    </choice> thrill, resembling the loud purring of a cat, was distinctly felt, extending along the
    course of the vessels into the pelvis, but not communicating laterally. The little finger was
    introduced into the wound at the time of the operation, and the pulsation and thrill were found
    to be closely localized and confined to the divided ends of the femoral vessels. There was no
    extensive effusion of blood into the tissues of the thigh, and hence this was not in the strict
    surgical sense of the word a traumatic <choice>
     <orig>aneurism</orig>
     <reg>aneurysm</reg>
    </choice>. It was concluded that the sac was composed only of the sheath, which had been united
    by inflammation after the division and retraction of its vessels, and had then been some what
    distended after the heart had regained its force. It was also suggested by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon Lidell</name>, who kindly saw the case with me, that there was a free
    communication between the divided artery and vein in this sac which permitted the arterial blood
    to return freely by the vein, as evinced by the pulsation communicating with such force backward
    toward the heart in the line of the vessels. It was unmistakable that there existed a wound of
    the femoral artery sufficient to cause its obliteration, that an <choice>
     <orig>aneurism</orig>
     <reg>aneurysm</reg>
    </choice> was being developed at the divided proximal extremity, and that the proper surgical
    procedure would be to secure the ends of the vessel at the point of the injury. It was
    determined to emulate the example of Mr. Syme, to lay open boldly the sac by a free incision and
    search for and secure the bleeding orifices. It was hoped that the profunda had escaped injury
    and every precaution was to be used to secure the femoral below its origin. A small
    hæmorrhage on <date type="operation" when="1863-12-09">December 9th</date> rendered
    immediate interference necessary, and the following operation was then done with the assistance
    of <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon Lidell</name> and the medical officers of the hospital.
    After the patient had been fully etherized and the femoral artery thoroughly compressed on the
    pubes by the thumb of a reliable assistant, as evinced by the loss of pulsation in the tumor, an
    incision four inches in length was made through the skin and fasciæ, immediately over the
    tumor and including the gunshot wound, in a line parallel with the sartorius. A second incision
    was now made into the tumor, which was dilated instantly by the finger to the size of the first.
    Distal hæmorrhage was anticipated, and it caused but little surprise when a most profuse
    dark colored torrent poured out from the incision. The lower angle of the incision was rapidly
    searched in vain for the source of the hæmorrhage, and it was feared that it might come
    from the dark softened depth of the track of the ball. No pressure on the artery had the least
    controlling effect upon it. The removal of the sponge was followed instantly by a boiling dark
    torrent of venous blood, which so quickly filled the cavity as to prevent any examination. So
    profuse and uncontrollable was the flow that visions of ligating the external iliac were vividly
    presented to the mind. When the flow was found to arise from the superior angle of the incision
    numerous and ineffectual efforts were made to secure the vessel, but the parts were so hardened
    by local inflammation that the forceps glided over them as it would over a cartilaginous
    surface. This point, from whence the dark blood seemed to flow, was finally compressed by the
    point of the left index finger, and by means of the nail of the small finger of the right hand a
    vessel was isolated, a ligature passed around it with an <choice>
     <orig>aneurism</orig>
     <reg>aneurysm</reg>
    </choice> needle, and this hæmorrhage, most embarrassing because uncontrolled by pressure,
    was finally suppressed. The first ligature was applied at the superior angle of the incision to
    the proximal extremity of the divided femoral vein, from which this unexpected and most annoying
    artery and vein, hæmorrhage escaped by regurgitation from the <choice>
     <orig>saphena</orig>
     <reg>saphenous</reg>
    </choice>. The blood found its way into the limb by means of arteries arising from the iliac
    above the point compressed, was finding its way back by the <choice>
     <orig>saphena</orig>
     <reg>saphenous</reg>
    </choice>, enlarged to compensate for the occlusion of the femoral, was poured into the femoral
    a short distance above its divided proximal extremity, and then regurgitated through the stump
    of the femoral into the superior angle of the incision. The proximal end of the femoral artery,
    from which a crimson tide escaped on relieving the pressure slightly, was now easily found, and
    this was ligated. The wound was now thoroughly cleansed of all clots of blood. The femoral
    artery and vein, denuded of their sheath for a distance of two inches, were clearly seen at the
    bottom of the wound, their divided extremities having become adherent to the neighboring tissues
    during the inflammatory action of the previous ten days. As a precautionary measure a ligature
    was cast around the femoral artery at the lower angle of the wound, and some little difficulty
    was experienced in discriminating between the artery and vein, owing to the fact that from ten
    days disuse the vein in becoming an impervious cord had become similar in size, color, and
    consistency to the artery. A small orifice was observed in the vein near its distal extremity,
    and from this occurred a free black flow on moving the limb. This was also included in a
    ligature. The wound was now closed by one or two sutures and the patient placed in his bed. A
    brief recapitulation may give clearness to the above account. The first vessel tied was,
    therefore, the proximal extremity of the femoral vein near the entrance of the <choice>
     <orig>saphena</orig>
     <reg>saphenous</reg>
    </choice>; the second, the femoral artery a short distance below the origin of the profunda,
    both at the superior angle of the incision; the third, the femoral artery at the lower angle of
    the incision and two inches from its distal extremity; the fourth, the femoral vein near its
    distal extremity at the centre of the incision, and to control a flow from an incision through
    its coats, which may have been made accidentally. The profunda had not been seen, and it was
    hoped that it would suffice to keep up the circulation. No important arterial channels had been
    interfered with by the operation, and a successful issue might be expected. The man was
    stimulated, took morphia, and his leg was covered closely in bed with blankets to preserve the
    animal warmth. This man had lost blood freely at the time of the injury; he had been subjected
    to a very long and fatiguing transport in ambulances and cars before reaching the hospital, and
    for seven days his food had not been as good or sufficient as might have been desired for one
    about to undergo such an operation. He was pallid and haggard looking, and iron, nutrients, and
    stimulants were freely ordered. There was great pain and restlessness during the ensuing night,
    and large quantities of morphia were required to procure sleep. December 10th, no interference
    with the circulation; leg and foot both warm. The whole limb is swollen, and bloody serum
    escapes freely at the point of the injury. December 12th, the restlessness has been the most
    marked symptom, caused seemingly by constant and severe but indescribable pain in the limb. The
    pulse is 120, the countenance pale and haggard, the tongue dry and coated, and the general
    symptoms indicate great nervous prostration. Large quantities of morphia have been found
    requisite. The whole limb and foot are much swollen and œdematous. On the evening
    unmistakable signs of sphacelus appeared, the foot became cold, and a hue of purple
    discoloration was observed as high up as the ankle. The neuralgic pain and restlessness still
    continued. On <date type="death" when="1863-12-13">December 13th</date>, all the symptoms were
    worse. The discoloration, the dark purple hue of gangrene, extended rapidly upward, particularly
    on the inside of the limb. The whole thigh became crepitant, the pulse more rapid and feeble. He
    became more and more depressed, and finally died at 12 o'clock at night. These final scenes all
    surgeons can imagine. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> revealed nothing interesting in the
    great cavities. The whole thigh and leg were found gangrenous as far as the point of the injury.
    The vessels were dissected, spread upon a board, and a most faithful picture was made of them by
    the artist under <name type="person" key="288">Dr. Brinton</name>'s direction. Only the proximal
    extremities of the vessels were found in the softened gangrenous mass; but they threw light upon
    the history of the case. The artery was divided below the origin of the profunda, which was
    uninjured, but not enlarged, as one would expect if the whole force of the circulation had been
    directed toward it by the obliteration of the main artery. In ten days the profunda should here
    have been as large as the femoral, if all the blood brought to the divided femoral had been
    seeking a passage through its calibre. Its undilated condition gives color to the idea that most
    of the blood brought to the divided femoral extremity found its way quickly back by the divided
    femoral vein; that the pressure was thus relieved, and that the profunda received only its usual
    supply of blood. That the limb was nourished by a collateral circulation, arising above the brim
    of the pelvis, is clear from the fact that no pressure on the external iliac would restrain the
    flow of blood from the <choice>
     <orig>saphena</orig>
     <reg>saphenous</reg>
    </choice> through the femoral vein. The <choice>
     <orig>saphena</orig>
     <reg>saphenous</reg>
    </choice> vein is normal, and its relation with the femoral indicates how easily the
    regurgitating hæmorrhage was caused, as no valves are there to prevent it. For several
    days—from the 9th to the 12th—there were no signs of an interference with the
    circulation, but at that time gangrene appeared and spread with great rapidity. This may have
    been due to the recent phlebitis of the profunda vein, which is now filled with a pink firm
    coagulum. The irritation caused by the operation, or due to the passage of the ball, may have
    induced the inflammation of this vein, now so vital to the support of the circulation. This
    seems to have been a wound of an artery, resulting in an <choice>
     <orig>aneurism</orig>
     <reg>aneurysm</reg>
    </choice> the sac of which was composed of the re-united sheaths and enlarged probably by some
    dissection upward, in which a free passage of blood took place from the artery to the vein. No
    question as to the propriety of the operation now exists in my mind, since, as the sequel shows,
    no digital compression over the femoral would have sufficed to prevent or control a secondary
    hæmorrhage." The two specimens were contributed by the operator, <name type="person" key="200">Dr. William Thomson</name> (see <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 19). The case is
    cited by <name type="person" key="70">Dr. Lidell</name>¹. </p>

   <p> ¹ <hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>IDELL (<hi rend="initialcap">J</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>.). <hi rend="italic"/>On the Wounds of Blood-Vessels, Traumatic Hæmorrhage,
    Traumatic <choice>
     <orig>Aneurism</orig>
     <reg>Aneurysm</reg>
    </choice>, and Traumatic Gangrene, in Surgical Memoirs of the War of the Rebellion, collected
    and published by the United States Sanitary Commission<hi rend="italic"/>, 1870, Vol. I
    (Surgical), p. 143. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001518.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 19.—Ligation of femoral artery and vein. <hi rend="italic">Specs</hi>. 2249, 2250.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
