<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e40478">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Blake, Charles N.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d1e40478</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">157</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>purpuric spots on chest</term>
       <term>subarachnoid space contained considerable quantity of liquid</term>
       <term>both lungs contained miliary tubercles</term>
       <term>masses of cheesy tubercle, large cavity communicated anteriorly with bronchial tube</term>
       <term>bronchial glands much enlarged, contained pus in places</term>
       <term>miliary tubercles in liver, deposit of tuberculous matter upon diaphragm immediately above right lobe of liver</term>
       <term>spleen contained numerous miliary tubercles</term>
       <term>both kidneys contained tubercles, especially lower portions</term>
       <term>mesenteric glands enlarged, some tuberculous</term>
       <term>Peyer's patches dotted with black pigment, solitary glands enlarged and hard, ileum presented extravasations of blood into mucous membrane</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of large intestine very thin, dark congested patches in rectum</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-29">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="241">Surgeon Henry Bryant</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge to May, 1863.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 335.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Charles N. Blake</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company B, 4th Vermont volunteers</name>; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-01-02">January 2, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-01-25">January 25th</date>, at 8 A. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-01-26">twenty-nine hours after death</date>: Height five feet five inches; body somewhat emaciated; the abdomen was discolored, and there were purpuric spots on the front of the chest. The brain weighed fifty-two ounces; it was light colored and of normal consistence; the choroid plexuses pale; the pons and medulla congested; the sinuses of the dura mater full of coagulated blood; the subarachnoid space contained a considerable quantity of liquid. Both lungs contained miliary tubercles, and in places masses of cheesy tubercle, especially in the lower lobe of the left lung; in the same lobe there was a large cavity which communicated anteriorly with a bronchial tube of the third magnitude; the right lung weighed thirteen ounces, the left twenty ounces and a quarter. The heart weighed four ounces and a quarter; its muscular tissue had a somewhat gelatinous appearance; the right and left ventricles each contained a small clot; there was very little fat about the heart; the lining membrane of the aorta was reddened as far as its bifurcation; the bronchial glands were much enlarged, white internally, and contained pus in places. The liver weighed forty ounces; scattered throughout its substance were numerous miliary tubercles; the bile was dark colored and viscid; there was a considerable deposit of tuberculous matter upon the under surface of the diaphragm immediately above the right lobe of the liver. The spleen weighed seven ounces; it was of a light reddish-brown color, and contained numerous miliary tubercles. The right kidney weighed five ounces and a quarter, the left kidney five ounces; both kidneys contained tubercles, especially in their lower portions. The pancreas weighed two ounces. The mesenteric glands were slightly enlarged, and some of them were tuberculous. The stomach was large; its mucous membrane soft near the pyloric orifice. Numerous round, hard, small bodies were observed on the mucous membrane of the duodenum; some of them were translucent; the mucous membrane was of a pale purplish color. In the upper part of the jejunum was a small white body a line in diameter, which was surrounded by a reddish areola; other similar white bodies occurred farther down; Peyer's patches were dotted with black pigment; the solitary glands were enlarged and hard; the ileum was red, congested, and presented extravasations of blood into its mucous membrane. In the large intestine the mucous membrane was very thin, and there were several dark congested patches in the rectum.—<name type="person" key="244">Assistant Surgeon George M. McGill</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
