<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e453">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Hight, James</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e453</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">131-132</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>pathology of malarial disease</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial fever</term>
                                        <term>tertian intermittent fever</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-05-26">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch3.sc4.0057">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 57.—<name type="person" key="849">Private James Hight</name>, <name type="organization" key="366">Co. D, 23d Ohio
                                                Vols.</name>; age 23; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1865-01-18">January 18,
                                                1865</date>, with tertian intermittent fever. He had
                                        chills at irregular intervals succeeded by profuse sweating;
                                        his intellect was unnaturally dull; he would not eat nor try
                                        to help himself though he appeared strong; he had no pain;
                                        pulse regular and compressible. The chills yielded readily
                                        to quinine, but he remained without appetite or energy.
                                        After the first week he declined gradually, becoming morose
                                        in disposition and absent-minded, and affected with cough
                                        and diarrhœa. On <date when="1865-02-20">February 20</date> he was reported as
                                        emaciated and imbecile; he had no diarrhœa but
                                        passed his stools in bed. On <date when="1865-03-01">March 1</date> he rallied so as to
                                        answer simple questions correctly; but he had
                                        dyspnœa, much expectoration and extensive crepitus
                                        in both lungs. On the <date type="death" when="1865-03-05">5th</date> he became half comatose with quick short
                                        breathing, and died on the evening of that day. <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination thirteen
                                        hours after death: Much emaciation; blister mark on back of
                                        neck. There was effusion under the cerebral membranes, which
                                        were not injected but pale; the arachnoid at the foramen of
                                        Bichat was thick, opaque and white; the ventricles were
                                        distended with serum; there was a cream-colored spot of
                                        softening, apparently covered by serous membrane, on the
                                        ventricular wall formed by the right corpus striatum; the
                                        middle commissure was remarkably firm, as it stretched out
                                        to nearly an inch in length and so remained without breaking across;
                                        the substance of the cerebrum was hard, that of the
                                        cerebellum and cord soft. The anterior mediastinum was
                                        emphysematous. The bronchi in the right lung and in the
                                        lower lobe of the left lung, especially behind and below,
                                        were dilated, of a dark purple color and filled with a
                                        pus-like fluid, while the lung-tissue around them was here
                                        and there dark and solid, the affected lobes as seen from
                                        the surface being sunken and of a dark lead color. The heart
                                        contained a fibrinous clot. The liver was large and finely
                                        marked with nutmeg foliations; the spleen normal. There were
                                        patches of reddening along the ileum, and pigment patches in
                                        the sigmoid flexure.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="189">Third Division
                                                Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria, Va.</name></hi></p>
                       
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
