<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41857">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Churn, John</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41857</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">260-261</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>typhoid fever</term>
       <term>negro man</term>
       <term>accumulation of pinkish serum in posterior fossæ of cranium</term>
       <term>crude tubercle at base of lung</term>
       <term>accumulated serum in pleural cavities and pericardial sac</term>
       <term>aortic valves atheromatous</term>
       <term>liver enlarged</term>
       <term>both kidneys fatty, right very small, left larger than normal</term>
       <term>omentum contracted into band</term>
       <term>ileum covered with pseudomembrane, particularly lower portion</term>
       <term>Peyer's patches thickened and presented points of commencing ulceration in lower ileum</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of cæcum and colon coated with pseudomembrane and presented large but superficial ulcers</term>
       <term>ileum near ileo-cæcal valve thickened and roughened by adherent pseudomembrane</term>
       <term>large ulcers and patches of adherent pseudomembrane in mucous membrane of rectum, minute follicular ulcers between large ulcers</term>       
       <term>case really dysentery</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-28">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>The history of the following case was forwarded to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>, with the specimens, since the close of the war, by the medical officer whose name is attached:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 870.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private John Churn</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 2d United States colored troops</name>; admitted to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., <date type="admit" when="1866-01-11">January 11, 1866</date>.  Typhoid fever.  Died,<date type="death" when="1866-01-12"> January 12th</date>, at 6 P. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1866-01-14">forty hours after death</date>: A well-formed negro man, five feet six inches high; weight 130 pounds; slightly emaciated; a large triangular scar on the right thigh about an inch above the knee; rigor mortis well marked. The veins of the pia mater were finely congested; the pia mater readily separated from the convolutions of the brain; the substance of the brain was firm; the lining membrane of the lateral ventricles was opaque and appeared to be slightly softened; about two drachms of serum were found in each lateral ventricle; the fornix was slightly softened, the choroid plexus very pale; the pineal gland contained a small amount of calcareous matter; the cerebellum was large, its membranes finely congested; there was an accumulation of about three ounces of pinkish serum in the posterior fossæ of the cranium; weight of the brain was not obtained. At the base of the left lung there was a small amount of crude tubercle; the upper lobe was slightly congested, otherwise the lung was normal; the upper lobe and the posterior portion of the inferior lobe of the right lung were slightly congested; the middle lobe was apparently healthy; about three ounces of serum were found in each pleural cavity. The pericardial sac contained about two ounces of clear yellow serum. The heart was very large and flabby; it was dark colored and presented on its surface numerous dark spots, apparently ecchymoses; there were large white fibrinous clots in all the cavities of the heart, ramifying through the pulmonary artery, the aorta and their branches; the tricuspid and mitral valves were somewhat thickened, the aortic valves atheromatous, the columnæ carneæ; pale. The liver was large, of a dark bronze color, very firm, and slightly congested; the gall-bladder filled with bile. The spleen was normal in size and very firm, of a dark purple color externally, dark brown internally. The right kidney was very small and fatty; the left was larger than normal, being about three times the size of the right kidney; it was congested and very fatty. The ureters showed no abnormal condition. The omentum was firm, dark and congested; it was contracted into a band. The pancreas was large, very firm, and of a dark color. The stomach, near the cardiac orifice, was much congested; its mucous membrane slightly thickened. The mucous coat of the duodenum was thickened, its upper portion much discolored with bile; near the pylorus the solitary follicles were slightly enlarged. The mucous membrane of the jejunum was slightly thickened and congested. The ileum was covered with pseudomembrane, particularly its lower portion; in the upper portion Peyer's patches were slightly thickened, in the lower portion they presented a few points of commencing ulceration. The mucous membrane of the cæcum and colon was coated with pseudomembrane, greatly thickened, and presented a number of large but superficial ulcers. The urinary organs appeared healthy.—<name type="person" key="3420">Hospital Steward Samuel S. Bond</name>.   [Nos. 698 and 699, Medical Section, <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, are from this case.  No. 698 is a portion of the ileum near the ileo-cæcal valve, thickened and roughened by adherent pseudomembrane.  No. 699 is a portion of the rectum much thickened; its mucous membrane presents large ulcers and patches of adherent pseudomembrane; between the large ulcers are numerous minute follicular ulcers.  It will be observed that the case was really one of dysentery. ]</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
