<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e11762">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Fitzgerald, Walter</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e11762</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">890</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>certain diseases not heretofore discussed</term>
                                        <term>poisoning</term>
                                        <term>poisoning by deadly drugs</term>
                                        <term>fatal cases resulted apparently from opium taken by mistake or with suicidal intent</term> 
                                        <term>miliary tubercles in upper lobe of lung</term>
                                        <term>admitted with rheumatic affection</term>
                                        <term>membranes of brain contained bloody serum</term>
                                        <term>liver enlarged and fatty</term>
                                        <term>kidneys fatty, one half usual size</term>
                                        <term>aortic valves presented cartilaginous deposits</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-07-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                        
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body>                        
                        <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1.—<name type="person">Private Walter Fitzgerald</name>, <name type="organization">Co. H., 4th V.R. Corps</name>; age 68; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1865-06-14">June 14, 1865</date>, with a rheumatic affection, from which he so far
                                        recovered as to be able to evade the guard and keep himself
                                        supplied with whiskey. On August 6 he had a slight attack
                                        of delirium which confined him to bed for some days, and on
                                        the 21st a more severe recurrence.  At 9.40 P. M. of <date type="injury" when="1865-08-22">the 22d</date>
                                        it was found that one ounce of laudanum had been
                                        administered by mistake: he was insensible, but could be
                                        aroused by shaking; pupils much contracted, pulse 150;
                                        respiration 10; skin pale and warm; hands like a
                                        washerwoman's. Eight grains of extract of belladonna were at
                                        once given and the patient was kept aroused by the galvanic
                                        battery and friction. At 10.30 the pupils began to dilate;
                                        pulse 144; respiration 10 when in repose, 14 when aroused; the skin seemed regaining its color and the face and hands
                                        were nearly natural. Half an hour later four grains of the
                                        extract of belladonna were administered, under the influence
                                        of which the dilatation of the pupils continued and the
                                        respiration became more frequent, 17; pulse 144; but the
                                        drowsiness increased, and the skin became cooler and assumed
                                        a blue color. Whiskey and carbonate of ammonia were given by
                                        enema.  He lived until 5 P. M. of <date type="death" when="1865-08-23">the next day</date>.  Artificial
                                        respiration was attempted.   <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination: Rigor
                                        mortis slight. The membranes of the brain contained three
                                        ounces and a half of bloody serum and the lateral ventricles
                                        half an ounce, the choroid plexus of each being enlarged;
                                        the cavernous portion of the right internal carotid
                                        contained a long fibrinous clot; the superficial cerebral
                                        veins were engorged. The lungs presented some old
                                        adhesions,—the right was congested, the left had
                                        a small vomica in its apex and miliary tubercles in its
                                        upper lobe. The heart was flabby and contracted; it
                                        contained fibrinous clots which extended into the great
                                        vessels; one of the aortic valves presented a
                                        cartilaginous deposit about the size of a small pea,
                                        another showed a harder deposit, the third was healthy. The
                                        œsophagus was red; the stomach normal; the liver enlarged
                                        and fatty; the gall-bladder distended; the spleen shrunken
                                        and flabby; the kidneys fatty,—the left of
                                        normal size, the right half the usual size and nodulated.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi> </p>                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
