<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31819">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Maxon, C. A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31819</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="at">Alex Thomas</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">374</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the pelvis</term>
       <term>injuries of the genital organs</term>
       <term>wounds of the penis</term>
       <term>wounds of the urethra</term>       
       <term>injuries of the urethra not caused by shot</term>
       <term>atony of bladder</term>
       <term>want of power in bladder to expel contents</term>
       <term>stricture of urethra and false passage</term>
       <term>uses catheter thrice daily</term>
       <term>facial erysipelas</term>              
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-31">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#at" when="2011-02-25">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1086.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private C. A. Maxon</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. C, 130th New York</name>, aged 23 years, was admitted into David's Island Hospital, <name type="place">New York Harbor</name>, <date type="admit" when="1863-11-15">November 15, 1863</date>, with atony of the bladder.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. L. Van Norden</name> reported: "The patient was below the medium size, and of healthy appearance. He stated that since his earliest recollection he had experienced at intervals a want of power in the bladder to expel its contents, and that there never was sufficient contractile power to enable him to throw his water any distance. After a march of two days, some six months since, he arrived at <name type="place">Yorktown</name> in an exhausted condition; says that he first came to himself on the boat going to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> when he found that he had been insensible for five days. At this period his urine was drawn by catheter for the first time. Arriving in <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, he was placed in barracks, where he had retention of urine for two days. He was then sent to <name type="hospital" key="428">Judiciary Square Hospital</name>, where, a day after his arrival, a number of surgeons tried to relieve him by catheterization. Failing in this attempt, puncture of the bladder was advised, when the patient requested to be allowed to try the introduction of the catheter. This being granted, he forced the instrument in and drew off the contents of the bladder. Since then he has not been able to pass his water without a catheter, which he uses thrice daily.  On examination, a false passage was found, but a No. 12 sound could be passed without difficulty. The urine flowed from the bladder without force; the passage of instruments is followed by considerable constitutional disturbance, depriving him of sleep the night following their use.  On <date type="injury" when="1863-11-22">November 22d</date>, the patient had facial erysipelas, for which tincture of iron was prescribed. under this treatment the disease, which had surrounded and partly closed the right eye quite disappeared by the 26th.  The urine was still passed by the catheter on November 29th."  This man was discharged the service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-01-29">January 29, 1864</date>, for "stricture of the urethra and false passage."  He is not a pensioner.</p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
