<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e400101">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Bemis, Edson D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e400101</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1870">1870</date>
     <biblScope type="page">162</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
     <term>gunshot fractures of both tables of the skull</term>
     <term>depressed fractures of both tables</term>
     <term>ball impinged obliquely upon vault of skull</term>
     <term>detached portion of <choice>
       <orig>calvaria</orig>
       <reg>calvarium</reg>
      </choice> without depression of margins</term>
     <term>musket ball fractured shaft of humerus, united kindly with slight angular
      displacement</term>
     <term>musket ball wound to iliac fossa</term>
     <term>ball entered outside frontal protuberance, removed piece of squamous portion of temporal
      bone with brain substance and membranes</term>
     <term>brain matter oozed from wound</term>
     <term>hæmorrhage, not from important vessel</term>
     <term>one side paralyzed, total insensibility</term>
     <term>hemiplegia, later disappeared</term>
     <term>headaches, memory affected, cannot hear as well</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-10-26">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and
    encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Edson D.
     Bemis</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 12th Massachusetts Volunteers</name>,
    was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="33">Antietam</name> by a musket ball which fractured the
    shaft of his left humerus. The fracture united kindly, with very slight angular displacement and
    quarter of an inch shortening. Promoted to be corporal, <name type="person" key="xxx">Bemis</name> received <date type="injury" when="1864-05-06">May 6th, 1864</date>, at the
    battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name> a wound from a musket ball in the
    right iliac fossa. He was treated in the Chester Hospital, near <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>. There was extensive sloughing about the wound, but it ultimately healed
    entirely, leaving a large cicatrix, parallel with Poupart's ligament. <date type="duty" when="1865-01">Eight months after the injury</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Bemis</name>
    returned to duty with his regiment. On <date type="injury" when="1865-02-05">February 5th,
     1865</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal Bemis</name> was again severely wounded at
    the engagement at <name type="BATTLE" key="78">Hatcher's Run</name>, near <name type="place">Petersburg, Virginia</name>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon A. Vanderveer</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">66th New York Volunteers</name>, reports that the ball entered a
    little outside of the left frontal protuberance, and passing backward and upward, removed a
    piece of the squamous portion of the temporal bone, with brain substance and membranes. When the
    patient entered the hospital of the 1st division of the Second Corps, brain matter was oozing
    from the wound. There was considerable hæmorrhage, but not from any important vessel.
    Respiration was slow; the pulse 40; the right side was paralyzed and there was total
    insensibility. On <date type="operation" when="1865-02-08">February 8th</date>, the missile was
    removed from the substance of the left hemisphere, by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon
     Vanderveer</name>. It was a conoidal musket ball, badly battered. The patient's condition at
    once improved. He told the surgeon his name, and seemed conscious of all that was going on about
    him. Water dressings were applied, and an ingeniously arranged sponge absorbed the discharge
    from the wound. He was kept on very light diet and remained very quiet for ten days, answering
    direct questions, but indisposed to continue a conversation. He had no convulsions and his sleep
    was not disturbed by delirium. About February 18th, a marked improvement was manifest. The
    patient conversed freely, and the wound was rapidly cicatrizing, and the hemiplegia had entirely
    disappeared. On February 23th he was able to walk about the ward. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-03-18">March 18th</date> the wound was nearly healed. The patient was sent northward
    on a hospital transport to <name type="place">Fort Richmond, New York Harbor</name>. He
    recovered perfectly, and <date type="furlough" when="1865-05">in May</date> was furloughed, and
    on May 18th he wrote to <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. Vanderveer</name>, that he was doing
    well at his home in <name type="place">Huntington, Massachusetts</name>, suffering only slight
    dizziness in going out in the hot sun. <date type="pension" when="1865-07">In July</date> he
    went to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> to apply for a pension, and
    entered <name type="hospital" key="174">Campbell Hospital</name>. He was discharged on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-07-13">July 13th, 1865</date>, on surgeon's certificate of
    disability. At <date type="photo" when="1865-07-13">this date</date> he was photographed at the
     <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>. The wound in the head was then
    nearly healed. There was a slight discharge of healthy pus from one point. The pulsations of the
    brain could be felt through the integument. The mental and sensory faculties were unimpaired.
    The corporal had been discharged from service and recommended for a pension. The plate opposite
    is a very accurate copy of the photograph, which is numbered 58 of the surgical series, A. M. M.
     <name type="person" key="xxx">Mr. Bemis</name> was pensioned at eight dollars per month. On
     <date type="pension" when="1870-10-30">October 30th, 1870</date>, he wrote to the editor of the
    surgical history from his home in <name type="place">Suffield, Connecticut</name>, as follows:
    'I am still in the land of the living. My health is very good considering what I have passed
    through at <name type="BATTLE" key="78">Hatcher's Run</name>. * * * My head aches
    some of the time. I am married and have one child, a little girl born last Christmas. My memory
    is affected, and I cannot hear as well as I could before I was wounded.'</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001510.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE: GUNSHOT WOUNDS OF EDSON D. BEMIS</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
