<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3987">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Perkins, Jas. H.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e3987</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">239-240</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>continued fevers</term>
          <term>clinical records</term>
          <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
          <term>typhoid fever</term>  
          <term>peritonitis</term>
          <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
          <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
          <term>rheumatism</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00090">
      
        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 90.—<hi rend="italic">Diarrhœa;
            delirium; sordes; pneumonic complication; eruption; slightly marked improvement on 15th
            day, after which free perspirations alternated with diarrhœa; vibices;
            epistaxis; peritonitis; death on the 31st day.</hi>—<name type="person" key="548">Teamster Jas. H. Perkins</name>, <name type="organization" key="635">quartermaster's department</name>; age 23; a
          Virginian; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-09-30">Sept. 30, 1861</date>.
          Diagnosis—typhoid fever. He had been taken with diarrhœa on <date type="injury" when="1861-09-25">the 25th</date>
          and with head-pain and rheumatism on the 27th. On admission his face was flushed, eyes
          bright, pulse 96, quick and strong, tongue moist and slightly coated white; his bowels had
          been opened three times during the previous twenty-four hours, and the iliac regions were
          tender and tympanitic; he had also some cough. Calomel, opium and tartar emetic were
          prescribed. On October 1 the bowels were quiet, but there was some pain in the chest when
          coughing, with <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> over the lower lobes of the lungs. Small doses of calomel and
          quinine were given. He had three stools on the 2d. Next day the pulse ran up to 112, and
          complaint was made of headache and backache. Tincture of iron and camphor with opium were
          prescribed. He vomited twice on the 4th. His skin became moist on the 5th, and on the
          following day was covered with a profuse perspiration; but there was some delirium and
          much twitching of the tendons. On the 6th emulsion of turpentine was administered. On the
          7th the pulse was 105, quick and strong, the skin natural, the tongue moist and heavily
          coated yellow; four stools were passed; the transverse and descending portions of the
          colon were tympanitic and the umbilical region tender; he had some cough, with slight pain
          in the right side below the nipple, and there was <choice><orig>dulness</orig><reg>dullness</reg></choice> on percussion over the lower
          lobes of both lungs, especially marked on the right side. On the 8th the skin was hot and
          dry and the bowels loose. On the 9th the patient was wakeful at night and dull and stupid
          during the day; the pulse 120, quick and strong; the skin hot and dry, showing some
          eruption (the character of which is not stated); the tongue red, fissured at the edges and
          coated dark-brown in the centre; the teeth and lips covered with sordes; he had, moreover,
          deafness, delirium, anorexia and diarrhœa. He continued in this condition until
          the 15th, when the tongue became moist, yellowish at the centre and red at the tip and
          edges, and the delirium and deafness were somewhat less marked; the pulse had fallen to
          100. The skin was bathed in perspiration on the 16th and 17th, and this condition recurred
          on the 19th, 21st, 23d and 25th. Three or four stools were passed on the alternate days
          when the skin was hot and dry, but on the days when the skin was moist the bowels remained
          quiet except on the 21st, when they were moved six times. On the 19th vibices appeared on
          the skin and on the 23d became very numerous. On the 21st the pulse rose again to 120, and
          there was epistaxis with low delirium and increased deafness. The epistaxis recurred on
          the 22d. The patient became almost pulseless on <date type="death" when="1861-10-25">the 25th</date>; his skin was bathed in perspiration, and there was acute pain in the
          abdomen. He died on this day. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
