<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e30896">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Boyce, W. D.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e30896</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="cm">Clint Mink</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">953</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and operations of the forearm</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the forearm</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the forearm</term>
       <term>excisions in the continuity of the bones of the forearm for shot injury</term> 
       <term>intermediary excisions in the bones of the forearm</term> 
       <term>recoveries after intermediary excisions</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of forearm</term>
       <term>ball entered posterior and middle forearm, produced fracture of middle third of ulna, lodged in wound</term> 
       <term>compound comminuted fracture of middle third of shaft of ulna</term>
       <term>middle portion of shaft of ulna removed</term>
       <term>loss of rotatory motion of forearm, elbow dislocated</term>
       <term>cannot close hand, arm useless</term>
       <term>pronation and supination destroyed</term>        
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#cm" when="2011-02-24">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1907.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private W. D. Boyce</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. I, 124th New York</name>, age 37 years, was wounded before <name type="BATTLE" key="xxx">Petersburg</name> <date type="injury" when="1864-10-27">October 27, 1864</date>. On <date type="admit" when="1864-10-28">the following day</date> he was admitted to the Depot Hospital of the Second Corps, at <name type="place">City Point</name>, where <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon G. B. Parker</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, recorded:  " Gunshot wound of right arm. <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon O. A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, reported the wounded man's admission to <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="transfer" when="1864-10-30">October 30th</date>, and described
    the injury and operation, which he performed, as follows:  "Gunshot wound of right forearm, a conoidal ball entering the posterior and middle portion, producing a compound
    comminuted fracture of the middle third of the shaft of the ulna, and lodging in the wound. At date of admission the wounded parts were greatly swollen and slightly œdematous.
    The constitutional state, however, was tolerably good, but he seemed somewhat exhausted, and was suffering from anorexia.  On <date type="operation" when="1864-11-01">November 1st</date>, the patient was anæsthetized and
    the wound thoroughly examined, when it was thought proper that excision should be performed. Six inches of the middle portion of the shaft of the ulna was removed by a
    straight incision and the missile was extracted. The patient rallied promptly from the shock of the operation and continued to improve without any unfavorable complication, the
    wound filling rapidly with healthy granulations. Simple dressings were applied, and tonics and nourishing diet were administered.  December 31st, the wound is healing rapidly.
    The above treatment has been continued; patient has had no unfavorable symptom.  March 31st, the wound has entirely healed with loss of rotatory motion of forearm, otherwise the
    arm being very useful."  The specimen, consisting of the excised portion of the ulna, and represented in the adjacent wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 692), was contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="102">the operator</name>.  The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-04-13">April 13, 1865</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. Nichols</name>, of <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, <date type="pension" when="1865-04-20">April 20, 1865</date>, certified:  " *  *  Great deformity. Limb entirely useless for even light labor. It is an impediment to labor," etc.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. H. Helmer</name>, of <name type="place">Lockport, N. Y.</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1865-08-29">August 29, 1865</date>:  " *  *  Elbow dislocated. He cannot close his hand," etc. The <name type="organization" key="xxx">Lockport Examining Board</name>, consisting of <name type="person" key="xxx">Drs. Helmer</name> and <name type="person" key="xxx">S. T. Clark</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1873-10-11">October 11, 1873</date>:  " *  *  Dislocation of elbow still unreduced.  *  *  Pronation and stipulation is destroyed. The arm is "useless, as perfectly so as if amputated at the elbow joint." The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>. A photograph, taken <date type="photo" when="1865-04">about the time of his discharge</date>, and recently obtained from the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Pension Bureau</name>, is copied in the annexed cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 693).</p>
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001835.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 692.—Six inches of right ulna excised for shot fracture.—<hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 4235.</head>
   </figure> 
   
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001833.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 693.—Cicatrix six months after an excision in the shaft of the ulna.</head>
   </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
