<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20155">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Burk, John C.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e20155</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">575</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term> 
                                                                  <term>operations on the chest</term>
                                                                  <term>excisions</term>
                                                                  <term>thoracentesis</term>
                                                                  <term>thoracentesis for effusion following perforation of chest by small projectile</term>
                                                                  <term>paracentesis thoracis</term>
                                                                  <term>ball entered half way between sternum and side, between sixth and seventh ribs</term>
                                                                  <term>ball injured lung</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                                <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 13.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private John C. Burk</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. B, 5th United States Cavalry</name>, aged 28 years, was
                                                                wounded at <name type="battle">Manassas Gap</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-07-21">July 21st, 1863</date>, by a
                                                  ball, which entered the left side of the body
                                                  better than half way between sternum and side,
                                                  between sixth and seventh ribs, passing backwards
                                                  and upwards, emerging just below the outer and
                                                  inferior angle of the left scapula, injuring the
                                                  left lung. There was considerable hæmorrhage at
                                                  time of injury. He was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., on <date type="admit" when="1863-07-30">July 30th, 1863</date>,
                                                  when vesicular murmur was heard over upper portion
                                                  of lung; dull over lower; but over region of
                                                  wound, loud crackling; air rushing in and out
                                                  during respiration; pulse, 84; tongue somewhat
                                                  flabby and furred; bowels, costive; no passage
                                                  for nine days. On <date type="operation" when="1863-08-21">August 21st</date>, after consultation,
                                                                paracentesis thoracis was performed by <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, between the sixth and seventh
                                                  ribs; no pus escaped. Patient improved until
                                                  September 8th, after which he grew worse,
                                                  suffering from pain in chest, and failing rapidly;
                                                  continually calling for water, but refusing food
                                                  and medicine. He died on <date type="death" when="1863-09-11">September 11, 1863</date>. <hi rend="italic">Post mortem</hi> nineteen hours after death; rigidity well
                                                                  marked; not much emaciated; parts <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi>; right
                                                  lung barely visible; left lung bound anteriorly
                                                  to costal pleura, a little behind the junction of
                                                  the cartilages in the ribs, extending from the
                                                  clavicle to the fourth rib. Behind and below it,
                                                  was a collection of pus measuring thirty-six fluid
                                                  ounces and six drachms. The pleura everywhere was
                                                  covered with a thick layer of lymph; a small sac
                                                  was found between the internal portion of the
                                                  lung and the pericardium, filled with a straw
                                                  colored limpid serum. Position of heart somewhat
                                                  deviated, the apex being in the median line on a
                                                  level with the fifth rib, the left side of the
                                                  heart being parallel with the median line, the
                                                  right side being thrown much beyond it,
                                                  encroaching considerably on the right thoracic
                                                  cavity. The left lobe of the liver extended three
                                                  inches to the left of the median line; the free
                                                  margin of the right lobe extended down within an
                                                  inch of the umbilicus. The fundus of the stomach
                                                  was seen beneath the left lobe. Intestines, normal; a few fibrinous threads were present; omentum
                                                  not visible; œsophagus of dark purple color;
                                                  mucous membrane firm; trachea purplish; contained
                                                  a small quantity of viscid mucus. Bronchial glands
                                                  enlarged and blackened 1st lobe of right lung;
                                                  pigmentary matter abundant externally, parenchyma
                                                  of a darkish red color, paler toward the surface;
                                                  permeated everywhere with air, and a large
                                                  quantity of thin frothy matter exuded on pressure.
                                                  On the second lobe was a conspicuous depressed
                                                  puckered spot on its anterior surface, which, upon
                                                  examination proved to be calcareous deposit. Third
                                                  lobe intensely congested, being of a deep dark
                                                  reddish color; veins filled with clotted blood,
                                                  and the same character of bronchial secretion as
                                                  seen in the first lobe. Left lung much collapsed,
                                                  being a little over an inch in thickness; much
                                                  compressed; of a dull mahogany color, and not
                                                  permeated with air, except the anterior median
                                                  portion. Right lung weighed nineteen ounces; left
                                                  lung weighed twenty-two ounces. Heart measured
                                                  three and a quarter inches in width and four
                                                  inches long; right auricle contained a small
                                                  quantity of venous blood, which was entangled in
                                                  soft clots in the meshes of the tricuspid valve,
                                                  particularly at the base, and a firm fibrinous
                                                  clot ran through the auricle into the ventricle,
                                                  thence up into the pulmonary artery, the valves of
                                                  which were healthy. The left side of the heart
                                                  contained no clot; a small quantity of blackish
                                                  fluid was seen at the base of the ventricle; the
                                                  organ was perfectly healthy, and weighed ten and a
                                                  half ounces. Pericardial fluid, twenty-six
                                                  drachms, of a turbid yellowish color, turbid with
                                                  lymph. Liver measured twelve by ten inches, and
                                                  four and a half inches thick; weighed ninety-five
                                                  and a half ounces; bile, one drachm; of a dark
                                                  sienna brown color, very viscid, semi opaque;
                                                  liver perfectly healthy. Spleen, six inches long
                                                  by three and a half inches wide; of a darkish
                                                  mahogany color externally and internally; weight,
                                                  twelve ounces. Right kidney, five inches long by
                                                  three wide; of a dark purple color throughout;
                                                  pyramidal bodies of a lighter color than the
                                                  cortical, especially at their apices. Left kidney,
                                                  five and a half inches long by two and a half wide; similar in appearance to the opposite kidney;
                                                  right weighed seven and three-quarter ounces;
                                                  left, eight and a quarter ounces. Pancreas weighed
                                                  four and a quarter ounces, ten inches long by two
                                                  and a quarter inches across head. Brain, membranes
                                                  healthy; quantity of fluid in the ventricles
                                                  inappreciable; organ, firm and healthy; weight,
                                                  forty-eight ounces. Intestines, perfectly healthy.
                                                  The ball entered in the back two inches below the
                                                  spine of the scapula, and four inches from the
                                                  vertebræ, making its exit eight and a half inches
                                                  below the coracoid process between the seventh and
                                                  eighth ribs of the left side. The case is reported
                                                  by the operator, <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name> </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
