<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41088">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Pickett, Orange</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41088</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">170</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>pericardium contained fluid</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of lower third of small intestine of dark-purple color, purple color seemed below surface, due to altered color of villi</term>
       <term>entire large intestine presented extensive ragged confluent ulcerations, surface studded with elevated patches of dark-red</term>        
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-12">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="242">Assistant Surgeon Roberts Bartholow</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge from August 21st to December, 1863.</p>              
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 369.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Orange Pickett</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company K, 7th Michigan cavalry</name>; age 33; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-08-18">August 18, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  [This man appears on the register of the hospital of the Cavalry corps of the army of the Potomac, then near <name type="place">Warrenton Junction, Virginia</name>, admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-08-16">August 16th</date>—diarrhœa—sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1863-08-18">August 18th</date>.]  Died, <date type="death" when="1863-08-24">August 24th</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1863-08-25">twenty hours and a half after death</date>: Body not emaciated; rigor mortis strong; height five feet six inches. The brain was healthy, and weighed fifty-four ounces; the lateral ventricles contained but little fluid. The mucous membrane of the œsophagus œsophagus was pale above, of a light-ochre color toward the cardiac orifice. The trachea contained a small quantity of frothy secretion; its mucous membrane was pale with purplish spots, the spaces between the rings being of a darker hue than the rings themselves. There were extensive old pleuritic adhesions on the right side. The right lung weighed nineteen ounces and a half; it was congested throughout, but sections floated in water; the left lung also was congested, and weighed eighteen ounces and a half. The pericardium contained four drachms and a half of fluid. The heart weighed ten ounces; its valves were healthy; its right cavities contained a large fibrinous clot which extended into the pulmonary artery beyond its bifurcation; the left cavities contained a smaller clot. The liver was firm, its acini well marked, its capsule readily elevated; it weighed seventy-six ounces and a half; the gall-bladder contained eight drachms and a half of thick tar-like sienna-brown bile. The spleen weighed fourteen ounces; it was of a dark flesh-color externally; its trabeculæ were prominent, its texture unusually firm. The pancreas was firm and of a dull white color. The kidneys were flabby, and weighed five ounces and a half each; their cortical substance was unusually pale, with slightly injected vessels, the pyramids of a darker hue, the pelves of a delicate pink; the left kidney was somewhat more injected than the right. The small intestine presented nothing abnormal except in its lower third; here the mucous membrane was of a dark-purple color and greatly softened, being readily detached by the fingernail; the purple color seemed to he below the surface, and was surmounted by a tawny-green appearance resembling an exudation; this was due to the altered color of the villi, as was evident on placing the specimen under water; Peyer's patches were not affected, and the solitary glands were not visible. The large intestine, from one end to the other, presented extensive ragged confluent ulcerations; the surface was studded irregularly with elevated patches of a dark-red color, which at first sight resembled mucous membrane, but which were found to consist of a soft exudation-product readily removed by the finger.—<name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon Harrison Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>⃰</p>
   <p>⃰ September 14, 1864, <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name> presented to the Pathological Society of Philadelphia a brief "<hi rend="italic">Synopsis of Autopsies made at <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln General Hospital</name></hi>," to which the reader is referred.—(Proceedings of the Pathological Society of Philadelphia, in the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, January, 1865, page 133.)  In this paper he analyzes the appearances observed in forty-one cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, thirty-five of fever, twenty-one of pneumonia, and five of diphtheria. The notes of <name type="person" key="245">Dr. Allen</name>'s autopsies, from which the accounts here presented have been condensed, were not contained in the case-books of <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln hospital</name> turned in to the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Surgeon General's Office</name> at the close of the war, but have since been copied into them from the originals, loaned for the purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
