<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e4199">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Hensel, Samuel</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e4199</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">75-76</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>                                                                 
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot wounds at the hip with fracture of the articular surfaces</term>
     <term>treated on expectant plan</term> 
     <term>incisions and removals of fragments or foreign bodies consistent with true conservative treatment</term> 
     <term>parts injured not particularly specified</term>
     <term>ball entered central portion of buttock</term> 
     <term>ball fractured head of femur</term>
     <term>compound fracture of thigh, upper third</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 153.—<name type="person" key="931">Private Samuel
      Hensel</name>, <name type="organization" key="380">Co. H, 114th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 31
     years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="257">Chancellorsville, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3, 1863</date>, by a musket ball,
     which entered the central portion of the left buttock. The soldier was conveyed by steamer to
     <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, where, on <date type="admit" when="1863-05-08">May 8th</date>, he was received into
      <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>. The wound was probed daily in
     search of the missile, which, at the end of two weeks, presented itself at the point of
     entrance and was extracted by the patient. He states that it was a round ball, but was
     flattened on one side, and had, in this surface, a clean cut filled with osseous matter. The
     treatment consisted of rest, position, and the application of cold-water dressings. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-06-16">June 16th</date> the patient was transferred to McKim's Mansion Hospital, in <name type="place">Baltimore</name>. About the <date type="injury" when="1863-07">middle of
       July</date> the nurse, while dressing the wound, discovered in it a foreign substance, which, upon
     removal, proved to be a portion of the haversack. The patient was soon afterwards transferred
     to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Mower Hospital, Philadelphia</name>. <date type="injury" when="1863-09">Early in September</date> a
     spicula of bone, nearly two inches in length by one in width in its central portion, was extracted from the wound. Flaxseed poultices
     were applied. Subsequently ten other pieces, varying in size from one-fourth to one inch in
     length, were eliminated. The wound soon closed and the patient was able to get about on
     crutches. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-09-24">September 24th</date> he was transferred
     to <name type="hospital" key="xx">McClellan Hospital, Philadelphia</name>, where, on <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-05-13">May 13, 1864</date>, he was discharged from service "because of a compound fracture of the left thigh, upper third,
     incapacitating him for duty." <name type="person" key="xx">Pension Examining Surgeon H. L. Hodge</name>, of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, reported, <date type="pension" when="1864-05-26">May 26, 1864</date>: "On account of a gunshot fracture, probably of the os innominatum (left), there is a luxation of the head of the femur, which destroys the usefulness of the whole limb." On <date type="pension" when="1866-11-01">November 1, 1866</date>, an apparatus was fitted to the
     disabled limb by <name type="organization" key="xx">Gemrig</name>, of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Examining Surgeon James Cummiskey</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1867-04-06">April 6, 1867</date>: "Was wounded by a ball entering the left buttock and lodging
     for a time in the left groin, fracturing the head of the femur badly, and resulting in shortening of the limb about three and
     a half inches and much wasting and feebleness of the limb. He is obliged to wear constantly an
     iron instrument to support the limb in walking. He suffers much pain at night." In a
     communication to this office dated <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, <date type="pension" when="1868-02-13">February 13, 1868</date>, <name type="person" key="931">Mr. Hensel</name> states that he is unable to walk without the use of the apparatus
     and a cane, but by the aid of these he can walk from a half to three-quarters of a mile, being
     obliged, however, to rest for two or three minutes once or twice by the way on account of pain
     and weakness in the limb. The <name type="organization" key="xx">Philadelphia Examining
      Board</name>, <name type="person" key="xx">Drs. H. E. Goodman</name>, <name type="person" key="xx">T. C. Rich</name>, and <name type="person" key="xx">James Collins</name>, reported,
     <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>: "Has had a ball enter the left buttock, which was extracted from the wound
     of entrance. Has lost bone from head of femur, and the limb is nearly three and a half inches
     shortened. He has to wear a support with a high heel and sole shoe. Motion of hip joint limited
     to one-eighth degree. Spine curved from short limb."  </p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
