<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e28724">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Steel, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2011</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e28724</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">818, 850</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term> 
     <term>hospital gangrene</term>
     <term>ball struck outer side of leg, passed straight inward through upper belly of gastrocnemius, came out on inner side of calf</term>
     <term>foot became blue, toes deeper hue, gradually increased up ankle and lower third of the leg</term> 
     <term>amputation through wound</term> 
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>gangrene due to impaired arterial circulation</term> 
     <term>furnished with artificial leg</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-31">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-06-05">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1209.—<name type="person" key="1513">Private W.
      Steel</name>, <name type="organization" key="525">Co. G, 70th New York</name>, aged 26 years,
     was wounded in the left leg, at <name type="BATTLE" key="80">Manassas Gap</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-07-23">July 23, 1863</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-07-30">one week afterwards</date>.  <name type="person" key="245">Assistant Surgeon H. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, recorded the following description of the injury: "The ball struck on the outer
     side of the leg, passing in a straight line inward through the upper part of the belly of the
     gastrocnemius, and coming out on the inner side of the calf. The bleeding was copious.
     Immediately after the reception of the wound the man experienced a severe pain in the ankle and
     was totally unable to walk, only dragging the limb after him. When admitted into <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name> the foot had become bluish, which appearance
     the patient stated had come on two days previously. The pain in the ankle passed off the first
     evening, but when the blueness commenced the pain reappeared and continued to increase in severity until the date of
     amputation. The color of the foot was that of bluish stone, but not shrivelled, the toes being
     of a deeper hue than the rest. This appearance gradually increased up to the ankle, and then
     ran up posteriorly to the lower third of the leg. Amputation through the wound was performed by
     flap method on <date type="operation" when="1863-08-03">August 3d</date>. After the operation the constitutional symptoms, such as pale and
     tremulous tongue, quick and feeble pulse, continued about the same. The flaps were pale and rather flabby, but not gangrenous. A
     diarrhœa set in, which was checked by August 25th; appetite capricious. By October
     20th had entirely recovered, the stump having healed without exfoliating any bone."  On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-01-30">January 30, 1864</date>, the patient was discharged from
     service and pensioned, and subsequently he was furnished with a "Palmer" artificial leg. In his
     application for commutation the pensioner describes the stump as being in a healthy condition.
     He was paid <date type="pension" when="1880-12-04">December 4, 1880</date>. A representation of the gangrenous limb is given in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXXIX</hi>, opposite p. 818.</p>
   
     <figure>
      <graphic url="cww.001826.001"/>
      <head>PLATE  LXXIX.      FIG.  2   GANGRENE  OF  FOOT  AFTER  SHOT  WOUND  OF  LEG  UPPER  THIRD.     Case of Pt Wm. Steel, 70 New York</head>
     </figure>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
