<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e22655">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Perkins, J. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e22655</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">594</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations at the ankle joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the ankle joint</term>
     <term>excisions at the ankle joint for shot injury</term> 
     <term>secondary excisions at the ankle joint</term> 
     <term>fatal secondary excisions at the ankle joint</term> 
     <term>wounds of right and left ankle joints</term>
     <term>ball entered above external malleolus of right ankle, passed through and entered internal malleolus of left ankle</term>
     <term>resection of right ankle joint</term> 
     <term>amputation of left leg at lower third</term> 
     <term>suppuration followed resection, extending up leg to its middle</term>     
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 862.—<name type="person" key="1379">Private J. C. Perkins</name>, <name type="organization" key="522">Co. B, 81st New York</name>, aged 27
     years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="16">Cold Harbor</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-03">June 3, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon W. H. Rice</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="xx">81st New York</name>, reported his admission to the field hospital of the 1st division, Eighteenth Corps, with "wound of ankles by a minié ball."  <date type="transfer" when="1864-06-15">Twelve
     days after the reception of the injury</date> the wounded man was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="173">Harewood Hospital</name>, Washington, where both limbs were operated upon by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who made the following report:  "The patient was suffering from wounds of the
     right and left ankle joints, the ball entering above the external malleolus of the right ankle,
     passing directly through, and entering the internal malleolus of the left ankle. On admission
     and at the time of the operation the condition of the injured parts was not good. The wounds
     suppurated freely. There were detached portions of bone in each joint, and necrosed fragments came away from time to time. The
     constitutional state of the patient was poor. Resection of the right ankle joint and circular
     amputation of the left leg at the lower third was performed on<date type="operation" when="1864-07-07">July 7th</date>, the anæsthetic
     consisting of sulphuric ether and chloroform. The result of the operation was unfavorable. The
     stump sloughed and profuse unhealthy suppuration followed the resection, extending in every
     direction and burrowing up the leg nearly to its middle. The patient became very weak and sank
     gradually. He died of exhaustion <date type="death" when="1864-07-17">July 17, 1864</date>. The
     treatment was tonic and supporting throughout."  The tarsal bones of the right foot, together
     with the lower extremity of the tibia, were contributed to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon Bontecou</name> and constitute specimen 3035 of the <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>. </p>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
