<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e5050">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wright, Hugh</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e5050</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">102-103</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>excision at the hip after shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary excisions</term>
     <term>ball entered thigh, shattered neck and trochanters of femur, lodged amid fragments of
      bone</term>
     <term>joint distended with pus</term>
     <term>persistent recurring abscesses, discharge of pus</term>
     <term>infected fistulæ and sinuses</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
     <term>cardiac disease</term>
     <term>remaining end of femur attached to pelvis by ligamentous tissue</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-16">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 240.—<name type="person" key="948">Private Hugh
     Wright</name>, <name type="organization" key="389">Co. G, 87th New York</name>, aged 28 years,
    a robust, healthy man, was wounded on <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>,
    at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="259">the Wilderness</name>, by a conoidal musket ball,
    which entered the right thigh an inch within the track of the femoral vessels and two inches
    below Poupart's ligament, passed backward and outward, shattering the neck and trochanters of
    the femur, and, having been greatly flattened and distorted by the impact, it lodged amid the
    fragments of bone. The precise direction of the fracture is indicated in the accompanying
    wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 54).¹ He stated that after being wounded, he was
    carried to the rear by a number of his companions, and, in the evening, was taken to the field
    hospital of the 2d division of the Second Corps. Here he remained for <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-08">three days</date>. He was then sent in an ambulance wagon to <name type="place">Fredericksburg</name>, and placed in a temporary hospital. He stated that his
    wound was repeatedly examined by different surgeons, but that no treatment was instituted beyond
    the application of a compress dipped in cold water to the wound. He was transferred, <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-22">after a fortnight</date>, on a hospital steamer, to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, and on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-25">May 25th</date> he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>,
    then under the charge of <name type="person" key="405">Surgeon B. B. Wilson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name> He was placed in Ward 6, under the care of <name type="person" key="949">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. B. Garland</name>, who communicated a
    special report of the case. The injured limb was swollen, everted, and shortened. Pus had
    accumulated in the tissues about the hip. Notwithstanding the gravity of the injury, the
    patient's constitutional condition is said to have been hopeful. On exploring the wound with the
    finger, the patient being under the influence of chloroform, detached fragments of bone could be
    felt. On consultation with <name type="person" key="459">Acting Assistant Surgeon George A.
     Mursick</name>,² an operation was decided upon, for the purpose of removing these loose
    fragments, and the missile, if it could be found. On <date type="operation" when="1864-05-27">May 27th</date>, the patient was rendered insensible by sulphuric ether, and <name type="person" key="459">Dr. Mursick</name>, assisted by <name type="person" key="949">Dr.
     Garland</name> and others, made a straight incision, commencing above and behind the trochanter
    major and carried downward in the axis of the thigh. It was not in contemplation, at the
    beginning of the operation, <name type="person" key="949">Dr. Garland</name> states, to
    exarticulate the head of the femur; but when the muscular attachments were divided, and the full
    extent of the fracture was revealed, and the joint was found distended with pus, it was at once
    determined to make a formal excision. The fragments of the neck were extracted piecemeal. The
    ball was found lying behind the neck, and was extracted. The capsular ligament being freely
    incised, a bistoury was inserted into the cotyloid cavity and the round ligament was severed,
    and the head of the femur was removed without difficulty. The jagged upper extremity of the
    shaft of the femur was then turned out of the wound by carrying the limb over the opposite knee,
    and was smoothed off by a chain saw. There was but trifling hæmorrhage, and no ligatures
    were required. The wound was carefully cleansed, dressed with dry lint, and left to heal by
    granulation. To keep the limb in position, long sand bags were laid on either side of it, and
    moderate extension was made by means of a weight attached to the leg and suspended from the foot
    of the bed. At night he took a grain of sulphate of morphia in a draught. The operation seemed
    to depress him very much, and reaction was slow. He passed a restless night, manifesting much
    nervous excitement. In the morning his pulse was feeble and frequent; his tongue dry and furred.
    He was ordered an ounce of brandy every three hours, a grain of opium every four hours, and as
    much beef tea and concentrated nourishment as he could take. On May 29th his general condition
    had much improved; the pulse was less frequent and stronger. There was free suppuration. The
    wound was dressed with a weak solution of permanganate of potassa. On June 1st he continued to
    improve, the wound looked well, and the character of the suppuration was good. The amount of
    brandy was reduced to four ounces daily. On August 1st he was still doing well. The wound was
    filled up with granulations from the bottom, with the exception of a sinus leading to the bone.
    It continued to suppurate quite freely, and some small pieces of dead bone had come away with
    the discharges. He had gained in flesh, and his health and spirits were good. On August 22d, he
    attempted, for the first time, to sit up in bed, but, owing to the rigidity of the parts and the
    agglutination of the muscles, the pain caused by the sitting posture was so severe that he was
    compelled to lie down again. Cold evaporating lotions were applied to the thigh. On August 23d
    the upper part of the thigh swelled and was painful, and the discharge was increased in
    quantity. On August 27th the swelling of the thigh had increased, the discharge from the wound
    was very free, thin, and flaky, and the surrounding surface was glazed and doughy to the touch.
    The wound of entrance had re-opened and discharged thin pus. An abscess formed on the inner side
    of the thigh, and about four ounces of thin flaky pus was discharged. The patient was restless.
    He was ordered twenty drops of the tincture of the sesquichloride of iron every six hours, with
    stimulants and nutritious diet. On September 1st the swelling and inflammation of the thigh
    continued. He complained of nausea and want of appetite. An abscess formed on the outer side of
    the thigh. On September 5th the abscess was incised, and a large quantity of thin, flaky, and
    offensive pus was evacuated. He had an irritable stomach, and Hoffman's anodyne was
    administered. On September 6th the edges of the incision in the abscess were beginning to
    slough, and nitric acid was freely applied. On September 9th he had diarrhœa; ten grains of
    subnitrate of bismuth and a grain of opium were given every six hours. On September 13th the
    diarrhœa had nearly ceased. The patient's general condition had improved, and the wound
    looked well, though the suppuration was still copious, and had improved in quality. On <date type="operation" when="1864-09-25">September 25th</date> a large ring-shaped exfoliation from
    the upper end of the femur was removed through the wound of operation. On September 26th another
    exfoliation was removed. On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-10-06">October 6th,
     1864</date>, <name type="person" key="948">Private Wright</name> was discharged from the
    military service on account of the expiration of his enlistment. On <date type="injury" when="1864-10-07">October 7th</date> the swelling of the thigh had subsided; the discharge from
    the wounds had much diminished in quantity, and presented the appearance of laudable pus; the
    diarrhœa had ceased, and his general condition was much improved, he being able to sit up
    in bed. On October 30th, a sinus communicating with necrosed bone opened on the outside of the
    thigh. In the <date type="operation" when="1864-12">latter part of December</date>, another
    abscess formed on the outer side of the thigh. When this was opened the swelling and
    inflammation subsided. He continued to do well until <date type="operation" when="1865-02-06">February 6, 1865</date>, when another abscess formed in the lower third of the thigh, on the
    outer side. This was incised and the pus evacuated. Several pieces of dead bone came away with
    the discharges from the wound of operation. About the middle of March, 1865, he was able to get
    out of bed, and to walk about the ward on crutches. Soon after, in getting out of bed, "he
    let his leg fall and hurt it." This accident was followed by inflammation and swelling of
    the thigh, and an abscess in the lower third of it, on the inner side. This was incised, and a
    small quantity of pus was evacuated. He was now attacked with erysipelas, which extended from
    the knee to the hip. This was combated with tonics and stimulants, such as iron and quinine, and
    rapidly disappeared. From this time he did well, taking daily exercise about the hospital on
    crutches. On <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-17">April 17th</date>, he was transferred to
    the Ward Hospital, at <name type="place">Newark, New Jersey</name>. His general health was
    tolerably good. He could not bear much weight on his limb, and inflammation and abscesses
    followed any unusual exertion. He remained at this hospital until <date type="hospitaldischarge" when="1865-05-06">May 6, 1865</date>, when it was reported that he "eloped." As a
    discharged soldier, he was no longer under military authority, and was at liberty to go. For
    many months, though diligent inquiries were made, he could not be traced; but, in <date type="pension" when="1866-07">July, 1866</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon General
     L. W. Oakley</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">New Jersey</name>, transmitted a letter
    from <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. W. Pierson</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Orange,
     New Jersey</name>, which stated that <name type="person" key="xx">Wright</name> had entered the
    almshouse at that place in <date type="pension" when="1865-06">June, 1865</date>, and had
    remained there until the following spring, under <name type="person" key="xx">Dr.
    Pierson</name>'s professional care. At first, the mutilated limb had been enormously swollen
    from œdema, and there was an ichorous discharge from a sinus near the hip joint. With
    careful bandaging, the œdema gradually disappeared. In the spring of 1866, <name type="person" key="948">Wright</name> left the almshouse, and engaged himself as a laborer on a
    farm. He wore, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Pierson</name> reported, a cork-soled shoe of
    his own manufacture. The limb was shortened precisely five inches. The circumference of the
    injured thigh at the highest part was one inch less than that of its fellow. He walked well
    without crutch or cane, bearing his full weight on the mutilated limb. There was quite free
    motion at the hip, but little at the knee. There were no open <choice>
     <orig>fistules</orig>
     <reg>fistulæ</reg>
    </choice>, and no tenderness about any of the cicatrices. <name type="person" key="xx">Dr.
     Stephen Wickes</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Orange</name>, reported, in the summer of
    1866, that <name type="person" key="948">Wright</name> was in good health, though somewhat
    intemperate; that he worked daily at light tasks, and was even able to mow grass. He commonly
    walked with a cane. According to the measurement of <name type="person" key="xx">Dr.
     Wickes</name>, the limb was shortened four and three-quarter inches. About this period, <name type="person" key="459">Dr. Mursick</name>, the operator in the case, discovered his former
    patient, and examined him. He found the resected end of the femur firmly attached to the pelvis
    by ligamentous tissue an inch and a half long. The agglutination of the muscular sheaths had
    nearly disappeared. The limb was quite under control. The man could flex and extend it slightly,
    and adduct to a limited extent; the power of rotating and abducting was lost. Motion at the knee
    was quite restricted, on account of the thickening and consolidation of the surrounding tissues
    resulting from inflammation. He stated that latterly the improvement in his limb had been very
    decided; that when he first commenced to walk, the limb felt like a weight attached to the body;
    this sensation had entirely disappeared. <date type="pension" when="1867-01-15">January 15,
     1867</date>, <name type="person" key="948">Hugh Wright</name> was found duly established at his
    residence in <name type="place">North Orange, Essex, New Jersey</name>, receiving a pension
    dating from <date type="pension" when="1864-10">October, 1864</date>, the date of his injury.
    The Pension Examiner, <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. A. W. Woodhull</name>, of <name type="place">Newark</name>, reported "that at that date there was about six inches
    shortening, with no power of flexion or extension at the hip and the power of rotation to a very
    limited degree. All motion of the injured limb for progression was imparted by lateral swing of
    the body itself. I may add that the knee joint of the injured limb is stiffened. " On <date type="pension" when="1867-10-19">October 19, 1867</date>, <name type="person" key="459">Dr.
     Mursick</name> again examined <name type="person" key="xx">Wright</name>, and took him to <name type="place">New York</name>, and had his photograph taken. The negative is preserved at the
     <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>, and is No. 188 of the Surgical
    Series of Photographs, a reduced copy of the lower limbs as shown, in the photograph, is
    presented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 53). At this period, <name type="person" key="948">Wright</name> reported that his limb had given him no trouble since the
    sinuses healed, in May, 1865, and that it sufficed for all purposes of locomotion. He stood on
    it very firmly, and could move it in any direction with an easy, swinging motion. He had been
    engaged for a year and a half as a farm hand, and was employed at that time as a wood-chopper.
    He had for a short time earned larger wages as a hod bearer, and had climbed high ladders with a
    heavy hod of bricks on his shoulders; but he found this avocation too fatiguing. His general
    health and physical condition were good. The knee joint continued quite stiff. It could be
    flexed to about quarter, perhaps, of the normal extent. When he walked, the rounded upper
    extremity of the femur played up and down on the dorsum of the ilium over a space of an inch and
    a half. In <date type="pension" when="1868-11">November, 1868</date>, <name type="person" key="459">Dr. Mursick</name> again examined <name type="person" key="948">Wright</name>, and
    reported on his condition. The utility of his limb had augmented during the twelve months that
    had elapsed since the last examination. The attachment of the femur to the pelvis was strong;
    the cicatrices were firm and healthy. All the movements of the thigh were performed with almost
    as much facility as in the normal state; rotation, even, as well as flexion, extension,
    adduction, and abduction. His general health was good. On <date type="pension" when="1872-08-03">August 3, 1872</date>, <name type="person" key="948">Wright</name>'s pension was increased to
    $18 per month on account of increasing disability and because additional legislation permitted
    larger payment to the more gravely mutilated. In <date type="pension" when="1873-09">September,
     1873</date>, <name type="person" key="xx">Pension Examiner A. W. Woodhull</name> reported the
    local disability unchanged, and, on <date type="death" when="1874-10-26">October 26,
    1874</date>, the sudden death of the pensioner, <name type="person" key="948">Hugh
    Wright</name>, from supposed cardiac disease was reported. Unfortunately no autopsy was made and
    the valuable opportunity of examining the relations of the resected joint was unimproved. </p>

   <p>¹ An anterior view of this specimen is printed in the surgical report in <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 74, and in the <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the <choice>
      <sic>Surgica</sic>
      <corr>Surgical</corr>
     </choice> Section of the Army Med. Museum</hi>, 1866, p. 246. </p>
   <p>² <hi rend="initialcap">M</hi>URSICK (<hi rend="initialcap">G</hi>. <hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>.), <hi rend="italic">A successful Case of Excision of the Head of the Femur for Gunshot
     Fracture</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">New York Med. Jour.</hi>, 1865, Vol. I, p. 424. See also
     <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6, S. G. O., 1865, p. 68, <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi>
    No. 2, S. G. O., 1869, pp. 41, 135, <hi rend="italic"/>Photographic Series<hi rend="italic"/>,
    A. M. M., Vol. IV, p. 38. </p>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001530.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 53.—Appearance of limb two years and five months after
    operation. [From a photograph.]</head></figure>

   <figure><graphic url="cww.001531.001"/><head>
    <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 54.—Shot comminution of neck and trochanters of right
    femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3375.</head></figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
