<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e3375">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Evans, John</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e3375</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted:
                                        <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">232</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>clinical records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>evidence of malarial affection</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>epistaxis</term> 
                                        <term>hebetude</term>
                                        <term>rose-spots</term> 
                                        <term>perspirations and sudamina</term> 
                                        <term>tendency to stupor</term>
                                        <term>anorexia</term>
                                        <term>jaundice</term>
                                        <term>bowels constipated and tender on pressure</term>
                                        <term>right iliac tenderness</term>
                                        <term>typho-malarial and typhoid fevers</term>
                                        <term>Seminary Hospital cases</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#ajh" when="2013-06-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-06">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc2.3.00067">
                       
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 67.—<hi rend="italic">Headache; epistaxis; hebetude; abdominal symptoms
                                                not marked; rose-spots on the 9th day, with
                                                perspirations and sudamina about the beginning of
                                                the 3d week, accompanying
                                                defervescence.</hi>—<name type="person" key="525">Sergeant John Evans</name>, <name type="organization" key="620">Co. H, 12th
                                                        Pa.</name>, had a chill on the morning of <date type="injury" when="1861-08-30">Aug. 30, 1861</date>,
                                        followed next day by fever which increased towards evening,
                                        and was associated with headache and pains in the bones and
                                        small of the back. To these symptoms, on September 2,
                                        epistaxis, lassitude and a tendency to stupor were added;
                                        but the bowels remained regular and urination free. On <date type="admit" when="1861-09-04">the 4th</date> he
                                        was admitted to hospital as a case of typhoid fever: pulse
                                        78, skin hot and dry, tongue coated white, bowels
                                        constipated and tender on pressure. Two grains each of
                                        compound cathartic mass and blue-pill were given at once,
                                        with sulphate of quinia, by which the bowels were moved
                                        three times. He rested well during the night, and on the
                                        morning of the 5th his pulse was 80, skin warm and moist,
                                        but his tongue was dry, red, coated and flabby, and he
                                        complained of pain in the limbs. During the day he had three
                                        small thin stools, and in the evening the pulse was 72, the
                                        tongue red, flabby and coated white, the skin dry and warm;
                                        there was also some dizziness. A ten-grain dose of Dover's
                                        powder was given. During the progress of the disease there
                                        was but little variation in the pulse; it did not go over
                                        80, and on the 11th fell to 64, coincident with a warm moist
                                        skin and the development of an abundant crop of sudamina on
                                        the abdomen and shoulders. The skin was warm and generally
                                        dry, but sometimes it felt moist; it was covered with
                                        perspiration on the 11th and 14th, after which latter date
                                        it was generally either cool or natural. The tongue became
                                        brown-coated and dry on the 7th coincident with the
                                        occurrence of anorexia and some obtuseness of the
                                        intelligence followed by drowsiness; it became moist again,
                                        but very red and coated on the next day, when also the
                                        appetite showed signs of return, and a few rose-spots were
                                        noted on the abdomen, with slight tenderness and borborygmus
                                        in the right iliac fossa, but it was not until after the
                                        appearance of the sudamina on the 15th and 16th that the
                                        mental hebetude was removed. The bowels were not notably
                                        loose at any time save immediately after admission, as already related; but there was a tendency to
                                        laxness, as two drachms of castor oil on the 9th produced
                                        two thin stools:—on the other hand, ten grains
                                        each of calomel and jalap on the 14th, after yielding three
                                        thin stools, created no further disturbance of the
                                        intestinal tract. During the night of the 6th he had a
                                        colic, which was relieved by the application of mustard. On
                                        the 16th, as a slightly jaundiced hue of the face was
                                        apparent, small doses, two grains each, of blue-pill and
                                        quinia were given with port wine three times daily. After
                                        the 20th the patient did some light duty about the ward, and
                                        was returned to his command <date type="duty" when="1861-10-05">October 5</date>. </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
