<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16691">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">M——, M.</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16691</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">265</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>trephining practiced, fatal termination</term>
          <term>conoidal ball comminuted and depressed left parietal bone near upper border to left
            of longitudinal sinus</term>
          <term>oozing of medullary brain substance and blood on admission</term>
          <term>depressed portion of cranium firmly <choice>
              <orig>imbedded</orig>
              <reg>embedded</reg>
            </choice> in the brain</term>
          <term>membranes and medullary substance of brain lacerated by depressed bone
            fragments</term>
          <term>meningeal inflammation and infiltration of purulent matter in region of
            injury</term>
          <term>left lateral ventricle distended with blood, piece of bone projected into its
            cavity</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>autopsy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-10">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>
      <p>
        <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private M.
        M——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. C, 48th Pennsylvania
          Volunteers</name>, aged 45 years, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="3"><choice>
            <orig>Spottsylvania</orig>
            <reg>Spotsylvania</reg>
          </choice> Court-house, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-12">May 12th,
          1864</date>, by a conoidal ball, which comminuted and depressed the left parietal bone
        near the upper border to the left of the longitudinal sinus. He was admitted to the hospital
        of the Ninth Corps and thence sent to the <name type="hospital" key="167">Carver
          Hospital</name>, Washington, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-14">the 14th</date>,
        somewhat morose and taciturn, and at times manifesting slight symptoms of compressions, but
        expressing himself quite intelligibly. On the evening of the 15th, he became decidedly
        comatose. On <date type="operation" when="1864-05-16">the following morning</date> the
        patient was placed under the influence of ether. <name type="person" key="xx">Acting
          Assistant Surgeon J. O. French</name> trephined the skull over the affected region and
        removed several large splinters of the external table. The depressed portion was of an
        irregular quadrangular shape, measuring an inch or more in its longest diameter, and was
        firmly <choice>
          <orig>imbedded</orig>
          <reg>embedded</reg>
        </choice> in the brain. The membranes and medullary substance of the brain were lacerated by
        the depressed fragments, accounting for the slight oozing of medullary substance and blood
        that had existed ever since his admission. Considerable hæmorrhage occurred during the
        operation, which was controlled by dry lint. The operation relieved the patient from his
        comatose condition, and he became quite animated, remaining so until the 18th, when coma
        again set in. Death supervened on <date type="death" when="1864-05-20">the 20th</date>. The
        autopsy revealed traces of meningeal inflammation and infiltration of purulent matter in the
        region of the injury. The left lateral ventricle was distended with blood, and a small piece
        of bone was found projecting into its cavity. The pathological specimen is a disk and three
        fragments of bone, removed from the cranium. The largest fragment is from the inner table
        and measures one inch in diameter. The specimen and history were contributed by <name type="person" key="102">Surgeon O. A. Judson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>
      </p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001418.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 131.—Disk and fragments of skull removed by
          trephining. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 2302, Sect. I, A. M. M. [Nat. size.]</head>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
