<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e35008">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Zilch, George</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e35008</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">840-841</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>hospital gangrene</term>
     <term>leg amputated at upper third</term>
     <term>bullet wound</term>
     <term>stumped slowly closed by granulation</term>
     <term>ulcer on face of stump</term>
     <term>feverish, inclined to nausea</term>
     <term>tendency to diarrhœa and perspiration</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-02-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
    and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   <p>In <date type="injury" when="1863-02">February, 1863</date>, a number of cases of hospital
    gangrene occurred at the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D.
    C., and were observed by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who, in a special report to the Surgeon
    General, gives the following interesting account of the pathology and treatment of the cases. In
    several instances later information has been added to the cases cited by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>: <!--<ref xml:id="n01" target="#n48" n="1" /> --></p>

   <p>"On the 26th of December, 1862, about two hundred wounded from the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name> were received into the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>.</p>
   <p>CASE IX.—<name type="person" key="xxx">George Zilch (Zuelch)</name>. Sergeant, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 7th New York</name>, aged 25 years, had his left leg
    amputated at its upper third for a bullet wound received at <name type="battle" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. He was
    admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>
    <date type="admit" when="1862-12-26">December 26th</date>, and placed in ward No. 5. The stump
    had closed slowly by granulation until there remained an ulcer as large as a half dime on its
    face. April 14, 1863, this ulcer was inflamed around its edges and covered with a white
    pultaceous slough; there was no constitutional disturbance, and the patient was allowed to
    remain on his crutches. The ulcer was cauterized with nitric acid and dressed with solution
    sodre chlorinatse. 18th : The ulceration and areola are both enlarged, and the slough, yet very
    tough, is thicker. Acid was again used locally. 21st: He is feverish and inclined to nausea; his
    pulse 120, skin hot. and tongue thickly coated. The ulcer is extending in depth, and he was
    removed to the gangrene ward. 22d: The solution of bromine was applied to the sore after
    cleansing the surface as much as possible of the tenacious slough. His general condition was
    unfavorable, and there was a tendency to diarrhœa and perspiration. Internally he took
    muriatic acid, with extra diet and stimulants. 24th: Bromine was again applied to the surface
    and used in the form of vapor. The ulcer was now three inches in diameter, irregularly circular
    in form, with ragged, everted, and thickened edges, and surrounded by a purple areola. The
    slough was one inch in thickness, and resisted the action of the bromine. 26th: The sore is
    looking better; it has been disinfected since the first application of bromine, and the
    constitutional symptoms are better. 27th : A pointing in oil was made to-day by <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon
     Brinton's</name> direction, which would be pronounced a good representation of hospital gangrene. 28th:
    The slough is much thinner to-day, and the granulations are showing the thin gray covering.
    29th: The sore is much better, is becoming covered with granulations, and has lost almost
    entirely its specific appearance. There is no constitutional disturbance, no fever, no headache,
    the tongue is cleaning oft , and there is a return of the appetite. The bromine vapor was
    discontinued, and sol. sod. chlorinat. substituted. 30th : The livid areola has been changing
    daily in hue under the bromine treatment, has now entirely disappeared, and the sore is
    perfectly healthy. May 6th: He is still improving, and is taking tonics and nutrients. 20th:
    The sore is reduced to half its original size and is now cicatrizing rapidly. 24th: There is
    now a surface as large as a penny unhealed; health is very good; he is about the ward on
    crutches, and is no longer considered an interesting case. This man steadily improved; recovered
    with a good stump, and was finally sent to <name type="place">New York</name> to be mustered out of service. He was
    discharged <date type="servicedischarge" when="1863-05-08">May 8, 1863</date>, and died <date type="death" when="1878-07-02">July 2, 1878</date>, of valvular disease of the heart and
    cardiac asthma.</p>

   <p>We have in this case another instance in which the acid, locally used, proved useless, and in
    which the solution of bromine caused an immediate improvement. It was found necessary to apply
    the caustic solution to the ulcer three times, owing to the thickness of the slough, which was
    too closely attached to be removed by spatula or forceps. Its action here seemed to correct the
    fetor at once, to check the molecular death, and to change the hue of the areola, by causing a
    more healthy action in the capillaries. The gnawing burning pain was relieved, and the patient
    was able to sleep in comfort. The absorption of the virus produced in the ulcer was prevented by
    its destruction, and the nervous system quickly regained its tone.</p>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
