<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e20347">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">Cook, Francis</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e20357</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">590-591</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the chest</term> 
                                                    <term>operations on the chest</term>
                                                    <term>excisions</term>
                                                    <term>balls and foreign bodies lodged</term>
                                                    <term>remarkable lodgement of foreign bodies on post-mortem</term>
                                                    <term>ball penetrated lungs</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wound through lungs</term>
                                                    <term>bullet entered left side posteriorly</term>                                                                 
                                                    <term>fractured tenth rib</term>
                                                    <term>subcutaneous emphysema</term>
                                                    <term>pneumonia in lower lobe</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                  <change who="#mb" when="2012-01-27">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                  <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                  <p> <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 27.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Francis Cook</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 2d Michigan Volunteers</name>, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Bailey's Cross Roads, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1861-09-04">September 4th, 1861</date>, by a conoidal ball, which penetrated the lungs. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon William O'Meagher</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">37th New York Volunteers</name>, in a report of the case in <hi rend="italic">Am. Med. Times</hi>, Vol. IV, p. 6, says: "While on picket duty near the Cross Roads, he received from the
                                                                enemy's picket a gunshot wound through the lungs, and when discovered by his comrades, who had hastened to the spot, was found
                                                                faint from profuse hæmorrhage, and lying on the wounded side. By them he was conveyed in a blanket to the main body
                                                                stationed at the Cross Roads, the distance being about a mile, and on their arrival I saw him immediately. On examination, his
                                                                clothes behind were found saturated with blood, while several large clots were removed from the immediate vicinity of the wound.
                                                                As he was extremely prostrated, some stimulants were gradually administered until reaction took place, and, in the meantime, I
                                                                was searching for the exit of the bullet, which had entered the left side posteriorly, fracturing the tenth rib and making a large
                                                                irregular wound. On introducing my finger for about two inches for the purpose of exploring and removing foreign substances,
                                                                I felt the lung tissue, and found the wound itself partially filled with coagula and extending toward the opposite side in a
                                                                transverse direction; emphysema appeared to some extent in the vicinity. I did not attempt a further exploration, especially as
                                                                the wound, as far as I could discern, appeared free from foreign substances and partially closed. Shredded lint was then applied
                                                                to the wound, and the patient gently turned over on the wounded side. On searching for the exit of the ball, the only indication
                                                                of its presence was a patch of emphysema on the opposite side, somewhat higher up than the aperture, but the ball itself could
                                                                not be felt, so I resolved to wait awhile in order to allow the patient to recover somewhat, hoping that, in the meantime, the
                                                                respiratory efforts, increased by a pretty tight bandage, would force the ball outward and thus render it palpable. Accordingly, in about four hours, be began to experience severe pain in this part, and on removing the bandage, at the same time directing him to take a full breath, which he did with ease and evident relief, I was exceedingly gratified to find the ball presenting itself
                                                                in the sixth intercostal space. On cutting down I found it firmly imbedded in the costal pleura, and after a little delay,
                                                                occasioned by a desire not to make a large opening, removed it with a common forceps, and immediately closed the wound with
                                                                interrupted sutures. The bandage was again applied, and a full anodyne administered, after which he slept well for two hours
                                                                and felt very much relieved. The missile, contrary to my first anticipations, turned out to be a small triangular-shaped rifle-bullet,
                                                                irregular and rough at the edges, as if it were so designed to produce greater mischief. He continued very comfortable for
                                                                two days, taking light nourishment and appearing quite cheerful and intelligent, occasionally only being attacked with dyspnœa,
                                                                which, however, was never sufficient to cause any apprehension. Obedient to directions, he lay perfectly still, without talking,
                                                                except in answer to a necessary question as to his condition. His bed was a canvas field-stretcher, with poles inserted into the
                                                                folded canvas, which was also attached to the end pieces by buttons and cords. The iron framework at the ends raised it from
                                                                the ground sufficiently to afford a safe, easy, and efficacious means of transportation, far superior, in my opinion, to any other
                                                                thus far presented, and certainly better than field ambulances over rough roads. On this he was conveyed, on <date type="transfer" when="1861-09-07">the third day</date>, a
                                    distance of perhaps ten miles, to the general hospital in <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, where he died on <date type="death" when="1861-09-09">the fifth day</date>. I am indebted to <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. H. Laurence Sheldon</name>, the surgeon in charge, for the following record of the autopsy: Left side of chest filled with bloody serum; lung compressed, and a space between anterior parietes and surface of lung filled with air. Lymph covered the visceral and
                                                                parietal pluræ, and clots of blood were on the most dependent portion of the cavity. The ball struck the tenth rib, fracturing it
                                                                three inches from its articulation with vertebræ, passed through the lower lobe of left lung, where there was intense inflammation
                                                                in its track, with numerous spiculæ of bone carried two inches into substance of lung from the fractured rib, thence through body
                                                                of tenth vertebra, through diaphragm and upper surface of liver, a distance of two inches; again through diaphragm, and was
                                                                removed externally between sixth and seventh ribs. There was a patch of pneumonia on the right lower lobe. Half a gallon
                                                                of serum and blood was taken from both pleural cavities.' I should have mentioned as rather remarkable, that for three days,
                                                                though he had considerable dyspnœa, and pain referred to in both places, he had neither cough nor expectoration until the fourth
                                                                day, leading some to suppose that both lungs were not seriously wounded, as I had at first reported, the ball rather making a
                                                                circuit outside the lung. But I think it almost impossible that the right lower lobe could escape when the ball passed twice
                                                                through the diaphragm and upper surface of the liver, being finally removed from the <hi rend="italic">sixth</hi> intercostal space; besides, 'there
                                                  was a patch of pneumonia on the right lower lobe, and half a gallon of serum taken from <hi rend="italic">both</hi> pleural cavities.' " </p>
                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
