<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e26281">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Cole, G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e26281</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">717</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term> 
     <term>shot wounds</term>
     <term>effect of missiles and projectiles on bony structure</term>
     <term>contusion of femur at middle third without fracture</term> 
     <term>flattened bullet extracted</term> 
     <term>erysipelas</term>   
     <term>skin and conjunctivæ jaundiced</term>   
     <term>pyæmic abscesses</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2012-06-19">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1057.—<name type="person" key="1461">Private G.
      Cole</name>, <name type="organization" key="501">Co. A, 91st New York</name>, aged 35 years,
     was wounded in the right thigh, at <name type="BATTLE" key="58">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1865-03-31">March 31, 1865</date>.  From a field hospital he passed, on
     <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-03">April 3d</date>, to the Fifth Corps Depot Hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name>, and <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-05">two days later</date> he was transferred to
     Washington.  <name type="person" key="201">Assistant Surgeon W. F. Norris</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, contributed the following history:  "The patient
     was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, <date type="transfer" when="1865-04-06">April 6th</date>, with a wound inflicted by a minié ball, which caused a
     severe contusion of the femur at the middle third without producing fracture. His constitutional condition at the time of his admission was good and the wound looked healthy. On
     <date type="operation" when="1865-04-12">April 12th</date> a very much flattened bullet was extracted by <name type="person" key="214">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. Gibbons</name>.  On the 17th, erysipelatous inflammation appeared about
     the wound, which increased on the following day in spite of the application of poultices and
     tincture of iodine. On the 20th there was a slight attack of erysipelas of the nose, and the
     following day the patient had two severe chills, which were repeated on the 22d, 23d, and 24th.
     On the 25th he again had two chills, and one on the next day. The conjunctivæ now had assumed
     a yellow tinge, and he had pain in the chest; pulse 132.  On the 27th there was another chill,
     the constitutional condition remaining as before, and on the following day there was one more
     repetition, and secondary involvement of the knee joint manifested itself. The skin and
     conjunctivæ were now deeply jaundiced, and the discharge from the wound unhealthy, fetid, and
     bloody.  On the 29th there was hiccough, delirium, and vomiting, and the patient sank rapidly.
     He died on the following day—<date type="death" when="1865-04-30">April 30, 1865</date>.  At the
     autopsy, both lungs were found to be covered posteriorly with an offensive greenish flaky lymph
     and to contain a number of small pyæmic abscesses. There was about five ounces of effusion
     in the thoracic cavities. The other organs were but slightly affected. On removing the femur
     the periosteum was found to be wanting for five inches in length and one-third of the
     circumference of the bone, the part so bared showing evidence of absorption of its tissue
     except at the point struck by the bullet. On sawing open the shaft of the femur longitudinally
     the lower half was discovered to be in a gangrenous condition, the medulla being greenish,
     soft, and offensive, and the cancellated structure of the condyles presenting the same appearance. There
     was about two ounces of thin brownish-yellow fluid in the knee joint, and the femoral vein near
     the joint as well as the small articular veins were filled with clots, their inner coats in
     some places being reddened and in others of a greenish hue." </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
