<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e8738">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Krall, Christian</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e8738</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">122</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                    <term>gunshot contusions of the cranial bones</term>
                    <term>contusion of the skull without fracture</term>
                    <term>tetanus</term>
                    <term>concussion of brain</term>
                    <term>musket ball caused contusion of outer table of parietal bone</term>
                    <term>concussion slight, not knocked down nor disturbed mental faculties</term>
                    <term>bone denuded of periosteum</term>
                    <term>burrowing pus in wound</term>
                    <term>pus under dura mater beneath point of injury</term>
                    <term>excessive hæmorrhage followed injury</term>
                    <term>autopsy performed</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
            <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-16">added figure encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-04">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-22">additional proofing of transcription and
                encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF;
                encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc3.0127">
            <p><name type="person" key="401"><hi rend="initialcap">K</hi>RALL, <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>HRISTIAN</name>, Private, <name type="organization" key="610">Co. K,
                    130th Pennsylvania Volunteers</name>, was wounded, at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th, 1862</date>, by a musket ball which caused a
                contusion of the outer table of the right parietal bone above and behind the
                protuberance. The concussion was slight, not even knocking him down, or causing any
                disturbance of his mental faculties. Excessive hæmorrhage followed the injury,
                which was not arrested for five hours. He was, on <date type="admit" when="1862-12-17">December 17th</date>, admitted to the <name type="hospital" key="159">Patent Office Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C., and on <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-19">December 19th</date>, sent to the <name type="hospital">Jarvis Hospital at Baltimore</name>, Maryland. On admission, the
                wound looked healthy, and discharged normal pus. No fracture could be detected, but
                the bone was denuded of periosteum. On <date type="injury" when="1862-12-24">December 24th</date>, symptoms of tetanus, confined chiefly to the muscles of
                the neck, supervened, followed by nausea and vomiting. <date type="operation" when="1863-01-01">January 1st, 1863</date>, tetanus was general and well-marked.
                The wound was extremely sensitive, and the scalp around it puffed, indicating a
                burrowing of pus. The pains in the head became intolerable, and, during the
                intervals of the spasmodic throes, he would scream and groan. A free incision of the
                scalp was made, and the fresh wound allowed to bleed unchecked for some time.
                Instantaneous relief followed, the pain in the head abated, and the spasms did not
                recur the following morning. Still no fracture could be detected, but the parietal
                bone was somewhat roughened, and was evidently exfoliating. On the following day the
                symptoms had returned. Opium was given, and afterward, <choice>
                    <sic>cannabis indiea</sic>
                    <corr>cannabis indica</corr>
                </choice> was substituted, with some benefit. Death occurred on <date type="death" when="1863-01-04">January 4th, 1863</date>. At the autopsy, a film of pus was
                found under the dura mater, beneath the point of injury, amounting to a half drachm.
                The dura mater was bruised and discolored; the substance of the brain was normal,
                but a small quantity of bloody serum existed in the lateral ventricles. The
                pathological specimens were sent to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical
                    Museum</name>. One of them is represented in the adjacent wood cut, (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 36.) It consists of the vault of the cranium,
                showing incipient caries and necrosis of the outer table of the right parietal bone.
                The scale of bone, around which the line of demarcation has formed, is elliptical in
                shape, measuring one inch by one and a half. The inner table presents no
                pathological appearance. The second specimen is a wet preparation of the dura mater,
                thickened, inflamed, and having a deposit of pus upon its inner surface. The
                specimens and history were contributed by <name type="person" key="402">Assistant
                    Surgeon D. C. Peters</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>
            </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="cww.001667.001"/>
                <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 36.—Exfoliation from the right parietal,
                    from gunshot contusion. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 613, Sect. I, A. M.
                    M.</head>
            </figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
