<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e14485">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Bulman, G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e14485</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted:   
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">354</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>recoveries after shot fractures of the upper third of the femur treated by conservation</term> 
     <term>ligations of femoral artery in cases of shot fractures of the femur treated by conservation</term>
     <term>wounded by ball through upper third of thigh, fracturing femur</term> 
     <term>femoral vein ligated on day of injury</term>
     <term>circulation of limb much impeded</term>
     <term>varices and ulceration on calf from obstruction of circulation</term>     
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
   <p>In one case it is stated that the femoral vein was successfully ligated on the day of the injury; but unfortunately neither the records of the field hospital nor of the Columbian Hospital at Washington, where the patient was treated during the first five months after the injury, allude to the ligation of the femoral <sic>vein</sic><corr>artery</corr>, and not until the soldier reached the hospital at Madison, Wisconsin, is the operation, said to have been performed on the field, mentioned, probably
     upon the patient's own statement. A brief account of the case is appended:</p>
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 501.—<name type="person" key="1111">Corporal G.
      Bulman</name>, <name type="organization" key="460">Co. G, 36th Wisconsin</name>, aged 22
     years, was wounded through the upper third of the left thigh, at <name type="BATTLE" key="8">Hatcher's Run</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-10-27">October 27, 1864</date>. He was
     sent from the field to <name type="hospital" key="157">Columbian Hospital</name>, Washington,
     <date type="admit" when="1864-11">several days after the injury</date>, and <date type="transfer" when="1864-04">five months later</date> he was transferred to Harvey Hospital, <name type="place" key="xx">Madison</name>. <name type="person" key="xx">Surgeon H. Culbertson</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the
     latter, reported that the femur was fractured by the missile, and that the femoral vein had
     been ligated on the day of the injury. The patient was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1865-05-22">May 22, 1865</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner W. H. Walker</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Fond du
       Lac</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1865-08-11">August 11, 1865</date>: "He was wounded by a ball through the upper third of
     the thigh from without inward, fracturing the femur. The muscles are adherent and the thigh is diminished in circumference two
     and a half inches. The circulation of the limb is much impeded from extensive loss and
     induration of the soft parts from hospital gangrene." Several years after the same examiner
     reported "deep and extensive varices and ulceration on the outer aspect of the calf from the
     obstruction of the circulation of the limb. The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-12-04">December 4, 1879</date>.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
