<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41694">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Benson, Jerome</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41694</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">202</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the Third Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>diarrhœa and pleurisy</term>
       <term>cough, bloody expectoration, pain in chest</term>
       <term>sordes on teeth and lips</term>
       <term>pleuritic adhesions</term>
       <term>deposit of tubercle in upper lobe of lung</term>
       <term>pericardium contained light-colored serum</term>
       <term>mucous membrane of pyloric orifice inflamed and ulcerated</term>
       <term>small intestine presented tubercular ulcers</term>
       <term>kidney contained tubercles</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2013-01-14">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms and figures</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">T</hi>HIRD <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Edwin Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:⃰</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 530.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Jerome Benson</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company C, 123d Indiana volunteers</name>; age 18; admitted from <name type="hospital" key="200">Soldiers Rest</name> <date type="admit" when="1865-02-18">February 18, 1865</date>.  Diarrhœa and pleurisy.  This patient had a severe diarrhœa, cough, and bloody expectoration, with pain in the chest, increased on inspiration; his skin was hot; the pulse quick. The diarrhœa diminished under astringent treatment, but the chest-symptoms became more severe, and sordes collected on the teeth and lips.  February 22d: Ordered a combination of ipecacuanha with mercury and chalk.  February 23d: The dyspnœa has become intense. Ordered stimulants.  Died, <date type="death" when="1865-02-23">February 23d</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1865-02-24">sixteen hours after death</date>: Body well nourished; decided rigor mortis; the marks of a blister on the right side of the chest; suggillation posteriorly. There were recent, pleuritic adhesions on the left side, but no effusion in the pleural sac. In the upper lobe of the left lung there was a deposit of tubercle. The pericardium contained four ounces of light-colored serum. The heart was small but normal. The stomach was large and filled with gas; near the pyloric orifice its mucous membrane was inflamed and ulcerated. The small intestine presented a number of tubercular ulcers. The appendix vermiform is was doubled upon itself, and bound in that position by bands of lymph. The left kidney contained tubercles. The other viscera appeared to be normal.</p> 
   <p>⃰ It is to be regretted that, in most instances, the records of this hospital do not show by whom the autopsies were made. It is known that many of them were made by <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon Bentley</name> himself, or under his immediate supervision, but it is only possible to distinguish these from the others in a few cases.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
