<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e7820">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Higgins, O. C.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e7820</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">176</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>partial shot fractures of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>ball entered middle third of thigh anteriorly, exploded, scattered fragments of lead
      through thigh</term>
     <term>partial fracture of femur</term>
     <term>femur shows local necrosis and profuse suppuration</term>
     <term>post-mortem examination</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-22">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-03-01">additional case copied from MSHWR, performed proofing of copy
    and XML encoding, and key terms identified</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 359.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private O. C.
     Higgins</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. D, 31st Maine</name>, aged 24 years,
    was wounded before <name type="BATTLE" key="7">Petersburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-06-23">June 23, 1864</date>. <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon J. Harris</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="xxx">7th Rhode Island</name>, reported his admission into the
    field hospital of the 2d division, Ninth Corps, with a "shot wound of thigh caused by a
    musket ball." From the field hospital the wounded man passed to the Depot Hospital at <name type="place">City Point</name>, and thence, on <date type="transfer" when="1864-07-03">July
     3d</date>, to the <name type="hospital" key="512">Third Division Hospital</name> at <name type="place">Alexandria</name>. <name type="person" key="134">Surgeon E. Bentley</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of the latter, reported the following
    description of the injury and its result: "A conical explosive ball entered the external
    aspect of the middle third of the right thigh anteriorly, and, exploding, scattered fragments of
    lead through the thigh and partially fractured the femur, not, however, preventing the patient
    from using his leg at will. Water dressings were applied. When admitted the patient was not in
    good condition, having been suffering from diarrhœa for some time, for which astringents
    were given. On July 6th, he was somewhat improved. The cold-water dressings were changed to
    warm. By July 10th the diarrhœal discharges had ceased, but the wound was very much
    inflamed. On <date type="injury" when="1864-07-15">July 15th</date>, a slight discharge of dark
    and unhealthy pus set in, and flaxseed poultices were applied. Tonics and stimulants were
    administered. On July 21st, the patient felt better, and his treatment was continued. Two days
    later there were dark and unhealthy discharges from the wound, but the patient looked bright and
    his tongue was cleaning. Death occurred suddenly at 4 A. M., on <date type="death" when="1864-07-24">July 24, 1864</date>, the patient having been given water to drink about an
    hour previously by the nurse, and no signs of rapid exhaustion being then apparent. The <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination, made nine hours after death, showed the thigh
    filled with fragments of the bullet, and a partial fracture of the femur; there was profuse
    suppuration above and around the bone, and great emaciation. The viscera were found to be
    perfectly healthy." The upper two-thirds of the injured femur were contributed to the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="134">Dr.
     Bentley</name>, and are represented in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initial cap">F</hi>IG. 131). The
    specimen shows the existence of local necrosis, with trivial osseous deposit near by, and the
    traces of profuse suppuration following the fragments of lead are seen in the roughening of the
    shaft. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001558.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initial cap">F</hi>IG. 131.—Partial shot fracture of right femur. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 3339.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
