<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e5744">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">Beckwith, James</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e5744</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
          <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
          <date when="1888">1888</date>
          <biblScope type="page">337</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>post-mortem records</term>
          <term>continued fevers</term>
          <term>typhoid fever</term>  
          <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated, ileum or small intestine only affected</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file, </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00016">
      
        <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 16.—<name type="person" key="549">Private James
            Beckwith</name>, <name type="organization" key="630">Co. F, 2d Me.</name>; age 23; was
          admitted <date type="admit" when="1861-09-06">Sept. 6, 1861</date>, with typhoid fever
          occurring as a relapse. The patient had a full strong pulse, 120, heavily coated and dry
          tongue, hot and dry skin. One ounce of sulphate of magnesia was ordered. He rested poorly
          during the night, having had some head symptoms; his bowels were moved twice, although by
          mistake the Epsom salt had not been taken. His skin at the midnight visit, September 7,
          was warm and perspiring, tongue dry and brown in the centre, pulse full, 114. Half an
          ounce of tincture of rhubarb with ten drops of oil of anise was administered, by which the
          bowels were moved rapidly. In the evening he was unconscious, and during the night
          delirious with involuntary stools of a brown color. Next day there was rather less fever;
          pulse 104. Quinine, which had been given the previous day, was continued in eight-grain
          doses, with whiskey-punch and beef-essence, and an astringent injection at night. His
          bowels were moved twice on this day, the 8th, and he had tenderness in the right iliac
          region. During the following night there was walking delirium, and a few minute red spots
          were discovered, which did not disappear on pressure. At 11 A. M. of the 9th he had a
          severe congestive chill; during the paroxysm his pulse was strong and rapid; he raved and
          showed much strength. Morphia was given to quiet him. His bowels were moved involuntarily
          during the day, and he was very restless, requiring to be held in bed. On the 10th, after
          a quiet night, he was dull and stupid, his pulse 117, skin hot, face flushed, teeth
          covered with sordes; in the evening he became drowsy and was quiet during the night.
          Turpentine emulsion was given. On the 11th his pulse was quick and weak, 130, tongue
          cracked and protruded with difficulty, stools involuntary, countenance haggard and eyes
          fixed; he had also subsultus, grinding of the teeth, rose-colored spots and sudamina. In
          the evening his skin became cool, the prostration increased and the involuntary stools
          were large and fetid. On <date type="death" when="1861-09-12">the 12th</date> the symptoms
          were: Pulse 137, soft, small and weak; respiration 14; skin hot and moist; hands and feet
          cold and clammy; face pale; nose pinched; eyes and mouth half closed; lips livid; nausea;
          subsultus; black vomiting. He died at 3 P. M. <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi>
          examination: The ileum was much thickened, inflamed and ulcerated for five feet above the
          ileo-cæcal valve; Peyer's glands were elevated, extensively ulcerated and
          perforated in two places near the valve. No fæcal matter was found in the
          peritoneal cavity. The stomach was not examined.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="hospital" key="156">Seminary Hospital</name>, Georgetown, D. C.</hi>
        </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
