<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e18894">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">McD——, John</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e18894</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in
                                                  the
                                                  Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible
                                                  for particular readings or for changes to this
                                                  file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl><title>The Medical and Surgical History of
                                                  the War of the Rebellion.
                                                  (1861–65.)</title><editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                                                  Army</editor><pubPlace>Washington,
                                                  D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
                                                  Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope><date when="1870">1870</date><biblScope type="page">445</biblScope></bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of
                                                  the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                                  <term>wounds and injuries of the spine</term> 
                                                                  <term>gunshot wounds of the spine</term>   
                                                                  <term>gunshot injuries of the lumbar vertebrae</term>
                                                                  <term>gunshot fractures of the apophyses of the lumbar spine</term>
                                                                  <term>gunshot fractures of the second lumbar vertebra</term>
                                                                  <term>state of intoxication</term>
                                                                  <term>unable to move lower limbs</term>
                                                                  <term>no sensation below anterior superior spinous process of ilium</term>
                                                                  <term>ball passed through body of second lumber vertebra</term>
                                                                  <term>spinal cord divided</term>
                                                                  <term>ball passed through diaphragm and great curvature of stomach</term>
                                                                  <term>necropsy performed</term>
                                                                  <term>ball passed between seventh and eighth ribs, through diaphragm, dependant portion of great curvature of stomach, through mesentery, entirely through body of second lumber vertebra, lodged in muscles of back</term>
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-12-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>                                                
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched
                                                  encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated
                                                  file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking
                                                  of OCR text against PDF; encoded </change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>
                                                
                                                <p>  <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private John McD——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. K, 7th Michigan
                                                                Cavalry</name>, while in a state of intoxication, on <date type="injury" when="1863-07-01">July
                                                  1st, 1863</date>, was wounded by a ball from a Colt's
                                                  revolver (navy size), fired by the guard at the
                                                  camp of the 1st Rhode Island Cavalry. The pistol
                                                  was discharged at a distance of ten feet, the
                                                  missile entering the left side, four inches below
                                                  and a little to the right of the nipple. He
                                                  dropped instantly, and upon attempting to remove
                                                  him to a tent, it was discovered that he was
                                                  wholly unable to move the lower limbs, and that
                                                  below the anterior superior spinous processes of
                                                  the ilium there was no sensation whatever, except
                                                  a very slight sense of feeling when hard pressure
                                                  was made upon the genitals. The shock and
                                                  prostration were very great, and followed the
                                                  injury immediately, while the system did not
                                                  respond to the stimulants exhibited. It was found
                                                  impossible to probe the wound to any extent, and
                                                                <date type="admit" when="1863-07-01">one hour after the infliction of the injury</date>, the
                                                                patient was removed to <name type="hospital" key="157">Columbian Hospital</name>,
                                                  Washington. Up to this time no blood had issued
                                                  from the mouth, nor was there any emphysema. Half
                                                  an hour after admission, the patient commenced to
                                                  vomit blood very freely. Although thirst was
                                                  intense, he ejected the drinks given him almost as
                                                  soon as swallowed. The vomiting of blood continued
                                                  until four o'clock P. M., five hours after the
                                                  injury, when it ceased altogether, although water
                                                  was thrown up as before. The vomiting was
                                                  spasmodic, and unaccompanied by pain. About this
                                                  time some reaction took place, and the patient was
                                                  comparatively comfortable until a quarter before
                                                                <date type="death" when="1863-07-01">eight o'clock P. M.</date>, when he became slightly
                                                  convulsed, and expired in a few minutes. There
                                                  were several respirations observed after the
                                                  action of the heart had ceased entirely. He was
                                                  perfectly conscious to the last moment. Necropsy:
                                                  Ball passed inward and downward, going between the
                                                  seventh and eighth ribs, through the diaphragm
                                                  near its attachment upon the left side, thence
                                                  through a fold of a dependant portion of the great
                                                  curvature of the stomach, through the mesentery,
                                                  and entirely through the body of the second lumber
                                                  vertebra, lodging in the deep muscles of the back.
                                                  The spinal cord was divided. Both the thoracic and
                                                  abdominal cavities were filled with bloody serum,
                                                  while at the bottom of each were coagula of
                                                  considerable size. With the exception of a few old
                                                  pleuritic adhesions, the body was perfectly
                                                  healthy. The pathological specimen is No. 1331,
                                                  Section I, A. M. M., and was contributed, with a
                                                  history of the case, by <name type="person">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. H. Crosby</name>. 
                                                </p>                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
