<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e15643">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Kisner, S.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e15643</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">380</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot injuries of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the knee joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by conservation</term>
     <term>fatal cases of shot fractures of the bones of the knee joint treated by
      conservation</term>
     <term>carbine shot entered thigh anteriorly at its middle, passed downward and inward, lodged
      beneath integument on inner side of knee joint</term>
     <term>erysipelas</term>
     <term>diarrhœa</term>
     <term>bullet lacerated sartorius muscle, splintered internal condyle of femur</term>
     <term>articular surfaces of femur and tibia denuded of cartilage</term>
     <term>joint and cellular tissues of thigh filled with pus</term>
     <term>autopsy performed</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-23">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-25">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 569.—<name type="person" key="1164">Private S.
     Kisner</name>, <name type="organization" key="160">Co. E, 7th Michigan</name>,¹ aged 29
    years, was wounded on picket near <name type="place">Chantilly</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-06-19">June 19, 1863</date>, by a carbine shot, which entered the left thigh
    anteriorly at about its middle, passed downward and inward, and lodged beneath the integument on
    the inner side of the knee joint. He was brought to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name> and admitted to <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>
    <date type="admit" when="1863-06-25">six days after being wounded</date>. On <date type="operation" when="1863-06-27">June 27th</date>, a conical ball was readily extracted
    through an incision, its situation being superficial. The joint at this time was neither swollen
    nor tender and did not appear to be involved in any way. On July 2d, some pain and swelling was
    noticed for the first time, when an ice-bag was applied to the knee. <date type="injury" when="1863-07-04">Two days later</date> the swelling had extended up the thigh, and by July 6th
    there was well-marked erysipelas as well as effusion in the knee joint. Tincture of iodine was
    applied and tincture of muriate of iron was administered; stimulants were given freely. By July
    8th, the erysipelas had extended clear up to the groin. On July 12th, the discharge of pus was
    free, and in consequence the tension and swelling of the thigh were sensibly diminished. The
    patient, however, was manifestly failing. On <date type="death" when="1863-07-18">July
     18th</date>, he was seized with diarrhœa, and death supervened in the evening. The autopsy
    showed that the bullet had lacerated the sartorius muscle extensively and splintered the
    internal condyle of the femur. The joint and the cellular tissues of the thigh were filled with
    dark colored and very offensive pus, and the articular surfaces of the femur and tibia were
    denuded of cartilage. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, who furnished the history, with the pathological
    specimen (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 232) and the missile (<hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi>
    3074, <hi rend="italic">Surgical Section</hi>, A. M. M.), remarks: "The case interested me
    greatly, because when the bullet was extracted there was not the slightest evidence of injury to
    the inner condyle, nor indeed to any other bone whatever. The bullet was located quite
    superficially and not in relation with the injured condyle. During the eight days which elapsed
    between the receipt of the wound and the extraction of the missile said bullet must have slipped
    away from the bone into a new position. When, therefore, on July 2d, some inflammatory trouble
    in the knee appeared, we thought it was not due to an injury of the bone, but that the
    involvement of the joint originated from the soft parts. The case also affords a good
    illustration of the obscurity of the symptoms and the difficulty of diagnosis which may attend a
    serious gunshot injury of an articulation so thinly covered with soft parts and so easy of
    examination from every side as the knee joint." </p>
   <p>¹ A brief abstract of this case was published in <hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> No. 6,
    War Department, S. G. O., Washington, 1865, p. 36.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001608.001"/>
    <head><hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 232.—The bones of the left knee; the posterior
     portion of the internal condyle is split off. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 1399.</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
