<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e35004">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Kosack, Otto</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e35004</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
     <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
     <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1883">1883</date>
     <biblScope type="page">838</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and complications</term>
     <term>hospital gangrene</term>
     <term>ligations of the common carotid</term>
     <term>struck by shell, middle of leg</term>
     <term>amputation of leg at middle</term>
     <term>open wound commenced to slough</term>
     <term>anaemic, very pallid, haggard, expression of great depression in features</term>
     <term>burning pain in stump</term>
     <term>ulcer with yellowish-gray pultaceous slough, serous and fetid discharge</term>
     <term>artificial leg</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-02-13">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
    and added keyword terms, added figures</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>In <date type="injury" when="1863-02">February, 1863</date>, a number of cases of hospital
    gangrene occurred at the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>, Washington, D.
    C., and were observed by <name type="person" key="200">Assistant Surgeon William Thomson</name>,
     <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, who, in a special report to the Surgeon
    General, gives the following interesting account of the pathology and treatment of the cases. In
    several instances later information has been added to the cases cited by <name type="person" key="200">Dr. Thomson</name>.<!--<ref xml:id="n01" target="#n48" n="1" /> --></p>
   
   <p>"On the 26th of December, 1862, about two hundred wounded from the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg    
   </name> were received into the <name type="hospital" key="162">Douglas Hospital</name>.</p>

   <p>"CASE I.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Sergeant Otto Kosack</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. K, 2d Maryland</name>, who had been struck by a shell, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>, which made it necessary to amputate
    his left leg at the middle. The operation was done ten minutes after the injury. He was received
    here on tin- <date type="admit" when="1862-12-25">25th of December</date>. The stump closed by
    granulation, a small portion of the tibia having been removed by exfoliation. The cicatrization
    had been almost complete, when, a few days previous to the 17th, the still open wound commenced
    to slough. He was anaemic, very pallid, haggard, and with an expression of great depression in
    his features ; his pulse was very feeble and rapid ; he had been feeling very badly for several
    days, and complained of a burning pain in the stump. -On the outer side of the tibia there was
    an ulcer one inch in diameter, covered with a yellowish-gray pultaceous slough, and a serous and
    very fetid discharge ; the edges were thickened and everted, and an areola of purple livid
    congestion extended for half an inch from the margin, which was undermined. This sore was at
    once treated with pure nitric acid, applied both to the ulcer and to the areola ; the ulcer was
    dressed with an antiseptic solution of creasote, and citrate of iron and quinine, with
    stimulants and nutrients, were freely given. On the 18th the sloughing had extended to the
    border of yesterday s livid areola, but was now more superficial, and the areola, which had
    likewise invaded the surrounding skin, was more florid. The ulcer was now two inches in
    diameter. As there was some doubt as to its specific character, the patient was not removed from
    the ward until the 23d, when he was transferred, with several others, to a small ward prepared
    in the brick building, and completely isolated from the other wounded men. The iron and quinine
    were found to disturb his stomach and destroy his appetite, and was replaced by a mixture of
    nitromuriatic acid and tincture of opium. March 3d: The sore was now perfectly healthy and was
    granulating rapidly. [The patient was discharged <date type="discharge" when="1864-06-15">June
     15, 1864</date>, and was a pensioner in <date type="pension" when="1882">1882</date>. A plaster
    cast of the stump is preserved in the <name type="hospital" key="431">Army Medical Museum</name>
    and is numbered 6706 of the Sunjicul Section. ] </p>

   <p>"This was a mild case, treated in its iucipieucy with nitric acid most thoroughly. The
    ulceration had not extended so deeply, nor so far beneath the margin of the skin, as to make it
    almost impossible to reach every portion of the diseased surface. There was no scorbutis. The
    gums were firm and hard. The patient was very pallid, his heart feeble, and his pupils dilated.
    The mucous membranes were very pale, and the expression of the face haggard and anxious. He
    recovered rapidly with a good stump, and was seen, several months after, walking with great ease
    on an artificial leg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
