<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e4678">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">R——, Alfred G.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e4678</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">85-86</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term>
     <term>wounds and injuries of the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint</term>
     <term>shot fractures at the hip joint unsuccessfully treated by conservation</term>
     <term>shot injuries of femoral neck and trochanters, or neck, trochanters and shaft of
      femur</term>
     <term>wound in upper part of femur by a round ball</term>
     <term>ball found in scrotum</term>
     <term>fractured trochanter major</term>
     <term>clonic spasms, opisthotonos</term>
     <term>epileptiform convulsions</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2014-07-03">added period to figure head</change>
   <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-21">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-02-15">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified
    keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">Sarah Synovec initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5
    Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>

   <p>
    <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 191.— "<name type="person" key="937">Alfred G.
     R——</name>, <name type="organization" key="330">Adjutant 134th Pennsylvania</name>,
    aged 24 years, was wounded in the upper part of the left femur by a round ball, which partially
    fractured the trochanter major, at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="251">Fredericksburg</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13, 1862</date>. The
    wound received no attention for some days, and was then dressed with side splints firmly bound
    by a roller, a plug of lint being tightly inserted in the wound. On the <date type="admit" when="1862-12-20">20th of December</date> he was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="445">E
     Street Infirmary</name>, Washington. He stated that for some days he had experienced occasional
    twitchings in the limb, and had taken large doses of opium. The wound was a little behind the
    trochanter major. Upon removing the plug of lint about half a pint of blood and pus was
    discharged. There was no crepitus upon rotation, nor shortening. Owing to his weakened
    condition, no extended search was made for the missile. Simple dressings were applied, and half
    grain doses of sulphate of morphia were given. For the two succeeding days he seemed to improve.
    The twitchings of the limb occurred every few minutes, with occasional intermissions of a few
    hours. On <date type="operation" when="1862-12-23">the 23d</date> the spasms became more violent
    and frequent, and it was deemed advisable to extract the missile. He was etherized, and the
    wound was enlarged two inches downward and backward. A gum catheter was made to follow the
    course of the missile behind and beneath the neck of the femur to the body of the pubis, where
    the ball was found in the scrotum near the spermatic cord. A flattened round musket ball was
    extracted through an incision at the base of the scrotum. A portion of it had been chipped off.
    The patient rested well that night, but on the following day the spasms were increased in
    intensity, commencing in the injured limb and extending over the body. Cloths saturated with
    chloroform and olive oil were applied to the limb, and an antispasmodic and anodyne mixture was
    prescribed. He rested quietly until <date type="injury" when="1862-12-25">the following
     morning</date>, when clonic spasms returned and persistently increased. The patient's
    countenance became pinched, wan, and haggard, and expressive of fright. There was no pain nor
    trismus, and he partook freely of <choice>
     <sic>nouishment</sic>
     <corr>nourishment</corr>
    </choice>. At times there was complete opisthotonos. On December 25th he took four dozen pills
    of assafœtida of four grains each, and one half ounce of fluid extract of Cannabis Indica
    in divided doses, without any benefit. Sulphate of morphia in doses of one grain was then
    prescribed, to be administered every two hours, and a poultice of powdered opium and cinchona
    applied to the wound, but, as before, without apparent benefit. The mind, up to this time,
    continued clear and undisturbed, his pulse moderately full and strong, ranging at about 100. He
    now became drowsy, and at times lay in a semi-comatose condition. His pulse ran up to 150.
    Respiration was free, but at times hurried, from 25 to 28 per minute. The skin became bathed in
    sweat, which exhaled a peculiar pungent odor. The bowels were regular; the urine was scantily
    secreted and high colored, though voided without difficulty. The discharge from the wound was
    thin, bloody, and offensive. On December 27th opisthotonos recurred, and was temporarily
    relieved by the application of chloroform to the entire extent of the spine. Subsequently,
    violent epileptiform convulsions set in, and death resulted from exhaustion, on <date type="death" when="1862-12-28">December 28, 1862</date>." The pathological specimen is
    figured in the wood-cut (<hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 44) and shows a fracture of the great
    trochanter of the left femur and a piece of a leaden ball embedded in the neck. The specimen and
    history were contributed by <name type="person" key="938">Surgeon C. L. Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>—(<hi rend="italic">Circular</hi> 2, S. G.
    O., 1869, p.80. <hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 94.)</p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001528.001"/>
    <head>
     <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 44.—Fracture of trochanter and neck of the left femur by a
     round musket ball. A fragment of lead is impacted in the neck. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>.
     545.</head>
   </figure>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
