<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41225">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Keenholtz, Gilbert</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41225</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ao">Alyssa Olson</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">180</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from Lincoln Hospital, Washington, D. C.</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa and hepatitis</term>
       <term>yellow and anæmic</term>
       <term>trachea contained yellowish-white sputa</term>
       <term>yellowish-white frothy fluid exuded on section of lung</term>
       <term>left lobe of liver entirely destroyed by abscesses, right lobe contained two large abscesses</term>
       <term>large intestine congested, several large ulcers in cæcum</term>       
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-11-20">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2010-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2010-05-01">enrich encoding, proof and edit</change>
   <change who="#ao" when="2008-10-02">encoding and editing</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the case-book of <name type="hospital" key="176"><hi rend="initialcap">L</hi>INCOLN <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL</name>, Washington, D. C.; <name type="person" key="243">Surgeon J. Cooper McKee</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in charge.</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 407.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private Gilbert Keenholtz</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company D, 7th New York artillery</name>; age 37; admitted from <name type="place" key="#Alexandria">Alexandria, Virginia</name>, <date type="admit" when="1864-09-19">September 19, 1864</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa and hepatitis.  [This man appears on the register of the <name type="hospital" key="218">Augur hospital</name>, near Alexandria, Virginia, admitted <date type="admit" when="1864-09-11">September 11th</date>—remittent fever—sent to general hospital <date type="transfer" when="1864-09-19">September 19th</date>.]  The patient stated that he had been sick <date type="injury" when="1864-05">about four months</date>; he was very yellow and anæmic.  Died, <date type="death" when="1864-09-23">September 23d</date>.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Acting Assistant Surgeon C. H. Burgess</name>.   <hi rend="italic">Autopsy</hi> <date type="autopsy" when="1864-09-23">five hours and a half after death</date>: Height five feet six inches; rigor mortis well marked; body well nourished; skin icteroid. The brain appeared to be normal, and weighed forty-seven ounces; there was a larger amount of fluid in the sub-arachnoid space than usual. The trachea contained a considerable quantity of yellowish-white sputa. On section of the right lung an abundance of yellowish-white frothy fluid exuded; the left lung appeared to be normal; the right lung weighed fourteen ounces and a half, the left thirteen ounces. The heart weighed nine ounces; its valves were normal; there was a mixed clot in its right cavities, in the left a small vermiform fibrinous clot. The spleen weighed only three ounces; on section it had a granular appearance. The liver weighed seventy-two ounces and a half; its left lobe was entirely destroyed by abscesses; the right lobe contained two abscesses, one about the size of a goose-egg, the other about the size of a hen-egg. Both kidneys were slightly congested; the right weighed five ounces and a half, the left six and a half. The œsophagus, stomach, and small intestine appeared to be normal. In the cæcum there were several large ulcers, the longest diameter of which was transverse to the length of the intestine; the remainder of the large intestine was very much congested.—<name type="person" key="246">Acting Assistant Surgeon H. M. Dean</name>.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
