<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e2616">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Buckley, John B.</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2011</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>med.d1e2616</idno>
                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2011</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                        Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the
                        Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent
                        from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University
                        of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for
                    changes to this file, as noted: 
                    <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
                        (1861–65.)</title>
                    <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States
                        Army</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                    <date when="1870">1870</date>
                    <biblScope type="page">32</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                    <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                    <term>punctured wounds of the head</term>
                    <term>punctured fractures of cranium</term>
                    <term>bayonet wound of the forehead, passed backwards into brain</term>
                    <term>partial loss of vision, optical illusions</term>
                    <term>pus in two lateral and third ventricles, fourth ventricle, and beneath cerebellum</term>                                   
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-02">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
            <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
                file</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
            <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
            <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="case">
        <body xml:id="ch1.sc1.0075">
            
                <p><name type="person" key="1155"><hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>UCKLEY, <hi rend="initialcap">J</hi>OHN <hi rend="initialcap">B</hi>.</name>,
                    Corporal, <name type="organization" key="766">Co. D, 62d Pennsylvania
                        Volunteers</name>, aged 24 years, received a bayonet wound of the forehead,
                    through the right superciliary ridge, at <name type="BATTLE" key="257">Chancellorsville, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-05-03">May 3d, 1863</date>. It was found, on examination, that the weapon had
                    penetrated the frontal sinus, and passed horizontally backwards into the brain.
                    The patient was transferred to Washington, and was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="152">Finley Hospital</name> on <date type="admit" when="1863-05-09">the 9th</date>, in a perfectly conscious condition, with a
                    natural pulse and freedom from febrile excitement. <name type="person" key="910">Acting Assistant Surgeon Lewis Heard</name> passed a bougie along the track
                    of the wound into the right anterior lobe of the brain the distance of four
                    inches, without force, and without the least pain to the patient. The
                    perforation in the skull barely admitted the point of the index finger. There
                    were found a few small fragments of bone still hanging at the inner edge of the
                    orifice. There was no hæmorrhage. Perfect quietness was strictly enjoined, a
                    saline laxative was ordered, and cold water dressings were applied. The diet was
                    light. On May 14th, he continued conscious and comparatively comfortable,
                    complaining of but little pain in the head. Temporizing treatment was continued.
                    For the next two days signs of mental disturbance were noticeable, and partial
                    loss of vision, with optical illusions. He complained of headache, and a febrile
                    movement arose, with intense thirst. The bowels were kept open by Epsom salts.
                    Pus and disorganized brain tissue were discharged from the wound. At noon, on
                    the 16th, he moved his arms about tremulously, catching at imaginary objects,
                    arousing, occasionally, from the stupor into which he had fallen, complaining of
                    increased pain in the head, and then talking incoherently. The skin was of
                    natural temperature, and the pulse at 80. On <date type="death" when="1863-05-17">May 17th</date>, the patient had passed a quiet night. The
                    pulse was at 125; there was greater tremulousness of the arms, with increased
                    stupor, and vision was nearly extinct. The patient had great thirst, but no
                    appetite. The discharge of pus and disorganized brain substance continued.
                    Slight convulsions occurred in the afternoon, and the patient sank gradually,
                    and died at six o'clock P. M., thirteen days after the reception of the injury.
                    At the post mortem examination, made fourteen hours after death, the sinuses and
                    the dura mater were found to be highly engorged with blood. The right hemisphere
                    of the brain was sliced off, and over the right lateral ventricle a slight
                    prominence was observed, which, on being punctured, gave exit to a quantity of
                    pus. The wound penetrated through the anterior lobe of the brain under the right
                    edge of the corpus callosum, opened the right lateral ventricle, and extended
                    back to the posterior crus of the fornix, which seemed to have sustained injury.
                    The two lateral and third ventricles were filled with pus, and pus was also
                    found in the fourth ventricle, and beneath the cerebellum around the medulla
                    oblongata. <name type="person" key="910">Acting Assistant Surgeon Lewis
                    Heard</name> reported the case.*</p>
            
            <p>* <hi rend="italic">American Medical Times</hi>, June 10, 1863, Vol. VI, p. 292.</p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
