<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e5670">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Vaness, Herbert</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e5670</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War
                                                of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">335</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the
                                                Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>post-mortem records</term>
                                        <term>continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>typhoid fever</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated, ileum or small intestine only affected</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from
                                larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,
                        </change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00008">
                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 8.—<name type="person" key="601">Private Herbert Vaness</name>, <name type="organization" key="646">Co. D, 171st
                                                Pa.</name>; age 20; was admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-07-08">July 8, 1863</date>, with typhoid
                                        fever of twelve days' duration, which progressed favorably
                                        until the 9th, when diarrhœa set in. On the 15th
                                        there was delirium, with dry and tremulous tongue, sordes on
                                        the teeth and swelling of the abdomen; a troublesome hacking
                                        cough was also present. He died on <date type="death" when="1863-07-17">the 17th</date>. <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination ten hours after death:
                                        The brain weighed fifty-eight ounces and a half; its
                                        membranes were considerably congested and its substance
                                        rather soft; a small quantity of fluid was found in its
                                        ventricles. The trachea was much congested, of a
                                        purplish-red color and filled <pb n="336" xml:id="med.00004.336"/>
                                        <fw type="sub">POST-MORTEM RECORDS OF</fw> with bronchial
                                        secretion; the lymphatic glands at its bifurcation were
                                        enlarged, blackened and softened. The upper lobe of the
                                        right lung was highly congested, especially at the apex; the
                                        middle lobe was also somewhat congested and presented
                                        evidences of bronchitis posteriorly; the lower lobe was
                                        intensely engorged, purple in color and in some places
                                        almost black. The left lung was generally congested; there
                                        was a considerable transudation of blood beneath the pleura
                                        at its middle and posterior part; its lower lobe contained
                                        splenified lobules, black in color, and separated from each
                                        other by permeable tissue. The right lung weighed
                                        twenty-four ounces and a half, the left twenty one ounces
                                        and a half. A thin fibrinous clot adhered to the anterior
                                        wall of the right auricle and extended through the ventricle
                                        into the pulmonary artery; the left auricle also contained a
                                        fibrinous clot extending into the ventricle and attached to
                                        the mitral valve. The fundus of the stomach was of a dull
                                        lake-red and the pyloric portion paler; it contained five
                                        lumbricoid worms. The liver was soft but of normal color,
                                        its capsule easily torn. The spleen was of a mulberry color
                                        and moderately firm. The mucous membrane of the jejunum was
                                        rather soft and the villi were easily scraped off. The
                                        lining membrane of the three feet of the ileum nearest to
                                        the ileo-cæcal valve was greatly congested, and
                                        Peyer's patches were ulcerated though not perceptibly
                                        thickened; the first ulcer was small, superficial and of a
                                        darker color than the surrounding membrane; about a foot
                                        above the valve a large patch, softened and very
                                        hyperæmic but not elevated, presented near its
                                        border an ulceration about the size of a pea, with elevated
                                        walls and blackened centre. The kidneys were somewhat
                                        injected, the cortical substance firm and
                                                pale.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. Harrison
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washinigton, D. C.</hi>
                                </p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
