<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31642">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Carter, W. E.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31642</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="nm">Nate Mattison</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">94</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>injuries of the abdomen</term>
       <term>penetrating wounds of the abdomen</term>
       <term>wounds of the large intestines</term>
       <term>gunshot wounds</term>
       <term>cases of recovery</term> 
       <term>gunshot wound of abdominal walls</term>
       <term>first wound through abdomen, cut intestine</term>
       <term>second wound through hand at articulation of upper phalanx of thumb with trapezium</term>
       <term>third wound of thigh near knee, ball penetrated to bone</term>
       <term>missile wounded intestine, tore abdominal walls, bowel protruded from both wounds</term>
       <term>fæcal matter discharged freely from both orifices</term>
       <term>bullet entered between left inguinal and lumbar regions</term>
       <term>moved twelve times after receiving wounds</term>
       <term>intestine adhered to abdominal wall</term>
       <term>disability two ruptures, useless thumb-joint, and pain in leg</term>
       <term>ball entered inguinal region above and external to internal abdominal ring, came out near corresponding point on opposite side</term>
       <term>intestinal coats perforated, fæcal discharge from wound nearly a month</term>
       <term>hernia at point of entrance, wears truss</term>
       <term>ball passed through metacarpo-phalangeal articulation of thumb, anchylosis of joint</term> 
       <term>ball lodged in popliteal region of leg, extracted</term>
       <term>disability seven-eighths</term>
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-08-24">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#nm" when="2011-02-24">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 284.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant W. E. Carter</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. G, 4th Vermont</name>, aged 33 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="12">the Wilderness</name>, <date type="injury" when="1864-05-05">May 5, 1864</date>. He was admitted to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, Washington, on <date type="admit" when="1864-05-25">May 25th</date>, when the injury was recorded as a "gunshot wound of the abdominal walls."  On <date type="furlough" when="1864-06-13">June 13th</date>, he was furloughed, and on <date type="admit" when="1864-08-06">August 6th</date>, was readmitted and subsequently transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xxx">Volunteer Officers Hospital</name>, where he was admitted on <date type="transfer" when="1864-08-10">August 10th</date>, and from which he was returned to duty on <date type="duty" when="1864-08-12">August 12, 1864</date>.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Dr. George F. Stevens</name>, late Surgeon <name type="organization" key="xxx">77th New York</name>, in a communication received at this office in June, 1868, gives the following account of the case: "Within half an hour he received three wounds: first, through the abdomen, from left to right, cutting the intestine; second, a bullet wound through the hand, at the articulation of the upper phalanx of the thumb with the trapezium; third, a bullet wound of the left thigh, near the knee, the ball penetrating to the bone. The wound of the abdomen was made by some rough missile, either a bullet much battered, or a fragment of shell, or, as the lieutenant supposed, by an explosive bullet. It had entered at a point near the outer extremity of a line between the left inguinal and lumbar regions, and had made its exit at a corresponding point on the right side. In its course, the missile had wounded the intestine, and had torn the abdominal walls so as to allow the bowel to protrude from both the left and right wounds.  He was taken to the hospital of the 2d division, Sixth Corps, <date type="operation" when="1864-05-05">when</date> I returned the protruded bowels, and brought the wounds together by sutures.  On the evening of <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-06">May 6th</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant Carter</name>, with the rest of the wounded of the Sixth Corps, was removed to <name type="place">Chancellorsville</name>.  On the evening of <date when="1864-05-07">the 7th</date>, as the army was to fall back, and as there was insufficient transportation for all the wounded, it was determined to leave those who seemed least able to bear moving. The surgeons, whose duty in was to designate those to be left, selected <name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant Carter</name>, among many others, declaring that any attempt to move him would be absolutely fatal. After the rear guard had passed, in the retreat, <name type="person" key="xxx">Lieutenant Carter</name>’s brother and a wagoner placed him on a stretcher and carried him until they overtook the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Vermont Brigade</name>, three miles to the rear, when the commander of his regiment detailed men to carry him. After some time an ambulance was procured, in which he was carried until evening, when he was transferred to another ambulance, in which he rode all night, reaching <name type="place">Fredericksburg</name> at daylight on the morning of the 9th, and finally obtained comfortable quarters. I found him, on the 10th, suffering considerably from his wounds, and with a high inflammatory fever. Water dressings were applied to the wounds, with ice to those of the abdomen, and opium was freely administered. Like most other wounded men, he became very anxious to have a movement of the bowels, and begged for cathartics, which were refused.  On the 12th, an officious agent of the <name type="organization" key="xxx">Sanitary Commission</name>, hearing of his distress for physic, procured and administered to him a large dose of castor oil. Cathartic action soon commenced, and matter was discharged freely from both orifices made by the missile. Immediately upon discovery of the mischief, I administered a very large dose of opium, and he was kept fully under the influence of that drug for several days. The severe inflammatory symptoms gradually subsided, though fæcal matter continued at times to escape from the wounds.  <date type="transfer" when="1864-05-24">May 24th</date>, he was sent to <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington</name>, to <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory Square Hospital</name>, this being the twelfth time he was moved after receiving his wounds. Recovery progressed steadily; fæcal matter frequently passing from the wounds until healing took place, which was early in July, when both orifices were closed, the intestine adhering to the abdominal wall. He returned to his regiment <date type="duty" when="1864-08">in August</date>, but, finding the duties of the command of his company too severe for him, he resigned.  In a letter to me, dated <date type="pension" when="1868-05-31">May 31, 1868</date>, he says: "The extent, of disability remaining is two ruptures, a useless thumb-joint, and a good deal of pain in my left leg."  Previous to rejoining his regiment he had been promoted to a captaincy, which he resigned <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-09-14">September 14, 1864</date>, and was discharged the service.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examining Surgeon C. P. Frost</name>, of <name type="place">Brattleboro, Vermont</name>, reported <date type="pension" when="1868-04-18">April 18, 1868</date>: “Ball entered left inguinal region of abdomen, just above and external to the left internal abdominal ring, and came out nearly at the corresponding point on the opposite side. The intestinal coats were perforated, as was made certain by a fæcal discharge from the wound for nearly a month after it was received. There is a hernial protrusion at the point of entrance of the ball, which compels him to wear a truss. At the point of exit the abdominal walls are weak, and much more pain is felt there than when he was originally pensioned, still further incapacitating him from labor than it did at that time. He was also wounded by a musket ball, which passed through the metacarpo-phalangeal articulation of right thumb, producing anchylosis of that joint. A musket ball was also lodged in the popliteal region of the left leg, and was extracted. Disability seven-eighths."  Last paid to <date type="pension" when="1873-03-04">March 4, 1873</date>. </p>        
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
