<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16662">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="m" type="main">H——, W——</title>
        <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
        <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
        <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno>med.d1e16662</idno>
        <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
        <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
          <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
        </distributor>
        <date>2011</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution
            or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
            copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
          this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kmp">Kenneth M. Price</persName> 
          <persName xml:id="ajh">AJ Howell</persName>
          <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
          <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
          <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
          <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
            (1861–65.)</title>
          <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
          <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
          <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
          <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
          <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
          <date when="1870">1870</date>
          <biblScope type="page">263-264</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
          <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
          <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
          <term>gunshot wounds</term>
          <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term>
          <term>trephining after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
          <term>trephining practiced, fatal termination</term>
          <term>conoidal ball caused gaping ragged wound antero-posteriorly over left parietal,
            fractured bone</term>
          <term>probe passed into wound to touch dura mater</term>
          <term>pupils contracted and fixed, dysphagia, constant tingling in right arm and
            hand</term>
          <term>extensive comminution of internal table of bone toward vertex</term>
          <term>dura mater lacerated by small puncture made by spicula</term>
          <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
          <term>symptoms of compression of brain</term>
          <term>surface of cerebrum disorganized and pulpy, convolutions obliterated, white and gray
            matter undistinguishable</term>
          <term>autopsy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kmp" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
      <change who="#ajh" when="2013-08-19">added figure encoding</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-14">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited
        and added keyword terms</change>
      <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
      <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger
        file</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
      <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
      <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="case">
    <body>
      <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Private W——
          H——</name>, <name type="organization" key="xx">Co. B, 4th Michigan
          Volunteers</name>, was wounded at the battle of <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th,
          1862</date>, by a conoidal ball, which caused a gaping ragged wound an inch and a half
        long, antero-posteriorly over the left parietal, fracturing the bone. A probe could be
        passed through the opening so as to touch the dura mater. He was admitted to the hospital of
        the 1st division, Fifth Corps, and on <date type="transfer" when="1862-12-16">December
          16th</date>, sent to <name type="hospital" key="163">Eckington Hospital</name>,
        Washington, D. C. He was rational, but his mind was confused; the pulse was 80 and normal;
        the skin moderately warm; pupils somewhat contracted and fixed; some dysphagia, but no
        paralysis existed, and he complained of a constant tingling in his right arm and hand. On
          <date type="operation" when="1862-12-19">the 19th</date>, his memory was entirely gone.
        The operation of trephining was decided upon; the patient was etherized, and <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon Henry W. Fisher</name> elongated the
        original wound and made another section, forming a ⊤ shaped incision. Upon turning
        back the flaps an extensive irregular fracture was discovered, also a small piece of bone
        was found driven down half its thickness below the surface. At its posterior edge a small
        fragment of lead was impacted. The trephine was applied and a button removed, revealing
        extensive comminution of the internal table toward the vertex. A tongue of bone, extending
        from the opening made by the trephine to a radiating fracture was removed by a Hays's saw,
        and two irregular fragments of the inner table, besides numerous small spiculæ, were
        removed. The dura mater was discolored but not lacerated save by a small puncture made by
        one of the spiculæ. All extraneous substances having been removed, the wound was closed
        and cold water dressings were applied. On December 20th, the patient was semi-comatose, but
        quite rational when spoken to. The <date type="operation" when="1862-12-21">next
          morning</date> the pupils became contracted, the coma deepened, and all the symptoms of
        compression of the brain appeared. Thinking that there might be a clot under the dura mater.
          <name type="person" key="xx">Dr. Fisher</name> made a small <choice>
          <orig>crucial</orig>
          <reg>cruciate</reg>
        </choice> incision in the membrane, but no clot was found. The wound of the scalp and the
        dura mater were covered with an ash-colored, semi-fluid, sloughy matter; but on cleaning the
        dura mater it was found not to be sloughing, but roughened and livid. No improvement took
        place and the patient gradually sank until three o'clock P. M., <date type="death" when="1862-12-21">December 21st</date>, when he died. On removing the calvarium, the
        membranes were found congested, but without change of texture, save the roughening and
        discoloration before noted immediately about the wound. On removing the membrane, the
        surface of the cerebrum was found to be in a disorganized pulpy condition for a space of an
        inch and a half. The convolutions were obliterated, the white and gray portions being
        undistinguishable, and the tissue a disorganized sanious mass, so thin that several drops
        ran, by their own gravity, out upon the table. The rest of the brain was healthy. This
        disorganization was found to extend down to a level with the lateral ventricle and inward
        almost to the outer margin of the ventricle. The adjacent wood-cut represents the specimen,
        and shows the vault of the cranium, with a disk and twelve fragments removed by the trephine
        from the left parietal bone. The opening of the operation measures three-fourths by one and
        a quarter inches, and a fissure traverses the bone diagonally from the anterior superior to
        the posterior inferior angle. The specimen and history were contributed by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon S. A. Starrow</name>.</p>
      <figure>
        <graphic url="cww.001414.001"/>
        <head>
          <hi rend="initial cap">F</hi>IG. 127.—<choice>
            <orig>Calvaria</orig>
            <reg>Calvarium</reg>
          </choice> and fragments from a case of trephining after gunshot fracture. <hi rend="italic">Spec</hi>. 496, Sect. I, A. M. M.</head>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
