<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e31312">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Rawlins, I. H.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
       <idno>med.d2e31312</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="nb">Nate Bernth</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
     <date when="1876">1876</date>
     <biblScope type="page">929</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>wounds and injuries of the upper extremities</term>
       <term>wounds and operations in the forearm</term>
       <term>shot wounds of the forearm</term> 
       <term>shot fractures of the forearm</term>
       <term>shot fractures of the forearm treated by expectation</term> 
       <term>fractures of the radius treated by expectation</term>
       <term>successful cases of shot fracture of the radius</term>
       <term>gunshot wound of forearm, fracture simple</term> 
       <term>shell entered far enough to break the radius above wrist</term>
       <term>tendons of extensor muscles injured, strength of arm and hand impaired</term>
       <term>original wound reopened by exfoliation of bone</term>
       <term>pronation and supination impaired, wrist functionally impaired</term>       
       <term>extended necrosis of diaphysis</term>    
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-07-17">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#nb" when="2011-02-22">checked OCR; added minimal mark-up for personal names, place names, and dates</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 1876.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal I. H. Rawlins</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">Co. E, 76th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 20 years, was wounded at <name type="battle" key="xxx">Pocotaligo</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-10-22">October 22, 1862</date>.  <name type="person" key="158">Surgeon R. B. Bontecou</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge of Hospital No. 1, <name type="place">Beaufort</name>, noted: "He was admitted, <date type="admit" when="1862-10-24">October 24th</date>, with gunshot wound of right forearm, a portion of shell having entered far enough to break the radius two inches above the wrist, and not tearing the coat. The fracture was a simple one, and the wound slight. A straight, splint to the palmar aspect of the forearm was applied, and lint with cerate to the wound.  December 1st, the patient has required very little attention, the injury of the arm not disturbing his general health nor creating much local disturbance. He has been dressed and about the ward nearly all the while since his admission.  <date type="duty" when="1862-12-20">December 20th</date>, arm sound; bone a little enlarged by callus, but the patient is considered well, and sent to-day to his regiment."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Surgeon M. A. Withers</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">6th Connecticut</name>, recorded this man's admission and treatment for nearly three weeks at the regimental hospital during the following month <date type="admit" when="1863-01">January, 1863</date>.  On <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-11-28">November 28, 1864</date>, <name type="person" key="xxx">Corporal Rawlins</name> was mustered out of service and pensioned.  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner J. Phillips</name>, of <name type="place" key="#Washington">Washington, D. C.</name>, <date type="pension" when="1867-05-16">May 16, 1867</date>, certified: " *   *   Fracture of radius; the tendons of the extensor muscles injured; the strength of the arm and hand somewhat impaired."  <name type="person" key="xxx">Examiner D. S. Hays</name>, of <name type="place">Hollidaysburg, Pa.</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1872-03-12">March 12, 1872</date>: " *   *   The original wound has recently reopened, caused by exfoliation of bone, and presents an unhealthy, dark, inflamed appearance, surrounded by a large purple areola. There is considerable suffering, and the applicant is unable to use the arm to any extent. A partially detached spicula can be felt."  An <name type="organization" key="xxx">Examining Board</name>, consisting of <name type="person" key="xxx">Drs. Hays</name> and <name type="person" key="xxx">G. W. Smith</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1873-09-04">September 4, 1873</date>: " *   *   Necrosis of bone and loss of pronation and supination," etc.  The <name type="organization" key="xxx">same Board</name> reported, <date type="pension" when="1874-07-01">July 1, 1874</date>, that they found "the cicatrix red and somewhat tender; some enlargement of joint; pronation and supination somewhat impaired though tolerably good; wrist not as strong as natural, and functionally impaired. The wound reopened some months ago, but is now well. There is no evidence of its reopening."  This pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1875-09-04">September 4, 1875</date>.</p>      
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
