<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e12175">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Vannatta, W.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e12175</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
 <persName xml:id="kw">Kenneth Winkle</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName> 
     <persName xml:id="kk">Kourtney Klein</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">242, 287-288</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>injuries of the shaft of the femur</term>
     <term>amputations in the shaft of the femur</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the shaft of the femur for shot injury</term>
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>successful cases of intermediary amputations in the lower third of the thigh</term> 
     <term>wound of right knee by carbine ball</term> 
     <term>missile entered limb on anterior inner face below joint, escaped through popliteal space, without opening joint</term>
     <term>inner part of head of tibia extensively injured, deep groove with comminution, broken fragments connected with joint</term> 
     <term>internal semilunar cartilage completely covered opening in head of tibia</term>
     <term>fistulous opening in stump</term>     
     <term>unable to wear artificial limb</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
 <change who="#kw" when="2014-05">blessed</change>
   <change who="#kk" when="2014-01-29">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-05-18">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>
   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 464.—<name type="person" key="1087">Private W.
      Vannatta</name>, <name type="organization" key="84">Co. D, 4th Pennsylvania Cavalry</name>,
     aged 24 years, was wounded at <name type="BATTLE" key="49">Upperville</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-06-21">June 21, 1863</date>, and entered <name type="hospital" key="175">Stanton Hospital</name>, Washington, <date type="admit" when="1863-06-24">three days afterwards</date>. <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon J. A. Lidell</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>,
     reported: "The patient, a man of sound constitution, had received a wound of the right knee by
     a carbine ball. The missile entered the limb on its anterior inner face a short distance below
     the joint, passed backward and upward, and escaped through the popliteal space, apparently
     without opening the joint. From the course and direction of the wound the upper part of the
     tibia was supposed to be injured. At the time of admission the patient's condition was good,
     there being no pain, heat, or swelling about the injured knee. He was directed to refrain from
     using it by remaining quietly in bed, to have ice applied to the wound constantly so as to
     lessen the danger of inflammatory action, and to be supported by nutritious diet. Under this
     treatment his case progressed without an untoward symptom until July 5th. At inspection, on
     this day, I especially noticed his condition as very promising, the anterior orifice of the
     wound being nearly healed. But, about the middle of the following night, he was seized with
     great pain and distress in the injured knee, and full doses of morphia were administered
     without producing much relief. On the following morning the knee was found to be greatly
     swollen, hot, and exceedingly tender, the patient complaining of intense gnawing pain in it,
     and crying out from agony occasioned by it. Although his pupils were markedly contracted from
     the large quantities of anodynes taken, his countenance was expressive of great distress; pulse
     frequent, quick, and irritable; skin hot and dry: he was also thirsty, had a coated tongue, and
     had had a slight chill. Free abstraction of blood from the neighborhood of the knee by cups was
     ordered, also ten grains of calomel, and anodynes as required. On <date type="operation" when="1863-07-07">July 7th</date>, the patient's
     condition had not materially changed. Seeing that the arthritis was secondary to the wound, and
     believing that it was associated with fracture and comminution of the upper end of the tibia,
     amputation appeared to be the proper remedy. The operation was accordingly performed by <name type="person" key="141">Assistant Surgeon P. C. Davis</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, in the lower third of the thigh, by the circular method, about
     midday—thirty-six hours after the attack. Anæsthesia was produced by sulphuric
     ether. The patient bore the operation well. On examining the amputated limb the inner part of
     the head of the tibia was found to be extensively injured by the bullet, a deep groove having
     been made in the bone, associated with much comminution, and some of the broken fragments
     connected directly with the joint. The cavity of the knee joint was found to contain about four
     ounces of dirty-brown colored viscid liquid, in which yellowish shining globules (synovia),
     looking like oil, floated. The lining membrane of the joint was stained with a dull red hue
     throughout its whole extent and had entirely lost its polished and shining appearance. The
     internal semilunar cartilage completely covered the opening in the head of the tibia. On July 10th, the patient was
     progressing pretty well." On <date type="transfer" when="1863-10-02">October 2d</date>, he was
     transferred to <name type="hospital" key="xx">Turner's Lane Hospital, Philadelphia</name>,
     where a second operation was performed by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon
      C. B. King</name>, who described it as follows: "When admitted, the femur was protruding about
     half an inch, and appeared to be dead as far up as could be felt with the probe, a ring of new
     bone being thrown around it. The discharge was very profuse. On <date type="operation" when="1863-10-05">October 5th</date>, the patient having been placed under the influence of ether, an oval
     incision was made around the end of the bone and through the cicatrix and some unhealthy
     granulations, when, after dissecting the muscles for a short distance, the vitality of the new
     bone was found to be small, and lateral incisions were made and the flaps dissected up for
     about four inches, where the new bone seemed to be more healthy, and was sawn off. About four
     inches of the remaining dead bone, which I judged as reaching up as far as the great
     trochanter, was extracted with the forceps. The femoral artery was avoided by making the
     internal lateral incision below the vessel, and the patient lost but little blood. Three or
     four small arteries were ligated, and the wound was closed with iron wire and adhesive straps.
     The patient, being very weak from suppuration and the shock of the operation, was rallied with
     difficulty. Cold-water dressings were applied and stimulants administered. On the following day
     the patient was still very weak, had a slight fever and coated tongue, and the stump was very
     much inflamed and swollen. The sutures were removed and the straps loosened, and milk punch,
     beef tea, and generous diet were ordered. On October 12th, the inflammation was somewhat
     reduced, the discharge free but very offensive, and the patient was gaining strength slowly and
     his appetite improving. The ligatures were now removed. On October 18th, the bands were
     removed, union having taken place in the stump. On November 4th, the wound had closed with an
     abundance of flap, and the patient was going about on crutches. On <date type="transfer" when="1863-11-16">November 16th</date>, he was transferred to Haddington Hospital for the purpose of getting an artificial limb." <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon J. R. Levis</name>, in charge of the latter hospital,
     recorded the following result of the case: "At date of admission a fistulous opening existed in
     the stump, and on examination by the probe the whole wall of this sinus was found to have an
     osseous fell leading directly to the end of the femur, where loose spiculae of bone were
     clearly perceived. A small pledget of sponge tent was applied, and on <date type="operation" when="1863-11-20"><choice><sic>November, 20th</sic><corr>November 20th</corr></choice></date> the
     orifice was well dilated, and, with the dressing forceps, several pieces of bony formation were
     removed, which crumbled readily under pressure; also a good sized spicula from the sawed
     surface of the femur. Some inflammation followed this operation, for which lead and opium
     lotion was applied; perfect quiet was enjoined, and anodynes given at bedtime. On November 23d, the inflammation was still continuing and the
     patient suffering intense pain in the stump, but two days afterwards both were subsiding. On December
     1st, another examination was made by the probe and another small piece of bone was extracted.
     By December 10th, his health had improved, the discharge had much lessened, and the stump was
     doing well, the patient stating that it felt better than at any previous time. In <date type="furlough" when="1864-01">January,
     1864</date>, the patient went to his home on furlough, and in the following month, when he returned,
     the discharge had almost ceased. On March 1st, the sinus had closed and the stump was
     apparently sound." The patient was subsequently transferred to Christian Street Hospital, and was discharged from service <date type="servicedischarge" when="1864-06-07">June 7, 1864</date>, and pensioned. <name type="person" key="xx">Examiner J. Walker</name>, of <name type="place" key="xx">Bethany, Missouri</name>, certified, <date type="pension" when="1874-05-02">May 2, 1874</date>: "I find him unable to wear an artificial limb on account of tenderness and shortness of the stump. He is unable to raise the stump in walking, and wears a wooden peg with a leather
     socket, buckled around his waist. He is also unable to raise the peg, but moves it by moving
     the side of his body. The stump chafes so easily that he can wear the socket but a short time,
     and then has to use a crutch." The pensioner was paid <date type="pension" when="1879-06-04">June 4, 1879</date>. The bones comprising the
     knee of the amputated limb were transmitted to <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name> by <name type="person" key="70">Surgeon Lidell</name>, and the involucrum and
     sequestrum, removed at the second operation, together with a cast of the stump, were
     contributed by <name type="person" key="xx">the operator</name>. (<hi rend="italic">Cat. Surg. Sect.</hi>, 1866, pp. 341, 309, and
     555, <hi rend="italic">Specs.</hi> 1306, 2602, and 1529.) <hi rend="italic">Specimen</hi> 2602
     is represented in <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IG. 1 of <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">LXX</hi>,
     opposite p. 242.</p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001812.001"/>
    <head>PLATE  LXX.__INVOLUCRA  OF  THE  FEMUR.      Fig. 1_Case of <name type="person" key="1087">Pt. W. Vannatta</name>,  <name type="organization" key="84">4 Pennsylvania Cav.</name>,  Spec. 2602,  Surg. Sect.  A. M. M.</head>
   </figure>

   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
