<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e41359">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Wagner, G. A.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d1e41359</idno>
       <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
       <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor>
       <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
       <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
       <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
       <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
       <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
    </distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
         republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
         law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
         publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>     
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861-65.)</title>
     <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
     <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
     <biblScope type="part">Part 2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
     <date when="1879">1879</date>
     <biblScope type="page">188</biblScope>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
       <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
      <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
       <term>diarrhœa and dysentery</term>
       <term>fatal cases of diarrhœa and dysentery, with accounts of the morbid appearances observed</term>
       <term>from the First Division of the Alexandria Hospital, Virginia</term>
       <term>chronic diarrhœa</term>
       <term>cough, pneumonia</term>
       <term>state of stupor</term>
       <term>inflammation of ileum, cæcum, and colon</term>       
       <term>passages mixed with blood</term>
       <term>severe pain in right iliac region</term>
       <term>autopsy performed</term>       
     </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-12-06">copied case from MSHWR, added proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body> 
   <p>Case from the medical descriptive lists of the <name type="hospital" key="501"><hi rend="initialcap">S</hi>ECOND <hi rend="initialcap">D</hi>IVISION</name> of the <name type="place" key="#Alexandria"><hi rend="initialcap">A</hi>LEXANDRIA</name> <hi rend="initialcap">H</hi>OSPITAL, Virginia, <name type="person" key="307">Surgeon T. Rush Spencer</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, in charge:</p>
   <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 442.—<name type="person" key="xxx">Private G. A. Wagner</name>, <name type="organization" key="xxx">company K, 150th New York volunteers</name>; age 23; admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-09-17">September 17, 1863</date>.  Chronic diarrhœa.  At the time of admission, besides diarrhœa, the patient had symptoms of pneumonia. He was much debilitated. To take, morning and evening, four grains of Dover's powder, half a drachm of subnitrate of bismuth, and five grains of calomel in one powder; milk diet.  September 18th: The cough is slightly better, and the passages are less frequent. Treatment and diet continued.  September 19th: The stools are less frequent, but are still watery; the cough continues. To take a teaspoonful of syrup of squill three times a day besides the powders.  September 29th: Condition improving; stools still watery, but not frequent. To take twenty drops of the syrup of the iodide of iron three times a day; also tincture of cinchona.  October 5th: Is again attacked with violent diarrhœa, having eight passages in the twenty-four hours. Renew the subnitrate of bismuth in half-drachm doses; milk diet.  October 7th: Patient very low; passages ten per day. Continue the subnitrate of bismuth; also give enemata of tannic acid and opium.  October 8th: The passages have decreased in number to five in the twenty-four hours, but are mixed with blood. Stop the bismuth. Take three grains of powdered opium twice a day; milk-punch.  October 9th: Patient complains of severe pain in right iliac region; had five bloody passages in the last twenty-four hours. To take powders of tannic acid, calomel, and opium every three hours; a mustard plaster to the abdomen; milk-punch.  <date type="death" when="1863-10-10">October 10th</date>: The patient lies in a state of stupor, pulse feeble and trembling. Died at 9 A. M.  <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> There was extensive inflammation of the ileum, cæcum, and colon.—<name type="person" key="1602">Acting Assistant Surgeon Thomas H. Stillwell</name>.</p> 
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
