<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e9538">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title level="m" type="main">Wolfanger, Frederick</title>
                                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                                <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition>
                                        <date>2011</date>
                                </edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <idno>med.d1e9538</idno>
                                <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                <distributor>
                                        <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                                        <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                </distributor>
                                <date>2011</date>
                                <availability>
                                        <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all
                                                rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in
                                                any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use
                                                provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express
                                                written consent from the editors and advance
                                                notification of the publisher, the University of
                                                Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <notesStmt>
                                <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular
                                        readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                        <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                        <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                </note>
                        </notesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <bibl>
                                        <title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</title>
                                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                        <biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="volume">Volume 1</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1888">1888</date>
                                        <biblScope type="page">387</biblScope>
                                </bibl>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <encodingDesc>
                        <classDecl>
                                <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                        <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                </taxonomy>
                        </classDecl>
                </encodingDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <textClass>
                                <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                        <term>the continued fevers</term>
                                        <term>post-mortem records of continued fevers</term>                                       
                                        <term>cases reported as typhoid fever, the clinical history insufficient or absent</term>
                                        <term>Peyer's patches ulcerated and the large intestine also implicated</term>   
                                        <term>suppurative inflammation of parotid gland</term>
                                        <term>pus discharged in mouth between tongue and inferior maxilla and externally between mastoid process and clavicle</term>
                                        <term>thyroid gland contained calcareous mass and cysts in each lobe</term>
                                        <term>apoplectic extravasation in lower thyroid gland</term>
                                        <term>lobes of lungs interadherent but not attached to ribs</term>
                                        <term>intestines dark grayish color, Peyer's patches ulcerated in places</term>
                                </keywords>
                        </textClass>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2013-04-08">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-10-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#mb" when="2011-06-23">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                        <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                        <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-23">Encoding and Proofing</change>
                        <change who="#et" when="2009-12-01">Initial Checking OCR Text to PDF file,</change>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text type="case">
                <body xml:id="ch4.sc4.1.00193">                        
                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 193.—<name type="person" key="721">Private Frederick
                                                Wolfanger</name>, <name type="organization" key="125">Co. C, 93d N. Y.</name>; age 43; was
                                        admitted <date type="admit" when="1863-10-24">Oct. 24,
                                                1863</date>, and died <date type="death" when="1863-11-18">November 18</date>.  <hi rend="italic">Post-mortem</hi> examination <date type="autopsy" when="1863-11-19">thirty
                                        hours after death</date>: Body much emaciated. Brain healthy. The
                                        left parotid gland was the seat of suppurative inflammation;
                                        the pus had discharged from two openings, one in the mouth,
                                        between the tongue and the inferior maxilla, the other
                                        externally, between the mastoid process and clavicle. The
                                        left lobe of the thyroid gland contained a calcareous mass
                                        as large as a walnut, and in its upper portion a cyst the
                                        size of a pea, filled with a dark-brown fluid; the right
                                        lobe contained a cyst the size of a small chestnut, and in
                                        its lower portion an apoplectic extravasation one inch and a
                                        half long by one inch in width. The right lung weighed
                                        forty-seven ounces and a half; its lobes were interadherent
                                        but not attached to the ribs; the lateral and posterior
                                        parts were œdematous. The left lung resembled the
                                        other, but contained a greater quantity of blood in many
                                        places, the parenchyma being of a darker hue. The bronchial
                                        tubes were thickened and their mucous membrane reddish; a
                                        yellow tenacious mucus was contained in the smaller tubes,
                                        giving a granular appearance to a section of the lung. Both
                                        sides of the heart contained mixed fibrinous and dark clots;
                                        its muscular tissue was much softer than usual. The liver
                                        was normal; the spleen soft, flabby and of a turbid purple
                                        color. The intestines were of a dark grayish color; Peyer's
                                        patches were ulcerated in places but were not elevated. The
                                        kidneys were slightly congested.—<hi rend="italic"><name type="person" key="245">Ass't Surg. H.
                                                  Allen</name>, <name type="organization" key="190">U. S. A.</name>, <name type="hospital" key="176">Lincoln Hospital</name>, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>
