<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d2e20548">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title level="m" type="main">Mock, L.</title>
    <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
    <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
    <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition><date>2011</date></edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <idno>med.d2e20548</idno>
    <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
    <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
    <distributor><name>Center for Digital Research in the
     Humanities</name><address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address></distributor>
    <date>2011</date>
    <availability>
     <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or
      republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright
      law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
      publisher, the University of Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to
     this file, as noted: 
     <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
     <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
     <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
     <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ss">Sarah Synovec</persName>
     <persName xml:id="ak">Alex Kinnaman</persName>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title level="j">The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion.
      (1861-65.)</title><pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace><publisher>Government Printing
      Office</publisher><biblScope type="part">Part 3</biblScope><biblScope type="volume">Volume
      2</biblScope><date when="1883">1883</date><biblScope type="page">529, 712-713</biblScope></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <classDecl>
    <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
     <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
    </taxonomy>
   </classDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
     <term>wounds and injuries of the lower extremities</term> 
     <term>wounds and operations in the leg</term>
     <term>shot fractures of the bones of the leg</term>
     <term>amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot fractures</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the continuity of the leg for shot injury</term> 
     <term>intermediary amputations in the lower third of the leg for shot injury</term> 
     <term>fatal intermediary amputations in the lower third of the leg</term>
     <term>ball passed through <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice> and grazed <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>, opening ankle joint</term> 
     <term>ball entered below internal malleolus, passed upward and outward, exit anterior and under external malleolus, opening ankle joint</term> 
     <term>leg amputated above ankle, three vessels ligated</term>     
     <term>shoulder and elbow joints contain pus</term>
     <term>pyæmia</term> 
     <term>general anesthesia, ether</term>
     <term>general anesthesia, chloroform</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change who="#ak" when="2014-10-08">added figure encoding</change>
   <change who="#mb" when="2012-06-11">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, identified keyword terms</change>
   <change who="#el" when="2011-05-11">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-06-04">Enrich Encoding, Edit and validate</change>
   <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">Validated File</change>
   <change who="#ss" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text; encoded P5 Encoding</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="case">
  <body>   
    <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE 777.—<name type="person" key="1309">Private L.
      Mock</name>, <name type="organization" key="449">Co. I, 119th Pennsylvania</name>, aged 22
     years, was wounded in the left foot, at <name type="BATTLE" key="15">Rappahannock
      Station</name>, <date type="injury" when="1863-11-07">November 7, 1863</date>, by a musket
     ball, which entered about one and a half inches below the internal malleolus, passing upward
     and outward, making its exit anterior and under the external malleolus and opening the ankle
     joint in its passage through the parts. He entered <name type="hospital" key="171">Armory
      Square Hospital</name> at Washington <date type="admit" when="1863-11-09">two days after receiving the injury</date>. On <date type="operation" when="1863-12-06">December 6th</date>,
      <name type="person" key="123">Surgeon D. W. Bliss</name>, <name type="organization" key="132">U. S. V.</name>, amputated the leg above the ankle by flap operation, the patient being under
     ether, to which a little chloroform was added towards the last. Three vessels were ligated, the loss of blood being small. The patient reacted well from
     the anæsthetic. At the time of the operation his constitutional condition was tolerably
     good and the tissues of the wounded parts were in a healthy state. The stump grew painful, but
     its appearance was good. Cold-water dressing was used and nourishing diet with stimulants were
     administered. On December 9th the patient had three chills, followed by profuse perspiration.
     On the following day there was no chill, the stump still looked well, and the patient suffered
     no pain. Quinine and opium were now prescribed in addition to the former treatment. By December
     18th there was well-developed pyæmia, from the effects of which the patient died <date type="death" when="1863-12-21">December 21, 1863</date>. After death yellowness, to an extreme
     degree, came on, and, on inspection, the shoulder and elbow were found to contain pus, the
     shoulder having a large quantity and the other joints being believed to be in a like condition.
     The tarsal bones of the amputated limb, contributed with the history by <name type="person" key="123">the operator</name>, constitute specimen 1903 of the Surgical Section of <name type="hospital" key="431">the Museum</name>. The specimen exhibits no perceptible attempt at repair, and shows that the ball passed through the <choice><orig>calcaneum</orig><reg>calcaneus</reg></choice>, which is necrosed, and grazed the <choice><orig>astragalus</orig><reg>talus</reg></choice>, opening the
     ankle joint. The appearance of the entrance and exit wounds is shown in <hi rend="initialcap">P</hi>LATE <hi rend="initialcap">XXXIX</hi>, <hi rend="initialcap">F</hi>IGURE 2. </p>

   <figure>
    <graphic url="cww.001839.001"/>
    <head>
     PLATE  XXXIX.    EARLY  APPEARANCES  OF  ENTRANCE  AND  EXIT  SHOT  WOUNDS.    [see Figures numbered 2]
    </head>
   </figure>   
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
