<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="med.d1e16357">
                <teiHeader>
                                <fileDesc>
                                                <titleStmt>
                                                                <title level="m" type="main">M——, James D.</title>
                                                  <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable
                                                  transcription</title>
                                                  <principal>Susan C. Lawrence</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth M. Price</principal>
                                                  <principal>Kenneth J. Winkle</principal>
                                                </titleStmt>
                                                <editionStmt>
                                                  <edition>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  </edition>
                                                </editionStmt>
                                                <publicationStmt>
                                                  <idno>med.d1e16357</idno>
                                                  <authority>Civil War Washington</authority>
                                                  <publisher>University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                                                  <distributor>
                                                  <name>Center for Digital Research in the
                                                  Humanities</name>
                                                  <address><addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine><addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine><addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine></address>
                                                  </distributor>
                                                  <date>2011</date>
                                                  <availability>
                                                  <p>Copyright © 2011 by University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln, all rights reserved.
                                                  Redistribution or republication in any medium,
                                                  except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of
                                                  U.S. copyright law, requires express written
                                                  consent from the editors and advance notification
                                                  of the publisher, the University of
                                                  Nebraska–Lincoln.</p>
                                                  </availability>
                                                </publicationStmt>
                                                <notesStmt>
                                                  <note type="project">The following are responsible for particular readings or for changes to this file, as noted: 
                                                                  <persName xml:id="mb">Matthew Bosley</persName>
                                                                  <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="sb">Stacey Berry</persName>
                                                  <persName xml:id="et">Elisabeth Tracey</persName>
                                                  </note>
                                                </notesStmt>
                                                <sourceDesc>
                                                  <bibl>
                                                  <title>The Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion. (1861–65.)</title>
                                                  <editor role="compiler">Surgeon General Joseph K. Barnes, United States Army</editor>
                                                  <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                                  <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                                                  <biblScope type="part">Part 1</biblScope>
                                                  <biblScope type="volume">Volume 2</biblScope>
                                                  <date when="1870">1870</date>
                                                  <biblScope type="page">250-251</biblScope>
                                                  </bibl>
                                                </sourceDesc>
                                </fileDesc>
                                <encodingDesc>
                                                <classDecl>
                                                  <taxonomy xml:id="medsurg">
                                                  <bibl>Medical and Surgical History of the War of the Rebellion</bibl>
                                                  </taxonomy>
                                                </classDecl>
                                </encodingDesc>
                                <profileDesc>
                                                <textClass>
                                                  <keywords scheme="#medsurg">
                                                    <term>on special wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>wounds and injuries of the head</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wounds</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot fractures of the cranial bones</term> 
                                                    <term>removal of fragments after gunshot fractures of the skull</term>
                                                    <term>fatal cases of gunshot fractures of the skull treated by the removal or elevation fragments</term>
                                                    <term>treated by operation, not by formal trephining</term>
                                                    <term>extent of injury ascertained with precision, organic alterations accurately observed</term>
                                                    <term>conoidal ball lacerated scalp over upper anterior portion of left parietal bone</term>
                                                    <term>gunshot wound of scalp</term>
                                                    <term>convulsions affected right side, tonic spasms</term>
                                                    <term>coma, constant rigidity of right side, right pupil dilated</term>
                                                    <term>piece of bone driven into brain matter</term>
                                                    <term>immense abscess occupied anterior left cerebral hemisphere, penetrated into left lateral ventricle</term>
                                                    <term><choice><orig>septum lucidum</orig><reg>septum pellucidum</reg></choice> broken down, right ventricle also filled with pus</term>
                                                    <term>meninges of brain inflamed, pus formed under arachnoid</term>
                                                    <term>cranium fractured below anterior superior angle of parietal bone</term>
                                                    <term>post-mortem examination performed</term>                                                    
                                                  </keywords>
                                                </textClass>
                                </profileDesc>
                                <revisionDesc>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2013-08-07">additional proofing of transcription and encoding, edited and added keyword terms</change>
                                                <change who="#mb" when="2011-08-03">additional proofing of transcription and encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#el" when="2011-11-05">case text extracted and transformed from larger file</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-02-09">enriched encoding</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2011-01-28">validated file</change>
                                                <change who="#et" when="2009-08-01">encoded</change>
                                                <change who="#sb" when="2008-09-22">initial checking of OCR text against PDF; encoded</change>
                                </revisionDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text type="case">
                                <body>                                                
                                                <p><hi rend="initialcap">C</hi>ASE.—<name type="person">Corporal James D. M——</name>, <name type="organization">Co. D, 108th New
                                                                York Volunteers</name>, was wounded at the battle of
                                                                <name type="BATTLE" key="4">Fredericksburg, Virginia</name>, <date type="injury" when="1862-12-13">December 13th, 1862</date>, by
                                                  a conoidal ball, which lacerated the scalp over
                                                  the upper anterior portion of the left parietal
                                                  bone.  He was admitted into <name type="hospital" key="">Grace Church Hospital</name>, <name type="place">Alexandria</name>, on <date type="admit" when="1862-12-19">the 19th</date>, where the wound was
                                                  <choice><orig>diagnosticated</orig><reg>diagnosed as</reg></choice> as a gunshot wound of the scalp. He
                                                  was able to walk about, and stated that he had
                                                  been unconscious only a short time.  After a few
                                                  days he was attacked with convulsions, which
                                                  affected only the right side, producing tonic
                                                  spasms, only lasting about one hour. He recovered
                                                  from these sufficiently to be again able to walk
                                                  about.  About <date type="operation" when="1863-01-19"><date type="injury" when="1863-01-18">the 18th or 19th of January, 1863</date></date>,
                                                  the convulsions returned and grew more frequent,
                                                  until he sank into a comatose state, with constant
                                                  rigidity of the right side. He could be aroused
                                                  sufficiently to answer questions by yes and no.
                                                  The right pupil was dilated, and the pulse slow
                                                  and intermitting.  <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. W. Tryon</name>, cut down on the skull and removed several
                                                  pieces of bone, one of which, triangular in shape,
                                                  and about half an inch in length, had been driven
                                                  into the brain matter.  The operation afforded no
                                                  relief, and the symptoms above described gradually
                                                  increased, till death supervened on <date type="death" when="1863-01-30">January 30th</date>.  At the <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination an immense abscess
                                                  was found, which occupied nearly the whole
                                                  anterior lobe of the left hemisphere, and
                                                  penetrated into the ventricle of that side. The
                                                  <choice><orig>septum lucidum</orig><reg>septum pellucidum</reg></choice> was broken down, and the right
                                                  ventricle filled with pus. The under portions of
                                                  the meninges of the brain were inflamed, being
                                                  much injected with blood. At a number of places
                                                  pus had formed under the arachnoid. There were
                                                  congested spots in the brain matter, about the sac
                                                  of the abscess, and nearly the whole mass of brain matter was
                                                  much softer than natural.  The pathological
                                                  specimen is No. 1723, Sect. I, A. M. M.  The vault
                                                  of the cranium is fractured just below the
                                                  anterior superior angle of the left parietal bone.
                                                  Fragments have been removed from an opening
                                                  three-fourths of an inch in diameter. Two fragments
                                                  of the outer and inner tables remain attached,
                                                  being depressed two lines on the free edge. The
                                                  surrounding bone is soft and porous.   The specimen
                                                  and history were contributed by <name type="person" key="xx">Acting Assistant Surgeon A. W. Tryon</name>.</p>                                                
                                </body>
                </text>
</TEI>
